<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Ramsgate, Friday, 21 April 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let078"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">078</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">62</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">076</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Ramsgate</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Friday, 21 April 1876</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Ramsgate, Friday, 21 April 1876.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mr and Mrs van Gogh’s twenty-fifth anniversary on 21 May <ref target="let064.xml">(64)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b75 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Ramsgate 21 April 1876’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0075" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000078_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000078_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000078_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000078_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0075" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000078_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000078_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000078_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000078_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Ramsgate 21 April 1876</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Ingesloten vindt gij een Post office Order van 10/─;<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>wees zoo goed daarvoor in een of andere courant, <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>beslis zelf maar in welke, bijgaande advertentie <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>voor Anna te plaatsen.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Mocht het te weinig <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>zijn dan stuur ik U wat er aan ontbreekt, en <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>is er teveel<c type="kk">/</c> koop er dan de eene of andere <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>photographie voor, voor Etten op 21 Mei.─ <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Maar geef s.v.p. in elk geval op wat gij voor <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>het plaatsen betaalt, daar dat meer te pas <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>kan komen wil ik het adres wel weten.─</ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoop zoo dat Anna wat zal vinden, Willemien <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>zal nu betrekkelijk spoedig naar huis gaan.─<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Eerst heden is Mr Stokes terug gekomen; hij is een <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>vrij groot man met kaal hoofd en bakkebaarden; <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>de jongens schijnen respekt voor hem te hebben <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>en toch van hem te houden; een paar uur <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>nadat hij terug was, was hij reeds met hun aan <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>het knikkeren.─</ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wij gaan dikwijls naar het strand; dezen <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>morgen hielp ik daar de jongens om eene <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>vesting van zand te bouwen zooals wij wel te Zundert <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>in den tuin maakten.─</ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wel graag zou ik hebben gij eens door het schoolraam <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>zien kondt.─ Het huis staat op een plein (al de <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>huizen daarom heen zijn eender, dat is hier dikwijls <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>het geval); in het midden van dat plein een 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>groot grasveld, afgesloten met een ijzeren hek en <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>omgeven door seringenstruiken; in het middaguur <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>spelen de jongens daar. Het huis waar mijne kamer <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>is staat op het zelfde plein.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toen ik te Rotterdam was en merkte dat ik daar een <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>geruimen tijd moest wachten, heb ik nog op het punt <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>gestaan om naar den Haag te komen; ben zelfs <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>nog aan het station geweest.─ Toch deed ik het <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>niet, later hoop ik allen en alles daar met wat <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>kalmer oog nog wel eens weer te zien.</ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het van ’t huis afscheid nemen op Goeden Vrijdag zal ik wel <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>niet vergeten. s’Morgens gingen wij aan de Hoeve<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> naar <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>de kerk en aan het Avondmaal,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> te zamen, en <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>Vader zeide daar: “Staat op<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons van hier gaan”<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>En s’middags stonden wij op, en zag ik uit het raampje <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Pa en het broêrken<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> op den weg, den trein staan nakijken. <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>En Zondag middag was ik te Ramsgate in de kerk en <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>daar trof mij het woord dat daar op den muur stond,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> en <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>dat gij in Anna’s brief (die hierbij ter lezing gaat maar <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>zend dien terug) vindt.─</ab>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hierbij de advertentie in kwestie.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> Groeten bij Roos en <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>aan ieder die naar mij mocht vragen, ook aan Borchers<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>mocht gij dien zien; komt gij daar nog wel eens?</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">In gedachten U de hand gedrukt en steeds</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab>Uw liefh. broeder</ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="56*" xml:id="l-56s"/>
<ab>Schrijf eens spoedig<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab>Eene jonge dame, Predikantsdochter, sedert geruimen <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>tijd in Engeland in betrekking<c type="kk">/</c> zoekt eene betrekking <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>als jufvrouw van gezelschap of ter verpleging eener <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ziekelijke dame.</ab>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
<ab rend="indent">Brieven adres G.H.M.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Post Office Welwyn (Herts)<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>(England)<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="29 »" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab>Spreek er tegen niemand van gij de advertentie plaatst. Gij ziet uit den brief zij dat <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>liever niet heeft.─</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-3" n="3">10/─; &lt; 10/─.;</note>
<note target="l-29" targetEnd="l-30" n="29-30">
                        <hi rend="ital">In the left margin on p. 1 (`Ramgate [...] plein een´).</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-44" n="44">“Staat &lt; Staat</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Ramsgate, 21 April 1876</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Enclosed you’ll find a Post office Order for 10 shillings;<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> be so good as to place the enclosed advertisement for <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> for that amount in some newspaper or other, you decide which one.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> If it’s not enough I’ll send you the rest, and if it’s too much, buy some photograph or other for Etten, for 21 May. But in any event please tell me how much you pay for the advertisement; I do want to have the address as it may be of further use.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hope so much that <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> will find something; <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> will be going home soon now.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="764">Mr Stokes</rs> didn’t come back until today; he’s a rather large man with a bald head and whiskers. The boys seem to respect him yet love him all the same; he was already playing marbles with them, only a couple of hours after he got back.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">We go to the beach often; this morning I helped the boys build a sand-castle like those we made in the garden at Zundert.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How much I’d like you to be able to look through the school window. The house stands on a square (all the houses around it are the same, which is often the case here). In the middle of the square a 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> large green, closed in by an iron fence and surrounded by lilac bushes. The boys play there during the midday break. The house where I have my room is on the same square.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When I was in Rotterdam and saw that I’d have to wait there a long time, I very nearly came to The Hague, even went to the station. And yet I didn’t do it, I hope that later I’ll be able to see everyone and everything there again with a calmer eye.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Saying farewell at home on Good Friday is something I won’t forget. In the morning we went to  Hoeven<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> together to attend church and the Lord’s Supper,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> and Father said there: ‘Arise, let us go hence’.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> And in the afternoon we did arise, and through the small window I saw <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="420">little brother</rs>
                    <anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> in the road, watching the train leave. And Sunday afternoon I was in the church in Ramsgate and was struck by the words written there on the wall,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> which you’ll find in <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna’s</rs> letter (enclosed for you to read, but send it back).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Enclosed is the advertisement in question.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> Regards to everyone at <rs type="pers" key="642 643">the Rooses</rs>’ and to anyone else who might ask after me, also to <rs type="pers" key="298">Borchers</rs>, if you run into him. Do you still go there now and then?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I shake your hand in thought, and ever</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Do write soon.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>A young lady, a clergyman’s daughter, having worked in England for some time, is looking for a situation as lady’s companion or nurse to a sickly lady.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Address: G.H.M.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> Post Office, Welwyn (Herts)<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> (England).</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Tell no one that you’re placing the advertisement. You can see from the letter that she’d prefer you didn’t.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>A postal order for 10 shillings.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>, who lived and worked in Welwyn, was looking for a new situation (FR b954, b2765 and b2769). See the text of the advertisement at the end of the letter.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> had been staying with <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> at Welwyn since mid-August 1875; on 13 May 1876 she travelled back to her <rs type="pers" key="524 526">parents</rs> in Etten (FR b2356 and b2749).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
  <ab>Two drawings Van Gogh made of this place – Spencer Square – have survived; one was sent in <ref target="let083.xml">letter 83</ref>. There is no proof that the other known drawing of the square, <hi rend="ital">View of Royal Road, Ramsgate</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="82">F Juv. XXVI / JH -</rs>) was enclosed with the present letter, as assumed in earlier editions. See also cat. Amsterdam 1996, p. 61, cat. no. 9, fig. 9. Vincent might have enclosed it in a letter to his <rs type="pers" key="524 526">parents</rs>, because on 2 June 1876, Mrs van Gogh wrote to Theo: ‘Early in the week we received a letter from Vincent with a nice little drawing of his house, but he didn’t write about anything in particular, so we’re already looking forward to the next letter. We’ve asked him to tell us about everything, which we hope he’ll do’ (FR b2752).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">A photograph of Spencer Square (of c. 1900) is to be found in exhib. cat. London 1992, p. 12.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> regularly conducted divine service for the Protestant community in the nearby hamlet of Hoeven; cf. Kools 1990, p. 121.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Part of the Protestant service.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="14" v="31">John 14:31</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Vincent and Theo’s younger brother <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs>, who was nearly nine.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Cf. <ref target="let076.xml#l-102">letter 76, ll. 102-104</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Van Gogh wrote the text of the advertisement below his signature. The advertisement appeared a week later, in exactly the same words, in the <hi rend="ital">Oprechte Haarlemsche Courant</hi> of 28 April 1876.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>According to information supplied by the Postal Museum in Bath (UK), this abbreviation presumably stands for ‘General Holding Mail’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Hertfordshire.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>