<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Paris, Thursday, 15 July 1875.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let038"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">038</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">31</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">038</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 15 July 1875</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Paris, Thursday, 15 July 1875.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b40 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘<hi rend="ital">[</hi>Paris, le<hi rend="ital">]</hi> 15 Juillet <hi rend="ital">[</hi>187<hi rend="ital">]</hi>5’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0040" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000042_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000042_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000042_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000042_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000042_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0040" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000042_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000042_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000042_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000042_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>
                    <vg:suppliedMilestone type="open"/>Goupil &amp; C<hi rend="ss">ie</hi>
                </ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Editeurs Imprimeurs</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Estampes Françaises &amp; Étrangères</ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab>Tableaux Modernes</ab>
                <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>
<ab>Rue Chaptal, 9, PARIS.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab>Succursales à la Haye, Londres, Berlin, New-York.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab>Paris, le<vg:suppliedMilestone type="close"/> 15 Juillet <supplied>187</supplied>5</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab>Oom V<hi rend="ss">t</hi> is weer hier geweest, ik was nog al eens <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>met hem samen &amp; heb over een &amp; ander gesproken. <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Ik vroeg hem of hij geen kans zag om U hier, <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>in het huis te Parijs, te krijgen. In ’t begin <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>wilde hij daar niets van hooren &amp; zei ’t veel <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>beter was gij in den Haag bleeft; ik heb <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>echter aangedrongen, &amp; gij kunt er op rekenen <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>hij het nu in gedachten houdt.─</ab>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wanneer hij in den Haag komt zal hij <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>waarschijnlijk wel met U praten; houdt <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>U dan maar bedaard &amp; laat hem maar <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>zeggen wat hij wil; het zal U geen kwaad <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>doen, &amp; waarschijnlijk zult gij hem later nog <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>wel eens noodig hebben. Gij moet niet over <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>mij spreken als ’t niet te pas komt.</ab>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hij is geducht knap, toen ik verl<c type="kp">_</c> winter hier <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>was<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> zei hij mij o.a. “bovennatuurlijke dingen <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>weet ik misschien niet, maar natuurlijke <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>dingen weet ik allemaal,” ik weet niet of het <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>dezelfde woorden waren, maar ’t kwam toch <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>daarop neer.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>
                <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik wil U ook nog wel zeggen dat één van <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>zijne geliefde schilderijen is “Les illusions perdues” <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>van Gleyre.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">S<hi rend="ss">te</hi> Beuve zei: “il est dans la pluspart <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>des hommes un poëte mort jeune, à qui l’homme <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>survit”<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> &amp; Musset: “sachez qu’en nous il existe <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>souvent, un poëte endormi, toujours jeune &amp; <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>vivant”<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Ik geloof het eerste met Oom Vincent <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>het geval is.─ Gij weet dus met wien gij <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>te doen hebt, &amp; dus opgepast.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Vraag hem gerust ronduit om te maken gij <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>naar hier of Londen komt.─</ab>
                <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik dank U voor uw brief van dezen morgen, <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>&amp; voor het vers van Rückert. Hebt gij zijne <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>gedichten? ik zou er graag meer van kennen. <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>Als er gelegenheid is, stuur ik U een Franschen <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>bijbel &amp; l’Imitation de Jesus Christ.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> Dit was <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>waarschijnlijk het geliefde boek van die <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>vrouw die Ph. de Champaigne schilderde;<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>in de Louvre is het portret van hare dochter, <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>eene non, ook door Ph. de Ch., zij heeft l’Imita<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>tion op een stoel naast zich liggen.─<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pa heeft mij eens geschreven: “gij weet dat <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>dezelfde mond die sprak ‘wees oprecht als <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de duiven’ er ook onmiddelijk bijvoegde: <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>‘en voorzichtig als de slangen.’”<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Houd 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>gij dat ook maar in gedachten, en geloof <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>mij steeds</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="57*" xml:id="l-57s"/>
<ab>Uw liefh. broeder</ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab>Hebt gij in den winkel de phot<c type="kp">_</c> naar <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>Meissonier?<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Bekijk die maar dikwijls; <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hij heeft <hi rend="ital">mannen</hi> geschilderd. Mogelijk <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>kent gij wel l’fumeur à la fenêtre &amp; le jeune <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>homme déjeûnant.─<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-1" targetEnd="l-7" n="1-7">
                        <hi rend="ital">Printed letterhead.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-35" n="35">“sachez &lt; sachez</note>
<note target="l-53" n="53">‘wees &lt; “wees</note>
<note target="l-54" n="54">duiven´ &lt; duiven”</note>
<note target="l-55" n="55">‘en &lt; “en</note>
<note target="l-55" n="55">slangen.´” &lt; slangen.”</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>[Letterhead: Goupil Paris]</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Paris, 15 July 1875</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>

<ab>
                    <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs> was here again, we were together quite a lot and talked about one thing and another. I asked him whether he thought there would be an opportunity to get you here, into the Paris branch. At first he wouldn’t hear of it, and said it was much better that you stay in The Hague; but I kept insisting, and you can be sure that he’ll bear it in mind.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">When he comes to The Hague he’ll probably talk to you; stay calm and let him have his say; it won’t do you any harm, and later on you’ll probably need him now and again. You shouldn’t talk about me if it’s not the right moment.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He’s terribly clever, when I was here last winter<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> one of the things he said to me was ‘perhaps I know nothing of supernatural things, but of natural things I know everything’. I’m not sure whether those were his exact words, but that was the gist of it. 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I also want to tell you that one of his favourite paintings is ‘Lost illusions’ by <rs type="pers" key="1053">Gleyre</rs>.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="736">Sainte-Beuve</rs> said, ‘There is in most men a poet who died young, whom the man survived’<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> and <rs type="pers" key="715">Musset</rs>, ‘know that in us there is often a sleeping poet, ever young and alive’.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> I believe that the former is true of <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs>. So you know who it is you’re dealing with, and so be warned.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Don’t hesitate to ask him openly to have you sent here or to London.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I thank you for your letter of this morning, and for the verse by <rs type="pers" key="734">Rückert</rs>. Do you have his poems? I’d like to know more of them. When there’s an opportunity I’ll send you a French Bible and L’imitation de Jesus Christ.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> This was probably the favourite book of that woman whom <rs type="pers" key="937">P. de Champaigne</rs> painted;<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> in the Louvre there’s a portrait, also by P. de C., of her daughter, a nun; she has L’imitation lying on a chair next to her.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> once wrote to me: ‘you know that the same lips that uttered “be harmless as doves” also immediately added “and wise as serpents”’.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> You should bear 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> that in mind as well, and believe me to be ever</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Do you have the photos of the <rs type="pers" key="1208">Meissonier</rs>s in the gallery?<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> Look at them often; he painted <hi rend="ital">men</hi>. You may well know The smoker at the window and The young man having lunch.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>In 1874 Van Gogh was transferred for two months to Paris, where he arrived on 26 October. He spent Christmas with his <rs type="pers" key="524 526">parents</rs> and then travelled from Helvoirt back to London (FR b2728 and b2738).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1053">Charles Gleyre</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Evening (Lost illusions)</hi>, 1843 (Paris, Musée du Louvre). <rs type="ill" key="1725">Ill. 1725</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>In 1837 <rs type="pers" key="736">Charles Augustin Sainte-Beuve</rs> wrote about the poet <rs type="pers" key="1629">Millevoye</rs>: ‘There’s better. In all of us, if we are poets, and even if we clearly are not, there exists or there has existed some fine flower of feelings, of desires, some primal dream, which soon vanishes into humdrum works and expires in the course of life’s business. It is found, in a word, in three-quarters of mankind, like a poet who dies young, while the man lives on.’ (Il y a mieux. En nous tous, pour peu que nous soyons poètes, et si nous ne le sommes pourtant pas décidément, il existe ou il a existé une certaine fleur de sentiments, de désirs, une certaine rêverie première, qui bientôt s’en va dans les travaux prosaïques, et qui expire dans l’occupation de la vie. Il se trouve, en un mot, dans les trois quarts des hommes, comme un poète qui meurt jeune, tandis que l’homme survit). See <hi rend="ital">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi>, April-June 1837, pp. 645-646.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="715">Louis Charles Alfred de Musset</rs> included his reaction to <rs type="pers" key="736">Sainte-Beuve</rs> in his poem ‘A Sainte-Beuve’:</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>‘Friend, you’ve said it well, and yet you’ve said it all too well.</ab>
<ab>In setting out your thoughts, you failed to guard against</ab>
<ab>Your pen’s creating of them pleasing verse,</ab>
<ab>Or your blaspheming in the language of the Gods.</ab>
<ab>Read your work again; I send you back to your affronted Muse.</ab>
<ab>Remind yourself that in us often lives</ab>
<ab>A sleeping poet, ever alive and young.’</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>(Tu l’as bien dit, Ami, mais tu l’as trop bien dit.</ab>
<ab>Tu ne prenais pas garde, en traçant ta pensée,</ab>
<ab>Que ta plume en faisait un vers harmonieux,</ab>
<ab>Et que tu blasphémais dans la langue des Dieux.</ab>
<ab>Relis-toi; je te rends à ta Muse offensée.</ab>
<ab>Et souviens-toi qu’en nous il existe souvent</ab>
<ab>Un poëte endormi, toujours jeune et vivant.)</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Sainte-Beuve published Musset’s poem in September 1837 in his own collection titled Pensées d’août. See Poésies complètes de Sainte-Beuve. Paris 1845, p. 379. It was also included in the 1850 edition of the Poésies nouvelles by Alfred de Musset. See De Musset 1957, pp. 378-379, 795-796.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Van Gogh was familiar with the poetry of both men, as evidenced by the poetry albums he made for Theo; see Pabst 1988, pp. 13, 22-24. It can no longer be ascertained whether he knew these passages from the work of Sainte-Beuve or that of Musset, but it seems likely that he picked up both passages from the new magazine <hi rend="ital">L’Art</hi>, first published shortly before this time in Paris. See <hi rend="ital">L’Art. Revue Hebdomadaire Illustrée</hi> 1-1 (1875), pp. 86-87.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>A French edition of <rs type="lit" key="35">
                            <hi rend="ital">De imitatione Christi</hi>
                        </rs> (The imitation of Christ) by <rs type="pers" key="679">Thomas a Kempis</rs>. In this book the writer presents self-abnegation and complete submission to God’s will in the light of God’s love and inner peace, at the same time offering the reader a guide to devotional practice. A number of French translations of this book were available.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Regarding <rs type="pers" key="937">De Champaigne</rs>'s <rs type="ill" key="1661">
                            <hi rend="ital">Portrait of a woman</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let014.xml#n-19">see letter 14, n. 19.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="937">Philippe de Champaigne</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Mother Catherine-Agnès Arnauld and Sister Catherine de Sainte Suzanne Champaigne</hi> (<hi rend="ital">The ex-voto of 1662)</hi> (Paris, Musée du Louvre). <rs type="ill" key="1726">Ill. 1726</rs>. There is nothing to suggest that the little book depicted in the painting is titled <rs type="lit" key="35">
                            <hi rend="ital">The imitation</hi>
                        </rs>; this was Van Gogh’s own idea.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Christ’s words in <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="10" v="16">Matt. 10:16</bibleref>, though Van Gogh quotes these phrases the wrong way around with respect to the biblical passage.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The photographer <rs type="pers" key="877">Robert Jefferson Bingham</rs> reproduced numerous works by <rs type="pers" key="1208">Meissonier</rs>. An overview of them appeared in Burty 1866. The two works mentioned by Van Gogh are included in this article. <ref target="#n-10">See n. 10.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1208">Ernest Meissonier</rs>,<hi rend="ital"> Le fumeur à la fenêtre </hi>(The smoker at the window) and <hi rend="ital">Jeune homme déjeunant </hi>(Young man having lunch) (both in Paris, BNF, Cabinet des Estampes). <rs type="ill" key="1727">Ill. 1727</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="1728">Ill. 1728</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>