<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Welwyn, Saturday, 17 June 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let084"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">084</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">69</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">082</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Welwyn</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 17 June 1876</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Welwyn, Saturday, 17 June 1876.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b82 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Welwyn 17 Junij 1876’.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>A letter of the same date from Anna to Theo was probably enclosed with this letter. <ref target="#n-1">See n. 1</ref> below. At the end of the letter Van Gogh included a Dutch translation of a letter he had written to an English clergyman (<ref target="#n-3">see n. 3</ref>). We are not publishing it as a letter in its own right, because it is not Vincent’s original text.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0082" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000085_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000085_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000085_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000085_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000085_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0082" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000085_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000085_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000085_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000085_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000085_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000085_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Welwyn 17 Junij 1876<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Verl. Maandag ben ik van Ramsgate vertrokken <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>naar Londen. Dat is een heele wandeling<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>en toen ik wegging was het geducht warm en <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>dat bleef het tot s’avonds toen ik te Canterbury <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>aankwam. Dien zelfden avond ging ik nog wat <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>verder totdat ik bij een paar groote beuken <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>en iepenboomen kwam bij een kleinen vijver <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>waar ik wat heb gerust. s’Morgens om half 4 <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>begonnen de vogels reeds te zingen op het zien <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>van de morgenschemering en ging ik weer <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>op weg. Het was goed om te loopen toen. <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>S’Middags kwam ik te Chattam,<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> waar men in de <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>verte in de gedeeltelijk overstroomde lage weilanden, <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>met iepenboomen hier en daar, de Theems vol <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>schepen ziet; het is daar geloof ik altijd grijs weer. <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Daar kwam ik een kar tegen die mij een mijl <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>of wat verder bragt, maar toen ging de voerman <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>in eene herberg en ik dacht hij wel lang daar <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>zou blijven<c type="kk">/</c> dus stapte ik verder door en kwam <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>tegen den avond in de zoo welbekende voorsteden <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>van Londen aan en wandelde verder naar de <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>stad door de lange lange “Roads”. Twee dagen ben <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>ik te Londen gebleven en heb nog al eens van <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>het eene einde van de stad naar het andere gedraafd <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>om verschillende menschen te zien, o.a. een dominé <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>aan wien ik schreef<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Hierbij vertaling van den brief<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> ik 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>stuur U dien opdat Gij weten zoudt dat ik met een <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>gevoel van “Vader ik ben het niet waardig!”<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> en “Vader <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wees mij genadig!”<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> begin.─ Mocht ik iets vinden <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>dan zal het waarschijnlijk zijn eene betrekking <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>tusschen predikant en zendeling in, in de voor<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>steden van Londen onder arbeidersmenschen.─ <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Spreek er nog maar tegen geen mensch over<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Theo. Mijn salaris bij Mr. Stokes zal maar heel <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>klein zijn. Waarschijnlijk alleen kost en inwoning <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>en wat vrijen tijd om les te geven of als er geen <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>vrijen tijd kan overschieten hoogstens £ 20 per <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>jaar.─<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar nu verder: Een nacht heb ik gelogeerd bij <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Mr Reid<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> en den volgenden bij Mr. Gladwell waar <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zij zeer, zeer vriendelijk waren. Mr. Gladwell kuste <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>mij s’avonds goeden nacht en dat deed mij goed, <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>mocht het mij gegeven worden ook in vervolg van <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>tijd nog wat vriendschap aan zijn Zoon te <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>bewijzen zoo nu en dan. Ik wilde s’avonds weg <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>naar Welwijn doch letterlijk met geweld hielden zij mij <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>terug vanwege den stortregen. Toen die echter s’morgens <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>tegen 4 uur wat bedaarde ben ik uitgestapt naar Welwyn<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Eerst eene heele wandeling van het eene einde van <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>de stad naar het andere<c type="kk">/</c> zoowat 10 mijl (van 20 <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>minuten gaans)<c type="kp">_</c> s’Middags om 5 uur was ik bij <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de zuster en was wat blij Haar te zien<c type="kp">_</c> Zij ziet er <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>goed uit en gij zoudt even als ik schik hebben in haar kamer <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>met Le vendredi Saint, Le Christ au jardin des oliviers, Mater <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Dolorosa<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> &amp;c. met klimop in plaats van lijsten er om <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>heen.─ Mijn jongen als gij dezen brief aan dien <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>domine leest zegt ge misschien: hij is toch zoo <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>kwaad niet, maar dat is hij wel.─ Denk <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>zoo als hij is echter maar zoo nu en dan eens <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>aan hem<c type="kp">_</c> Een handdruk in gedachten van</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>
<ab>Uw liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab>WelEerw. Heer.</ab>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab>Een predikantszoon die, daar hij moet werken om aan zijn <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>brood te komen, geen geld en geen tijd heeft om de <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>studies aan Kings College<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> bij te houden <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>en behalve dat reeds een paar jaar ouder is dan <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>men gewoonlijk daar komt<c type="kk">/</c> en nu nog niet eens <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>aan de voorbereidende studiën, Latijn en Grieksch <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>is begonnen, zou ondanks dat alles zoo heel <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>graag eene betrekking vinden in verband met <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>de kerk<c type="kk">/</c> al zij het dat de betrekking van predikant <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>die eene opleiding aan de hoogeschool heeft <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>gehad buiten zijn bereik is.─</ab>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mijn Vader is predikant op een dorp in Holland. <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Op mijn 11<hi rend="ss">de</hi> jaar ging ik naar school en bleef daar <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>tot mijn 16<hi rend="ss">de</hi> jaar.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Toen moest ik een beroep <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>kiezen en wist niet wat te kiezen. Doch door bemid<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>deling van een mijner ooms,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> compagnon in de <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>firma Goupil &amp; C<hi rend="ss">o</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> kunsthandelaars en uitgevers <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>van gravures, kreeg ik eene betrekking in zijne <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>zaak te s’Hage. Gedurende 3 jaar was ik in die <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>zaak werkzaam. Van daar ging ik naar Londen <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>om Engelsch te leeren en van daar na 2 jaar <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>naar Parijs. Door verschillende omstandig<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>heden gedrongen heb ik echter de zaak van de <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>Heeren G.&amp;C<hi rend="ss">o</hi> verlaten en ben sedert 2 maanden <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>onderwijzer geweest aan de school van Mr Stokes <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>te Ramsgate.─ Daar echter mijn doel is eene <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>betrekking in verband met de kerk, moet ik nog <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>verder zoeken.─</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoewel ik niet voor de kerk ben opgeleid kan toch <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>misschien mijn verleden leven van reizen, van <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>leven in verschillende landen<c type="kk">/</c> van omgaan met <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>verschillende personen, arm en rijk, godsdienstig <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>en niet godsdienstig, van werk van verschillenden <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>aard, dagen van handenarbeid tusschen de dagen van <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>kantoorwerk &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> door, misschien ook het spreken van <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>verschillende talen<c type="kk">/</c> gedeeltelijk vergoeden dat ik niet ge<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>studeerd heb.─ Maar wat ik nog liever als reden <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>zou opgeven waarom ik mij aan U aanbeveel, dat <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>is de aangeboren liefde voor de kerk en wat de kerk <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>aangaat, die zoo nu en dan wel eens geslapen heeft <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>maar toch telkens weer wakker werd, en als ik het<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>hoewel met een gevoel van groote ongenoegzaam<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>heid en tekortkoming<c type="kk">/</c> mag zeggen: de Liefde tot God <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>en tot de menschen.─ En ook<c type="kk">/</c> als ik aan mijn verloopen <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>leven<anchor n="c" xml:id="note-o-c"/> denk en aan mijns vaders huis in het dorp in <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>Holland<c type="kk">/</c> het gevoel van “Vader ik heb gezondigd tegen <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>den hemel en voor U en ik ben niet meer waardig Uw <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>kind genaamd te worden,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> maak mij tot een van Uwe <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>huurlingen.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> Wees mij arme genadig”.─<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> Toen ik te <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>Londen woonde ging ik wel bij U ter kerk en heb U <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>niet vergeten<c type="kp">_</c> Nu vraag ik U om uwe aanbeveling <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>wanneer ik zoek naar eene betrekking<c type="kk">/</c> en houd <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>Uw vaderlijk oog op mij indien ik zoo’n betrekking <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>mocht vinden. Nog al heel veel was ik aan mij <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>zelven overgelaten, ik geloof dat Uw vaderlijk oog <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>mij goed zou kunnen doen nu:</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>
<ab>The early dew of morning</ab>
                <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>
<ab>has passed away at noon.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>
<ab>U vooruit dank zeggende voor wat U voor mij zoudt <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>willen doen ———</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-30" n="30">waardig!” &lt; waardig!</note>
<note target="l-31" n="31">genadig!” &lt; genadig!</note>
<note target="l-102" n="102">reden &lt; rede</note>
<note target="l-114" n="114">genadig”.─ &lt; genadig.─</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Welwyn, 17 June 1876<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Last Monday I left Ramsgate for London. That’s a long walk indeed,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and when I left it was awfully hot and it remained so until the evening, when I arrived at Canterbury. That same evening I walked a bit further until I came to a couple of large beeches and elms next to a small pond, where I rested for a while. In the morning at half past 3 the birds began to sing upon seeing the morning twilight, and I continued on my way. It was good to walk then. In the afternoon I arrived at Chatham, where, in the distance, past partly flooded, low-lying meadows, with elms here and there, one sees the Thames full of ships. It’s always grey weather there, I think. There I met a cart that brought me a couple of miles further, but then the driver went into an inn and I thought he might stay there a long time, so I walked on and arrived towards evening in the well-known suburbs of London and walked on towards the city down the long, long ‘Roads’. I stayed in London for two days and often ran from one end of the city to the other in order to see various people, including a <rs type="pers" key="1652">minister</rs> to whom I’d written.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> Herewith a translation of the letter,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> I’m 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> sending it to you because you should know that the feeling I have as I start out is ‘Father, I am not worthy!’<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and ‘Father be merciful to me!’<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> Should I find anything it will probably be a situation somewhere between minister and missionary, in the suburbs of London among working folk. Don’t speak about this to anyone, Theo. My salary at <rs type="pers" key="764">Mr Stokes</rs>’s will be very small. Probably only board and lodging and some free time in which to teach, or if there’s no free time, at most 20 pounds a year.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But to continue: I spent one night at <rs type="pers" key="184">Mr Reid</rs>’s<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> and the next at <rs type="pers" key="396">Mr Gladwell</rs>’s, where they were very, very kind. Mr Gladwell kissed me good-night and that did me good, may it be granted me sometime in the future to show some more friendship to his <rs type="pers" key="394">son</rs> every now and then. I wanted to leave for Welwyn that evening, but they literally held me back by force because of the pouring rain. However, when it had let up somewhat, around 4 in the morning, I set out for Welwyn. First a long walk from one end of the city to the other, something like 10 miles (each taking 20 minutes). In the afternoon at 5, I was with our <rs type="pers" key="412">sister</rs> and was very glad to see her. She looks well and you would be as pleased with her room as I am, with ‘Good Friday’, ‘Christ in the Garden of Olives’, ‘Mater Dolorosa’<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> &amp;c. with ivy around them instead of frames. Old boy, when you read my letter to that minister you’ll perhaps say: he’s<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-t-b"/> not so bad after all, though in fact he is. Think of him as he is, however, every once in a while. A handshake in thought from</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab rend="indent">
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab>Rev. Sir.</ab>
<ab>A clergyman’s son, who, because he must work to earn a living, has no money and no time to study at King’s College,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and who, besides that, is already a couple of years older than is usual for someone starting there, and has not even begun on the preparatory studies of Latin and Greek, would, in spite of everything, dearly like to find a situation connected with the church, even though the position of a clergyman who has had college training is beyond his reach.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">My <rs type="pers" key="526">father</rs> is a clergyman in a village in Holland. When I was 11 years old I started going to school and stayed there until I was 16.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> At that time I had to choose a profession and didn’t know what to choose. Through the offices of one of my <rs type="pers" key="423">uncle</rs>s,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> an associate in the firm of Goupil &amp; Co., art dealers and publishers of engravings, I was given a position in his branch at The Hague. I worked for the firm for 3 years. From there I went to London to learn English, and after 2 years from there to Paris. Forced by various circumstances to quit the firm, however, I left Messrs G.&amp;Co. and have since taught for 2 months at <rs type="pers" key="764">Mr Stokes</rs>’s school at Ramsgate. As my goal is a situation connected with the church, however, I must look further. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Although I have not been trained for the church, perhaps my past life of travelling, living in various countries, associating with a variety of people, rich and poor, religious and not religious, working at a variety of jobs, days of manual labour in between days of office work &amp;c., perhaps also my speaking various languages, will compensate in part for my lack of formal training. But what I should prefer to give as my reason for commending myself to you is my innate love of the church and that which concerns the church, which has at times lain dormant, though it awakened repeatedly, and – if I may say so, despite feelings of great inadequacy and shortcoming – the Love of God and of humankind. And also, when I think of my past life and of my <rs type="pers" key="526">father</rs>’s house in that Dutch village, a feeling of ‘Father, I have sinned against heaven, and in thy sight, and am no more worthy to be called thy son,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> make me as one of thy hired servants.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> Be merciful to me.’<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> When I was living in London I often attended your church and I have not forgotten you. Now I am asking you for a recommendation in my search for a situation, and to keep a fatherly eye on me should I find such a situation. I have been left very much to myself; I believe that your fatherly eye could do me good, now that</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>The early dew of morning</ab>
<ab>has passed away at noon.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Thanking you in advance for whatever you may be willing to do for me...</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This letter was written when Van Gogh was visiting his sister <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>. On the same day Anna sent a short note to Theo, in which she wrote, among other things, ‘You can imagine how wonderful it is for me to see Vincent again’, and ‘Vincent is busy showing prints to the children’. See <hi rend="ital">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 1, p. 61, no. 69a (FR b769).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>It is c. 120 km from Ramsgate to London.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Chattam: Read Chatham.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Vincent probably sent this letter to <rs type="pers" key="1652">Edmund Henry Fisher</rs>, the vicar of St Mark’s in Kennington. At that time this parish also had four curates, who were technically also ‘Reverends’: Robert Herbert Fair; Alfred Fairbrother; Alfred Lionel Lambert and Franklen Llewelyn (<hi rend="ital">Crockford’s Clerical Directory</hi> 1877). In <ref target="let092.xml#l-39">letter 92, ll. 39-47</ref>, Van Gogh says that he used to attend this church often (when he was living with the Parkers). In the present letter <ref target="#l-114">(ll. 114-116)</ref>, he says (in the letter addressed to the minister): ‘I often attended your church’. See also Bailey 1990, pp. 80-81, 88.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This letter is included at the end of the present letter.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="8" v="8">Matt. 8:8</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="7" v="6">Luke 7:6</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="15" v="21">Luke 15:21</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>The wording of this prayer recurs in a number of psalms; cf. also <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="18" v="13">Luke 18:13</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>The financial repercussions of Vincent’s vocational choice and the nature of his new situation was a matter of concern to <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, who wrote the following to Theo on 1 July 1876: ‘<rs type="pers" key="764">Mr Stokes</rs> doesn’t want to give him a salary, but instead some free time in which to teach. He doesn’t know how to come by pupils, though. He imagines that Mr Stokes would be willing to let him go. If he senses this even more strongly, he will even take the initiative himself. So the situation is not clear. If he <hi rend="ital">truly</hi> has a passion for the church or evangelizing and is really serious about it, I should think that he could start his studies here and we could see if funds could be obtained, but it would take at least 8 years. For that matter, it would perhaps be best for him to look either there or here, but possibly better here, for a position as a bookkeeper, or an office clerk or shop assistant. He continually makes journeys lasting hours and I fear that his appearance will begin to suffer from it and he’ll become even less presentable’ (FR b2756).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Presumably <rs type="pers" key="184">George R. Reid</rs>; <ref target="let082.xml#n-7">see letter 82, n. 7.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
  <ab>Three photographs of paintings by <rs type="pers" key="983">Paul Delaroche</rs>; for <rs type="ill" key="1743">
                            <hi rend="ital">Good Friday</hi>
                        </rs> and <rs type="ill" key="1745">
                            <hi rend="ital">Mater Dolorosa</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let054.xml#n-14;">see letter 54, n. 14;</ref> the third is <hi rend="ital">Le Christ au Jardin des oliviers</hi> (Christ on the Mount of Olives) (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil). <rs type="ill" key="1770">Ill. 1770</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
                <note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-t-b">
                    <ab>‘He’ refers to Van Gogh, not to the minister.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>King’s College is one of the oldest colleges of the University of London.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>After attending elementary school, Van Gogh attended a secondary school in Zevenbergen from October 1864 until August 1866 (<ref target="let076.xml#n-4">see letter 76, n. 4</ref>), after which he attended the Hogere Burgerschool (HBS) (high school) Willem <hi rend="sc">ii</hi> at Tilburg from September 1866 until March 1868. Cf. Meyers 1989, pp. 64-81; and H.F.J.M. van den Eerenbeemt, <hi rend="ital">De onbekende Vincent van Gogh. Leren en tekenen in Tilburg, 1866-1868</hi>. Tilburg 1972, pp. 5-26.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Uncle <rs type="pers" key="423">Vincent (Cent) van Gogh</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="c" xml:id="n-c" target="#note-o-c">
<ab>Meaning: ‘my life up to now’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="15" v="21">Luke 15:21</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="15" v="19">Luke 15:19</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="18" v="13">Luke 18:13</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
  <ab>Passage from the hymn ‘Tell me the old, old story’ from the book <rs type="lit" key="69">
                            <hi rend="ital">The old, old story</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="99">Arabella Catherine Hankey</rs>; <ref target="let082.xml#n-1">see letter 82, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>