<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Friday, 27 July 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let123"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">123</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">103</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">123</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Friday, 27 July 1877</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Friday, 27 July 1877.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b122 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 27 Julij 1877’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0122" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000131_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000131_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000131_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000131_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0122" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000131_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000131_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000131_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000131_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam 27 Julij 1877</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Dank voor Uw laatsten brief, van huis hoorde ik dat Gij reeds bij Mauve zijt <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>geweest,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> dat zal wel een goeden dag zijn geweest, bij gelegenheid hoor ik er <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>zeker wel eens van.─ Hierbij eene bijdrage voor uwe verzameling, n.l. drie <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>lithographiën naar Bosboom<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> en twee door J. Weissenbruch,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> vond ze dezen <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>morgen bij een boekenjood.─ Zou dat eene naar Bosboom de kerk te Scheveningen <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>zijn? het andere is de Groote kerk te Breda<c type="kk">/</c> het derde naar zijne Sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> die op <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>de groote tentoonstelling te Parijs geweest is. Die twee naar Weissenbruch troffen <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>mij ─ misschien hebt gij ze al maar mogelijk ook wel niet. Ga toch maar <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>door met het verzamelen van dergelijke prenten en van boeken ook.</ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tegenwoordig verzamel ik latijnsche en grieksche themas en allerlei geschriften <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>over geschiedenis enz.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Ben aan een over de Kerkhervorming bezig dat nogal <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>lang wordt.─</ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Sprak onlangs een jongmensch die pas zijn admissie examen voor de Leidsche <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>hoogeschool had gedaan met gelukkigen uitslag ─ gemakkelijk is het niet<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>hij vertelde mij wat hem gevraagd was, maar heb toch maar goeden moed<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>met Gods hulp zal ik er door komen en door de volgende examens <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>ook. Mendes heeft mij alle hoop gegeven dat wij aan het einde van drie <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>maanden zoo ver zullen komen als hij zich had voorgesteld indien <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>het goed ging.─<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> Toch zijn Grieksche lessen in het hartje van Amsterdam<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>in het hartje van de jodenbuurt op een zeer warmen en drukkenden <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>zomermiddag, met het gevoel dat vele moeielijke examens die door <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>zeer geleerde en listige Heeren professoren zullen worden afgenomen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>boven het hoofd hangen<c type="kk">/</c> wel eens meer benaauwd dan eene wandeling <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>aan het strand of in de Brabantsche korenvelden, die nu wel mooi zullen zijn, <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>op zulk een dag.─ Maar wij moeten maar door alles “voortstreven” <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>zoo als Oom Jan zegt.─</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Een paar dagen geleden vielen bij de Kattenburger brug een paar kinderen in <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>het water. Oom zag het en kommandeerde de sloep van de Makasser die <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>hier in het dok ligt<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> Er werd een jongetje opgehaald; met twee <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>scheepsdokters die Oom er naar toe zond ben ik met de mannen die het jongske droegen in eene <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Apotheek geweest en zijn alle pogingen in het werk gesteld om het kind <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>weer bij te brengen doch dat is niet gelukt. Terwijl <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>werd het herkend door den vader die op de werf stoker is en is het <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>lijkje in eene wollen deken naar huis gebragt. Nog <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>anderhalf uur lang heeft men gezocht<c type="kk">/</c> meenende er nog een meiske ook <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>was ingevallen, doch dat schijnt gelukkig zoo niet te zijn.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> s’Avonds <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>ben ik nog eens naar de menschen terug geweest<c type="kk">/</c> het was toen reeds donker <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>in huis, het lijkje lag zoo stil in een zijkamertje op een bed, het was zoo’n lief jongske<c type="kp">_</c> Er was groote droefheid, <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>dat kind was het licht van dat huis als het ware, en dat licht was nu uitgedoofd<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Al uit zich de smart bij ruwe menschen ook ruw en zonder waardigheid<c type="kk">/</c> zooals bij de Moeder onder anderen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>toch gevoelt men in zulk een klaaghuis veel<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> en die indruk bleef mij den geheelen avond toen <lb n="43a" xml:id="l-43a"/>ik nog eene wandeling maakte bij.─</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">ll. Zondag morgen deed ik een mooien togt<c type="kk">/</c> nl. eerst naar de vroegpreek<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Posth. Meyes in de Noorderkerk<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> toen naar het Bickerseiland<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> waar ik op den <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>dijk langs het IJ wandelde tot het weer kerktijd was en toen naar de Eilandskerk <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>waar Oom Stricker preekte.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Zoo gaat de tijd voort en snel ook<c type="kk">/</c> wij <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>zijn reeds weder bijna aan het einde der week.─</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoe gaat het U kerel, zoo heel dikwijls, dagelijks, denk ik aan U<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">God helpe ons om al worstelende boven te blijven,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> het is goed Gij U aan goede <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>artisten aansluit, ook ik klem mij nog zoo aan de gedachtenis van <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>velen hunner vast. Overwin het kwade door het goede<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> staat er en daar <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>kan men naar zoeken ─ en daartoe kan God helpen en ons de dagen <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>dragelijk maken met veel goeds er tusschen door en ons voor al te groot zelfverwijt bewaren.─</ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toen Oom Jan dien middag waarop dat ongeluk gebeurde de sloep en de dokters <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>kommandeerde om te gaan helpen<c type="kk">/</c> zag ik Hem in Zijn element.─ </ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu moet ik aan mijn werk maar moet toch nog dit blaadje vol <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>schrijven.─ Anna is te Leiden zoo als Gij zeker weet en komt <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>dezer dagen met onzen aanstaanden Zwager<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> naar hier, <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ben zeer verlangend naar hen, Pa schreef zoo opgewekt over ll<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Zondag toen zij te Etten waren en het was alles goed in zijne <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>oogen, en die zien wel juist, dus laat ons hetgeen <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>de zuster ontmoette ook maar als een zegen aan ons huis <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>beschouwen, waarin wij allen deelen, als één lid zich verblijdt dan <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>verblijden zich al de leden mede.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab rend="indent">De volgende week of misschien reeds morgen komen Oom en Tante <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>Pompe<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> hier logeeren en ook Fanny en Bet s’Graeuwen,<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>het is lang geleden sedert ik een hunner zag.─</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ben s’morgens nog al eens vroeg op en als de zon dan opgaat <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>over de werf en eenigen tijd later het werkvolk komt is het een heerlijk <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>gezigt uit het raam en zou ik U wel eens hier wenschen.─ Zou ik later <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>op zoo’n morgen nog eens zitten werken aan eene preek over <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>“Hij doet Zijne zon opgaan over boozen en goeden”<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/> of over <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>“Ontwaak gij die slaapt en sta op uit de dooden en Christus zal over U lichten”<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> of over <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>“Het is goed den Heer te prijzen in den morgenstond”<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> en “het is den <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>oogen goed de zon te aanschouwen”<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/> ─ ik hoop het.─</ab>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is toch alsof de zon nergens zoo mooi schijnt als in <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>eene pastorie of in eene kerk. Het is heerlijk om aan “de geschriften” <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>te werken zoo s’morgens vroeg.─</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als Gij tijd en een postzegel en papier hebt schrijf dan weer eens spoedig, Oom <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>Jan laat U groeten, daar in de duinen moet het dien avond dien <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>gij beschrijft wel goed geweest zijn. Bij Oom Cor in den winkel zag ik <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>dezer dagen Les Evangiles van Bida<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="22" xml:id="note-o-22"/> wat is dat schoon<c type="kk">/</c> wat moet het <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>heerlijk zijn zulk een Christen werkman<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-o-23"/> te zijn, maar het is niet om <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>te zeggen hoe mooi het is, <hi rend="ital">dat</hi> is <hi rend="ital">het</hi>
                    <anchor n="24" xml:id="note-o-24"/> weer, er is zeer veel <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>in dat werk dat aan Rembrandt doet denken. En nu een handdruk <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>in gedachten en van harte het beste U toegewenscht en geloof mij steeds </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab>Uw zoo liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-74" n="74">lichten” &lt; lichten</note>
<note target="l-75" n="75">“Het &lt; Het</note>
<note target="l-75" n="75">morgenstond” &lt; morgenstond</note>
<note target="l-75" n="75">“het &lt; het</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam, 27 July 1877</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Thanks for your last letter, I heard from home that you’ve already been to <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>’s,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> that was undoubtedly a good day, I’ll certainly hear about it sometime, when the opportunity arises. Herewith a contribution for your collection, namely three lithographs after <rs type="pers" key="884">Bosboom</rs>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and two by <rs type="pers" key="235">J. Weissenbruch</rs>,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> found them this morning at a Jewish bookseller’s. Is that one after Bosboom the church in Scheveningen? The other is the Grote Kerk in Breda, the third after his painting that was at the large exhibition in Paris. Those two after Weissenbruch moved me – perhaps you already have them, but then again possibly not. Do go on collecting such prints, and books too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m now collecting Latin and Greek themes and all kinds of writings on history and so on.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> Am working on one on the Reformation that’s getting rather long.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Recently spoke to a young man who had just done his entrance examination for the Leiden college with a good result – it isn’t easy, he told me what they asked him, but I do keep up my courage, and with God’s help I’ll pass them, and the following examinations as well. <rs type="pers" key="520">Mendes</rs> has given me every reason to believe that at the end of three months we’ll be as far as he imagined we would be if everything went well.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Still, Greek lessons in the heart of Amsterdam, in the heart of the Jewish quarter on a very warm and oppressive summer afternoon, with the feeling hanging over me that many difficult examinations will have to be taken, set by very learned and cunning professors, are rather more oppressive than a walk on the beach or in the Brabant wheatfields, which will certainly be beautiful now, on a day like that. But we must ‘strive on’ through everything, as <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan</rs> says.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">A couple of days ago a couple of children fell into the water near the Kattenburg bridge. <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle</rs> saw it and commandeered the sloop of the Makasser that is in dock here.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> A little boy was pulled out; I went along with two ship’s doctors whom Uncle had sent over, and the men carrying the boy into a chemist’s shop made every effort to resuscitate the child, but to no avail. In the meantime it was recognized by the father, who’s a stoker at the dockyard, and the little body was taken home in a woollen blanket. The search went on for an hour and a half, as it was thought that a girl had fallen in as well, though happily that seems not to be the case.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> In the evening I went back to see the people, it was then already dark in the house, the little body lay so still on a bed in a side room, he was such a sweet little boy. There was great sorrow, that child was the light of that house, as it were, and that light had now been put out. Even though coarse people express their grief in a coarse way and without dignity, as the mother did, among others, still, one feels a great deal in such a house of mourning,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> and the impression stayed with me the whole evening when I took a walk.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Last Sunday morning I made a nice excursion, namely first to the early sermon, the <rs type="pers" key="575">Rev. Posthumus Meijjes</rs> in the Noorderkerk,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> then to Bickerseiland,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> where I walked on the dyke along the IJ until it was time for church again, and then to the Eilandskerk where <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle Stricker</rs> preached.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> Thus the time passes, and quickly too, already we’re almost at the end of the week again.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">How are you, old chap? So very often, daily, do I think of you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">God help us, struggling, to stay on top,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> it is good that you associate with good artists; I, too, still cling to the memory of many of them. Overcome evil with good,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> it is written, and one can seek to do it – and to this end God can help and make our days bearable with much good in the meantime, and preserve us from too much self-reproach.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">When <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan</rs> commandeered the sloop and the doctors to go and help on the afternoon that accident happened, I saw him in his element.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now I must get to work, though I still have to fill this page. <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> is in Leiden, as you surely know, and will come here one of these days with our future <rs type="pers" key="413">brother-in-law</rs>,<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> am looking forward to seeing them very much, <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> wrote so cheerfully about last Sunday when they were in Etten and everything was good in his eyes, and they see rightly, so let us view what has happened to our sister as a blessing on our house, in which we all share; if one member be glad, let all the members be glad with her.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Next week, or perhaps even tomorrow, <rs type="pers" key="502 579">Uncle and Aunt Pompe</rs>
                    <anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> are coming to stay here, and also <rs type="pers" key="438 439">Fanny and Bet ’s Graeuwen</rs>,<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> it’s been a long time since I’ve seen any of them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Am quite often up rather early in the morning, and when the sun rises over the yard and the workers come a while later it’s a wonderful sight from the window, and I should wish to have you here. Will I later be working on such a morning on a sermon on ‘He maketh His sun to rise on the evil and on the good’,<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> or on ‘Awake thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ shall give thee light’,<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> or on ‘It is a good thing to praise the Lord in the morning’<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> and ‘It is a pleasant thing for the eyes to behold the sun’<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> – I hope so.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">All the same, it seems that the sun never shines so beautifully as it does in a parsonage or in a church. It’s wonderful to work on ‘the writings’ early in the morning.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you have the time and a stamp and paper, then write again soon. <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan</rs> sends you his regards, that evening you described there in the dunes must have been pleasant. In <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs>’s shop I recently saw The Gospels by <rs type="pers" key="856">Bida</rs>,<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> how beautiful it is, how wonderful it must be to be a Christian labourer<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/> like that, but it’s impossible to put into words how beautiful it is, <hi rend="ital">that’s</hi> <hi rend="ital">it</hi>
                    <anchor n="24" xml:id="note-t-24"/> again, there is much in that work that reminds one of <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>. And now a handshake in thought, and I sincerely wish you the best, and believe me ever</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your most loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Theo had gone to see <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> on Saturday, 21 July (FR b2546).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>As emerges from Van Gogh’s description further on, these three lithographs were taken from <hi rend="ital">Kunstkronijk</hi>. The first was made by <rs type="pers" key="1557">Carel Christiaan Antony Last</rs> after <rs type="pers" key="884">Johannes Bosboom</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">Gezicht op de kerk te Scheveningen </hi>(View of the church at Scheveningen), in <hi rend="ital">Kunstkronijk</hi> 5 (1844-1845), p. 20. <rs type="ill" key="1840">Ill. 1840</rs>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Bosboom made various ‘portraits’ of the church at Breda. Several reproductions of these works appeared in <hi rend="ital">Kunstkronijk</hi>, including the lithograph <hi rend="ital">Kerk te Breda met de tombe der graven Engelbrecht <hi rend="sc">i</hi> en Jan van Nassau</hi> (Church at Breda with the tomb of the counts Engelbrecht <hi rend="sc">i</hi> and Jan of Nassau) by <rs type="pers" key="1606">Frederik Hendrik Weissenbruch Dzn.</rs> (<hi rend="ital">Kunstkronijk</hi> 19 (1858), facing p. 46). <rs type="ill" key="1841">Ill. 1841</rs>. Cf. Marius and Martin 1917, pp. 123, 127, 134, 141, 144-147.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Bosboom had three works at the Paris World Exhibition of 1855: Monks of the order of Saint Francis, singing a ‘Te Deum’; The Lord’s Supper room in a Protestant church and Consistory room at Nijmegen. See exhib. cat. 1855, p. 156, cat. nos. 1526-1528. Only the first was reproduced as a lithograph, <hi rend="ital">Franciskaner monniken het Te Deum zingende</hi> (Franciscan monks singing the Te Deum) by  Frederik Hendrik Weissenbruch, in <hi rend="ital">Kunstkronijk</hi> 17 (1856), no. 3, so this must have been the one Vincent sent. <rs type="ill" key="1842">Ill. 1842</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
  <ab>In Theo’s scrapbook the lithograph <rs type="ill" key="461">
                            <hi rend="ital">Molen langs de Trekvaart</hi>
                        </rs> (Mill by the Trekvaart) by <rs type="pers" key="1443">Jan Hendrik Weissenbruch</rs> (<ref target="let011.xml#n-16">see letter 11, n. 16</ref>) is followed by Jan Hendrik Weissenbruch’s <hi rend="ital">Landschap met een bootje </hi>(Landscape with a boat) and on p. 3 a <hi rend="ital">Landschap met kerk en molens, gezien vanaf een duin</hi> (Landscape with church and windmills, seen from a dune), the last-mentioned lithographed by <rs type="pers" key="1191">Jacobus Jan  van der Maaten</rs>; p. 5 contains the lithograph by <rs type="pers" key="1606">Frederik Hendrik Weissenbruch Dzn</rs>. after <rs type="pers" key="235">Jan Weissenbruch</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Het hofje aan de Nieuwe Haven te ’s-Gravenhage </hi>(The ‘hofje’ at the Nieuwe Haven in The Hague) (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, t*1488). <rs type="ill" key="1652">Ill. 1652</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="1653">Ill. 1653</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="1654">Ill. 1654</rs>. (See also <ref target="let013.xml#n-2">letter 13, n. 2</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
  <ref target="let121.xml">See letter 121</ref> regarding Vincent’s collection of historical texts. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>The situation was in fact less promising. Two weeks later <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> intimated in a letter to Theo that he was pessimistic about the duration and financing of the preparations: ‘Vincent’s study for the entrance examinations will need to take at least 2, if not 3, years, but provision was made for a test to see whether he was suited to the study, and that seems to be the case. We should hope to find the means necessary’ (FR b2549, 6 August 1877). <rs type="pers" key="401">Lies</rs> wrote to her brother optimistically: ‘How wonderful for <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs> that Vincent’s master has assured him that he is suited for the study’ (FR b2550, 12 August 1877).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>The accident happened on Wednesday, 25 July in the afternoon, according to a report in the <hi rend="ital">Geïllustreerd Politie Nieuws</hi> of 28 July 1877. See Groot and De Vries 1990, pp. 36-37.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>The same newspaper article reported: ‘It proved impossible to save the other child. The body has not yet been recovered.’</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Eccl" chap="7" vr="2-4">Eccl. 7:2-4</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>On Sunday, 22 July, <rs type="pers" key="575">Jeremias Posthumus Meijjes</rs> preached the 7 a.m. sermon in the Noorderkerk.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Various shipyards were located on Bickerseiland, north-west of the city centre (now on the Westerdok). </ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>The Eilandskerk – built on Bickersgracht, at the edge of Bickerseiland – first opened its doors on 9 December 1736; it was demolished in 1950. On that Sunday morning <rs type="pers" key="318">J.P. Stricker</rs> conducted the 10 a.m. service at the Eilandskerk.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>An allusion to the saying ‘I struggle and emerge victorious’, which in the Latin version – ‘Luctor et emergo’ – makes up part of the arms of the province of Zeeland.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rom" chap="12" v="21">Rom. 12:21</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="413">Joan Marius van Houten</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>Here Van Gogh offers a variation on <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Cor" chap="12" v="26">1 Cor. 12:26</bibleref>, ‘And whether one member suffer, all the members suffer with it; or one member be honoured, all the members rejoice with it.’</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="579 502">Uncle Abraham Pompe and Aunt Elisabeth Pompe-Van Gogh</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="438">Francina (Fanny) ’s Graeuwen</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="439">Elisabeth (Bet) Hubertha ’s Graeuwen</rs>, both daughters of Commander in the Dutch navy <rs type="pers" key="93">Abraham Anthonie ’s Graeuwen</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="86">Geertruida van Gogh</rs>, a sister of Mr van Gogh. Fanny (a teacher) and Bet were living at the time with their parents in Helvoirt.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="5" v="45">Matt. 5:45</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>
                        <vg:bibleref book="Eph" chap="5" v="14">Eph. 5:14</vg:bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="92" v="3">Ps. 92:3</bibleref> (in <hi rend="ital">KJ</hi> <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="92" v="2">Ps. 92:2</bibleref>): ‘To shew forth thy lovingkindness in the morning’ and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Chron" chap="23" v="30">1 Chron. 23:30</bibleref>, ‘And to stand every morning to thank and praise the Lord’; presumably Van Gogh was quoting from another source.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Eccl" chap="11" v="7">Eccl. 11:7</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="22" xml:id="n-22" target="#note-t-22">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="856">Alexandre Bida</rs> designed the illustrations for the deluxe folio volume <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="476">Les Saints Evangiles</rs>
                        </hi>. Translated by <rs type="pers" key="542">Bossuet</rs>. 2 vols. Paris 1873; they were made into etchings by various artists under the supervision of <rs type="pers" key="1547">Pierre Edmond Alexandre Hédouin</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="23" xml:id="n-23" target="#note-t-23">
    <ab>For the concept of the ‘Christian Workman’, which is derived from the text <rs type="lit" key="125">
                            <hi rend="ital">De christen-werkman als zendeling</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="456">Ottho Gerhard Heldring</rs>, <ref target="let109.xml#n-15">see letter 109, n. 15.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="24" xml:id="n-24" target="#note-t-24">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="323">Anton Mauve</rs>’s motto.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>