<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 3 January 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let196"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">196</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">167</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">196</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Tuesday, 3 January 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 3 January 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mauve gives Van Gogh advice <ref target="let192.xml">(192)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b188 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh has meanwhile installed himself in a new studio, which he began renting on 1 January <ref target="#l-8">(l. 8)</ref>. The New Year’s greetings to Theo <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref> suggest that the letter was written at the very beginning of the month, since the following letter dates from 5 or 6 January. Possible dates are therefore 2, 3 or 4 January 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0188" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000213_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000213_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000213_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0188" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000213_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000213_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000213_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000213_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000213_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000213_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste broer,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Even kom ik je gelukwenschen met het nieuwe <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>jaar<c type="kk">/</c> moge het in alle opzigten een goed <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>jaar voor je zijn en egoistisch voeg ik er <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>bij<c type="kk">/</c> voor mij ook.–</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu mij aangaande<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zal je misschien niet <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>onaangenaam zijn te vernemen dat ik <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>me heb geinstalleerd in een eigen atelier. <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Een kamer &amp; alkoof, het licht is helder genoeg <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>want het raam is groot (dubbel zoo groot als een <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>gewoon venster) maar ’t is zoo ongeveer op ’t zuiden. <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Meubels heb ik in den echten “<hi rend="ital">rijks</hi>veldwachtersstijl”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>zooals gij zegt, genomen maar ik geloof <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>dat de mijnen meer direkt van dat allooi <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>zijn dan de Uwen ofschoon gij het woord hebt <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>uitgedacht. (ik heb b.v. echte keukenstoelen <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>en een echte stevige keukentafel.)</ab>
                <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mauve heeft me wat voorgeschoten<c type="kk">/</c> f<c type="kp">_</c> 100.- <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>om het te huren<c type="kk">/</c> te meubileeren &amp; om het <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>raam &amp; licht in orde te maken. Dat is me wel <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>een zekere zorg<c type="kk">/</c> ge zult dit begrijpen maar <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>enfin<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is de eenige solide manier <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>en op den duur is ’t veel goedkooper een <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>eigen gedoentetje te hebben dan altijd maar <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>weer geld voor een quasi gemeubeleerde kamer <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>te geven.</ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu ik heb heel wat gescharrel gehad voor ik <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>het vond en voor ik de meubels zóó schikken kon <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>dat het met ’t geen ik had er voor uitkwam. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Maar nu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik een echt eigen atelier <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>en ben er erg mee in mijn schik.–</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik had niet durven hopen dat het reeds zoo spoedig <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>zoo zou loopen maar nu vind ik het best <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>en gij ook hoop ik.–</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoor eens, ge weet er alles van, mijn <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>uitgaven zullen wat meer zijn dan te Etten <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>maar laat ons zien er flink door te <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>scharrelen. M. geeft veel hoop dat ik spoedig <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>aan ’t verdienen zal raken.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu ik in een eigen atelier zit zal dit alligt een <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>niet ongunstigen indruk maken op sommige <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>personen die tot nu toe dachten dat ik zoo maar <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>wat liefhebberde<c type="kk">/</c> rentenierde of lanterfante.–</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoop dat gij dezer dagen me wat zult kunnen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>zenden. Als ik iets hoog noodig had en ik <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>vroeg het aan Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> hij zou ’t mij niet weigeren <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>maar hij heeft nu voorloopig waarachtig genoeg <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>gedaan. Het overkomt ieder mensch zoo <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>eens in zijn leven dat hij zich eens installeeren <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>moet en ofschoon ik aanvankelijk tegen het gevoel <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>van schuld opzag<c type="kk">/</c> ik voel toch dat het zoo <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>beter is.–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het plan is dat ik geregeld naar model <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>blijf werken. dat is duur &amp; toch is het <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>het goedkoopste.</ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
    <ab rend="indent">De Bock valt me niet mee op den duur<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>er is iets van een te zwakke ruggegraat in <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>hem en hij wordt kwaad als men hem <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>sommige dingen zegt die toch maar ’t a<c type="kp">_</c>b.c. <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>zijn. Hij heeft gevoel voor landschap<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hij weet er een soort charme soms in <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>te brengen (o<c type="kp">_</c>a. in een groot Sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> dat hij <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>nu onder handen heeft)<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> maar ik vind toch <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>geen houvast aan hem. Hij is te vaag <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>en te ijl – du coton filé trop fin.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>Zijn schilderijen zijn een schaduw van een <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>impressie en die impressie is mijns inziens <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>ter nauwernood de moeite waard om zoo dikwijls <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>gerepeteerd te worden.</ab>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zal niet heel druk omgaan met de <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>schilders. Mauve vind ik iederen dag <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>knapper en degelijker. en wat wil ik meer. <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Theo ik zal me evenwel een beetje beter <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>moeten gaan kleeden nu<c type="kp">_</c> Ik weet nu zoo <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>de directie die ik uitmoet en kan daar rond <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>voor uitkomen<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal dus den omgang met <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>menschen niet vermijden – ook niet erg <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>de lui achtervolgen. M. &amp; Jet laten U <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>groeten, à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb nog een boel te doen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="80*" xml:id="l-80s"/>
<ab>t. à. t.</ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-40" n="40">een &lt; ee</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear brother,</ab>
<ab>I’m just writing to wish you a happy New Year, may it be a good year for you in every way and, I add egoistically, for myself as well.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now as to me, it will perhaps not be disagreeable for you to learn that I’m installed in a studio of my own. A room and alcove, the light is bright enough, for the window is large (twice as large as an ordinary window), and it’s more or less facing south. I’ve bought furniture in true ‘village constable style’,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> as you call it, but I think that mine resembles it much more than yours, although it was you who coined the phrase. (I have real kitchen chairs, for example, and a really sturdy kitchen table.)</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> lent me some money, 100 guilders, to rent it, furnish it and get the window and light fixed up. This is rather a worry, you’ll understand, but anyhow it’s the only sensible way, and in the long run it’s much less expensive having one’s own things than always spending money on yet another semi-furnished room.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve had a great deal of difficulty, what with finding it and then arranging the furniture in such a way that I could manage with what I had. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> But now, old chap, I have a real studio of my own and am terribly pleased with it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hadn’t dared hope that things would go this quickly, but now I think it superb and hope that you do too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Listen, you know it all, my expenses will be slightly higher than they were in Etten, but let’s put our shoulders to the wheel. <rs type="pers" key="323">M.</rs> gives me much hope that I’ll soon be earning something.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now that I’m in my own studio, it will most probably make a not unfavourable impression on some people who until now have thought that I’m merely dabbling, idling or loafing about.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hope that you’ll be able to send me something one of these days. If I needed something urgently and asked it of <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>, he wouldn’t refuse me, but for the time being he’s really done enough. It happens to everyone at some point in life that he has to set himself up in his own house, and although at first I couldn’t face being in debt, I do feel that it’s better this way. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The plan is that I continue to work regularly from a model. That’s expensive, and yet it’s the cheapest way.</ab>
    <ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="868">De Bock</rs> ultimately disappoints me, there’s something spineless about him, and he gets angry if one says certain things to him that are actually only the ABCs. He has a feeling for landscape, he sometimes manages to imbue them with a kind of charm (including the large painting he’s now working on),<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> but in himself there’s nothing to get hold of. He’s too vague and too insubstantial – cotton too finely woven.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> His paintings are a shadow of an impression, and in my opinion that impression is scarcely worth repeating so often.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I won’t associate very much with the painters. I find <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> more capable and more solid every day. And what more do I want? Theo, I’ll have to start dressing a bit better now, though. Now I know more or less the direction I must take, and can stand up for it openly, so I won’t avoid contact with people – also not follow them too much. <rs type="pers" key="321 323">M. and Jet</rs> send you their regards, adieu, I still have a lot to do, believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The term ‘village constable style’ characterizes the sober respectability of the furniture.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
    <ab>This description is too general to be linked to a specific painting by <rs type="pers" key="868">De Bock</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
                <note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
                    <ab>Said about the character Tillet in <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="421">La Maison Nucingen</rs>
                        </hi> (1838) by <rs type="pers" key="519">Honoré de Balzac</rs>. See <hi rend="ital">Oeuvres complètes</hi>. Paris 1879, vol 8, p. 605.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>