<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Laken, on or about Wednesday, 13 and Friday, 15 or Saturday, 16 November 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let148"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">148</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">126</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">147</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Laken</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Wednesday, 13 and Friday, 15 or Saturday, 16 November 1878</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:physDesc>
                        <vg:decoration>
                            <vg:decoList xml:id="sketches">
                                <vg:decoItem n="A" xml:id="sketch-1">
                                    <vg:decoDesc>
<p>
      <hi rend="ital">Café Au charbonnage</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="8">F Juv. XXXI / JH Juv. 9</rs>), enclosed sketch. Beside the café is a shed where, according to the sideboard ‘Charbons / Cokes &amp;c.’ coal and similar fuels were sold.</p>
                                    </vg:decoDesc>
                                </vg:decoItem>
                            </vg:decoList>
                        </vg:decoration>
                    </vg:physDesc>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Laken, on or about Wednesday, 13 and Friday, 15 or Saturday, 16 November 1878.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b146 V/1962 (sheet 1) and inv. no. d293 V/1970 (sheet 2)</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Laeken Nov. 1878’. The postscript was written after a decision had been made about Van Gogh staying on at the training college: ‘I kept this letter for a couple of days. 15 Nov. has passed’ (<ref target="#l-98">ll. 98-99</ref> and <ref target="#l-159">l. 159</ref>). The letter itself, which was written on the evening of a day Vincent and Theo spent together <ref target="#l-1">(l. 1)</ref>, therefore dates from ‘a couple of days’ before 15 November. In <ref target="#l-60">ll. 60-61</ref> Vincent expresses the wish that Theo <hi rend="ital">will have</hi> spent Sunday in Etten as well, so Sunday, 17 November had not yet gone by.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0146" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000154_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000154_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000154_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000154_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000154_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0146" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000154_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000154_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000154_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000154_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000154_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000154_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="d 0293" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001661_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001661_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001661_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001661_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
        <surface n="d 0293 V/1970" xml:id="surf-extra-2v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001661_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-extra-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001661_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001661_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001661_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Laeken<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Nov. 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Aan den avond van den dag waarop wij zamen waren<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> en die voor mij als in een oogwenk voorbij ging <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>wil ik U toch nog eens schrijven. Het was mij eene groote vreugde U eens weder te zien en te spreken en het is <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>gelukkig dat zulk een dag die in een oogwenk voorbij gaat en eene vreugd die slechts van zoo korten <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>duur is toch blijft in onze herinnering en dat de gedachtenis daaraan van <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>blijvenden aard is. Toen wij hadden afscheid genomen wandelde ik terug maar niet <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>den kortsten weg maar langs den Trekweg<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Er zijn daar werkplaatsen van allerlei soort <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>en die s’avonds met licht vooral er aardig uitzien en tot ons die toch ook arbeiders <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>en werklieden zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ieder in den kring en in het werk waartoe wij zijn geroepen<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> spreken <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>ook op hunne wijze<c type="kk">/</c> als wij er maar naar luisteren willen want zij zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>werk zoolang het dag is<c type="kk">/</c> eer de nacht komt waarin niemand werken kan<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> en zij herinneren <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>er ons aan dat de Vader werkt tot nu toe en wij ook moeten werken.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het was juist het oogenblik dat de straatvegers t’huis kwamen met hunne karren met de oude <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>witte paarden<c type="kk">/</c> er stond een lange reeks van die karren bij de zoogenaamde Ferme <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>des boues<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> aan ’t begin van den trekweg. Sommigen van die oude witte paarden <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>gelijken wel op zekere oude aquatint gravure die gij mogelijk wel kent, eene <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>gravure die wel geen zeer groote kunstwaarde heeft maar die mij toch evenwel <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>trof en een indruk op mij maakte. Ik bedoel de laatste uit die serie platen die getiteld <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>is “La vie d’un cheval”.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Die plaat stelt voor een oud wit paard<c type="kk">/</c> vermagerd en <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>uitgemergeld en tot den dood toe afgemat door een lang leven van zwaren arbeid <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>en veel en moeielijk werk. Het arme dier staat op eene plaats<c type="kk">/</c> onbeschrijfelijk <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>eenzaam en verlaten<c type="kk">/</c> eene vlakte begroeid met schraal dor gras met hier en <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>daar een verwrongen<c type="kk">/</c> door den stormwind gebogen en geknakten boom<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>Op den grond ligt een schedel en in de verte op den achtergrond een verbleekt geraamte van een paard en dat ligt <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>naast eene hut alwaar een man woont die de paarden afmaakt.</ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Over ’t geheel hangt een stormachtige lucht<c type="kk">/</c> het is een barre en gure dag<c type="kk">/</c> somber en donker weer. <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>’t Is een droevig en diep melankoliek tooneel en dat ieder treffen moet die weet en gevoelt dat <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>ook wij eenmaal moeten gaan door ’t geen wij sterven noemen en que la fin de la vie humaine <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>ce sont des larmes ou des cheveux blancs.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Wat daarachter nu nog ligt dat is eene groote <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>verborgenheid die God alleen weet, die ons in Zijn woord echter dit onwederlegbaar heeft geopenbaard<c type="kk">/</c> dat er is eene <lb n="31a" xml:id="l-31a"/>verrijzenisse der dooden.─<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het arme paard, de oude getrouwe gediende staat geduldig; en lijdzaam<c type="kk">/</c> moedig toch <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>en als ’t ware vastberaden als de oude garde die zeide “la garde meurt mais <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>elle ne se rend pas”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> wacht het zijn laatste uur af.─ Ik kreeg onwillekeurig die plaat in de gedachten toen ik <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>van avond die paarden van de vuilniskarren zag. En nu wat de voerlui zelve <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>aangaat, met hunne vuile groezelige kleeren<c type="kk">/</c> zij schenen haast nog dieper in de <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>armoede verzonken en geworteld dan die lange rei of liever die groep armen die <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>meester de Groux heeft geteekend op zijn banc des pauvres.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>schrijf eens of Gij die prent in kwestie kent. Ik zou wel gaarne eens spreken tot de mannen van de vuilniskarren<c type="kk">/</c> als zij maar <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>op le banc des pauvres wilden komen zitten en het de moeite waard achten om te komen hooren over het Evangelie<c type="kk">/</c> ook het deel der armen en <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>God ook<c type="kk">/</c> hun Bewaarder en hunne Schaduwe aan hunne regterhand<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> <lb n="38"/>Zie, het treft mij <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>altijd en het is iets eigenaardigs<c type="kk">/</c> als wij zien het beeld van onuitsprekelijke en <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>onbeschrijfelijke verlatenheid ─ van eenzaamheid ─ van armoed en ellende<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>het einde der dingen of hun uiterste ─ dan rijst in onzen geest op de gedachte <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>aan God. Ten minste bij mij is dit het geval en zegt niet Pa zelf ook ─ <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>ik spreek nergens liever dan op ’t kerkhof want aldaar staan wij allen op <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>gelijken grond ─ aldaar staan wij niet alleen op gelijken grond maar <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>aldaar <hi rend="ital">gevoelen</hi> wij ook dat wij op gelijken grond staan en elders gevoelen wij dat niet altijd<c type="kp">_</c> </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben blij dat wij nog te zamen het museum<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> zagen en vooral het werk van de Groux<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> en Leys<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> en <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>zooveel andere merkwaardige schilderijen als dat landschap v<c type="kp">_</c> Coosemans<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> onder anderen. <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>De twee platen die Gij mij hebt gegeven daar ben ik zeer blij mede maar gij hadt dat kleine etsje <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>Les trois moulins<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/> van mij moeten aannemen. Nu hebt gij het zelf gekocht geheel &amp; al<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs niet maar <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>half zoo als ik gaarne had gewild ─ ge moet het echter bewaren in uw plakboek want het is merkwaardig <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>al is ’t zoo heel erg mooi niet uitgevoerd, in mijne onwetendheid zou ik meenen het te moeten <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>toeschrijven liever aan Boeren Breugel dan aan Fluweelen Breugel.<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> Hierbij sluit ik in ’t bewuste <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>krabbeltje “Au charbonnage”.<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> Ik zou wel graag eens willen beginnen ruwe schetsen van ’t een &amp; ander te maken van <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>zoo talrijke dingen die men zoo op zijn weg ontmoet, maar aangezien ik toch daarin ’t niet ver zal brengen en het mij <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>al ligt van mijn eigentlijk werk zou afhouden<c type="kk">/</c> zoo is het beter ik er niet aan begin<c type="kp">_</c> Zoodra ik t’huis kwam begon ik aan <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>eene preek over “den onvruchtbaren vijgeboom”<c type="kk">/</c> Luk<c type="kp">_</c> XIII:6-9.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hartelijk hoop ik dat gij t’huis goede dagen zult hebben gehad, dat gij <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>ook den Zondag zult zijn over gebleven en het te Prinsenhage<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/> goed hebt getroffen.</ab>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als gij zult t’huis gekomen zijn in den Haag schrijf dan eens spoedig een woordje als <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>gij tijd kunt vinden<c type="kk">/</c> doe ook vooral mijne hartelijke groeten bij Roos.</ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat teekeningetje van au charbonnage is waarlijk niet veel bijzonders maar waarom <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>ik het zoo onwillekeurig maakte dat is daarom omdat men hier zoo <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>veel van die menschen ziet die in de kolen werken en dat wel <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>een eigenaardig volk is. Dit huiske staat niet ver van den trekweg<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>het is eigentlijk een klein estaminet aan de groote <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>werkplaats vast alwaar de werklui in hun schofttijd hun <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>brood komen eten &amp; een glas bier drinken.</ab>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab rend="indent">Reeds in der tijd in Engeland heb ik eens gesoliciteerd naar eene betrekking <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>van evangelist onder de mijnwerkers in de steenkolen <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>mijnen, toen sloeg men mijne vrage in den wind en zeide ik minstens 25 jaar moest zijn.<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-o-22"/> Gij weet wel <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>hoe een der wortel- of grondwaarheden<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> van het Evangelie niet alleen maar van den geheelen bijbel <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>ook is “Licht dat opgaat in de duisternis”. <hi rend="ital">Door duisternis tot Licht</hi>.<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-o-23"/> Welnu wie hebben <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>zeer zeker behoefte daaraan<c type="kk">/</c> wie zullen er ooren voor hebben<c type="kp">_</c> De ervaring <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>heeft geleerd dat degenen die in de duisternis<c type="kk">/</c> in het hart der aarde werken als de mijnwerkers <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>in de zwarte kolenmijnen onder anderen<c type="kk">/</c> door het woord van het Evangelie zeer getroffen <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>worden en het ook gelooven.─ Nu is er in ’t zuiden van Belgie, in Henegouwen <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>zoo in de buurt van Mons tot de Fransche grenzen<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="24" xml:id="note-o-24"/> ja ook nog verre daarover<c type="kk">/</c> eene <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>streek genaamd Le Borinage alwaar eene eigenaardige bevolking is van <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>arbeiders die in de talrijke steenkolenmijnen werken. Dit onder anderen vond ik in een aardrijkskundig <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>boekje<anchor n="25" xml:id="note-o-25"/> over hen: Les Borins (habitants du Borinage, pays au couchant de Mons) ne s’occupent que <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>de l’extraction du charbon. C’est un spectacle imposant que celui de ces <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>mines de houille ouvertes à 300 mètres sous terre, et où descend journellement une <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>population ouvrière digne de nos égards et de nos sympathies. Le houilleur est un type <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>particulier au Borinage; pour lui le jour n’existe pas, et sauf le Dimanche, il ne jouit guère <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>des rayons du soleil<c type="kp">_</c> Il travaille peniblement à la lueur d’une lampe dont la clarté <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>est pâle et blafarde, dans une galerie étroite, le corps plié en deux, et parfois obligé de <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>ramper; il travaille pour arracher des entrailles de la terre cette substance minérale <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>dont nous connaissons la grande utilité, il travaille enfin au milieu de mille dangers <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>sans cesse renaissants mais le porion Belge a un caractère heureux, il est habitué <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>à ce genre de vie, et quand il se rend dans la fosse, le chapeau surmonté d’une petite <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>lampe destinée à le guider dans les tenèbres, il se fie à son Dieu Qui voit son labeur et <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>Qui le protège<c type="kk">/</c> lui, sa femme et ses enfants. Ses vêtements se composent d’un chapeau <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>de cuir bouilli, d’une veste et d’un pantalon de toile.─ Dus ligt le Borinage <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>ten zuiden van Lessines<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-o-26"/> alwaar men de steengroeven vindt<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gaarne zou ik wenschen derwaarts te gaan als Evangelist. De drie maanden proeftijd <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>door de Heeren de Jong &amp; D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Pietersen gesteld<c type="kk">/</c> is welhaast verstreken.<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-o-27"/> Paulus is voor hij optrad <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>als prediker en zijne groote zendingreizen begon en zijn eigentlijk werk <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>onder de Heidenen<c type="kk">/</c> drie jaar in Arabië geweest.<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-o-28"/> Kon ik zoo eens een jaar of drie in <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>eene dergelijke streek werkzaam zijn in stilte en steeds leerende &amp; opmerkende<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>niet terugkomen van daar zonder iets te zeggen te hebben dat inderdaad de moeite <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>waard is om gehoord te worden;<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-o-29"/> met alle nederigheid, nogtans met <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>vrijmoedigheid zeg ik dit.─ Als God wil en mij het leven spaart<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-o-30"/> dan zou ik ongeveer <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>op mijn 30<hi rend="ss">ste</hi> jaar klaar zijn en met eene eigenaardige opleiding en ervaring kunnen <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>aanvangen<c type="kk">/</c> mijne zaak meer meester zijnde en rijper tot den arbeid dan nu. <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>Ik schrijf U dit nog eens hoewel wij er ook reeds over spraken. Er zijn in <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>de Borinage reeds verscheidene kleine Protestantsche gemeenten<c type="kk">/</c> zeker ook scholen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>mogt God er mij een plaatsje aanwijzen om er werkzaam te zijn als Evangelist op <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>de wijze waarover wij spraken<c type="kk">/</c> door het Evangelie te prediken aan armen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>dus zulken die er behoefte aan hebben &amp; voor wie het zoo bij uitnemendheid geschikt is<c type="kk">/</c> en <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>mijn tijd gedurende de week te wijden aan het onderwijs.─</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zijt zeker wel eens geweest te S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Giles.<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-o-31"/> Heb daar dien kant uit ook eens een togt gemaakt <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>bij l’ancienne barrière<c type="kp">_</c> Alwaar de weg naar Mont S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Jean begint is ook nog <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>een anderen<c type="kk">/</c> den Alsemberg<c type="kp">_</c> Hier is regts het kerkhof van S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Giles vol ceders en <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>klimop en van waar men over de stad kan heenzien<c type="kp">_</c> Verder gaande <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>komt men te Forest. De streek is daar zeer schilderachtig<c type="kk">/</c> op de hooge kanten <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>staan oude huizen zooals die hutten in de duinen die Bosboom <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>wel geschilderd heeft.<anchor n="32" xml:id="note-o-32"/> Men ziet er alle mogelijke landwerk verrigten<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>koren zaaien<c type="kk">/</c> aardappels rooien<c type="kk">/</c> knollen wasschen en alles is er schilderachtig <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>tot het hout sprokkelen toe en het heeft veel van Montmartre.</ab>
                <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er zijn oude huizen met klimop of wijngaard en aardige herbergen<c type="kk">/</c> onder de huizen <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>die ik opmerkte was onder anderen dat van een mostaard fabrikant<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>zekeren Verkissen<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="33" xml:id="note-o-33"/> Zijn gedoente<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-o-b"/> was volkomen geschikt voor een Sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> van Thijs Maris bij voorbeeld. Er zijn hier en daar plaatsen alwaar <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>steenen gevonden worden en dus kleine steengroeven waar <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>holle wegen met diepgegroefde karsporen heengaan<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="128a" xml:id="l-128a"/>waar men de kleine witte paarden ziet met roode kwasten en de voerlui met blaauwe kielen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="128"/>en de schaapherder <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>ontbreekt niet <lb n="129a" xml:id="l-129a"/>evenmin als oude vrouwen in ’t zwart met witte mutsen die aan die van deGroux herinneren. <lb n="129"/>Er zijn hier van die plaatsen, gelijk trouwens <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>God zij dank overal, alwaar men zich t’huis gevoelt meer dan elders<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>waar men een eigenaardig oud gevoel als van heimwee krijgt waarin wel <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>iets bitter weemoedigs is maar dat toch den geest sterkt en op wekt in <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>ons en ons<c type="kk">/</c> wij weten zelf niet hoe en waarom<c type="kk">/</c> nieuwe kracht en lust tot den <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>arbeid geeft en ons opwekt. Ik wandelde dien dag nog door tot voorbij <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>Forest en ging nog een zijweg in naar een oud kerkje<anchor n="34" xml:id="note-o-34"/> met klimop begroeid<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>Ik zag er veel lindenboomen nog meer in elkander gegroeid en <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>om zoo te spreken nog meer gothiek dan die wij in ’t park zagen en aan <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>den kant van den hollen weg die naar ’t kerkhof leidt verwrongen struiken en <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>boomwortels<c type="kk">/</c> grillig als die Albert Dürer etste in “Ritter<c type="kk">/</c> Tod und Tauful”<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="35" xml:id="note-o-35"/> <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>Hebt gij ooit gezien een Sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> of liever eene phot. er naar van Carlo Dolci<c type="kk">/</c> Het hofken der olijven<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="36" xml:id="note-o-36"/> <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>daar is iets Rembrantieks in, zag die onlangs. De groote ruwe ets naar datzelfde <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>onderwerp naar Rembrandt<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="37" xml:id="note-o-37"/> zijnde de pendant van die andere<c type="kk">/</c> La lecture <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>de la Bible met die twee vrouwen en de wieg<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="38" xml:id="note-o-38"/> kent gij zeker wel. Sedert gij mij <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>hebt gezegd dat gij dat Schij van Vader Corot over dat zelfde sujet hebt gezien <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>kwam het mij weer voor den geest<c type="kk">/</c> ik zag het op de tentoonstelling zijner <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>werken kort na zijn overlijden<anchor n="39" xml:id="note-o-39"/> en het trof mij zeer.</ab>
                <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat is er toch veel moois in de kunst<c type="kk">/</c> als men maar onthouden kan <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>hetgeen men heeft gezien dan is men nooit ledig of waarachtig eenzaam <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>maar nooit alleen.</ab>
                <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>
<ab rend="indent">à Dieu Theo, in gedachten druk ik U regt hartelijk de hand, heb <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>het goed, heb voorspoed bij Uw werk en ontmoet maar veel goede <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>dingen op Uw levensweg<c type="kk">/</c> zulke die blijven in de herinnering en die <lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>ons rijk maken al bezitten wij schijnbaar weinig.<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-o-40"/> Als gij Borchers eens ziet wees <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>zoo goed hem te zeggen dat ik hem nog wel zeer dank voor zijn <lb n="155" xml:id="l-155"/>schrijven van eenigen tijd geleden. Komt gij eens bij Mauve doe dan ook <lb n="156" xml:id="l-156"/>mijne groeten en geloof mij</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="157" xml:id="l-157"/>
<ab>Uw liefh<c type="kp">_</c> broer</ab>
                <lb n="158" xml:id="l-158"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="159" xml:id="l-159"/>
<ab>Ik hield dezen brief een paar dagen op<c type="kp">_</c> 15 Nov<c type="kp">_</c> is gepasseerd <lb n="160" xml:id="l-160"/>dus zijn de 3 maanden verstreken<c type="kp">_</c> Sprak met D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> de Jonge &amp; met Meester Bokma<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="41" xml:id="note-o-41"/> <lb n="161" xml:id="l-161"/>zij zeggen er is geen gelegenheid om op de school te zijn op de zelfde voorwaarden <lb n="162" xml:id="l-162"/>als zij aangeboren Vlamingen geven ─ ik kan de lessen bijwonen<c type="kk">/</c> desnoods <lb n="163" xml:id="l-163"/>kosteloos ─ maar dit is ook het eenige voorregt ─ ik zou dus om te kunnen <lb n="164" xml:id="l-164"/>blijven op den duur meer geldelijke middelen moeten hebben dan die waarover ik <lb n="165" xml:id="l-165"/>beschikken kan want die zijn geene.─ Dus zal ik welligt reeds spoedig het <lb n="166" xml:id="l-166"/>plan van de Borinage beproeven.<anchor n="42" xml:id="note-o-42"/> Eenmaal de stad uit zijnde zal <lb n="167" xml:id="l-167"/>ik niet ligt in eene groote stad terugkeeren. Het zou niet gemakkelijk zijn om <lb n="168" xml:id="l-168"/>te leven zonder het geloof in Hem en het oud vertrouwen<anchor n="43" xml:id="note-o-43"/> op Hem, maar zonder dat <lb n="169" xml:id="l-169"/>zou men den moed verliezen.</ab>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-74" n="74">wortel- &lt; wortel</note>
<note target="l-164" n="164">moeten hebben &lt; hebben</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Laeken,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Nov. 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>On the evening of the day we spent together,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> which for me passed as if in a twinkling, I want to write to you after all. It was a great joy for me to see and talk to you again, and it’s fortunate that such a day that passes in a twinkling and a joy of such short duration nevertheless remains in our memory, and that the remembrance of it is of a lasting nature. After we’d taken leave of each other I walked back, not the shortest way but along Trekweg.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> There are workshops of all kinds there that look pleasant, especially lit up in the evening, which also speak in their own way to us who are, after all, labourers and workers, each in the sphere and in the work whereunto we have been called,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> if only we care to listen, for they say, work while it is day, before the night cometh, when no man can work,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and they remind us that the Father worketh hitherto, and that we too must work.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It was the very moment when the street-sweepers were coming home with their carts with old white horses, there was a long line of those carts standing by the so-called sludge works<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> at the beginning of Trekweg. Some of those old white horses resemble a certain old aquatint that you perhaps know, an engraving with no very great artistic value but which nevertheless struck me and made an impression on me. I mean the last of the series of prints titled ‘The life of a horse’.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> That print depicts an old white horse, emaciated and spent and worn out to death by a long life of heavy labour and much and difficult work. The poor animal stands in an indescribably lonely and forsaken place, a plain with lank, withered grass and here and there a twisted tree, bent and cracked by the storm wind. On the ground lies a skull and in the distance, in the background, the bleached skeleton of a horse lying next to a hut, where the man who slaughters horses lives.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">A stormy sky hangs over the whole, it’s a foul and bleak day, sombre and dark weather. It’s a sorrowful and profoundly melancholy scene that must move everyone who knows and feels that we, too, must one day go through that which we call dying, and that at the end of human life there are tears or grey hair.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> What lies beyond is a great mystery that God alone comprehends, who has however revealed this irrefutably in His word, that there is a resurrection of the dead.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The poor horse — the old faithful servant, stands patient and submissive, but courageous nonetheless and as resolute, as it were, as the old guard who said ‘the guard dies but does not surrender’<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> — waits for its final hour. I couldn’t help thinking of that print this evening when I saw those dust-cart horses. And now, as far as the drivers themselves are concerned, with their dirty, dingy clothes, they seemed to be sunk or rooted in poverty almost more deeply than that long row or rather group of poor people drawn by master <rs type="pers" key="1063">Degroux</rs> in his paupers’ pew.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> Write and tell me if you know that print. I’d like to speak to the dustmen, if they would only come and sit in the paupers’ pew and consider it worthwhile to come and hear about the gospel and the lot of the poor and God, too, their Keeper and their Shade upon their right hand.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> You see, it always strikes me and it is remarkable, when we see the image of unutterable and indescribable forsakenness — of loneliness — of poverty and misery, the end of things or their extremity — the thought of God comes to mind. At least this is the case with me, and doesn’t <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> also say: There is no place I would rather speak than a cemetery, for there we are all on equal ground — there we not only stand on equal ground but there we also <hi rend="ital">feel</hi> that we are standing on equal ground, and elsewhere we don’t always feel that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m glad that we saw the museum<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> together, especially the works by <rs type="pers" key="1063">Degroux</rs>
                    <anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> and <rs type="pers" key="1176">Leys</rs>
                    <anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> and so many other remarkable paintings, such as that landscape by <rs type="pers" key="947">Coosemans</rs>,<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> among others. I’m very happy about the two prints you gave me, but you should have let me give you that small etching, The three mills.<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> Now you’ve paid it all yourself, not just half of it as I had so wished — you must keep it in your scrapbook, however, because it’s remarkable, even though it isn’t very well executed. In my ignorance I’d think it attributable to <rs type="pers" key="909">Peasant Bruegel</rs> rather than to <rs type="pers" key="908">Velvet Brueghel</rs>.<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> I hereby enclose that scratch, ‘The Au charbonnage café’.<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> I should really rather like to start making rough sketches of some of the many things one meets along the way, but considering I wouldn’t actually do it very well and it would most likely keep me from my real work, it’s better I don’t begin. As soon as I got home I began working on a sermon on ‘the barren fig tree’, Luke XIII:6-9.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I sincerely hope that you’ll have had good days at home, that you also will have stayed over Sunday and found things well at Princenhage.<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When you arrive home in The Hague write a quick note if you can find the time, and be sure to give my warm regards to <rs type="pers" key="642 643">the Rooses</rs>.</ab>
  <ab rend="indent">That little drawing, ‘The Au charbonnage café’ is really nothing special, but the reason I couldn’t help making it is because one sees so many coalmen, and they really are a remarkable people. This little house is not far from Trekweg, it’s actually a simple inn right next to the big workplace where the workers come in their free time to eat their bread and drink a glass of beer.</ab>
  <ab rend="indent">Back during my time in England I applied for a position as an evangelist among the coal-miners, but they brushed my request aside and said I had to be at least 25 years old.<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> You surely know that one of the root or fundamental truths, not only of the gospel but of the entire Bible, is ‘the light that dawns in the darkness’. <hi rend="ital">From darkness to Light</hi>.<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/> Well then, who will most certainly need it, who will have an ear to hear it? Experience has taught us that those who work in darkness, in the heart of the earth like the mine-workers in the black coal-mines, among others, are very moved by the message of the gospel and also believe it. In the south of Belgium, in Hainaut, from around the area of Mons to the French borders<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-t-24"/> and even extending far beyond them, there is a region called the Borinage, where there is one of those populations of labourers who work in the many coal-mines. I found this and other things about them in a geography book:<anchor n="25" xml:id="note-t-25"/> The Borins (people who live in the Borinage, an area west of Mons) do nothing but mine coal. They’re an impressive sight, these coal-mines, opened up 300 metres underground, down which a working population worthy of our respect and sympathy descends every day. The coal-miner is a type peculiar to the Borinage; daylight hardly exists for him, and he scarcely enjoys the sun’s rays except on Sunday. He works with great difficulty by the light of a lamp whose illumination is pale and feeble, in a narrow gallery, his body bent double, and sometimes forced to crawl; his work is to pull from the earth’s entrails this mineral substance whose great usefulness we know, he thus works in the midst of a thousand constantly recurring dangers, but the Belgian foreman has a cheerful character, he’s used to this way of life, and when he goes down the pit, his hat topped with a little lamp whose job is to guide him in the darkness, he entrusts himself to his God Who sees his labours and Who protects him, his wife and his children. His clothing consists of a hat of boiled leather, a jacket and a pair of canvas trousers. So the Borinage lies to the south of Lessines,<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-t-26"/> where one finds the stone-quarries.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I should like to go there as an evangelist. The three-month trial period set by Messrs <rs type="pers" key="460">De Jonge</rs> and the <rs type="pers" key="605">Rev. Pieterszen</rs> is nearly over.<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-t-27"/> Paul spent three years in Arabia before he became active as a preacher and began his great missionary journeys and his actual work among the heathens.<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-t-28"/> If I could spend three years or so in a similar region, working in peace and always learning and observing, then I wouldn’t return from there without having something to say that is indeed worth hearing;<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-t-29"/> I say this in all humility yet with frankness. If God wills it and spares my life,<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-t-30"/> I’d be ready by about the age of 30 and could begin, with my special training and experience, having more mastery of my affairs and more maturity for the work than I do now. I’m writing this to you again, even though we’ve already talked about it. There are already a number of small Protestant congregations in the Borinage, and certainly schools as well, may God point me to a place where I can be active as an evangelist in the way we spoke about, by preaching the gospel to the poor, thus to those who have need of it and for whom it is suited to perfection, and devoting my time during the week to teaching.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ve no doubt been to Saint-Gilles.<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-t-31"/> I once took a walk from there to the ‘old boundary mark’. Where the road to Mont Saint Jean begins there’s another hill, the Alsemberg. Here, on the right, is the cemetery of Saint-Gilles, full of cedars and ivy, from which one can look out over the city. Further on one comes to Forest. The region is very picturesque there, standing on the high slopes are old houses like the huts in the dunes that <rs type="pers" key="884">Bosboom</rs> painted.<anchor n="32" xml:id="note-t-32"/> One sees people doing all kinds of farm work, sowing wheat, lifting potatoes, washing turnips, and everything, right down to wood-gathering, is picturesque and looks very much like Montmartre.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">There are old houses with ivy or Virginia creeper and charming inns, among the houses I noticed was that of a mustard-maker, one <rs type="pers" key="798">Verkissen</rs>.<anchor n="33" xml:id="note-t-33"/> His place would be perfect for a painting by <rs type="pers" key="1202">Thijs Maris</rs>, for example. There are places here and there where stones are found and therefore small quarries to which sunken roads with the deep ruts of cart tracks lead, where one sees small white horses with red tassels and drivers with blue smocks, and the shepherd is not lacking, nor old women in black with white caps reminiscent of those by <rs type="pers" key="1063">Degroux</rs>. There are also places here — as there are everywhere, for that matter, thank God — where one feels at home more than elsewhere, where one gets a remarkable, familiar feeling like homesickness, which has something bitterly melancholy about it but which nevertheless strengthens and awakens the spirit in us and gives us new strength and appetite for work and stimulates us, we know not how or why. That day I walked on, past Forest, and took a side road to an old church<anchor n="34" xml:id="note-t-34"/> overgrown with ivy. I saw many lime trees, even more entwined with one another and even more Gothic, so to speak, than those we saw in the park, and at the side of the sunken road leading to the cemetery twisted bushes and the roots of trees, as gnarled as those <rs type="pers" key="990">Dürer</rs> etched in ‘Knight, Death and the Devil’.<anchor n="35" xml:id="note-t-35"/> Have you ever seen a painting, or rather a photo of it, by <rs type="pers" key="993">Carlo Dolci</rs>, The Garden of Olives?<anchor n="36" xml:id="note-t-36"/> There’s something Rembrandtesque about it, saw it recently. You no doubt know the large, rough etching of the same subject after <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>,<anchor n="37" xml:id="note-t-37"/> being the pendant of the other, Reading the Bible, with those two women and the cradle.<anchor n="38" xml:id="note-t-38"/> It came to mind after you told me that you had seen the painting by <hi rend="ital">père</hi> <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs> of the same subject; I saw it at the exhibition of his work shortly after he died,<anchor n="39" xml:id="note-t-39"/> and it moved me deeply.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How much there is in art that is beautiful, if only one can remember what one has seen, one is never empty or truly lonely, and never alone.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Adieu Theo, I shake your hand right heartily in thought, I wish you well, may you thrive in your work and encounter many good things on your path in life, such as stay in the memory and make us rich though we seemingly have nothing.<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-t-40"/> If you see <rs type="pers" key="298">Borchers</rs> sometime, be so good as to tell him that I thank him very much for his letter of some time ago. If you go to <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>’s, give him my regards, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab>I kept this letter for a couple of days. 15 Nov. has passed, so the three months are up. Spoke with the <rs type="pers" key="460">Rev. De Jonge</rs> and with Master <rs type="pers" key="284">Bokma</rs>,<anchor n="41" xml:id="note-t-41"/> they say there is no opportunity to be at the school under the same conditions they offer to native Flemings — I can attend the lessons, for free if necessary — but this is the only privilege — in order to stay, therefore, I would need to have more financial means at my disposal than I do now, which is none. So I’ll probably soon try the Borinage plan.<anchor n="42" xml:id="note-t-42"/> Once out of the city I shan’t easily return to a big city. It wouldn’t be easy to live without believing in Him and without having the faith of old<anchor n="43" xml:id="note-t-43"/> in Him, and without that one would lose heart.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab>
                    <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
  <ab>Laken – spelled Laeken in French – is a suburb to the north of Brussels. Van Gogh boarded with the family of <rs type="pers" key="161">Pieter Jacobus Plugge</rs> who lived at 6 Chemin de Halage (Trekweg in Dutch). Plugge was a member of the church council of the church at Kathelijneplaats (place Sainte-Catherine), where the training college was then located. See Lutjeharms 1978, pp. 83, 105. Pieter Jozef Chrispeels, one of Van Gogh’s fellow students, recalled the strict regimen Vincent imposed on himself: in his lodgings at the Plugges’ he refused to use the bed, preferring to sleep on the floor, on the carpet next to his bed. See <hi rend="ital">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 1, pp. 180-182, and cf. <hi rend="ital">Plan guide de Bruxelles &amp; de ses faubourgs, novembre 1869</hi> (<hi rend="ital">SAB</hi>, Plan 102).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Probably ‘a couple of days’ before 15 November (see <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>). After his work for Goupil at the World Exhibition in Paris, Theo returned to the Netherlands, stopping off to see Vincent on his way to Etten.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>This path ran alongside the Willebroek Canal, ending in boulevard d’Anvers. Barges laden with coal moored at the Steenkoolkaai and the Koolmijnenkaai, which lay at the end of Trekweg. The gasworks beside the Willebroek Canal used coke to produce gas, and employed numerous coal-porters to carry the sacks of coal.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Acts" chap="13" v="2">Acts 13:2</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="9" v="4">John 9:4</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="5" v="17">John 5:17</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>The 16-page brochure <hi rend="ital">Entreprise de la ferme des boues</hi>. <hi rend="ital">Cahier des charges (adopté en séance du conseil communal, le 10 novembre 1866)</hi> gives a detailed description of the sanitation services performed by this firm. The first article reports: ‘L’Entreprise de la ferme des boues’ (sludge works) has as its purpose the cleaning and spraying of the public highways, the emptying of cesspools and, in general, everything concerned with municipal sanitation’ (<hi rend="ital">SAB</hi> 2903 83). It was located at the quai de la Voirie, near the Willebroek Canal (<hi rend="ital">SAB</hi> 6217-6224).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>This most likely refers to the last print in the series <hi rend="ital">La vie d’un cheval </hi>(The life of a horse), titled <rs type="otherart" key="145">
                            <hi rend="ital">Montfaucon</hi>
                        </rs>, after <rs type="pers" key="137">Hippolyte Lecomte</rs>. It is mentioned in the <hi rend="ital">Catalogue du fonds Goupil et Vibert</hi> (c. 1848), but has not been traced. Van Gogh showed an interest in this motif: he later drew <hi rend="ital">Old nag </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2441">F 1032 / JH 368</rs>) and spoke of the <hi rend="ital">Flat-bottomed fishing boat on the beach</hi> by <rs type="pers" key="323">Anton Mauve</rs> and the <hi rend="ital">Old white horse</hi> by <rs type="pers" key="1440">Herman J. van der Weele</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The source of this statement has not been found.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Biblical; cf., for instance, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="22" v="31">Matt. 22:31</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>It is a matter of some dispute as to who uttered these heroic words: General <rs type="pers" key="38">Pierre Jacques Etienne Cambronne</rs> or General <rs type="pers" key="148">Claude Etienne Michel</rs>. This remark – famous in France – which was made at Waterloo, is treated in detail in Pierre Larousse, <hi rend="ital">Grand dictionnaire universel du <hi rend="sc">xix</hi>e siècle</hi>. Paris 1867, vol. 3, pp. 203-204.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Three versions are known of <rs type="pers" key="1063">Charles Degroux</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">The paupers’ pew</hi>: a painting of 1854 (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts, acquired in 1930). <rs type="ill" key="134">Ill. 134</rs>. In 1869, <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs> bought the watercolour <hi rend="ital">The paupers’ pew </hi>(Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). A third version was exhibited in 1849 and 1850 (present whereabouts unknown). See exhib. cat. Ypres 1995, pp. 117-118, cat. nos. 143-145. <rs type="pers" key="232">Antoine Marie Eusèbe Voncken</rs> made a lithograph, published by B. Vanderkolck (Brussels, Prentenkabinet of the Koninklijke Bibliotheek). <rs type="ill" key="1880">Ill. 1880</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="121" v="5">Ps. 121:5</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>The Museum voor Schone Kunsten (Musée des Beaux-Arts) in Brussels.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>The works exhibited by <rs type="pers" key="1063">Charles Degroux</rs> were <rs type="otherart" key="130">
                            <hi rend="ital">Franciscus Junius secretly preaching the Reformation at Antwerp</hi>
                        </rs> (1860); <rs type="ill" key="139">
                            <hi rend="ital">The drunkard</hi>
                        </rs> (c. 1853); <rs type="ill" key="140">
                            <hi rend="ital">The pilgrimage of Saint Guido at Anderlecht</hi>
                        </rs> (c. 1856-1857); <rs type="ill" key="135">
                            <hi rend="ital">Saying grace</hi>
                        </rs> (c. 1860); <rs type="ill" key="138">
                            <hi rend="ital">The conscript’s departure</hi>
                        </rs> (c. 1869-1870) and <rs type="otherart" key="131">
                            <hi rend="ital">Head of an old woman</hi>
                        </rs> (presumably lost or destroyed). See cat. Brussels 1984, pp. 255-258.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>The works by <rs type="pers" key="1176">Henri Leys</rs> on display were <rs type="otherart" key="132">
                            <hi rend="ital">Rich and poor</hi>
                        </rs> (1837); <rs type="otherart" key="133">
                            <hi rend="ital">The reinstatement of worship in the Onze-Lieve-Vrouwkerk at Antwerp</hi>
                        </rs> (1845); <rs type="otherart" key="134">
                            <hi rend="ital">The thirty-day Mass for Berthal de Haze</hi>
                        </rs> (1854); <rs type="otherart" key="135">
                            <hi rend="ital">Archduke Charles of Austria, the later Emperor Charles <hi rend="sc">v</hi>, taking the oath at the triumphal entry in 1514</hi>
                        </rs> (1863) and <rs type="otherart" key="136">
                            <hi rend="ital">The studio of Frans Floris</hi>
                        </rs> (1868). See cat. Brussels 1984, pp. 374-380.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>As far as is known, <rs type="pers" key="947">Joseph Coosemans</rs>’s <rs type="otherart" key="137">
                            <hi rend="ital">The artists’ path at Barbizon</hi>
                        </rs>, 1878 (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts) was not purchased until 1889, so the brothers might have seen this landscape elsewhere – at Goupil’s, for example.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">The three windmills</hi> (1772) by <rs type="pers" key="1501">Balthasar Anton Duncker</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1502">Jean Philippe Le Bas</rs> after <rs type="pers" key="908">Jan Brueghel the Elder</rs> (H7) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="ill" key="654">Ill. 654</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="909">Pieter Bruegel the Elder</rs> was known as Peasant Bruegel, and <rs type="pers" key="908">Jan Brueghel the Elder</rs> as Velvet Brueghel. Below the print is written ‘Peint par Breugels de Velours’ (painted by the Velvet Brueghel).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>The small drawing <hi rend="ital">Café Au charbonnage</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="10">F Juv. XXXI/ JH Juv. 9</rs>).On the verso appear exercises in Greek pronouns, which Van Gogh probably did back in Amsterdam. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 66-68, cat. no. 11.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt Cornelie</rs> lived in Princenhage.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="22" xml:id="n-22" target="#note-t-22">
<ab>
  <ref target="let085.xml">See letter 85</ref>, in which Van Gogh wrote that one had to be <hi rend="ital">24</hi> years old to be an evangelist ‘among the workers and the poor’ in London.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>For ‘wortelwaarheid’ (root-truth), see the word ‘wortelstelling’ (proposition) in <ref target="let190.xml">letter 190</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="23" xml:id="n-23" target="#note-t-23">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Acts" chap="26" v="18">Acts 26:18</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="24" xml:id="n-24" target="#note-t-24">
<ab>The province of Hainaut, the capital of which is Bergen (Mons).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="25" xml:id="n-25" target="#note-t-25">
<ab>The first line of this quotation seems to have been taken from Emmanuel Soudan, <hi rend="ital">Petite description géographique du globe, au point de vue belge</hi>, Ghent 1854, p. 28. Most of the fragment was copied almost literally from Adolphe Siret, <hi rend="ital">Récits historiques Belges</hi>, Brussels 1855, pp. 217-218. See Bart Moens, ‘Van Gogh in Brussels: a little-known but decisive stage in his early development as an artist’, in exhib. cat. Mons 2015, p. 117, n. 11 and 12. It was also cited in A. Anthelme Fritz, <hi rend="ital">Esquisse d’une nouvelle Géographie de la Belgique...</hi>, Deuxième édition, Brussels 1860, pp. 45, 49-50; and in A. Anthelme Fritz, <hi rend="ital">La Belgique physique, politique, industrielle et commerciale...</hi>, Brussels 1864, pp. 45, 49-50. With thanks to Dominique Guillet.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="26" xml:id="n-26" target="#note-t-26">
<ab>Lessines is in the Flemish Ardennes on the River Dendre, some 30 km south-west of Brussels.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="27" xml:id="n-27" target="#note-t-27">
<ab>Little is known of these three months in Brussels. On 12 September 1878, <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> informed Theo: ‘Also a good letter from Vincent. He is working hard, attending classes at the training college from 9 in the morning until 4 in the afternoon, and sometimes until 8 o’clock at night. Last Sunday he was in Mechelen and Lier and held a Bible class there in the afternoon, and he has been invited back for two following Sundays.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He has not yet given any details about those classes. I am rather curious. He writes that he still feels like a cat in a strange warehouse. It could hardly be otherwise! May this lead to something lasting, however’</ab>
<ab> (FR b2437).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">A month later Mr van Gogh was less optimistic. Vincent’s social ineptness prompted him to remark sceptically: ‘Is it any wonder that we worry? Oh, how much we worry still about Vincent! He appears not to want to shed that eccentricity, regards his clothing and appearance as well, and it will, I think, make things impossible for him. I do not hear others’ opinion of him and I can’t bring myself to ask about it again. His letters do contain interesting news, but will he reach his goal?’ (FR b2440, to Theo, 14 October 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="28" xml:id="n-28" target="#note-t-28">
<ab>See <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Gal" chap="1" vr="17-18">Gal. 1:17-18</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="29" xml:id="n-29" target="#note-t-29">
<ab>This analogy is also expressed in <rs type="lit" key="113">
                            <hi rend="ital">Juweeltjes uit de gedachten van C.H. Spurgeon</hi>
                        </rs>: ‘The preaching of Paul must also be the preaching of the evangelist today’ (6th ed. Rotterdam n.d., p. 37). <rs type="pers" key="397">Görlitz</rs>, Van Gogh’s roommate in Dordrecht, said that he often saw Van Gogh reading <hi rend="ital">Juweeltjes</hi> (cf. <ref target="let104.xml#n-2">letter 104, n. 2</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="30" xml:id="n-30" target="#note-t-30">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Jas" chap="4" v="15">Jas. 4:15</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="31" xml:id="n-31" target="#note-t-31">
<ab>Saint-Gilles is a district in the south-west part of Brussels, south of Bruxelles Midi (Brussels South) railway station. ‘Ancien barrière’ likely refers to the Barrière Ancien Porte de Hal. At that time there was also a ‘Barrière’ at the fork of the Chaussée de Waterloo and the Chaussée d’Alsemberg – a map of Brussels in 1870 shows various toll-gates, including one near St Antoine. The cemetery of Saint-Gilles was (and still is) located behind the Chaussée d’Alsemberg. The ‘road to Mont Saint Jean’ is the road to Waterloo. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="32" xml:id="n-32" target="#note-t-32">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="884">Johannes Bosboom</rs> made a number of dune landscapes, mostly in watercolour. Cf. Marius and Martin 1917, pp. 146-147.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="33" xml:id="n-33" target="#note-t-33">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="798">François Antoine Verkissen</rs>, registered as a ‘mustard merchant’, lived at Chaussée de Waterloo 117 in Saint-Gillis. (<hi rend="ital">GASG)</hi>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-o-b">
<ab>‘Gedoente’ means the house and everything around it.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="34" xml:id="n-34" target="#note-t-34">
  <ab>This refers to the Chemin de Vossegat, which leads to the 12th-century ‘Kapel van Stalle’ (Notre-Dame de Bon Secours). It is now in Stallestraat, Ukkel.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="35" xml:id="n-35" target="#note-t-35">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="990">Albrecht Dürer</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Ritter, Tod und Teufel</hi> (Knight, Death and the Devil), 1513 (H74) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="ill" key="1882">Ill. 1882</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="36" xml:id="n-36" target="#note-t-36">
<ab>Van Gogh probably saw a photograph or photogravure after the painting by <rs type="pers" key="993">Carlo Dolci</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Christ in the Garden of Olives</hi>, c. 1643 (Genua, Palazzo Bianco, acquired in 1874). <rs type="ill" key="780">Ill. 780</rs>. A painting formerly attributed to Dolci, <hi rend="ital">Christ in the Garden of Olives</hi> (Florence, Galleria Palatina), is now described as ‘Scuola fiorentina’. See Francesca Baldassari,<hi rend="ital"> Carlo Dolci</hi>. Torino 1995, pp. 77-78, cat. no. 42.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="37" xml:id="n-37" target="#note-t-37">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Christ in the Garden of Gethsemane</hi>, c. 1657 (B75) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="ill" key="1883">Ill. 1883</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="38" xml:id="n-38" target="#note-t-38">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <rs type="otherart" key="44">
                            <hi rend="ital">Reading the Bible</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let037.xml#n-4">see letter 37, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="39" xml:id="n-39" target="#note-t-39">
  <ab>On <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs>’s <rs type="ill" key="1705">
                            <hi rend="ital">Christ on the Mount of Olives</hi>
                        </rs>, which Van Gogh had seen in May 1875, <ref target="let034.xml#n-1">see letter 34, nn. 1</ref> and <ref target="let034.xml#n-2">2.</ref> Corot was also called ‘le père Corot’. See Blanc 1876, p. 377.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="40" xml:id="n-40" target="#note-t-40">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="2 Cor" chap="6" v="10">2 Cor. 6:10</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="41" xml:id="n-41" target="#note-t-41">
<ab>The head of the training college at this time was <rs type="pers" key="284">Dirk Rochus Bokma</rs> of Friesland. In his capacity as director, he was responsible for the curriculum and the supervision of the students. Enrolled at the same time as Van Gogh were Pieter Jozef Chrispeels, Pieter Jozef Wauters, Willem vander Haeghen and Andries van Trijffel. Felix Chrispeels attended classes part-time in 1878. See Lutjeharms 1978 and Fagel, ‘Van Gogh in Brussel’, pp. 23-27.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="42" xml:id="n-42" target="#note-t-42">
<ab>Having failed to receive a study grant, Van Gogh now left to take up a six-month position as an evangelist in the Borinage, the mining district of Belgium.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="43" xml:id="n-43" target="#note-t-43">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rhy. ps" chap="42" v="7">Rhy. ps. 42:7</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>