<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Sunday, 31 December 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let100"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">100</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">83</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">100</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Etten</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 31 December 1876</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Sunday, 31 December 1876.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b100 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Etten 31 December 1876’.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>This letter was probably enclosed in a letter written by Mr and Mrs van Gogh to Theo, since they say in their letter that Vincent will have written about his Dordrecht plans (FR b2804).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0100" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000107_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000107_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000107_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000107_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0100" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000107_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000107_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000107_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000107_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Etten 31 December 1876<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Van harte alles goeds in het nieuwe jaar U toegewenscht<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>heb het goed en heb zegen in alle opzichten. Heerlijk <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>wij elkaar weer gezien hebben, wat was het mooi dien <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>morgen toen Gij zijt weggegaan en wat zullen wij nog <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>dikwijls aan de reis naar Chaam<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> denken.</ab>
                <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>
<ab rend="indent">Moe heeft weer zooveel pijn aan het oog en heeft een <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>doek om, Pa heeft weer zoo heel mooi gepreekt van <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>morgen.</ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu van avond weer Oudejaarsavond, waart Gij ook <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>maar hier.</ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er is nog iets nu dat ik U moet vertellen; een paar dagen <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>geleden kwam de Hr. Braat uit Dordt<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> een bezoek <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>brengen bij Oom Vincent en zij spraken over mij en <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>oom vroeg aan de Hr B., of er bij hem, indien ik dit <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>verlangde, voor mij plaats zou zijn. De Hr B. dacht <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>hij wel plaats zou hebben en zeide dat ik maar eens <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>moest komen om er over te spreken. Dus ben ik <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>gisteren morgen vroeg er heen geweest, Pa en Moe en <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>ik ook, vonden het iets dat wij niet moesten laten <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>voorbijgaan zonder te zien wat het was.</ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Sprak met hem af ik na Nieuwejaar eene week bij <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>hem zou komen en na verloop van dien tijd kunnen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>wij zien.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er zijn veel dingen die het wenschelijk maken, het <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>weer terug zijn in Holland in de buurt van Pa <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>en Moe en ook van U en de anderen vooreerst.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Dan zou het salaris daar zeker iets beter zijn <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>dan bij Mr Jones en vooral met het oog op later <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wanneer een mensch meer noodig krijgt 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>is het plicht daaraan te denken.</ab>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat nu het andere betreft<c type="kk">/</c> dat laat ik daarom <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>niet varen. Pa’s geest is zoo groot en zoo veel<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>zijdig uitgebreid en onder alle omstandigheden <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>hoop ik zich iets daarvan in mij zal ontwikkelen. <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>de verandering nu zal zijn dat ik in plaats <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>van les te geven aan die jongens in een boek<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>winkel werkzaam ben.─</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat hebben wij dikwijls verlangd bij elkaar te zijn <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>en hoe vreesselijk is het gevoel van ver van elkaar <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>te zijn bij ziekte of zorg gelijk wij het bij voorbeeld <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>voelden bij Uwe ziekte, en dan het gevoel dat het gebrek <lb n="43a" xml:id="l-43a"/>aan het noodige geld zeer goed een beletsel zou kunnen zijn om in nood <lb n="43b" xml:id="l-43b"/>bij elkaar te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> </ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dus is het best mogelijk ik daar heen ga.─</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gisteren avond was ik nog bij Oom Vincent om hem <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>te vertellen ik dadelijk naar Dordt was geweest, het <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>was een stormachtigen avond<c type="kk">/</c> gij kunt U denken hoe <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>mooi die weg naar Prinsenhage was met de donkere <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>wolken met hun zilveren randen. Ik ging ook <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>nog even in de Roomsche kerk waar avonddienst <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>was, het was een mooi gezicht<c type="kk">/</c> al die boeren en de <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>boerinnen met hun zwarte kleeren en witte mutsen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>en de kerk zag er zoo vriendelijk uit bij het avondlicht. <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>Gij moet het maar dadelijk aan den Hr. Tersteeg ook <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>zeggen ik 8 dagen daarheen ga om daarna verder <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>te zien, laat ZEd. dezen brief lezen als gij wilt en <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>wensch vooral Hem en Mevrouw veel goeds toe voor <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>mij in het nieuwe jaar. Schrijf U zeer in haast<c type="kk">/</c> Anna <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>en de meisjes<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> en Cor gingen naar Prinsenhage en Pa <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>wilde ik maar met hen zou medegaan<c type="kp">_</c> Tante<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> kwam met <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hen in het rijtuig terug en ik wandelde met Willem Car<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>bentus.─<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Nu jongen, beste broer, wat waren het goede <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dagen toen wij allen zamen waren,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> heb een goeden <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>oudejaarsavond en geloof mij</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab>Uw liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab>Spoedig wel meer ─ à Dieu. Mocht gij <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>schrijven adresseer dan Uw brief naar <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Dordt.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Etten, 31 December 1876<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I sincerely wish you the best in the new year, I wish you well and may you be blessed in all things. Wonderful to have seen each other again, how beautiful it was that morning you left, and how often we’ll think back on that trip to Chaam.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs>’s eye is hurting a lot again, she has a bandage on; <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> delivered such a beautiful sermon again this morning.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now this evening New Year’s Eve again, if only you were here.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now then, there’s something I must tell you: a couple of days ago <rs type="pers" key="306">Mr Braat</rs> of Dordrecht<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> paid a visit to <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs> and they spoke about me, and Uncle asked Mr B. whether he would have a place for me, if I should wish it. Mr B. thought he might have a place, and said that I should come sometime to talk about it. So I went there early yesterday morning; <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs> and I, too, thought it was something we shouldn’t let pass without seeing what it was.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Agreed that after the New Year I should go to him for a week, after that we’ll see.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">There are many things that make it desirable, first and foremost my being back in Holland near <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs>, and also you and the others.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Moreover, the salary would certainly be a little better than with <rs type="pers" key="682">Mr Jones</rs>, and especially with an eye to later, when a man has need of more, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> one is obliged to think of such things.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As far as the other thing is concerned, for these reasons I won’t give it up. <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs>’s spirit is so great and many-sided, and at all events I hope that something of it will develop in me. The change means that now, instead of teaching those boys, I’ll be working in a bookshop.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How often we’ve longed to be together, and how terrible it is to feel so far away from one another in cases of illness or anxiety, as we felt, for example, during your illness, and then the feeling that lack of money may very well stand in the way of our being together in times of need.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s quite possible, then, that I’ll go there.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yesterday evening I was at <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs>’s to tell him that I’d just been to Dordrecht, it was a stormy evening, you can imagine how beautiful the road to Princenhage was with the dark clouds with their silver linings. I also went briefly to the Roman Catholic church, where evening Mass was under way, it was a beautiful sight, all those peasants and their wives with their black clothes and white caps, and the church looked so friendly in the evening light. You must also tell <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> straightaway that I’ll be going there for a week to see how it goes, let His Hon. read this letter, if you will, and be sure to give him and <rs type="pers" key="788">his wife</rs> my best wishes for a happy New Year. I’m writing in great haste, <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="407 401">the girls</rs>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> and <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> went to Princenhage, and <rs type="pers" key=" 526">Pa</rs> wanted me to go with them. <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt</rs>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> came back with them in the carriage and I went for a walk with <rs type="pers" key="325">Willem Carbentus</rs>.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> Now, old boy, dear brother, what good days those were when we were all together,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> have a good New Year’s Eve and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>More soon – adieu. If you write, send your letter to Dordrecht.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Like Theo, Vincent had spent the Christmas holidays at home in Etten.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Presumably Vincent and Theo travelled to Chaam, a village c. 17 km south-east of Etten, to attend a service conducted by their <rs type="pers" key="526">father</rs>, who regularly substituted for the minister there. The trip was recollected again in <ref target="let414.xml">letter 414</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="306">Pieter Kornelis Braat</rs>, manager of the bookshop <rs type="pers" key="291">Blussé &amp; Van Braam</rs> in Dordrecht. <rs type="pers" key="305">Frans Braat</rs> had written to his father, urging him to give Vincent a job. <rs type="pers" key="307">Dirk Braat</rs>, another son of P.K. Braat, recollected that there was actually no vacancy, but ‘father did not want to refuse Frans’. See <hi rend="ital">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 1, pp. 108-110 (quotation on p. 108).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>There were plans to discuss Vincent’s future when he was home at the end of the year. <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote on 6 December 1876 to Theo: ‘I long so much to speak with Vincent when he comes at Christmas, to see what will become of him. I sometimes fear that the <rs type="pers" key="682">Rev. Jones</rs> exploits him a little as an errand boy and cannot believe that his present path will lead to a proper livelihood’ (FR b2800). <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> also wrote to Theo of the need for a change: ‘He himself did not see much light in his future, but imagined he had to persevere because he thought he must – though I see no grounds for that ‘must’ without study, but it’s good he’s coming and we can talk about it again properly’ (FR b2803, 18 December 1876).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Theo, for his part, got involved in the matter and told his parents of a vacancy, upon which <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to him: ‘I responded immediately to the advertisement you mentioned – but no answer. It is intended for someone who is at least 24 years old’ (FR b2802, 18 December 1876).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Even though <rs type="pers" key="306">Braat</rs> conferred with <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs>, and both Vincent and Theo were acquainted with his son <rs type="pers" key="305">Frans</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> maintained that the position had materialized without intercession or mediation: ‘You can understand that we positively recognize it as a ray of light from above and the answer to our prayers. By no means did we or anyone else, Uncle Cent included, have a hand in it – it is through meeting Vincent and having faith in him, so to speak, that it was offered to him. He himself sees no prospects in what has gone before and in his own wishes, so why look for something else abroad and not take this wonderful opportunity near us and you?’ (FR b2804, to Theo, 18 December 1876).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>On the same day as Vincent wrote this letter – 31 December – <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘An opportunity seems to be opening up for Vincent. He will have written to you about it. It’s like a ray of hope, the more so at the end of the year. I should so much like to have him closer, also to you. From Dordrecht to here it costs only 1.70 guilders return. He could be with us now and then on Sundays. Let us hope. It seems to us his eyes are clearer’ (FR b2804).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>His other sisters, <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="401">Elisabeth</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt Cornelie</rs>, Uncle Vincent’s wife.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Van Gogh’s cousin <rs type="pers" key="325">Willem Carbentus</rs>, the son of <rs type="pers" key="41">Uncle Arie Carbentus</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="13">Aunt Fie van Bemmel</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Possibly an allusion to <rs type="pers" key="31">Clemens Brentano</rs>’s ‘<rs type="lit" key="15">Der Spinnerin Nachtlied</rs>’, <ref target="let018.xml#n-1">see letter 18, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>This could mean either that Theo already knew Vincent’s new address in Dordrecht or that he could send his letters in care of the bookshop <rs type="pers" key="291">Blussé &amp; Van Braam</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>