<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Wednesday, 3 April 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let143"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">143</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">121</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">142</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Wednesday, 3 April 1878</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Wednesday, 3 April 1878.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b141 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 3 April 1878’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0141" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000149_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000149_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000149_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000149_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000149_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0141" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000149_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000149_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000149_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000149_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000149_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000149_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam 3 April 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Over hetgeen wij bespraken<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> heb ik nog gedacht, en onwillekeurig dacht ik aan het <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>woord “nous sommes aujourd’hui ce que nous étions hier”.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Dat wil niet <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>zeggen dat men moet stilstaan en niet mag trachten zich te ontwikkelen, integendeel <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>is er een drangreden om dat wel te doen en te vinden.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar om aan dat woord trouw te blijven mag men niet achteruitgaan en <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>als men is begonnen om de dingen met een vrijen en vertrouwenden blik <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>aan te zien dan mag men daar niet van terugkomen of afwijken.</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zij die zeiden “nous sommes aujourd’hui ce que nous étions hier”<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>dat waren honnêtes hommes,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> hetgeen blijkbaar is uit de grondwet die zij <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>opstelden<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> die wel ten allen tijde zal blijven en waarvan wel is gezegd <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>geworden dat zij was geschreven avec le rayon d’en haut et d’un doigt de feu.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>Het is goed te zijn “honnête homme” en te trachten dat inderdaad meer <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>te worden en bijna en ook geheellijk<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> en als men gelooft dat daartoe hoort te <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>zijn “homme intérieur et spirituel”<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> dan doet men wel.─</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als men het maar zeker en vast wist dat men daaronder hoorde zou men <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>altijd gerust en bedaard zijn gang gaan<c type="kk">/</c> niet twijfelende aan de goede <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>uitkomst in het einde.─ Er was eens een man die op zekeren dag in eene kerk ging <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>en vroeg<c type="kk">/</c> kan het zijn dat mijn ijver mij heeft bedrogen<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik een verkeerden weg <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>heb ingeslagen en het niet goed heb aangelegd, och<c type="kk">/</c> of ik uit deze onzekerheid <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>ware en de vaste overtuiging kon hebben dat ik eindelijk zal overwinnen <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>en slagen. En toen antwoordde hem eene stem<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> En als gij dat nu zeker <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>wist wat zoudt gij dan doen ─ doe nu alsof gij het zeker wist en <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>gij zult niet beschaamd worden.─<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Toen ging de man voort op zijn weg<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>niet ongeloovig maar geloovig<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> en terug naar zijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> niet langer twijfelende <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>of wankelende.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat nu aangaat homme intérieur et spirituel te zijn, zou men dat niet <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>in zich kunnen ontwikkelen door de kennis van de geschiedenis in het algemeen <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>en van bepaalde personen van alle tijden in het bijzonder<c type="kk">/</c> van de Bijbelsche <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>geschiedenis af tot die van de omwenteling<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> toe en van de Odyssée<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> tot de boeken <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>van Dickens en Michelet toe<c type="kp">_</c> En zou men niet iets kunnen leeren uit het werk <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>van zulken als Rembrandt of uit de Mauvaises herbes van Breton<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> of Les heures de la <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>journée van Millet<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> of le bénédicité van de Groux<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> of Brion<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> of le conscrit van de Groux<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/> <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>(of van Conscience<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> anders) of zijn apothécaire<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> of Les grands chênes van Dupré<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/> of de molens en <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>zandvlakten van Michel<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-o-22"/> zelfs.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is door steeds in die gedachten en dingen te volharden dat men ten laatste met <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>een goeden zuurdeessem doortrokken wordt<c type="kk">/</c> dien van droevig maar altijd blijde<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="23" xml:id="note-o-23"/> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>en dat blijkbaar zal worden als de tijd van de vruchten gekomen is in ons leven<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>aan vruchten van goede werken.─<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-o-24"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Le rayon d’en haut schijnt niet altijd op ons en is wel eens achter de wolken en <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zonder dat licht kan een mensch niet leven en is niets waard en kan niets goeds doen en wie zou beweeren <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>dat men zonder geloof in dat hooger licht kan leven en zich niet zou <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>bekommeren om dat te krijgen zou bedrogen uitkomen.</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wij hebben er nogal veel over gesproken wat voor ons pligt is en hoe wij tot <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>iets goeds zouden komen, en wij kwamen teregt tot het besluit dat vooreerst <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>het ons doel moet zijn om eene bepaalde betrekking te vinden en een vak <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>waaraan wij ons geheel kunnen toewijden.</ab>
                <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>
<ab rend="indent">En ik geloof dat wij het ook eens waren op dit punt<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. dat men letten moet <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>vooral op het einde en dat eene overwinning die men zou behalen <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>na een geheel leven van werken en inspanning beter is dan eene <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>die reeds spoediger wordt behaald.</ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wie opregt leeft en ware moeite en teleurstelling ondervindt en daardoor <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>toch niet wordt verslagen is meer waard dan een wien alles voor den <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>wind zou gaan en die niets zou kennen dan betrekkelijken voorspoed. <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Want wie zijn het in wie men het duidelijkst iets hoogers opmerkt ─ het zijn <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>zulken op wie het woord van toepassing is “laboureurs votre vie est triste, laboureurs <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>vous souffrez dans la vie, laboureurs vous êtes bienheureux”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="25" xml:id="note-o-25"/> het zijn zulken <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>die de teekenen dragen van “toute une vie de lutte et de travail soutenu sans <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>fléchir jamais”.─<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-o-26"/> Het is goed te trachten om zoo te worden.</ab>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dus gaan wij vooruit op onzen weg “undefessi favente Deo”.─<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-o-27"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
  <ab rend="indent">Wat mij aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> ik moet een goed prediker worden, die wat te zeggen heeft <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>dat goed is en nuttig kan zijn in de wereld, en het is misschien wel goed <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dat ik een betrekkelijk langen tijd van voorbereiding heb en sterk bevestigd <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>word in eene vaste overtuiging voor ik er toe word geroepen om daarover <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>tot anderen te spreken. <lb n="65a" xml:id="l-65a"/> Het is regt dat<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> voor men dat werk begint een schat vergadere <lb n="65b" xml:id="l-65b"/>van dingen waar anderen iets aan hebben kunnen.</ab>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab rend="indent">Laat ons maar stillekens voortgaan, alle dingen onderzoekende en het <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>goede behoudende<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-o-28"/> en trachtende altijd meer te weten te komen wat <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>nuttig is en meer ondervinding opdoende.</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wee-moed is wel een goed ding om te hebben als men het maar in twee <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>woorden schrijft<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="ital">wee</hi> is in ieder mensch<c type="kk">/</c> daar heeft een ieder reden genoeg <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>voor maar <hi rend="ital">moed</hi> moet men er bij hebben hoe meer hoe beter en <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>het is goed iemand te zijn die nooit wanhoopt.<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-o-29"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als wij maar trachten om opregt te leven, dan zal het ons goed gaan ook al zullen wij <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>dan ook onvermijdelijk opregt verdriet en ware teleurstellingen ondervinden en ook waarschijnlijk <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>ware fouten begaan en verkeerde dingen doen, maar het is zeker waar dat het beter is <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>te zijn vurig van geest<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-o-30"/> al begaat men dan ook meer fouten<c type="kk">/</c> dan bekrompen en al te voorzigtig<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>Het is goed om zooveel lief te hebben als men kan want daarin is de ware sterkte en wie <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>veel liefheeft die doet veel en die vermag veel<c type="kk">/</c> en wat met liefde gedaan wordt dat wordt <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>goed gedaan<c type="kp">_</c> als men getroffen wordt door t’een of ander boek<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. om maar <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>iets te noemen “L’hirondelle, l’alouette, le rossignol”,<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-o-31"/> Les aspirations de l’automne, “Je vois d’ici une dame”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="32" xml:id="note-o-32"/> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>“j’aimais cette petite ville singulière” van Michelet<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="33" xml:id="note-o-33"/> dan is het omdat het uit het hart is geschreven <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>in eenvoudigheid en met armoede van geest<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="34" xml:id="note-o-34"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als men maar weinige woorden zou zeggen, maar die eene beteekenis <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>hadden, zou men beter doen dan met er veel te zeggen die maar ijdele <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>klanken waren en even gemakkelijk zouden zijn uit te spreken als zij weinig nut <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>zouden doen.</ab>
                <lb n="86a" xml:id="l-86a"/>
<ab rend="indent">De liefde is het beste en edelste in het menschen hart, vooral wanneer zij in het leven <lb n="86b" xml:id="l-86b"/>is beproefd als het goud in het vuur,<anchor n="35" xml:id="note-o-35"/> gelukkig is hij en vast in zichzelven die veel heeft <lb n="86c" xml:id="l-86c"/>liefgehad en<c type="kk">/</c> al heeft hij ook gewankeld en getwijfeld<c type="kk">/</c> dat goddelijk vuur heeft bewaard en is teruggekeerd <lb n="86d" xml:id="l-86d"/>tot hetgeen was in den beginne<anchor n="36" xml:id="note-o-36"/> en niet sterven zal <lb n="86e" xml:id="l-86e"/>in eeuwigheid.─<anchor n="37" xml:id="note-o-37"/> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>Als men maar trouw blijft liefhebben wat waarlijk liefde waardig is<anchor n="38" xml:id="note-o-38"/> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>en zijne liefde niet verkwist over waarlijk onbeteekenende en nietige en flaauwhartige <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>dingen dan zal men gaandeweg steeds meer licht krijgen en sterker worden. <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>Hoe eerder men in een bepaalden werkkring en een <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>bepaald vak zoekt bekwaam te worden en eene betrekkelijk zelfstandige denk- en handelwijze aanneemt <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>en hoe meer men zich houdt aan vaste regels<c type="kk">/</c> hoe vaster karakter men zal verkrijgen <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>en daarom hoeft men toch niet bekrompen te worden<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is wijs om dat te doen daar het leven maar kort is en de tijd spoedig voorbij gaat<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>als men in één ding bekwaam is en ééne zaak goed begrijpt dan <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>heeft men inzigt en kennis van vele anderen tegelijk, op den koop toe<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is soms goed om veel in de wereld te gaan en onder menschen te verkeeren <lb n="97a" xml:id="l-97a"/>en men is er bij tijden wel toe verpligt en <lb n="97b" xml:id="l-97b"/>geroepen<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="39" xml:id="note-o-39"/> <lb n="98a" xml:id="l-98a"/>of het kan ééne manier zijn “de se jeter dans le travail sans arrière pensée et de toutes ses forces”<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-o-40"/> <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>maar wie eigentlijk liever maar stillekens alleen aan zijn werk zou <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>zijn en maar zeer weinig vrienden zou willen hebben die gaat het veiligst <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>onder de menschen en in de wereld rond. Men moet het nooit vertrouwen als <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>men zonder moeielijkheden of de een of andere zorg of hindernis is <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>maar het zich niet al te gemakkelijk maken. En ook in de beschaafdste <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>kringen en beste omgeving en omstandigheden moet men iets van den oorspronkelijken <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>aard van een Robinson Crusoe<anchor n="41" xml:id="note-o-41"/> of van een natuurmensch<anchor n="42" xml:id="note-o-42"/> behouden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>want anders heeft men geen wortel in zich zelven<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="43" xml:id="note-o-43"/> en het vuur in zijne ziel <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>nooit laten uitgaan maar het onderhouden, er komt altijd eene gelegenheid <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>waarin dat te pas komt. En wie voor zich zelven de armoede blijft behouden en die liefheeft <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>bezit een grooten schat en zal de stem van zijn geweten steeds duidelijk hooren spreken<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>wie die stem in zijn binnenste die de beste gave Gods is<anchor n="44" xml:id="note-o-44"/> hoort en volgt<c type="kk">/</c> vindt daarin ten laatste een vriend <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>en is nimmer alleen.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gelukkig is hij die geloof heeft in God want hij zal<c type="kk">/</c> al zij het niet zonder <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>moeite en verdriet<c type="kk">/</c> door alle moeielijkheden van het leven ten laatste heenkomen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>Men kan niet beter doen dan onder alles in alle omstandigheden aan <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>alle plaatsen en ten allen tijde de gedachte aan God te behouden en meer aangaande <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>Hem te trachten te weten te komen<c type="kk">/</c> dat kan men zoowel uit den Bijbel als <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>ook uit alle andere dingen.─ Het is goed om te blijven gelooven dat alles wonderbaar <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>is meer dan men zich begrijpen kan want dat is de waarheid<c type="kk">/</c> het is goed om gevoelig en nederig en <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>teeder te blijven van hart,<anchor n="45" xml:id="note-o-45"/> ook al moet men dat gevoelen soms verbergen want dat is dikwijls <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>noodig, het is goed zeer geleerd te zijn in de dingen die verborgen zijn voor de <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>wijzen en verstandigen der wereld maar die als van nature geopenbaard zijn aan de armen <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>en eenvoudigen<c type="kk">/</c> aan de vrouwen en de kinderkens.<anchor n="46" xml:id="note-o-46"/> Want wat kan men leeren dat beter <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>is dan hetgeen God van nature in iedere menschenziel heeft gegeven<c type="kk">/</c> wat in den grond <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>van iedere ziel leeft en liefheeft<c type="kk">/</c> hoopt en gelooft<anchor n="47" xml:id="note-o-47"/> tenzij men het moedwillig vernietige<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>Daar is de behoefte aan niets minder dan het oneindige en wonderbare, en een mensch doet <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>wel als hij met niets dat geringer is tevreden is en zich niet t’huis blijft gevoelen <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>zoolang hij dat niet heeft verkregen.─</ab>
                <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat is de bekentenis die alle groote mannen in hunne werken hebben uitgedrukt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>allen die wat verder hebben gedacht en wat meer hebben gezocht en gewerkt <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>en meer hebben liefgehad dan anderen, die zijn afgestoken naar de diepte <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>van de levenszee. Afsteken naar de diepte dat moeten ook wij doen indien <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>wij willen vangen en als het somtijds gebeurt dat wij den geheelen nacht te arbeiden hebben <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>en niets vangen dan is het goed om het toch nog niet op te geven maar in den morgenstond <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>nogmaals het net uit te werpen.<anchor n="48" xml:id="note-o-48"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>
<ab rend="indent">Laat ons dus maar stillekens voortgaan<c type="kk">/</c> ieder op zijn weg<c type="kk">/</c> steeds op het licht afgaande <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>“sursum corda”<anchor n="49" xml:id="note-o-49"/> en als zulken die weten dat wij zijn wat anderen zijn en dat anderen zijn <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>wat wij zijn<c type="kk">/</c> en dat het goed is om liefde te hebben onder elkander<anchor n="50" xml:id="note-o-50"/> en wel van de beste <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>soort<c type="kk">/</c> die alle dingen gelooft en alle dingen hoopt en alle dingen verdraagt en nimmermeer <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>vergaat.<anchor n="51" xml:id="note-o-51"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>
<ab rend="indent">En ons niet al te bekommerd makende als wij gebreken hebben want die <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>er geen heeft die heeft toch een gebrek namelijk dat hij er geen heeft, en wie volmaakt <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>wijs zou meenen te zijn die zou wel doen met maar weer eens van voren af aan <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>dwaas te worden<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="52" xml:id="note-o-52"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Nous sommes aujourd’hui ce que nous étions hier</hi>, namelijk “<hi rend="ital">honnêtes hommes</hi>” <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>maar die in het vuur van het leven moeten worden beproefd<anchor n="53" xml:id="note-o-53"/> om innerlijk versterkt <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>en bevestigd te worden in hetgeen zij door Gods genade van nature zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoo ga het met ons, jongen, en heb Gij het goed op Uwen weg en God zij met U in <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>alle dingen en doe <hi rend="ital">het</hi> U wel gelukken<c type="kk">/</c> dat is wat U toewenscht met een hartelijken <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>handdruk bij Uw vertrek<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="54" xml:id="note-o-54"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>
<ab>Uw zoo liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>
<ab>’t Is maar een heel klein lichtje<c type="kk">/</c> dat in het kamertje van de zondagschool in de Barndesteeg<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="55" xml:id="note-o-55"/> <lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>laat mij het brandende houden;<anchor n="56" xml:id="note-o-56"/> trouwens als ik het niet doe<c type="kk">/</c> geloof <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>ik niet dat Adler een man is die het zou laten uitgaan.─</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-5" n="5">drangreden &lt; drangrede</note>
<note target="l-70" n="70">reden &lt; rede</note>
<note target="l-80" n="80">rossignol”, &lt; rossignol,</note>
<note target="l-91" n="91">denk- &lt; denk</note>
<note target="l-131" n="131">te arbeiden &lt; arbeiden</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam, 3 April 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I’ve been thinking about what we discussed,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and I couldn’t help thinking of the words ‘we are today what we were yesterday’.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> This isn’t to say that one must stand still and ought not try to develop oneself, on the contrary, there are compelling reasons to do and think so.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But in order to remain faithful to those words one may not retreat and, once one has started to see things with a clear and trusting eye, one ought not to abandon or deviate from that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">They who said ‘we are today what we were yesterday’, those were <hi rend="ital">honnêtes hommes</hi>,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> which is apparent from the constitution they drew up,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> which will remain for all time and of which it has rightly been said that it was written with a ray from on high and a finger of fire.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> It is good to be an ‘honnête homme’ and truly to endeavour to become one both almost and altogether,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> and one does well if one believes that being an ‘homme intérieur et spirituel’ is part of it.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If one only knew for certain that one belonged among them, one would always go one’s way, calmly and collectedly, never doubting that things would turn out well. There was once a man who went into a church one day and asked, can it be that my zeal has deceived me, that I have turned down the wrong path and have gone about things the wrong way, oh, if only I could rid myself of this uncertainty and have the firm conviction that I will eventually overcome and succeed. And then a voice answered him,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> And if you knew that for certain, what would you do? Act now as though you knew it for certain and thou shalt not be ashamed.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> Then the man went on his way, not faithless but believing,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and returned to his work, no longer doubting or wavering.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">As far as being an <hi rend="ital">homme intérieur et spirituel </hi>is concerned, couldn’t one develop that in oneself through knowledge of history in general and of certain people of all eras in particular, from biblical times to the Revolution<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> and from The odyssey<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> to the books of <rs type="pers" key="580">Dickens</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>? And couldn’t one learn something from the work of the likes of <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> or from Weeds by <rs type="pers" key="899">Breton</rs>,<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> or The four times of the day by <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>,<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> or Saying grace by <rs type="pers" key="1063">Degroux</rs>,<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> or <rs type="pers" key="891">Brion</rs>,<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> or The conscript by Degroux<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> (or else by <rs type="pers" key="572">Conscience</rs>
                    <anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/>), or his Apothecary,<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> or The large oaks by <rs type="pers" key="986">Dupré</rs>,<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> or even the mills and sand flats by <rs type="pers" key="1228">Michel</rs>?<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s by persevering in those ideas and things that one at last becomes thoroughly leavened with a good leaven, that of sorrowful yet alway rejoicing,<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/> and which will become apparent when the time of fruitfulness is come in our lives, the fruitfulness of good works.<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-t-24"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The ray from on high doesn’t always shine on us, and is sometimes behind the clouds, and without that light a person cannot live and is worth nothing and can do nothing good, and anyone who maintains that one can live without faith in that higher light and doesn’t worry about attaining it will end up being disappointed.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">We’ve talked quite a lot about what we feel to be our duty and how we should arrive at something good, and we rightly came to the conclusion that first of all our goal must be to find a certain position and a profession to which we can devote ourselves entirely.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And I think that we also agreed on this point, namely that one must pay special attention to the end, and that a victory achieved after lifelong work and effort is better than one achieved more quickly.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He who lives uprightly and experiences true difficulty and disappointment and is nonetheless undefeated by it is worth more than someone who prospers and knows nothing but relative good fortune. For who are they, those in whom one most clearly notices something higher? — it is those to whom the words ‘workers, your life is sad, workers, you suffer in life, workers, you are blessed’ are applicable,<anchor n="25" xml:id="note-t-25"/> it is those who show the signs of ‘bearing a whole life of strife and work without giving way’.<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-t-26"/> It is good to try and become thus.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">So we go on our way ‘undefessi favente Deo’.<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-t-27"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">As far as I’m concerned, I must become a good minister, who has something to say that is good and can be useful in the world, and perhaps it’s good after all that I have a relatively long time of preparation and become secure in a firm conviction before I’m called upon to speak about it to others. It is wise, before one begins that work, to gather together a wealth of things that could benefit others.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Do let us go on quietly, examining all things and holding fast to that which is good,<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-t-28"/> and trying always to learn more that is useful, and gaining more experience.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Woe-spiritedness is quite a good thing to have, if only one writes it as two words, <hi rend="ital">woe </hi>is in all people, everyone has reason enough for it, but one must also have <hi rend="ital">spirit</hi>, the more the better, and it is good to be someone who never despairs.<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-t-29"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If we but try to live uprightly, then we shall be all right, even though we shall inevitably experience true sorrow and genuine disappointments, and also probably make real mistakes and do wrong things, but it’s certainly true that it is better to be fervent in spirit,<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-t-30"/> even if one accordingly makes more mistakes, than narrow-minded and overly cautious. It is good to love as much as one can, for therein lies true strength, and he who loves much does much and is capable of much, and that which is done with love is well done. If one is moved by some book or other, for instance, just to mention something, ‘The swallow, the lark, the nightingale’,<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-t-31"/> The longing for autumn, ‘From here I see a lady’,<anchor n="32" xml:id="note-t-32"/> ‘Never this unique little village’ by <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>,<anchor n="33" xml:id="note-t-33"/> it’s because it’s written from the heart in simplicity and with poverty of spirit.<anchor n="34" xml:id="note-t-34"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If one were to say but few words, though ones with meaning, one would do better than to say many that were only empty sounds, and just as easy to utter as they were of little use.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Love is the best and most noble thing in the human heart, especially when it has been tried and tested in life like gold in the fire,<anchor n="35" xml:id="note-t-35"/> happy is he and strong in himself who has loved much and, even if he has wavered and doubted, has kept that divine fire and has returned to that which was in the beginning<anchor n="36" xml:id="note-t-36"/> and shall never die.<anchor n="37" xml:id="note-t-37"/> If only one continues to love faithfully that which is verily worthy of love,<anchor n="38" xml:id="note-t-38"/> and does not squander his love on truly trivial and insignificant and faint-hearted things, then one will gradually become more enlightened and stronger. The sooner one seeks to become competent in a certain position and in a certain profession, and adopts a fairly independent way of thinking and acting, and the more one observes fixed rules, the stronger one’s character becomes, and yet that doesn’t mean that one has to become narrow-minded.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It is wise to do that, for life is but short and time passes quickly. If one is competent in <hi rend="ital">one </hi>thing and understands <hi rend="ital">one</hi> thing well, one gains at the same time insight into and knowledge of many other things into the bargain.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s sometimes good to go about much in the world and to be among people, and at times one is actually obliged and called upon to do so,<anchor n="39" xml:id="note-t-39"/> or it can be one way of ‘throwing oneself into one’s work unreservedly and with all one’s might’,<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-t-40"/> but he who actually goes quietly about his work, alone, preferring to have but very few friends, goes the most safely among people and in the world. One should never trust it when one is without difficulties or some worry or obstacle, and one shouldn’t make things too easy for oneself. Even in the most cultured circles and the best surroundings and circumstances, one should retain something of the original nature of a Robinson Crusoe<anchor n="41" xml:id="note-t-41"/> or a savage,<anchor n="42" xml:id="note-t-42"/> for otherwise one hath not root in himself,<anchor n="43" xml:id="note-t-43"/> and never let the fire in his soul go out but keep it going, there will always be a time when it will come in useful. And whosoever continues to hold fast to poverty for himself, and embraces it, possesses a great treasure and will always hear the voice of his conscience speaking clearly. Whosoever hears and follows the voice in his innermost being, which is God’s best gift,<anchor n="44" xml:id="note-t-44"/> ultimately finds therein a friend and is never alone. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Happy is he who has faith in God, for he shall overcome all of life’s difficulties in the end, though it be not without pain and sorrow. One cannot do better than to hold fast to the thought of God and endeavour to learn more of Him, amidst everything, in all circumstances, in all places and at all times; one can do this with the Bible as with all other things. It is good to go on believing that everything is miraculous, more so than one can comprehend, for that is the truth, it is good to remain sensitive and lowly and meek in heart,<anchor n="45" xml:id="note-t-45"/> even though one sometimes has to hide that feeling, because that is often necessary, it is good to be very knowledgeable about the things that are hidden from the wise and prudent of the world but that are revealed as though by nature to the poor and simple, to women and babes.<anchor n="46" xml:id="note-t-46"/> For what can one learn that is better than that which God has put by nature into every human soul, that which in the depths of every soul lives and loves, hopes and believes,<anchor n="47" xml:id="note-t-47"/> unless one should wilfully destroy it? There, in that, is the need for nothing less than the boundless and miraculous, and a man does well if he is satisfied with nothing less and doesn’t feel at home until he has acquired it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">That is the avowal that all great men have expressed in their works, all who have thought a little more deeply and have sought and worked a little harder and have loved more than others, who have launched out into the deep of the sea of life. Launching out into the deep is what we too must do if we want to catch anything, and if it sometimes happens that we have to work the whole night and catch nothing, then it is good not to give up after all but to let down the nets again at dawn.<anchor n="48" xml:id="note-t-48"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So let us simply go on quietly, each his own way, always following the light ‘sursum corda’,<anchor n="49" xml:id="note-t-49"/> and as such who know that we are what others are and that others are what we are, and that it is good to have love one to another<anchor n="50" xml:id="note-t-50"/> namely of the best kind, that believeth all things and hopeth all things, endureth all things and never faileth.<anchor n="51" xml:id="note-t-51"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And not troubling ourselves too much if we have shortcomings, for he who has none has a shortcoming nonetheless, namely that he has none, and he who thinks he is perfectly wise would do well to start over from the beginning and become a fool.<anchor n="52" xml:id="note-t-52"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">We are today what we were yesterday</hi>, namely <hi rend="ital">‘honnêtes hommes</hi>’, but ones who must be tried with the fire of life<anchor n="53" xml:id="note-t-53"/> to be innerly strengthened and confirmed in that which they are by nature through the grace of God.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">May it be so with us, old boy, and I wish you well on your way, and God be with you in all things, and make you succeed at <hi rend="ital">that</hi>, that is what is wished you with a hearty handshake at your departure<anchor n="54" xml:id="note-t-54"/> by</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your most loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>It’s only a very small light, the one in the room of the Sunday school in Barndesteeg,<anchor n="55" xml:id="note-t-55"/> let me keep it burning;<anchor n="56" xml:id="note-t-56"/> in any event, if I don’t do it, I don’t think that <rs type="pers" key="251">Adler</rs> is the kind of man who would let it go out.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>From <ref target="#l-44">ll. 44-45</ref> it emerges that the brothers discussed their duties and their vocation: Theo was to become acquainted with Goupil in Paris, and Vincent was planning to become a catechist. <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had advised Vincent against this on 16 March 1878 (FR b970), and had complained of it before to Theo: ‘Is it any wonder that we feel pain and sorrow upon discovering that he has absolutely no <hi rend="ital">joy</hi> in life? But he continues to plod on, with his head bowed, whereas we did what we could to help him towards an honourable goal! It is as though he deliberately chooses the difficult path’ (FR b968, 2 March 1878).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Theo, now on his sales trip for Goupil, planned his visit to Amsterdam to coincide with Vincent’s birthday on 30 March (FR b973 and b974).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Mr van Gogh asked Theo for his impression of Vincent: ‘We think it strange that we have had no letter from him, not even after his birthday. He doesn’t write as regularly as he used to. I do so fear that he feels very unhappy in himself, but what can one do about it? We encourage him, and give him the opportunity to continue his studies, even though we hardly know how we shall manage. It’s a sickly existence that he has made for himself, I’m afraid, and how much he will still have to struggle, and we with him. Tell us whether you visited him and how you found him’ (FR b973, 1 April 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Taken from <rs type="pers" key="707">Jules Michelet</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="162">
                            <hi rend="ital">Histoire de la Révolution française</hi>
                        </rs>. 2 vols. Paris n.d., vol. 1, p. 32. There are various editions of this book. The volumes in which Michelet treated the period from 1789 until the execution of Robespierre in 1794 appeared from 1847 to 1853. He later expanded this already sizeable work by including the history of events up to the Battle of Waterloo in 1815. Michelet attributed the most important role in the French Revolution to the people, and based his work on thorough archival research.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>It is possible that Van Gogh borrowed this common expression, originally stemming from French court culture of the seventeenth century, from <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="11">
                            <hi rend="ital">L’amour</hi>
                        </rs>: ‘but the universal, agreeable man, who is well-versed in everything, the kind Louis <hi rend="sc">xiv</hi>’s century admired and commended, the kind people called the “decent man”’ (mais l’homme universel et agréable, qui se connait à tout, ce que le siècle de Louis <hi rend="sc">xiv</hi> admirait et recommandait, ce qu’on appelait “l’honnête homme”’. Michelet, <hi rend="ital">L’amour</hi>, p. 271).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The constitution that was drawn up at the time of the French Revolution.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Both phrases occur in <rs type="pers" key="666">Victor Hugo</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="184">
                            <hi rend="ital">Les contemplations</hi>
                        </rs>, in book 3, chapter 30 ‘Magnitudo parvi’, and book 6, chapter 23 ‘Les mages’, respectively. Ed. Pierre Albouy. Paris 1990, pp. 204, 374. It is however uncertain whether Van Gogh, who in fact links these phrases to the constitution, actually took them from this work. Cf. <ref target="let309.xml">letter 309</ref>, <ref target="let388.xml">388</ref> and the saying ‘a ray from on high’ in <ref target="let368.xml">letter 368</ref> in a quotation from <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>. For the related phrase ‘something on high’, <ref target="let288.xml#n-15">see letter 288, n. 15.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Acts" chap="26" v="29">Acts 26:29</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Van Gogh could have taken this phrase from <rs type="pers" key="833">Taine</rs>’s essay on <rs type="pers" key="563">Carlyle</rs> in <rs type="lit" key="128">
                            <hi rend="ital">Histoire de la littérature anglaise</hi>
                        </rs> (see Taine 1874, vol. 5, p. 282 (chapter 4)). That he was familiar with it emerges from <ref target="let133.xml">letter 133</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Acts" chap="11" v="9">Acts 11:9</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Isa" chap="54" v="4">Isa. 54:4</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="20" v="27">John 20:27</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="679">Thomas a Kempis</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="35">
                            <hi rend="ital">L’Imitation de Jésus-Christ</hi>
                        </rs>, book I, chapter 25, 2. Van Gogh cited the title of this book in letter 129, <ref target="let129.xml#n-24">see letter 129, n. 24</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>The French Revolution.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="655">Homer</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="144">
                            <hi rend="ital">The Odyssey</hi>
                        </rs>, the antique tale of the wanderings of Odysseus.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="899">Jules Breton</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Mauvaises herbes</hi> (Weeds) (present whereabouts unknown), exhibited at the 1869 Salon, was once part of the Wilstach Collection (USA). The work was reproduced in <hi rend="ital">Album Boetzel. Le Salon</hi> <hi rend="ital">1869</hi>; the same reproduction appeared in Philippe Burty, ‘L’Album Boetzel. Salon de 1869’, <hi rend="ital">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 11 (1869), 2nd series, pp. 252-263 (ill. on p. 257). <rs type="ill" key="21">Ill. 21</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1226">Jean-François Millet</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="1679 1680 1682 1682">
                            <hi rend="ital">The four times of the day</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let037.xml#n-16">see letter 37, n. 16.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1063">Charles Degroux</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Saying grace</hi>&gt;, c. 1861 (Brussels, Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts). <rs type="ill" key="135">Ill. 135</rs>. There were various versions of this painting. See exhib. cat. Ypres 1995, pp. 102-108, cat. no. 97-111.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="891">Gustave Brion</rs>, <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="643">Saying grace</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let142.xml#n-5">see letter 142, n. 5.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
<ab>Van Gogh’s mention of <rs type="pers" key="1063">Charles Degroux</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">The conscript</hi> no doubt refers to <hi rend="ital">The conscript’s return </hi>(present whereabouts unknown) and not one of the two versions of <hi rend="ital">The conscript’s departure</hi>, which Van Gogh says in <ref target="let164.xml">letter 164</ref> not to have known previously. <rs type="ill" key="137">Ill. 137</rs>. See exhib. cat. Ypres 1995, pp. 97-101, cat. nos. 69-90, esp. no. 78.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="572">Henri Conscience</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="77">
                            <hi rend="ital">Le conscrit</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let089.xml">see letter 89</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>A work by <rs type="pers" key="1063">Degroux</rs> titled <hi rend="ital">Apothecary</hi> has not been traced. Perhaps Van Gogh is referring to the <rs type="otherart" key="142">
                            <hi rend="ital">Study for the doctor’s visit</hi>
                        </rs>, <rs type="otherart" key="143">
                            <hi rend="ital">The doctor’s visit</hi>
                        </rs> or <rs type="otherart" key="144">
                            <hi rend="ital">The quack</hi>
                        </rs> (present whereabouts of all three paintings unknown). Cf. exhib. cat. Ypres 1995, pp. 88, 135, cat. nos. 42-43, 256.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="986">Jules Dupré</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="78">
                            <hi rend="ital">The large oaks</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let137.xml#n-21">see letter 137, n. 21.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="22" xml:id="n-22" target="#note-t-22">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1228">Georges Michel</rs> painted numerous landscapes, a number of which appear in the series of reproductions published by Durand-Ruel; cf. <ref target="let073.xml">letter 73</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="23" xml:id="n-23" target="#note-t-23">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="2 Cor" chap="6" v="10">2 Cor. 6:10</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="24" xml:id="n-24" target="#note-t-24">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Col" chap="1" v="10">Col. 1:10</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="25" xml:id="n-25" target="#note-t-25">
<ab>Taken from <rs type="pers" key="744">Emile Souvestre</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="96">
                            <hi rend="ital">Les derniers bretons</hi>
                        </rs>. Paris 1858, vol. 2, p. 227: ‘O toilers! You lead a hard life in this world ... O toilers! You suffer in life; toilers, you are truly fortunate! ... brothers, life is sad’. (O laboureurs! vous menez une vie dure dans le monde ... O laboureurs! vous souffrez dans la vie; laboureurs, vous êtes bien heureux! ... frères la vie est triste). Van Gogh copied this passage into one of the poetry albums. See Pabst 1988, p. 29.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="26" xml:id="n-26" target="#note-t-26">
  <ab>Stemming from <rs type="pers" key="683">Lamennais</rs>’s text <rs type="lit" key="141">
                            <hi rend="ital">Amschaspands et Darvands</hi>
                        </rs>, quoted in <ref target="let120.xml#n-24">letter 120, n. 24.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="27" xml:id="n-27" target="#note-t-27">
<ab>Read: ‘indefessus (or indefessi)’ – ‘tirelessly with God’s grace’. See also <ref target="let136.xml#n-28">letter 136, n. 28.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Lees: ‘good (in the sense of being prudent) that ...’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="28" xml:id="n-28" target="#note-t-28">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Thess" chap="5" v="21">1 Thess. 5:21</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="29" xml:id="n-29" target="#note-t-29">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs>’s expression ‘I never despair’ is frequently quoted; it could have been derived from <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="hymn" chap="56" v="1">hymn 56:1</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="hymn" chap="56" v="9">hymn 56:9</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="30" xml:id="n-30" target="#note-t-30">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rom" chap="12" v="11">Rom. 12:11</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="31" xml:id="n-31" target="#note-t-31">
<ab>These three references to <rs type="pers" key="707">Jules Michelet</rs> were all taken from his <rs type="lit" key="133">
                            <hi rend="ital">L’oiseau</hi>
                        </rs>. The first refers to a translation of a poem by <rs type="pers" key="734">Rückert</rs> which appears in the chapter ‘Suite des migrations. L’hirondelle’. The second is part of the chapter ‘Le chant’. The last was taken from the title of the chapter ‘Le rossignol, l’art en l’infini’ (Michelet 1861, pp. 152-153, 196-204 and 243-253, respectively). Van Gogh copied ‘L’hirondelle’ and ‘Le rossignol’ into one of the poetry albums; see Pabst 1988, pp. 14-16.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="32" xml:id="n-32" target="#note-t-32">
<ab> ‘<rs type="lit" key="10">Les aspirations de l’automne</rs>’ is the title of a chapter in <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="11">
                            <hi rend="ital">L’amour</hi>
                        </rs> and ‘Je vois d’ici une dame’ the beginning of a passage within that chapter (<ref target="let014.xml#n-19">see letter 14, n. 19</ref>). Van Gogh had copied the piece earlier, both for his brother – in <ref target="let014.xml">letter 14</ref> and in a poetry album – and for <rs type="pers" key="201">Annie Slade-Jones</rs>, his former landlady in London; see Pabst 1988, pp. 22, 65.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="33" xml:id="n-33" target="#note-t-33">
  <ab>‘J’aimais cette petite ville singulière’ has been taken from <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="185">
                            <hi rend="ital">La mer</hi>
                        </rs> (1861), book 1, ‘Un regard sur les mers’, chapter 2, ‘Plages, grèves et falaises’, which describes the pleasant seaside town of Granville in Normandy. Ed. Paris 1861, pp. 13-20 (quotation on p. 14). This also occurs in a poetry album made for Theo, as well as on a loose sheet containing several texts (<ref target="RM05.xml">see RM5</ref>). See Pabst 1988, pp. 13, 87. In <hi rend="ital">La mer</hi>, Michelet describes in a lyrical, discursive manner the relationship between man and the sea.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="34" xml:id="n-34" target="#note-t-34">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="5" v="3">Matt. 5:3</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="35" xml:id="n-35" target="#note-t-35">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Zech" chap="13" v="9">Zech. 13:9</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="36" xml:id="n-36" target="#note-t-36">
<ab>Biblical.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="37" xml:id="n-37" target="#note-t-37">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="11" v="26">John 11:26</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="38" xml:id="n-38" target="#note-t-38">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 John" chap="2" v="5">1 John 2:5</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="39" xml:id="n-39" target="#note-t-39">
<ab>This conviction was inspired in part by <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs>, who urged Vincent to seek human society in order to improve his social skills. <ref target="let141.xml#l-55">See letter 141, l. 55</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="40" xml:id="n-40" target="#note-t-40">
<ab>This pronouncement can be traced to a conversation Van Gogh had with the <rs type="pers" key="385">Rev. Gagnebin</rs>; <ref target="let142.xml">see letter 142</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="41" xml:id="n-41" target="#note-t-41">
<ab>Robinson Crusoe is the protagonist of <rs type="pers" key="581">Daniel Defoe</rs>’s novel <rs type="lit" key="186">
                            <hi rend="ital">The life and strange surprising adventures of Robinson Crusoe of York, mariner</hi>
                        </rs> (1719), the story of a man who lived for years in isolation on a tropical island. His physical and moral survival is due to his strength of mind and resourceful nature.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="42" xml:id="n-42" target="#note-t-42">
<ab>Van Gogh is perhaps referring to the native Friday, Robinson Crusoe’s companion during his last years on the island.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="43" xml:id="n-43" target="#note-t-43">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" v="21">Matt. 13:21</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="44" xml:id="n-44" target="#note-t-44">
<ab>Regarding the conscience as a gift of God, <ref target="let133.xml#n-12">see letter 133, n. 12.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="45" xml:id="n-45" target="#note-t-45">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="11" v="29">Matt. 11:29</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="46" xml:id="n-46" target="#note-t-46">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="11" v="25">Matt. 11:25</bibleref>; cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="10" v="21">Luke 10:21</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="47" xml:id="n-47" target="#note-t-47">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Cor" chap="13" v="13">1 Cor. 13:13</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="48" xml:id="n-48" target="#note-t-48">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="5" v="4">Luke 5:4</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="49" xml:id="n-49" target="#note-t-49">
<ab>‘(Let us) raise our hearts on high’. An old liturgical exclamation uttered upon the elevation of the Eucharist; cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Lam" chap="3" v="41">Lam. 3:41</bibleref>, ‘Nun levemus corda nostra cum manibus ad Dominum in caelos’. ‘Sursum corda’ was <rs type="pers" key="711">Thomas Moore</rs>’s motto. Cf. also <vg:bibleref book="Hymn" chap="43">hymn 43</vg:bibleref>, ‘Hoog, omhoog, het hart naar boven’ (Raise, on high, our hearts to the heavens) and Pabst 1988, p. 62.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="50" xml:id="n-50" target="#note-t-50">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="13" v="35">John 13:35</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="51" xml:id="n-51" target="#note-t-51">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Cor" chap="13" vr="7-8">1 Cor. 13:7-8</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="52" xml:id="n-52" target="#note-t-52">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Cor" chap="3" v="18">1 Cor. 3:18</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="53" xml:id="n-53" target="#note-t-53">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Pet" chap="1" v="7">1 Pet. 1:7</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="54" xml:id="n-54" target="#note-t-54">
<ab>Vincent must have sent this letter to Theo’s temporary address. The sales trip lasted for several weeks: Theo had already visited Amsterdam, Utrecht and Rotterdam before 4 April, but by 19 April the trip had evidently come to an end. In this period Theo paid Vincent a second visit (FR b1085, <rs type="pers" key="787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs> to Theo, 4 April, and FR b975).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="55" xml:id="n-55" target="#note-t-55">
<ab>
  <ref target="let141.xml">See letter 141</ref> with regard to <rs type="pers" key="251">August Carel Adler</rs>’s Sunday school in Barndesteeg. <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> was not very enthusiastic about Vincent’s attachment to the Sunday school; over a week later he wrote to Theo: ‘I received a detailed letter from Vincent. He wanted so much to continue with that Sunday school, but even though I allowed him not to break it off so abruptly, I seriously advised him yet again to distance himself from it, in view of the great amount of work required by his studies and because of the danger of putting his heart into an activity of secondary importance and neglecting the main issue. Did you visit him? And how did you find him? We heard from <rs type="pers" key="317 318">the Strickers</rs> that they had once again been delighted to have him stay with them’ (FR b974, 12 April 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="56" xml:id="n-56" target="#note-t-56">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Lev" chap="6" v="9">Lev. 6:9</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Lev" chap="6" vr="12-13">Lev. 6:12-13</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>