<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Tuesday, 18 September 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let131"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">131</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">110</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">130</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Tuesday, 18 September 1877</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Tuesday, 18 September 1877.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Theo’s sales trip <ref target="let128.xml">(128)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Harry Gladwell’s visit <ref target="let130.xml">(130)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b129 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 18 Sept. 1877’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0129" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000138_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000138_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000138_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000138_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000138_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0129" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000138_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000138_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000138_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000138_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000138_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000138_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam 18 Sept. 1877.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>De tijd nadert dat Gij voor de Heeren G&amp;C<hi rend="ss">ie</hi> zult op reis gaan en reeds verheug ik mij er op <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>U weer te zien en te spreken.─</ab>
                <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat ik U wilde vragen is dit. Zoudt Gij het niet zoo kunnen schikken dat wij eenigen <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>tijd wat gerust en bedaard zamen zouden zijn, ik dacht zoo minstens een geheelen dag.</ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Deze week was Mendes uit de stad, logeert eenige dagen bij een D<hi rend="ss">s</hi>. Schröder<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> te Zwolle die in <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>der tijd les van hem kreeg. Hierdoor minder bezet zijnde kon ik het voornemen ten uitvoer <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>brengen om de etsen van Rembrandt op het Trippenhuis eens te gaan zien<c type="kk">/</c> ben er dezen</ab>
                <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>
<ab>morgen geweest en ben blij ik het heb gedaan.─<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu dacht ik daar zijnde: zouden Theo en ik die niet zamen eens kunnen <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>zien? denk er eens over of Gij een dag of nog langer kunt afzonderen voor dergelijke <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>dingen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat zou iemand als Pa die zoo menigmaal des nachts, ook met een lantaarn voorzien,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>togten maakt b.v. naar een zieke of stervende om met hem te spreken over Hem wiens woord ook nog een <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>licht is<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> in den nacht van lijden en doodsangst, gevoel hebben voor etsen van Rembrandt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Zooals de vlucht naar Egypte bij nacht<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> of de begrafenis van Jezus.─<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> Die verzameling <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>op het Trippenhuis is prachtig en ik zag er veel dat ik vroeger nooit had ontmoet, ook sprak men mij daar over teekeningen van R. op Fodor.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Als Gij denkt het goed is spreek er dan eens over met den Heer Tersteeg, en schrijf van tevoren <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>een woordje wanneer Gij komt<c type="kk">/</c> dan werk ik vooruit om vrij en ter uwer beschikking <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>te zijn wanneer Gij komt.─</ab>
                <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik kan niets van dien aard zien, ook schilderijen b.v., of ik denk aan U en aan Pa en <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>allen t’huis<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zit anders tot over de ooren in het werk want het wordt mij duidelijk wat ik eigentlijk <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>moet weten, wat zij weten en waardoor zij bezield worden die ik gaarne zou <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>willen volgen. “Onderzoek de schriften”<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> staat er niet voor niets maar dat woord is <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>een goeden wegwijzer, en ik zou wel zulk een schriftgeleerde willen worden die als een heer des huizes <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>uit zijnen schat oude en nieuwe dingen kan voortbrengen.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maandag avond bragt ik bij Vos &amp; Kee door, die hebben elkaar wel lief en dat waar Liefde woont <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>de Heer Zijn zegen gebiedt<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> kan men wel opmerken. het is daar aardig aan huis, alleen erg <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>jammer dat hij geen domine is kunnen blijven.─<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Als men hen zoo zamen ziet zitten des avonds <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>bij het vriendelijk licht<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> van hunne lamp in het huiskamertje en daar vlak bij de slaapkamer van <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>hun jongen<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> die van tijd tot tijd wakker wordt en zijn Moeder om het een of ander vraagt dan <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>is dat een idylle maar zij kennen de barre dagen en slapelooze nachten ook en angst en zorg.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Wandelde terug over de groote zandwerken daar bij de Oosterspoor<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> die gij wel kent, en langs den <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Buitenkant<c type="kk">/</c> de maan scheen en alles was vol van M<c type="kp">_</c> Maris of Andersen<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Vandaar is het zulk een heerlijk gezigt over de stad &amp; torens, met de lichten hier en daar, <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>aan den eenen kant en het IJ en Bickers eiland aan den anderen. En het was alles zoo doodstil<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>“’t verdorde blaadje ritzelt niet, ’t gestarnte spreekt alleen.─<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> When all sounds cease<c type="kk">/</c> God’s voice is heard <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>under the stars”<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Was ll. Zondag in de O<c type="kp">_</c>Z<c type="kp">_</c> Kapel<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> waar D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Jer. Meyes preekte over Pred. XI:7-XII:7<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab> <vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
<ab>“Verder<c type="kk">/</c> het licht is zoet en het is den oogen goed de zon te aanschouwen, maar <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>indien de mensch vele jaren leeft en zich verblijdt in die allen<c type="kk">/</c> zoo laat hem <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>ook gedenken aan de dagen der duisternis want die zullen vele zijn en al <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>wat gekomen is is ijdelheid. Verblijd u, o jongeling, in uwe jeugd, en laat uw hart <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>zich vermaken in de dagen uwer jongelingschap, en wandel in de wegen uws <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>harten, en in de aanschouwing uwer oogen, maar weet dat God om <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>al deze dingen u zal doen komen in het gerigt. Zoo doe dan de gemelijkheid <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>wijken van uw hart en doe het kwade weg van uw vleesch want de jeugd <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>en de jonkheid is ijdelheid.─ Gedenk aan uwen Schepper in de dagen Uwer <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>jongelingschap, eer dat de kwade dagen komen en de jaren naderen en <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>de sterren verduisterd worden, en de wolken wederkomen na den regen.─</ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ten dage wanneer de wachters des huizes zullen beven en de sterke mannen <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>zich zelve zullen krommen, en de maalsters zullen stilstaan, omdat zij <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>minder geworden zijn, en die door de vensteren zien zullen verduisterd <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>worden, en de twee deuren naar de straat zullen gesloten worden, als er <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>een zacht geluid der maling is en hij opstaat op de stem van het vogelken, <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>en al de zangeressen zullen nedergebogen worden.─ Ook wanneer zij <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>voor de hoogte zullen vreezen, en dat er verschrikkingen zullen zijn op <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>den weg, en de amandelboom zal bloeijen en dat de sprinkhaan <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>zich zelven een last zal wezen, en dat de lust zal vergaan, want de <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>mensch gaat naar zijn eeuwig huis en de rouwklagers zullen in de <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>straten omgaan.─ Eer dan de zilveren schaal ontketend wordt en <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>het rad aan den bornput in stukken gestooten wordt<c type="kk">/</c> En het stof wederom <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>tot de aarde keert, als het geweest is en de geest keert tot God Die hem <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>gegeven heeft.”─<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> Zoo wat de mensch zaait dat zal hij ook maaijen en <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>die naar den Geest zaait zal uit den Geest het Eeuwige Leven maaijen.─<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab>Dan heb ik ook D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Laurillard nog eens gehoord in de vroegpreek<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-o-22"/> over: Jer VIII:7<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Zelfs een ooijevaar aan den hemel weet zijne gezette tijden, en eene tortelduif <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>en kraan en zwaluw nemen den tijd harer aankomst waar.</ab>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hij vertelde hoe hij op een weg had gewandeld waar de bladeren reeds van de boomen vielen <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>en eene vlugt trekvogels had gezien en sprak over het verschijnsel van het trekken 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>der vogelen, en hoe ook de mensch eenmaal zal wegtrekken naar warmer land<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>Hij behandelde dit onderwerp in den geest van Michelet of Ruckert of zoo als velen <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>het ook hebben geschilderd<c type="kk">/</c> o.a. Protais<c type="kk">/</c> Souvenirs de la patrie<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="23" xml:id="note-o-23"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pa schreef Gij naar Antwerpen zijt geweest, ben verlangend om te hooren wat Gij daar <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>hebt gezien, lang geleden zag ik de oude Sch<hi rend="ss">ijen</hi> op het Museum ook<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-o-24"/> ─ en meen mij zelfs <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>nog een mooi portret van Rembrandt te herinneren,<anchor n="25" xml:id="note-o-25"/> als men alles duidelijk kon <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>onthouden zou heerlijk zijn maar het is daarmede even als met het gezigt op een <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>langen weg<c type="kk">/</c> in de verte schijnen de dingen kleiner en als in een nevel<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er is hier op een avond brand geweest op het water n.l. eene schuit met arak of <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>iets dergelijks<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="26" xml:id="note-o-26"/> Was met Oom op de Wassenaar,<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-o-27"/> er was betrekkelijk geen gevaar <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>daar men de brandende schuit tusschen de andere schepen uit had weten te krijgen en die aan een paal had <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>vastgelegd<c type="kp">_</c> Als de vlam wat hoog werd zag men den Buitenkant en de zwarte <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>rij menschen die daar stonden te kijken en de bootjes die om den gloed heen <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>en weer voeren schenen ook zwart in het water waarin de vlam weerkaatste, ik weet <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>niet of Gij photographiën naar Jazet kent die in der tijd in de Gal. photogr. waren<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>nu echter zijn vernietigd<c type="kk">/</c> “La nuit de noël”<c type="kk">/</c> “la conflagration” en anderen<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="28" xml:id="note-o-28"/> <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>het was iets dergelijks.─</ab>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het begint reeds te schemeren<c type="kk">/</c> “blessed twilight” noemde Dickens het<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-o-29"/> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>en wel had hij gelijk. Blessed twilight vooral wanneer twee of <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>drie in eensgezindheid bijeen zijn<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-o-30"/> en als schriftgeleerden uit hunnen schat <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>oude en nieuwe dingen voortbrengen even als een heer des huizes<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="31" xml:id="note-o-31"/> Blessed twilight <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>wanneer twee of drie vergaderd zijn in Zijnen naam en Hij zelf als in <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>het midden van hen.<anchor n="32" xml:id="note-o-32"/> En zalig hij die deze dingen weet en ze ook doet.<anchor n="33" xml:id="note-o-33"/> <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>Dat wist Rembrandt want uit den rijken schat Zijns harten<anchor n="34" xml:id="note-o-34"/> heeft Hij onder <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>anderen voortgebragt die teekening in sepia<c type="kk">/</c> houtskool<c type="kk">/</c> inkt &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> (die op het <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>Brittish museum is) voorstellende het huis te Bethanië.─<anchor n="35" xml:id="note-o-35"/> In die kamer <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>heerscht de schemering<c type="kk">/</c> de gestalte des Heeren<c type="kk">/</c> edel en indrukwekkend<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>teekent zich ernstig donker af tegen het raam waardoor de <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>avondschemering binnen valt. Even als de figuur van John Halifax<c type="kp">_</c> Die <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>zeide dat hij een Christen was<c type="kk">/</c> tegen een raam met witte gordijnen in eene <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>kamer in dat Rose Cottage meen ik<c type="kk">/</c> op een avond zooals er velen met zooveel <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>gevoel in het boek worden beschreven.─<anchor n="36" xml:id="note-o-36"/> Aan de voeten van Jezus <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>zit Maria die het goede deel had gekozen dat van Haar niet <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>zou weggenomen worden<anchor n="37" xml:id="note-o-37"/> en Martha is in de kamer bezig met <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>het een of ander<c type="kk">/</c> als ik mij wel herinner om het vuur aan te stoken <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>of iets dergelijks.─<anchor n="38" xml:id="note-o-38"/> Die teekening hoop ik niet te vergeten noch ook <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>hetgeen zij mij scheen te zeggen: Ik ben het licht der wereld, zoo wie Mij <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>volgt zal in de duisternis niet wandelen maar zal het licht des levens hebben<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="39" xml:id="note-o-39"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>het licht des Evangelies dat aan de armen gepredikt wordt in het <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>Koningrijk Mijns Vaders,<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-o-40"/> dat schijnt<c type="kk">/</c> als eene kaars geplaatst op <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>een kandelaar<c type="kk">/</c> op allen die in het huis zijn.─<anchor n="41" xml:id="note-o-41"/> Ik ben gekomen <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>opdat zij het leven zouden hebben en opdat zij het overvloedig <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>hebben<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="42" xml:id="note-o-42"/> Ik ben de Opstanding en het Leven. Zoo wie in <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>Mij gelooft zal leven al ware hij ook gestorven en een iegelijk <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>die leeft en in Mij gelooft zal niet sterven in eeuwigheid.─<anchor n="43" xml:id="note-o-43"/> <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>Zoo iemand Mij liefheeft<c type="kk">/</c> Mijn Vader zal hem eeren en Wij <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>zullen komen en woning bij hem maken<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="44" xml:id="note-o-44"/> wij zullen tot hem <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>komen en Wij zullen het Avondmaal met hem houden.─<anchor n="45" xml:id="note-o-45"/> <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>Zulke dingen zegt de schemering tot wie ooren heeft <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>om te hooren en een hart om te verstaan<anchor n="46" xml:id="note-o-46"/> en om geloof te <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>hebben in God ─ blessed twilight.─</ab>
                <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>
<ab rend="indent">En op dat schilderij van Ruyperez<c type="kk">/</c> l’Imitation de Jesus Christ<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="47" xml:id="note-o-47"/> is het ook schemering en <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>ook op eene andere ets van Rembrandt “<hi rend="ital">David in het gebed tot God</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="48" xml:id="note-o-48"/> ja! aan “blessed <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>twilight” hebben wij die woorden te danken “gelijk een hert schreeuwt naar de waterstroomen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>alzoo schreeuwt mijne ziel tot U o God. Mijne ziel dorst naar God<c type="kk">/</c> naar den levenden God<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>
<ab rend="indent">De afgrond roept tot den afgrond<c type="kk">/</c> al Uwe baren en al Uwe golven zijn over mij heengegaan<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>Maar de Heer zal des daags Zijne goedertierenheid gebieden en des nachts zal zijn lied <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>bij mij zijn en het gebed tot den God mijns levens. Wat buigt gij u neder, o mijne ziel<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>en wat zijt gij onrustig in mij, hoop op God. Want ik zal Hem nog loven, Hij is de menigvuldige <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>verlossing mijns aangezigts en mijn God.”<anchor n="49" xml:id="note-o-49"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar het is niet altijd “blessed twilight”<c type="kk">/</c> zooals Gij aan het schrift ziet zit ik bij de lamp boven<anchor n="50" xml:id="note-o-50"/> <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>want er zijn beneden menschen en kan daar niet met mijne boeken bij zitten<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>
<ab rend="indent">Oom Jan laat U groeten, Hendrik en Marie<anchor n="51" xml:id="note-o-51"/> waren een dag hier in de afgeloopen week en <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>zijn nu vertrokken<c type="kp">_</c> Maandag een telegram de Madura te Southampton was aangekomen<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="52" xml:id="note-o-52"/> <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>Den dag van hun vertrek is Oom des morgens met den trein om 6 uur met den Heer Vos<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="53" xml:id="note-o-53"/> die <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>den vorigen avond uit Utrecht naar hier was gekomen<c type="kk">/</c> naar Nieuwediep<anchor n="54" xml:id="note-o-54"/> vertrokken <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>om hun aan boord nog goeden dag te zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>
<ab rend="indent">Heb Gij het goed<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf eens spoedig en kom maar spoedig want het is <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>goed elkander eens weder te zien en eens te praten, misschien kunnen wij dan <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>zamen nog wel eens die tentoonstelling die dezer dagen wordt geopend gaan <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>zien.─<anchor n="55" xml:id="note-o-55"/> Groet ook Uwe huisgenooten. Jongen wat moet het toch heerlijk <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>zijn om een leven achter zich te hebben als Pa, God geve ons te zijn en meer <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>en meer te worden zonen naar Zijn geest en hart, daar kan nog wel <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>iets van tot stand komen, Hij kan den mensch verheffen boven wat hij van nature <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>is<c type="kk">/</c> Zijne kracht kan in onze zwakheid worden volbragt.<anchor n="56" xml:id="note-o-56"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>
<ab rend="indent">à Dieu<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang in gedachten een handdruk van</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>
<ab>Uw zoo liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-36" n="36">alles &lt; de alles</note>
<note target="l-92" n="92">bijeen &lt; bij een</note>
<note target="l-126" n="126">twilight” &lt; twilight</note>
<note target="l-132" n="132">God.” &lt; God.</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam, 18 Sept. 1877.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>The time is approaching when you’ll go travelling for the Messrs G&amp;Cie, and I’m already looking forward to seeing and talking to you again.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">What I wanted to ask you is this. Wouldn’t you be able to arrange it so that we could be together for a while, quietly and calmly, I was thinking of at least one whole day.</ab>
  <ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="520">Mendes</rs> was out of town this week, staying for a few days with a <rs type="pers" key="686">Rev. Schröder</rs>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> in Zwolle who had lessons from him at one time. Being less occupied because of this, I could carry out my plan to see the etchings by <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> in the Trippenhuis, went there this morning and am glad I did it.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When I was there I thought, won’t Theo and I be able to see them together sometime? Think about whether you couldn’t go off on your own for a day or even longer for such things.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How much someone like <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> – who oft-times travels at night, carrying a lantern,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> to a sick or dying person, for example, to speak to him about Him whose word is also a light<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> in the night of suffering and mortal fear – would have a feeling for <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s etchings. Such as the flight into Egypt<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> at night or the entombment of Jesus.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> That collection in the Trippenhuis is splendid, and I saw much that I’d never encountered before, there they also told me about drawings by R. in the Fodor.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> If you think it’s a good idea, speak to <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> about it, and write a few words in advance and tell me when you’re coming, then I’ll study ahead to be free and at your disposal when you come.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I can’t see anything of that kind, paintings either, for example, without thinking of you and of <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> and everyone at home.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Am otherwise up to my ears in work, because it’s becoming clear to me what I actually have to know, what they know and what inspires those whom I should like to follow. ‘Search the scriptures’<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> is not written for nothing, but those words are a good guide, and I’d really like to become such a scribe who is like unto a man that is an householder, which bringeth forth out of his treasure things old and new.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I spent Monday evening with <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="776">Kee</rs>, they’re fond of each other and one certainly notices that where Love lives the Lord commands His blessing.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> It’s nice at their house, only a great pity that he couldn’t go on being a minister.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> When one sees them sitting there together in the evening by the kindly light<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> of their lamp in the little living room and close by the bedroom of <rs type="pers" key="807">their little boy</rs>,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> who wakes from time to time and asks his mother for this or that, it’s an idyll, but they also know dreadful days and sleepless nights, and fear and anxiety.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> Walked back over the big sand works by the Oosterspoor<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> which you know, and along Buitenkant, the moon was shining and everything was full of <rs type="pers" key="1202">M. Maris</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="512">Andersen</rs>.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">From there it’s such a wonderful sight across the city and towers, with lights here and there, on one side the IJ and on the other Bickerseiland. And everything was so deathly still, ‘the withered leaf does not rustle, the stars alone speak.<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> When all sounds cease, God’s voice is heard under the stars’.<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>

<ab rend="indent">Was in the Oudezijdskapel<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> last Sunday, where the <rs type="pers" key="575">Rev. Jer. Meijjes</rs> preached on Eccl. XI:7-XII:7.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>‘Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun: but if a man live many years, and rejoice in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity. Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgement. Therefore remove heaviness from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth are vanity. Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, nor the stars be darkened, nor the clouds return after the rain.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows be darkened, and the door shall be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding is low, and he shall rise up at the voice of the bird, and all the daughters of musick shall be brought low; also when they shall be afraid of that which is high, and fears shall be in the way, and the almond tree shall flourish, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail: because man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the streets: or ever the silver bowl be loosed, or the wheel broken at the cistern. Then shall the dust return to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall turn unto God Who gave it.’<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> For whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap and he that soweth to the Spirit shall of the Spirit reap Life Everlasting.<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I then heard the <rs type="pers" key="53">Rev. Laurillard</rs> again in the early sermon<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> on Jer. VIII:7, Yea, the stork in the heaven knoweth her appointed times; and the turtle and the crane and the swallow observe the time of their coming.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He told about how he had walked on a road where the leaves were already falling from the trees, and had seen a flock of migratory birds and spoke about the phenomenon of 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> birds migrating, and how man will also migrate once to a warmer land. He treated this subject in the spirit of <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="734">Rückert</rs>, or as many have also painted it, including <rs type="pers" key="1288">Protais</rs>, Souvenirs of the homeland.<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> wrote that you’d been to Antwerp, am eager to hear what you saw there, long ago I also saw the old paintings in the museum<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-t-24"/> – and even seem to recall a beautiful portrait by <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>,<anchor n="25" xml:id="note-t-25"/> it would be wonderful if one could remember everything clearly, but it’s just like the sight of a long road, in the distance things seem smaller and as though in a mist.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">There was a fire here one evening on the water, namely a barge with arrack or something similar.<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-t-26"/> Was with <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle</rs> on the Wassenaar,<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-t-27"/> there was no real danger as they’d managed to get the burning barge out from between the other boats and had tied it to a post. When the flames got up a bit one saw Buitenkant and the black row of people standing there watching, and the little boats going back and forth around the blaze also appeared black in the water in which the flames were reflected, I don’t know if you’re familiar with photographs after <rs type="pers" key="1111">Jazet</rs> that were in the Galerie photographique at one time but have now been destroyed, ‘Christmas Eve’, ‘The conflagration’ and others,<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-t-28"/> it was something like that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Twilight is already falling, ‘blessed twilight’ <rs type="pers" key="580">Dickens</rs> called it,<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-t-29"/> and indeed he was right. Blessed twilight especially when two or three are gathered together in harmony of mind,<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-t-30"/> and like the scribes bring forth out of their treasure old and new things just like a householder.<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-t-31"/> Blessed twilight when two or three are gathered together in His name and He himself is in the midst of them.<anchor n="32" xml:id="note-t-32"/> And blessed is he who knows these things and also does them.<anchor n="33" xml:id="note-t-33"/> <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> knew that, for out of the rich treasure of his heart<anchor n="34" xml:id="note-t-34"/> he brought forth, among other things, that drawing in sepia, charcoal, ink &amp;c. (which is in the British Museum) depicting the house in Bethany.<anchor n="35" xml:id="note-t-35"/> In that room twilight dominates, the figure of the Lord, noble and impressive, stands out gravely against the window through which the evening twilight falls. Just like the figure of John Halifax. He said he was a Christian, in front of a window with white curtains in a room in Rose Cottage, I think, on an evening like so many that are described with so much feeling in that book.<anchor n="36" xml:id="note-t-36"/> At Jesus’ feet sits Mary, who had chosen that good part which would not be taken away from her,<anchor n="37" xml:id="note-t-37"/> and Martha is in the room busy with something or other, stirring up the fire or something like that,<anchor n="38" xml:id="note-t-38"/> if I remember rightly. I hope not to forget that drawing, nor what it seemed to be saying to me: I am the light of the world: he that followeth Me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life,<anchor n="39" xml:id="note-t-39"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> the light of the gospel that is preached to the poor in My Father’s Kingdom,<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-t-40"/> that shines, like a candle placed on a candlestick, on all that are in the house.<anchor n="41" xml:id="note-t-41"/> I am come that they shall have life and that they shall have abundance.<anchor n="42" xml:id="note-t-42"/> I am the Resurrection, and the Life: he that believeth in Me, though he were dead, yet shall he live: and whosoever liveth and believeth in Me shall never die.<anchor n="43" xml:id="note-t-43"/> If a man love Me, My Father will honour him and We will come unto him, and make our abode with him,<anchor n="44" xml:id="note-t-44"/> We will come in to him, and will sup with him.<anchor n="45" xml:id="note-t-45"/> The twilight says such things to those who have ears with which to hear and a heart with which to understand<anchor n="46" xml:id="note-t-46"/> and to have faith in God – blessed twilight.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And it’s also twilight in that painting by <rs type="pers" key="1335">Ruipérez</rs>, The imitation of Jesus Christ,<anchor n="47" xml:id="note-t-47"/> and also in another etching by <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, ‘<hi rend="ital">David praying to God</hi>’,<anchor n="48" xml:id="note-t-48"/> yes! we may thank ‘blessed twilight’ for the words ‘as the hart panteth after the water brooks, so panteth my soul after Thee, O God. My soul thirsteth for God, for the living God.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Deep calleth unto deep: all Thy waves and Thy billows are gone over me. Yet the Lord will command His lovingkindness in the daytime, and in the night his song shall be with me, and my prayer unto the God of my life. Why art thou cast down, O my soul? And why art thou disquieted within me? Hope thou in God; for I shall yet praise Him, Who is the health of my countenance, and my God’.<anchor n="49" xml:id="note-t-49"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But it isn’t always ‘blessed twilight’, as you see from my handwriting<anchor n="50" xml:id="note-t-50"/> I’m by the lamp upstairs, because there are people downstairs and I can’t sit with them with my books.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan</rs> sends you his regards, <rs type="pers" key="404">Hendrik</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="233">Marie</rs>
                    <anchor n="51" xml:id="note-t-51"/> were here for a day this past week and have now left. Monday a telegram that the Madura had arrived at Southampton.<anchor n="52" xml:id="note-t-52"/> The day of their departure Uncle left in the morning with the 6 o’clock train with <rs type="pers" key="411">Mr Vos</rs>,<anchor n="53" xml:id="note-t-53"/> who had come here the previous evening from Utrecht – for Nieuwediep<anchor n="54" xml:id="note-t-54"/> to say goodbye to them on board.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I wish you well, write soon and do come soon, because it’s good to see each other again and to talk, perhaps we could go together to see the exhibition that will open one of these days.<anchor n="55" xml:id="note-t-55"/> Give my regards, too, to your housemates. Old boy, how wonderful it must be to have a life behind one like <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> has, God grant that we be and that we may become more and more sons after His spirit and heart, something may yet come of that, He can raise a person above that which is his nature, His strength can be made perfect in our weakness.<anchor n="56" xml:id="note-t-56"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Adieu, accept in thought a handshake from</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your most loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The <rs type="pers" key="686">Rev. Johannes Elias Schröder</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
 <ab>A sizeable collection of <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> etchings was preserved in the Trippenhuis. Two days later Van Gogh visited the Trippenhuis again, writing his name in the visitors’ book. See Groot and De Vries 1990, p. 57.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>A reference to the two <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> prints which Van Gogh mentions a couple of lines later (see notes 5 and 6), both of which are nocturnal scenes lit by a lantern.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="119" v="105">Ps. 119:105</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <hi rend="ital">The flight into Egypt, at night</hi>, etching, 1651 (B 53,I) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="ill" key="375">Ill. 375</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <hi rend="ital">The entombment of Christ</hi>, etching, c. 1654 (B 86) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet). <rs type="ill" key="339">Ill. 339</rs>. There is an impression in the family estate (inv. no. t1441).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>The Museum Fodor (opened in 1863) at Keizersgracht 609-613 in Amsterdam concentrated on paintings, drawings and prints by nineteenth-century artists, though it also owned works by old masters, including 25 drawings attributed at that time to <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>; a number of those attributions have now been revised or cast into doubt. See cat. Amsterdam 1863 and Broos 1981, pp. 7-12. The collection is now housed in the Amsterdam Museum.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="5" v="39">John 5:39</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" v="52">Matt. 13:52</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="133" v="3">Ps. 133:3</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rhy. ps" chap="133" v="3">rhy. ps. 133:3</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>In the summer of 1873, <rs type="pers" key="806">Christoffel Martinus Vos</rs> was forced by a pulmonary condition to resign from the ministry. He subsequently took up an editorial post at the newspaper <hi rend="ital">Algemeen Handelsblad</hi> (FR b2638).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="hymn" chap="200" v="2">hymn 200:2</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="hymn" chap="271" v="2">hymn 271:2</bibleref>, and the hymn ‘Lead, kindly light, amid the encircling gloom’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="807">Johannes (Jan) Paulus Vos</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>Not only was <rs type="pers" key="806">Christoffel Vos</rs> suffering from an incurable illness, but on 4 February 1877 he and <rs type="pers" key="776">Kee</rs> lost their one-year-old son <rs type="pers" key="1697">Catharinus Henri</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>The groundwork being done to build the new Central Station; <ref target="let118.xml#n-14">see letter 118, n. 14.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>Van Gogh’s mention of <rs type="pers" key="512">Andersen</rs> was prompted by his <rs type="lit" key="63">
                            <hi rend="ital">Vertellingen van de maan</hi>
                        </rs> (What the moon saw) (<ref target="let068.xml">see letter 68</ref>); it is not certain whether he is referring to a specific work by <rs type="pers" key="1202">Matthijs Maris</rs>. Fairy-tale-like representations and atmospheric townscapes of his are known, however, including <rs type="otherart" key="117">
                            <hi rend="ital">Fairy tale</hi>
                        </rs>, c. 1877 (Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum), <rs type="otherart" key="118">
                            <hi rend="ital">City outskirts</hi>
                        </rs>, 1872 (private collection) and <rs type="otherart" key="119">
                            <hi rend="ital">The castle ploughman</hi>
                        </rs>, 1875-76 (Cardiff, National Museum of Wales) – the last one is mentioned in <ref target="let134.xml#n-18">letter 134, n. 18.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>The end of the first recitative in <rs type="pers" key="1">Hieronymus van Alphen</rs>’s poem ‘<rs type="lit" key="159">De starrenhemel. Eene cantate</rs>’ (The starry sky. A cantata). The variant is ‘ritzelt’ (rustles) instead of ‘schuifelt’ (shuffles). See Van Alphen 1857, vol. 2, pp. 57-61 (quotation on p. 58). From the list of subscribers (p. 488), it appears that <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs> had ordered ten copies of this work for his bookshop in Amsterdam. Van Gogh is possibly quoting Van Alphen indirectly, for the lines are also included in <rs type="pers" key="845">Johannes van Vloten</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="17">Aesthetica of schoonheidskunde</rs>
                        </hi>, to which Van Gogh referred in <ref target="let019.xml">letter 19</ref>. Ed. Deventer 1865, p. 8.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
  <ab>See for this quotation from the poem ‘<rs type="lit" key="419">Under the stars</rs>’ by <rs type="pers" key="713">Mulock Craik</rs>: <ref target="let119.xml#n-15">letter 119, n. 15</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>On Sunday, 16 September, <rs type="pers" key="575">Jeremias Posthumus Meijjes</rs> preached at 10 a.m. in the Oudezijdskapel.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>The quotation from Ecclesiastes is not rendered word for word.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Gal" chap="6" vr="7-8">Gal. 6:7-8</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="22" xml:id="n-22" target="#note-t-22">
<ab>On Sunday, 9 September, <rs type="pers" key="53">Laurillard</rs> preached the early sermon in the Zuiderkerk.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="23" xml:id="n-23" target="#note-t-23">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1288">Paul Alexandre Protais</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Souvenirs de la patrie </hi>(Souvenirs of the homeland), was included in Goupil’s list as an aquatint-engraving (engraved by ‘Masson’) and as a photograph, appearing in both the series ‘Musée Goupil’, ‘Carte-album’ (no. 178) (<rs type="ill" key="1221">Ill. 1221</rs>) and in the ‘Carte de visite’ series (Bordeaux, Musée Goupil).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="24" xml:id="n-24" target="#note-t-24">
<ab>There are no details of either Vincent’s or Theo’s visit to Antwerp, 33 km south of Zundert.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="25" xml:id="n-25" target="#note-t-25">
<ab>The Koninklijk Museum voor Schone Kunsten in Antwerp did not have a portrait by <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> in its collection, though it did have the panel of <hi rend="ital">An old man</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="1848">Ill. 1848</rs>), which is presumably a late-seventeenth-century copy after Rembrandt’s <hi rend="ital">Portrait of an old man</hi> in the Louvre. Van Gogh could also be referring to the <hi rend="ital">Saskia van Uylenburgh</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="1849">Ill. 1849</rs>), a contemporary copy of the original portrait by Rembrandt (now in Kassel, Gemäldegalerie), which was viewed by Vosmaer and Thoré as an autograph replica by Rembrandt. See cat. Antwerp 1988, p. 306, cat. nos. 615, 293.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="26" xml:id="n-26" target="#note-t-26">
<ab>On Monday evening, 10 September, fire had broken out on a barge carrying arrack (rice liquor), lying in the Oosterdok. The ‘Amsterdamsche Onheil-kroniek’ in the <hi rend="ital">Geïllustreerd Politie Nieuws</hi> of 15 September 1877 reported the attempts to extinguish the blaze.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="27" xml:id="n-27" target="#note-t-27">
<ab>For the ship <hi rend="ital">De Admiraal Van Wassenaer</hi>, <ref target="let125.xml#n-6">see letter 125, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="28" xml:id="n-28" target="#note-t-28">
<ab>Van Gogh is referring to a series of four works by <rs type="pers" key="1111">Alexandre Jean Louis Japhet (Jazet)</rs>, all photographed by Billon: <hi rend="ital">L’incendie </hi>(The fire), no. 77 (another name for ‘The conflagration’) <rs type="ill" key="1000">Ill. 1000</rs>; <hi rend="ital">La nuit de Noël </hi>(Christmas Eve), no. 78 <rs type="ill" key="1001">Ill. 1001</rs>; <hi rend="ital">Changement de garnizon </hi>(Changing of the garrison), no. 79 <rs type="ill" key="1851">Ill. 1851</rs>; and <hi rend="ital">Chasse aux loups </hi>(The wolf hunt), no. 80 <rs type="ill" key="1852">Ill. 1852</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="29" xml:id="n-29" target="#note-t-29">
<ab>Taken from <rs type="pers" key="580">Charles Dickens</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="160">
                            <hi rend="ital">Dombey and Son</hi>
                        </rs> (chapter 50): ‘Blessed twilight stealing on, and shading her so soothingly and gravely, as she falls asleep, like a hushed child, upon the bosom she has clung to’. See <hi rend="ital">Dealings with the firm of Dombey and Son</hi>. Introduction by W.H. Garrod. Oxford etc. 1981, p. 713. The same line served as a caption to the accompanying engraving by <rs type="pers" key="210">F. Barnard</rs>. Ed. London 1890, pp. 364-365.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="30" xml:id="n-30" target="#note-t-30">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="18" v="20">Matt. 18:20</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="31" xml:id="n-31" target="#note-t-31">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" v="52">Matt. 13:52</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="32" xml:id="n-32" target="#note-t-32">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="18" v="20">Matt. 18:20</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="33" xml:id="n-33" target="#note-t-33">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="13" v="17">John 13:17</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="34" xml:id="n-34" target="#note-t-34">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="6" v="45">Luke 6:45</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="35" xml:id="n-35" target="#note-t-35">
<ab>The drawing, attributed to <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, of <hi rend="ital">Christ with Mary and Martha</hi> (c. 1650) was also called <hi rend="ital">The house at Bethany</hi> (London, The British Museum). <rs type="ill" key="345">Ill. 345</rs>. Van Gogh visited the British Museum’s Department of Prints and Drawings on Friday, 28 August 1874, as evidenced by the visitors’ book. See Bailey 1990, p. 51.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="36" xml:id="n-36" target="#note-t-36">
<ab>John Halifax is the protagonist of the novel <rs type="lit" key="74">
                            <hi rend="ital">John Halifax, gentleman</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="713">Dinah Maria Mulock Craik</rs> (cf. <ref target="let122.xml">letter 122</ref>). ‘No, I am a Christian’, he says when, during a conflict, he is taken for a Quaker (ed. New York [c. 1900], p. 166). The scene sketched by Van Gogh has not been traced. It is probably a combination of passages, for example, ‘All were gathered in a group at the window, the child being held on her father’s lap’ (pp. 204-205) and the one where John Halifax tells his children that there is only one name that should be revered: that of the Lord (p. 306). Rose Cottage plays an important role, but the scenes mentioned do not occur in the book. Van Gogh’s ‘I think’ indicates his own doubt as to the accuracy of his recollections.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="37" xml:id="n-37" target="#note-t-37">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="10" v="42">Luke 10:42</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="38" xml:id="n-38" target="#note-t-38">
<ab>Van Gogh is mistaken in thinking that Martha is busy stirring up the fire.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="39" xml:id="n-39" target="#note-t-39">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="8" v="12">John 8:12</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="40" xml:id="n-40" target="#note-t-40">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="26" v="29">Matt. 26:29</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="41" xml:id="n-41" target="#note-t-41">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="5" v="15">Matt. 5:15</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="42" xml:id="n-42" target="#note-t-42">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="25" v="29">Matt. 25:29</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="43" xml:id="n-43" target="#note-t-43">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="11" vr="25-26">John 11:25-26</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="44" xml:id="n-44" target="#note-t-44">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="14" v="23">John 14:23</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="45" xml:id="n-45" target="#note-t-45">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rev" chap="3" v="20">Rev. 3:20</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="46" xml:id="n-46" target="#note-t-46">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Deut" chap="29" v="4">Deut. 29:4</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Isa" chap="6" v="10">Isa. 6:10</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" v="15">Matt. 13:15</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Acts" chap="28" v="27">Acts 28:27</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="47" xml:id="n-47" target="#note-t-47">
  <ab>Van Gogh knew <rs type="pers" key="1335">Ruipérez</rs>’s <rs type="ill" key="1689">
                            <hi rend="ital">La Imitación de Jesucristo</hi>
                        </rs> from a print; <ref target="let040.xml#n-16">see letter 40, n. 16.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="48" xml:id="n-48" target="#note-t-48">
  <ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, <hi rend="ital">David in prayer</hi>, etching, 1652 (B41) (Amsterdam, Rijksprentenkabinet).  There is an impression in the family estate (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. p111). <rs type="ill" key="1853">Ill. 1853</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="49" xml:id="n-49" target="#note-t-49">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="42" vr="2-3">Ps. 42:2-3</bibleref>, <vg:bibleref book="Ps" chap="42" vr="8-9">8-9</vg:bibleref> and <vg:bibleref book="Ps" chap="42" v="12">12</vg:bibleref> (in <hi rend="ital">KJ</hi> <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="42" vr="1-2">Ps. 42:1-2</bibleref>, <vg:bibleref book="Ps" chap="42" vr="7-8">7-8</vg:bibleref> and <vg:bibleref book="Ps" chap="42" v="11">11</vg:bibleref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="50" xml:id="n-50" target="#note-t-50">
<ab>To the end of the paragraph ending ‘blessed twilight’ <ref target="#l-123">(l. 123)</ref>, Van Gogh’s handwriting had gradually become less compact, owing to the increasing darkness; after this he wrote considerably smaller.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="51" xml:id="n-51" target="#note-t-51">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="404">Hendrik Jacob Eerligh van Gogh</rs> (son of Uncle Jan) and <rs type="pers" key="233">Maria Elisabeth Vos</rs> were married on 16 August 1877.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="52" xml:id="n-52" target="#note-t-52">
<ab>The ship the <hi rend="ital">Madura</hi> had put to sea on Sunday, 16 September, bound for Batavia (<hi rend="ital">Nieuwe Amsterdamsche Courant. Algemeen Handelsblad</hi>, no. 14638). Ships destined for far-off lands departed from the port of Southampton on the south coast of England.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="53" xml:id="n-53" target="#note-t-53">
<ab>The naval officer <rs type="pers" key="411">Jan Vos</rs>, the father of Marie, was deputy director of the navy at Amsterdam. From 1876 until his death, Vos was a member of the Hoog Militair Gerechtshof (Supreme Court Martial) at Utrecht. See <hi rend="ital">Adelborstopleiding te Delft – Medemblik – Breda 1816-1857</hi>. Ed. M.J.C. Klaassen. The Hague 1979, p. 79, no. M 144.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="54" xml:id="n-54" target="#note-t-54">
<ab>The Nieuwediep is the harbour on the eastern side of Amsterdam, near the mouth of the River IJ where it flows into what was then called the Zuiderzee (now the IJsselmeer).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="55" xml:id="n-55" target="#note-t-55">
<ab>On Thursday, 20 September 1877, the Levende Meesters (Living Masters) exhibition was to open in the premises of the former Koninklijke Akademie van Beeldende Kunsten. See exhib. cat Amsterdam 1877. Such exhibitions lasted three to four weeks. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1995, pp. 52-53.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="56" xml:id="n-56" target="#note-t-56">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="2 Cor" chap="12" v="9">2 Cor. 12:9</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>