<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Sunday, 30 December 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let138"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">138</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">116a</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">137</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Etten</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 30 December 1877</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Sunday, 30 December 1877.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b136 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Etten 30 December 1877’.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
    <p>The sisters Elisabeth and Willemien both wrote a note to Theo after Vincent had signed the letter. See <hi rend="ital">Documentation</hi>, <ref target="documentation.xml#id30December1877-1">30 December 1877</ref>. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0136" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000144_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000144_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000144_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000144_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0136" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000144_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000144_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000144_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000144_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Etten 30 December 1877<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Hartelijk wensch ik u geluk met het nieuwe jaar, moge het in vele opzigten voor U gezegend <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>zijn. Het waren goede dagen toen Gij hier waart maar zij hebben niet lang geduurd. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>mijne vacantie zal ook spoedig om zijn, toch blijf ik nog minstens een dag langer daar <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Pa het zoo druk heeft dezer dagen en het goed is wij nog eens bedaard <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>zamen bespreken hoe het best de verdere studie aan te leggen.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pa moet op Oudejaar ook nog te Prinsenhage preeken daar D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Kuylman<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> is gevallen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>en zich bezeerd heeft zoodat zijn arm uit het lid is<c type="kk">/</c> dus is hij niet in staat de beurt <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>op Oudejaarsavond te vervullen en heeft Pa aangeboden het voor hem te doen. <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Dus preekt Pa 9 maal in 10 dagen.</ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als Gij de bewuste kaart &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> nog niet aan Harry Gladwell hebt afgezonden<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>wacht er dan nog eenigen tijd mede, ik hoor hij niet meer te Parijs is,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> schreef <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>heden aan zijn vader.─ Mogelijk krijg ik wel antwoord en zal daarna bij <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>het rolletje nog wel iets anders voegen.</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij hebt vergeten de ets naar Meissonier<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> mede te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> die stuur ik U dezer dagen <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>met de lith. naar Jules Breton<c type="kk">/</c> Les champs en hiver<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> want ik wil die niet aannemen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>die hoort in Uwe verzameling t’huis.─</ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">Verl. week heeft het gesneeuwd en toen heeft Cor pleizier gehad met de slee <lb n="19a" xml:id="l-19a"/>en ik ook want ik heb met he<supplied>m</supplied> en een meiske dat bij <lb n="19b" xml:id="l-19b"/>Hackstroo<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> was gelogeerd op den weg gesleed, <lb n="19"/>vandaag <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>deden Pa<c type="kk">/</c> Moe<c type="kk">/</c> Cor en ik eene mooie wandeling waar Gij ook bij hadt moeten zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gisteren zag ik Moe’s naaischool die Zij tegenwoordig in de consistorie houdt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>dat is toch zoo aardig<c type="kk">/</c> men zou er een schilderij van willen hebben,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> het is <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>reeds een heel aantal kinderen die er komen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er is mij nog een sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> ingevallen betrekking hebbende op Bretagne<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>Ribot<c type="kk">/</c> La prière<c type="kk">/</c> een aantal kinderen geknield in een hoek eener kerk in de <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>schemering<c type="kk">/</c> er bestaat eene groote ets door hem zelven van<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> die Gij mogelijk <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>wel kent. Jacque heeft eens hetzelfde onderwerp geetst maar op kleiner <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>schaal.─<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Heb vandaag een lijstje gemaakt van alles wat ik mij kon herinneren betrekking <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>hebbende op de Fransche omwenteling<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> om dat achter op het kaartje van Frankrijk te <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>schrijven en datzelfde werk hoop ik langzamerhand uit te breiden, en b.v. op te schrijven <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>het voornaamste aangaande de middeneeuwen of den tijd van den 80jarige oorlog<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> enz. <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Men moet vasthouden wat men heeft gezien of wat men weet want dat komt <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>altijd te pas.─</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mogt Gij nu en dan dergelijke lijstjes maken<c type="kk">/</c> stuur ze mij dan bij gelegenheid<c type="kk">/</c> dan kunnen <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>wij vergelijken, het is goed dit te doen ─ wat kennis aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> het is zaak daarvan <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>te houden wat men heeft en het duidelijk te maken in zich zooveel men kan, <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>vooral bij gebrek aan geld is het goed de leemten daarmee en <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>met dergelijke zaken aan te vullen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Groet al uwe huisgenooten en wensch hun alles goeds voor mij toe. Onmogelijk <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>is het niet dat ik naar Amsterdam gaande nog een keer te s’Hage overblijf en U zelf <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>de prenten die gij hebt laten liggen kom brengen maar reken er niet op.</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">à Dieu<c type="kk">/</c> nogmaals het beste U toegewenscht en een hartelijken handdruk in <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>gedachten van</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab>Uw zoo liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-19" n="19">a he<supplied>m</supplied> &lt; <hi rend="ital">Text lost due to wear.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Etten, 30 December 1877<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I wish you much happiness for the new year, may it be blessed for you in many ways. Those were good days, when you were here, though they didn’t last long. My holiday will be over soon, too, but I’ll stay at least a day longer because <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs>’s so busy these days, and it would be good to discuss calmly how best to pursue further study.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> also has to preach at Princenhage on New Year’s Eve, because the <rs type="pers" key="484">Rev. Kuylman</rs>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> fell and hurt himself, dislocating his arm, and so is unable to take his turn on New Year’s Eve, and Pa has offered to do it for him. So Pa has to preach 9 times in 10 days.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you haven’t yet sent that map &amp;c. to <rs type="pers" key="394">Harry Gladwell</rs>,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> wait a while, I hear he’s no longer in Paris,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> wrote to <rs type="pers" key="396">his father</rs> today. I may get a reply and will then add something to the roll.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You forgot to take the etching after <rs type="pers" key="1208">Meissonier</rs>,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> I’ll send it to you one of these days with the lithograph after <rs type="pers" key="899">Jules Breton</rs>, The fields in winter,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> because I don’t want to accept it, it belongs in your collection.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It snowed last week and <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> had fun with the sledge and so did I, because I sledged on the road with him and a girl who was staying at <rs type="pers" key="440 441">the Hackstrohs</rs>’.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> Today <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa, Ma</rs>, Cor and I took a lovely walk, you should have been there.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yesterday I saw the sewing school that <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs> now holds in the consistory, it is indeed pleasant, one would like to have a painting of it,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> there are already quite a few children coming to it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Another painting has occurred to me that is related to Brittany, namely <rs type="pers" key="1316">Ribot</rs>, The prayer, a number of children kneeling in a corner of a church at dusk, there’s a large etching by him of the same thing,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> which you perhaps know. <rs type="pers" key="1117">Jacque</rs> once made an etching of the same subject, but smaller.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Made a list today of everything I could remember about the French Revolution,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> so as to write it on the back of the map of France, and I hope gradually to expand on that work, recording, for instance, the most important things about the Middle Ages, or the time of the 80 Years’ War,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> and so on. One must hold on to what one has seen or what one knows, for it always comes in useful.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you should make such lists from time to time, send them to me when you have the opportunity, then we can compare them, it’s good to do so — as far as knowledge is concerned, it’s important to hold on to what one has and to absorb it internally as much as one can; especially when one is short of money, it’s good to fill the gaps with this and similar things.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Give my regards to all your housemates and wish them all the best from me. It’s not impossible that, on my way to Amsterdam, I could spend another night in The Hague and bring you the prints that you left here myself, but don’t count on it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Adieu, again I wish you the best, and a hearty handshake in thought from</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your most loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Van Gogh spent the Christmas holidays with his parents.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>From a letter written by <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> to Theo, it emerges that Vincent’s further study was a matter of some concern: ‘How will it go? That is not yet clear, though we hope for the best’ (FR b961, 9 January 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="484">Johannes Kuylman</rs> was a minister at Princenhage.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The map of Scotland copied by Vincent from <rs type="pers" key="1374">Stieler</rs>’s atlas, which Theo was supposed to send to <rs type="pers" key="394">Harry Gladwell</rs> in Paris in one of Goupil’s shipments (<ref target="let137.xml">see letter 137</ref>); what ‘&amp;c.’ refers to is unclear.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>From <ref target="let141.xml">letters 141</ref> and <ref target="let142.xml">142</ref> it appears that <rs type="pers" key="394">Gladwell</rs> had quit his job at Goupil’s and returned to his <rs type="pers" key="396">parents</rs>’ home in London (Lewisham).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Possibly the etching after <rs type="pers" key="1208">Meissonier</rs>’s <rs type="ill" key="1884">
                            <hi rend="ital">The reader</hi>
                        </rs>; <ref target="let152.xml#n-13">see letter 152, n. 13.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>It is not certain which lithograph Vincent is referring to here. Cf. the possible reference to <rs type="pers" key="899">Breton</rs>’s <rs type="ill" key="1889">
                            <hi rend="ital">Women hoeing</hi>
                        </rs> in <ref target="let156.xml#n-11">letter 156, n. 11.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>The stationmaster <rs type="pers" key="440">Marinus Hackstroh</rs>, who was married to <rs type="pers" key="441">Elisabeth Clara Johanna de Bock</rs>. They lived at de Baai F 25 and were friends of the Van Gogh family (cf., among others, FR b995, b2474 and b2762).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The motif of the sewing school was depicted by a number of artists, including <rs type="pers" key="1107">Jozef Israëls</rs>: <rs type="ill" key="200">
                            <hi rend="ital">Sewing school at Katwijk</hi>
                        </rs> (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum).</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1316">Théodule Ribot</rs>, <hi rend="ital">The prayer</hi> (present whereabouts unknown; Salon 1863). Ribot’s etching <hi rend="ital">La prière</hi>, which measures 18 x 24 cm, was published in the first series of <hi rend="ital">Eaux-fortes modernes, publiées par la Société des Aquafortistes</hi> (September 1862), no. 5. The print, which is also known as <hi rend="ital">L’école maternelle </hi>(The nursery school), bears the text ‘Regina virginum ora pro nobis’. Published by A. Cadart &amp; F. Chevalier. <rs type="ill" key="1271">Ill. 1271</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1117">Charles Emile Jacque</rs>, <hi rend="ital">La prière</hi> (<hi rend="ital">Enfants en prière</hi>) (The prayer (Children praying)), 1843. Printed by Delâtre, Paris for <hi rend="ital">L’Artiste</hi>. J.-J. Guiffrey, <hi rend="ital">L’Oeuvre de Ch. Jacque. Catalogue de ses eaux-fortes et pointes sèches</hi>. Paris 1866, p. 36, no. 11 (<hi rend="ital">Alliance des Arts</hi>, no. 350). <rs type="ill" key="1865">Ill. 1865</rs>. This etching measures 6.4 x 10.0 cm.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>The French Revolution of 1789.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>The Netherlands’ war against Spain, 1568-1648.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>