<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Friday, 7 September 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let130"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">130</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">109</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">129</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Friday, 7 September 1877</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Friday, 7 September 1877.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Harry Gladwell’s visit <ref target="let129.xml">(129)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Theo’s sales trip <ref target="let128.xml">(128)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b128 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 7 Sept 1877’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0128" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000137_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000137_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000137_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000137_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0128" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000137_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000137_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000137_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000137_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam 7 Sept<c type="kp">_</c> 1877</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Het was mij eene heerlijke gewaarwording Gladwell’s stem te hooren in den gang terwijl ik boven zat te werken</ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab>en hem een oogenblik later te zien en de hand te drukken. Gisteren hebben wij eene goede wandeling gedaan <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>door de voornaamste straten en bij de meeste kerken en zijn dezen morgen voor 5 opgestaan om het volk op de werf te zien komen <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>en zijn daarop naar Zeeburg gewandeld en ook nog een kerkhof gezien en zijn naar het <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Trippenhuis geweest (2 maal) en hij alleen op van der Hoop en ook was hij bij Oom Cor in den winkel<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> (die <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>echter niet in stad was) en bij Mendes op de kamer.─ Nu hebben wij ook nog plan eens naar Oom <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Stricker te gaan (want daar ben ik heden ten eten gevraagd en waag het er maar op hem mede <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>te nemen), en als wij tijd hebben ook nog bij Vos en Kee.─ En ook zou ik zeer gaarne nog eens <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>met hem op Bickers eiland zijn maar misschien is er geen tijd. Heb hem zeer aangeraden <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>om ook naar Haarlem te gaan om de Sch<hi rend="ss">ijen</hi> van Frans Hals te zien<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> en daar gaat hij <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>nu heen en niet naar Antwerpen zoo als hij van plan was maar houdt Belgie voor <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>later en bepaalt zich nu uitsluitend tot Holland.</ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ook bragten wij een geruimen tijd op het studeerkamertje door en hebben gesproken over <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>things new and old.─<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">Weer gevoel ik terwijl hij naast mij zit hetzelfde gevoel dat mij zoo dikwijls tot hem <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>trok, als ware hij een zoon van hetzelfde huis en een broeder in het geloof omdat <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>hij liefheeft “the man of sorro<supplied>w</supplied>s and acquainted with grief”<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Die onze God <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>is en in Wiens leer en opstanding wij gelooven<c type="kk">/</c> naar Wiens geest wij zoeken<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>van Wiens liefde wij vragen dat zij ons dringe in het leven en dat niets ons <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>van Haar scheide<c type="kk">/</c> noch tegenwoordige noch toekomende dingen.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> In hem zal ook <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>de droefheid naar God werken wat zij in velen gewerkt heeft en werkt en zal werken<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>een onberouwelijke keuze<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> om het goede deel dat niet zal weggenomen worden<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> en <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>het ééne noodige te kiezen en het voortbrengen van vruchten des berouws <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>en der bekeering waardig.─<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Hij is een Christen en zal dat meer en meer worden. <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>Wij lazen deze morgen zamen het verhaal van Elia bij de beek Krith en bij <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>de weduwe<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="28a" xml:id="l-28a"/>─ want toen wij te Montmartre zamen woonden<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> ondervonden wij hoe het meel van de kruik niet verteerd werd en het <lb n="28b" xml:id="l-28b"/>water van de flesch niet ontbrak<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> ─ <lb n="28"/>en gisteren avond de gelijkenis van den zaaijer<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> en anderen.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Nu zal hij ook nog eenigen tijd bij U zijn en verlangd Uw kamertje te zien en <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>wat Gij van prenten hebt.</ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">Kreeg van hem Bunyan<c type="kk">/</c> the pilgrims progress, dat is eene aanwinst evenals <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>Bossuet<c type="kk">/</c> Oraison funèbres die ik onlangs zeer goedkoop heb gekocht<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> en de Imitation <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>van Th<c type="kp">_</c> à Kempis in het Latijn die ik van Vos<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> kreeg en die ik hoop eenmaal in het <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>Latijn te kunnen lezen.─</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hij heeft hier verscheiden stukjes gelezen uit Bungener, Esquiros, Lamenais, Souvestre, <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Lamartine (Cromwell) en had pleizier in de lithographiën naar Bosboom<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>wij hebben er een gekocht bij een jood en hij heeft mij order gegeven om er nog eenigen voor <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>hem te koopen bij voorkomende gelegenheid.─</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Van harte hoop ik Gij een goeden avond met hem zult hebben, en ik geloof hoe <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>meer Gij in hem zoekt hoe meer gij in hem zult vinden.─<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wij spraken over een en ander en wat wij tot elkander gezegd hebben is dit<c type="kk">/</c> velen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>hebben, gekomen zijnde op een punt van het leven waar men eene levenskeuze <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>doen moet<c type="kk">/</c> gekozen voor hun deel<c type="kk">/</c> “the love of Christ and poverty”<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/> of liever <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>“give me neither poverty nor riches<c type="kk">/</c> feed me with bread convenient for me”.─<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>De tijd van zamenzijn is mij omgevlogen en had wel gewenscht wij <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>wat langer zamen mogten zijn gebleven; maar dat kan niet en ieder moet <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>wederkeeren op zijn weg<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> en voortgaan te doen wat de hand vindt om te doen<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/> zoo als hij geroepen is<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-o-22"/> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>en ik voor mij ben er dankbaar voor in den grond van mijn hart dat ik hem <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>heb mogen wederzien en in hem terug te vinden wat mij tot hem aantrok. <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Hij vertelde mij dat Gij zeker de reis met de nouveautés zult doen en <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>wel over een week of 4, dan hoop ik dus U ook weer eens te zien<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Van harte hoop ik hij een aangename en goede herinnering aan zijn <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>bezoek aan Holland zal hebben, het is moedig van hem dat hij dat <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>plan maar eens heeft doorgezet.─</ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Groet Uwe huisgenooten, heb een goeden avond met hem, zou <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>U wel toewenschen aan hem gehecht te zijn zoo als ik mij op <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>t’oogenblik aan hem gehecht gevoel, en ontvang in gedachten <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>een handdruk van</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab>Uw zoo liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
<ab>Gij hebt zeker gehoord van het overlijden van Mevr. Richard; het moet een bangen <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>nacht geweest zijn.<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-o-23"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>
<ab rend="indent">Den Bijbel goed en grondig en met liefde te kennen<c type="kk">/</c> zou dat toch niet eene zeer <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>begeerlijke zaak zijn.─ </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-7" n="7">(2 maal) &lt; <hi rend="ital">Added later; parentheses added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-10" n="10">nemen), &lt; nemen,</note>
<note target="l-19" n="19">sorro<supplied>w</supplied>s &lt; <hi rend="ital">Text lost due to wear.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-43" n="43">gekozen &lt; hebben gekozen</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam, 7 Sept. 1877</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>It felt wonderful to hear <rs type="pers" key="394">Gladwell</rs>’s voice in the hall as I sat upstairs studying and to see him a moment later and to shake his hand. Yesterday we took a nice walk through the main streets and past most of the churches, and got up this morning before 5 to see the people coming to the dockyard and afterwards walked to Zeeburg and also saw a cemetery and went to the Trippenhuis (twice) and he alone to Van der Hoop, and he was also at <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs>’s gallery<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> (who isn’t in town, however) and with <rs type="pers" key="520">Mendes</rs> in the room. Now we also have plans to go to <rs type="pers" key="317 318">Uncle Stricker’s</rs> (because I’ve been invited to eat there today and will simply risk it and take him along), and if we have time also to see <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="776">Kee</rs>. And I would also like very much to go with him to Bickerseiland, but perhaps there won’t be time. Have also strongly suggested that he go to Haarlem to see the paintings by <rs type="pers" key="1073">Frans Hals</rs>,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and now he’s going there and not to Antwerp as he had planned, but will save Belgium for later and is concentrating now exclusively on Holland.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">We also spent a lot of time in the little study and talked of things new and old.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When he’s sitting beside me I again feel the same feeling that drew me to him so often, as though he were a son of the same family and a brother in faith because he loves ‘the man of sorrows and acquainted with grief’.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> Who is our God and in Whose teachings and resurrection we believe, Whose spirit we seek, of Whose love we ask that it constrain us in life and that nothing separate us from it, nor things present, nor things to come.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> In him, too, godly sorrow shall work that which in many it has worked and works and shall work, a choice not to be repented of,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> for that good part which shall not be taken away,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> and choosing the only thing necessary and worthy of bringing forth fruits meet for repentance.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> He is a Christian and will become one more and more. This morning we read together the story of Elijah by the brook Cherith and at the widow’s<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> – because when we lived together in Montmartre<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> we found that the barrel of meal did not waste and the cruse of water did not fail<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                    <hi rend="ss"> </hi>– and yesterday evening the parable of the sower<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> and others.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> Now he’ll stay with you for a while as well, and is longing to see your little room and what you have in the way of prints.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Received from him <rs type="pers" key="558">Bunyan</rs>, The pilgrim’s progress, that is an asset, as is <rs type="pers" key="542">Bossuet</rs>, Oraison funèbres, which I recently bought very cheaply,<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> and The imitation by <rs type="pers" key="679">T. a Kempis</rs> in Latin, which I got from <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs>
                    <anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> and which I hope to be able to read in Latin some day.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">He read here various bits of <rs type="pers" key="550">Bungener</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="600">Esquiros</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="683">Lamennais</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="744">Souvestre</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="685">Lamartine</rs> (Cromwell), and took pleasure in the lithographs after <rs type="pers" key="884">Bosboom</rs>,<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> we bought one from a Jew, and he gave me instructions to buy some more for him when the opportunity presents itself.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I sincerely hope that you’ll have a pleasant evening with him, and I believe that the more you seek in him the more you will find in him.<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">We talked about this and that, and what we said to each other is this: many, having come to a point in life where one must make a choice about life, have chosen for their part ‘the love of Christ and poverty’,<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> or rather ‘give me neither poverty nor riches, feed me with bread convenient for me’.<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> The time together flew past for me, and I wished we could have stayed together a little longer; but it cannot be, and everyone must return to his way<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> and continue to do whatsoever the hand findeth to do<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> in the calling wherein he was called,<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> and I for my part am thankful from the bottom of my heart that I was able to see him again, and found in him that which drew me to him. He told me that you will certainly make the trip with the <hi rend="ital">nouveautés</hi>, probably in about 4 weeks’ time, so I also hope to see you again then.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I sincerely hope that he’ll have pleasant and good memories of his visit to Holland, it’s courageous of him to have persisted with that plan.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Give my regards to your housemates, have a good evening with him; should wish for you to be attached to him as I feel attached to him at the moment, and accept in thought a handshake from</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your most loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>You’ve no doubt heard about the death of <rs type="pers" key="185">Mrs Richard</rs>; it must have been a difficult night.<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">To learn the Bible well and thoroughly and with love, would that not be a very desirable thing?</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The bookshop and art dealership of <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M. van Gogh</rs> was located at Keizersgracht 453.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>At that time an exhibition was being held on the top floor of a special wing between Haarlem’s Prinsenhof and the Stadhuis, at which seven works by <rs type="pers" key="1073">Frans Hals</rs> were on display: a canvas with the regents and regentesses of the Oudemannenhuis, a group portrait of the regents and regentesses of the Elisabeth Gasthuis and five militia pieces. See cat. Haarlem 1877.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" v="52">Matt. 13:52</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Isa" chap="53" v="3">Isa. 53:3</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rom" chap="8" vr="38-39">Rom. 8:38-39</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="2 Cor" chap="7" v="10">2 Cor. 7:10</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="10" v="42">Luke 10:42</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="3" v="8">Matt. 3:8</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
                        <vg:bibleref book="1 Kings" chap="17">1 Kings 17</vg:bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
  <ab>From October 1875 until January 1876, Van Gogh and <rs type="pers" key="394">Gladwell</rs> lived in the same building in Montmartre.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Kings" chap="17" vr="14-16">1 Kings 17:14-16</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>The parable of the sower is to be found in <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" vr="3-9">Matt. 13:3-9</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Mark" chap="4" vr="3-20">Mark 4:3-20</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="8" vr="5-15">Luke 8:5-15</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>Van Gogh had meanwhile compiled a notebook containing in various languages the parables (and miracles) related in the Gospels (<ref target="let128.xml">see letter 128</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
  <ab>For the purchase of <rs type="pers" key="542">Bossuet</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="72">
                            <hi rend="ital">Oraisons funèbres</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let129.xml">see letter 129</ref>; regarding <rs type="pers" key="558">Bunyan</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="103">
                            <hi rend="ital">The pilgrim’s progress</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let099.xml#n-22">see letter 99, n. 22</ref> and <ref target="let096.xml#n-17">letter 96, n. 17.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="806">Christoffel Martinus Vos</rs> gave Vincent <rs type="lit" key="35">
                            <hi rend="ital">De imitatione Christi</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="679">Thomas a Kempis</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
    <ab> For <rs type="lit" key="139">
                            <hi rend="ital">Cromwell</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="685">Alphonse Marie Louis Prat de Lamartine</rs>, <ref target="let119.xml#n-4">see letter 119, n. 4</ref>. 
      <ref target="let114.xml">See letter 114</ref> for the lithographs after <rs type="pers" key="884">Johannes Bosboom</rs> which Van Gogh bought. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="7" v="7">Matt. 7:7</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="11" v="9">Luke 11:9</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
  <ab>For the phrase ‘love of Christ’, cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rom" chap="8" v="35">Rom. 8:35</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="2 Cor" chap="5" v="14">2 Cor. 5:14</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Eph" chap="3" v="19">Eph. 3:19.</bibleref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Prov" chap="30" v="8">Prov. 30:8</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>Biblical.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Eccl" chap="9" v="10">Eccl. 9:10</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="22" xml:id="n-22" target="#note-t-22">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Cor" chap="7" v="20">1 Cor. 7:20</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="23" xml:id="n-23" target="#note-t-23">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="185">Mrs Richard</rs> died on 4 September 1877 at 2 a.m. <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had kept watch at her deathbed. On the day she died, he sent Theo a detailed report of her fateful accident and the tragic circumstances of her death: ‘there on the floor of the drawing-room suite – the dying woman, who could not even be picked up to be laid on a bed, her death throes lasted more than 3 times 24 hours, and it took that much time before that woman’s strong constitution was exhausted’ (FR b2554).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>