<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Thursday, 15 August 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let147"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">147</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">125</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">146</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Etten</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 15 August 1878</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Thursday, 15 August 1878.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Anna van Gogh and Joan van Houten register their banns <ref target="let146.xml">(146)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Aunt Cornelie van Gogh-Carbentus’s illness <ref target="let146.xml">(146)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b145 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Etten 15 Aug 1878’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0145" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000153_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000153_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000153_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000153_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0145" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000153_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000153_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000153_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000153_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Etten 15 Aug<c type="kp">_</c> 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Een enkel woordje sluit ik nog bij Pa en Moe in<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>om U nog even goeden morgen te zeggen. Het <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>regent buiten en dat doet het dezer dagen veel<c type="kk">/</c> met <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>storm erbij. Toen Anna en Joan zijn aangeteekend <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>was het een aardigen dag. Anna ziet er nu <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>terwijl Joan hier is heel wat opgeruimder en <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>beter uit dan voor dien tijd.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Zij denken voor <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>hun huwelijksreisje een togt door Belgie <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>te doen. eerst n. Brussel en vandaar denkelijk <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>naar het zuiden<c type="kk">/</c> Luik of Chaudfontaine of de <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>grot van Han. Schreef aan D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> de Jonge dat ik bereid <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>was om dadelijk n. Brussel te komen als werk of pligt <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>mij er riepen, maar dat als er geene gegronde reden bestond <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>waarom het wenschelijk zou kunnen geacht worden <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>dat ik er nu reeds heen ging ik nog gaarne (om reden <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>van Annas trouwen) een week hier zou blijven om <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>alsdan vóór Zondag 25 Aug<c type="kp">_</c> over te komen.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zeer nieuwsgierig ben ik of de tentoonstelling van <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>schilderijen aldaar dan nog open zal zijn<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zeer gaarne zou ik die zien.</ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is maar zeer treurig te Prinsenhage<c type="kk">/</c> Tante lijdt <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>veel, en allen zijn zeer bezorgd over haar<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik verlang naar een woordje van U, hoop U <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>wat uitvoeriger te schrijven zoodra ik te Brussel <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>zal zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ook over de tentoonstelling als die <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>ten minste nog niet gesloten is.</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Groet Braat &amp; Soek voor mij als gij hen ziet en Ernest. <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>A dieu, heb het zoo goed mogelijk, er gaat <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>geen dag om of er wordt over U gesproken. Schrijf <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>maar weer eens spoedig, en ontvang in gedachten <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>een hartelijken handdruk van</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab>uw liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="35*" xml:id="l-35s"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">in haast</hi>.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-18" n="18">blijven &lt; blijven)</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Etten, 15 Aug. 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I’m enclosing a few words with <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs>’s letter<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> to bid you good morning. It’s raining outside and has done so a lot lately, with strong winds too. It was nice the day <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="413">Joan</rs> registered their banns. Now that Joan is here, Anna looks a lot more cheerful and better than before.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> For their honeymoon they’re thinking of making a journey through Belgium, first to Brussels and from there probably south to Liège or Chaudfontaine or the cave in Han. Wrote and told the <rs type="pers" key="460">Rev. De Jonge</rs> that I was ready to come to Brussels straightaway if work or duty should call me, but that if there were no sound reasons that made it desirable for me to go there now, I’d like to stay here another week (because of Anna’s wedding), coming in that case before Sunday, 25 Aug.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m very curious to know whether the exhibition of paintings there will still be open,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> I should so much like to see it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Things are very sad at Princenhage, <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt</rs> suffers a lot, and they’re all very worried about her.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I long for a word from you, hope to write to you in more detail as soon as I’m in Brussels, also about the exhibition, at least if it isn’t over yet.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Give my regards to <rs type="pers" key="305">Braat</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="758">Soek</rs>, if you see them, and <rs type="pers" key="353">Ernest</rs>. Adieu, I wish you the very best, not a day goes by that we don’t speak of you. Do write again soon, and accept a hearty handshake in thought from</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">In haste.</hi>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The enclosed letters from <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Mr and Mrs van Gogh</rs> have both survived (FR b990 and b996). Nine days later Mrs van Gogh wrote again to Theo; her letter betrays her anxiety about Vincent’s future: ‘How will things turn out for Vincent? We watch him go with trepidation. His ideas about everyday life are so unhealthy that it seems to me he won’t be able to teach people; may things turn out better than expected. He travels there on Monday’ (FR b2433, 24 August 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Although <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> was cheered by the situation, her relations with Vincent did not improve. She wrote to thank Theo for the ‘splendid prints’ he had sent, and spoke plainly of Vincent’s stubbornness: ‘Vincent is more of a wooden lion than ever and is very annoyed at the preparations. For <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs>’s sake I hope so much that this thing in Belgium will succeed, but I fear that his extreme obstinacy and lack of human understanding won’t do him much good in his new situation’ (FR b989, 13 August 1878). Her characterization of Vincent as a ‘wooden lion’ probably refers to her brother’s lofty inaccessibility.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="412 413">Anna and Joan</rs> were married on 22 August 1878; Vincent originally planned to leave for Brussels on the 24th, according to a letter written by <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> to Theo: ‘Vincent will leave next Saturday. May he have the good fortune to succeed there.’ <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote the following about him in the same letter: ‘He is more withdrawn than ever, no doubt because he is concentrating hard on writing his sermons, which he is stocking up on’ (FR b991, 21 August 1878). The caves of Han, a tourist attraction, are in Han-sur-Lesse in the Ardennes. In the end he left on Monday 26 August (FR b2433).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This quite possibly refers to the Brussels Salon, which lasted from 5 September to 15 October. See <hi rend="ital">Exposition générale des Beaux-Arts 1878. Catalogue explicatif</hi>. Brussels 1878, pp. 11, 23.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>