<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Sunday, 10 February 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let140"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">140</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">118</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">139</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 10 February 1878</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Sunday, 10 February 1878.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Christoffel Vos’s illness <ref target="let131.xml">(131)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b138 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam 10 Februarij 1878’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0138" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000146_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000146_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000146_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000146_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000146_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000146_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0138" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000146_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000146_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000146_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000146_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000146_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000146_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam 10 Februarij 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Het is Zondagavond, en ik wil weer eens een woordje schrijven, want ik verlang ook niet weinig <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>om ook van U weer eens een brief te krijgen, schrijf maar weer eens spoedig, zoo dikwijls <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>ben ik in gedachten bij U. Hartelijk hoop ik dat Gij een goeden zondag hebt gehad.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoo als Gij weet is Pa hier geweest<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> en zeer blij ben ik daarom<c type="kk">/</c> wij gingen zamen naar Mendes<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Oom Stricker<c type="kk">/</c> Oom Cor<c type="kk">/</c> Vos en Kee en de beide families Meyes en de aangenaamste <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>herinnering aan Pa’s bezoek is nog die morgen die wij zamen doorbragten op mijne <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>studeerkamer met het nazien van werk en met het spreken over allerlei zaken. <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Gij kunt U denken dat die dagen omvlogen en toen ik<c type="kk">/</c> na Pa naar ’t station <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>te hebben gebragt en den trein te hebben nagezien zoolang die in het gezigt was <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>of ook zelfs maar den rook<c type="kk">/</c> weer terug kwam op mijn kamer en daar Pa’s stoel <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>nog stond bij het tafeltje waarop de boeken en schriften nog lagen van den <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>vorigen dag, al is het ook dat ik weet wij elkander toch betrekkelijk spoedig <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>zullen weerzien, ik kreeg het kwaad als een kind.</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zult wel reeds gehoord hebben dat Mendes ook op Pa een gunstigen indruk <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>maakte. Bij Oom Cor zagen wij s’avonds nog teekeningen en boeken<c type="kk">/</c> o.a<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>den Bijbel van Dore<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> en Le livre de Ruth en Histoire de Joseph van Bida<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">Was heden morgen in het Engelsche kerkje<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> en ontmoette daar bij het uitgaan <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>van de kerk Wierda die er ook was geweest. Wij wandelden een eind zamen <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>en hij vroeg mij of ik zijne kamer eens wilde komen zien<c type="kk">/</c> hij woont in de <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>Weteringstraat<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> een minuut of 10 van de Leidsche straat. Ik zeide hem dat <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>reeds sedert lang ik had verlangd die kamer te zien en waar en hoe hij woonde <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>en ging dus mede en bleef na het koffijdrinken tot zoowat 3 uur bij hem en zag <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>zijne boeken en hoorde het een en ander uit zijn leven, waar hij vroeger was <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>geweest enz<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> eerst is hij te Bolsward<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> geweest<c type="kk">/</c> toen te Haarlem en toen hier. Hij <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>heeft wel gewerkt in zijn leven en zal dat nog wel blijven doen en het niet ligt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>opgeven. Toen t’huis nog een stuk uit Caesar vertaald<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> en van middag bij Oom <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Stricker, daar kom ik nog al eens nu Oom<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> niet in stad en het hier in huis sedert <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Pa’s vertrek weer eenzaam is. Zij gingen vanavond naar Vos, die is nog niet beter<c type="kp">_</c> </ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik moet U nog feliciteeren met Pa’s verjaardag<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> al is die reeds voorbij<c type="kk">/</c> het zal wel een <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>goeden dag zijn geweest nu ook Anna er was, ik ben verlangend naar een <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>brief van t’huis om te hooren hoe dien dag is gevierd. Anna is wat ongesteld geweest <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>en was nog niet geheel beter<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> schreef zij in een brief dien Pa hier ontving. Misschien <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>heeft Pa U den brief van Moe voorgelezen die Zij schreef terwijl Pa hier was, daar <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>stond in van een bezoek bij een zieke als of het uit Adam Bede<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> was.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het mist hier vandaag<c type="kk">/</c> gelukkig trof Pa goed weer zoodat wij nog al hebben <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>geloopen.─</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik help U nog eens onthouden dat stuk van Jules Breton<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> niet dat het haast heeft maar <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>denk er om bij gelegenheid.</ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">In Maart zult Gij waarschijnlijk immers weer de reis doen<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> en ook weer naar <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>hier komen?</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dingsdag komt Oom Jan naar alle gedachten weer terug.</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zult wel veel te doen hebben in ’t begin van ’t jaar zooals bijna alle menschen. <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>Daarover gaf Wierda zijn hart ook eens lucht dezen morgen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Voor mij begint het ook hoe langer hoe meer van ernstigen aard te worden <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>naarmate het examen digter bij komt.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> ik zal blij zijn als het <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>s’morgens wat vroeger licht wordt en wij beginnen daaraan <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>reeds te wennen.</ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Heeft Pa erom gedacht U die photographie naar Maris<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> te geven<c type="kp">_</c> De <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>houtsnee naar v. Goyen<c type="kk">/</c> Dordrecht<c type="kk">/</c> hangt er voor in plaats, ging onlangs <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>dat schilderij nog eens zien hier op het museum<c type="kk">/</c> dat is toch door en <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>door goed.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> Ik zou met U als gij weer hier komt nog wel graag <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de etsen van Durer hier op het museum<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> ook nog eens doorzien zooals <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>wij het de vorige keer met die van Rembrandt deden.<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het zal in deze grijze dagen te Scheveningen wel mooi zijn<c type="kk">/</c> gaat gij <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>er nog al eens heen<c type="kp">_</c> ’t Zal er misschien zoo zijn als op dat sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> van Ruysdael <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>op het museum in den Haag. Hebt gij daarvan de lith. die indertijd in <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>de Kunstkronijk heeft gestaan,<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> die is wel goed.</ab>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoe gaat het bij Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> ik hoop voorspoedig<c type="kp">_</c> Zijt Gij er in lang<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> geweest?</ab>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tegenwoordig krijg ik van Oom Stricker ook eens of tweemaal s’weeks <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>les<c type="kk">/</c> dat is winst<c type="kp">_</c> Oom is er zeer ver in en ik ben blijde hij tijd heeft kunnen <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>vinden om het te doen.<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu jongen<c type="kk">/</c> een hartelijken handdruk in gedachten, ik ga aan mijn <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>werk<c type="kk">/</c> groet Uwe huisgenooten en ook Mauve als Gij hem tegenkomt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>heb het zoo goed mogelijk en schrijf eens spoedig, ook met de <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>verjaardag van Anna<c type="kk">/</c> al is die nog in ’t verschiet<c type="kk">/</c> geluk gewenscht<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>en geloof mij steeds</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab>Uw liefh. broer</ab>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab>Nacht jongen<c type="kk">/</c> ’k heb tot 12 uur zitten schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> een handdruk in gedachten.─</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam, 10 February 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>It’s Sunday evening, and I want to write a few words again, for I also really long to get another letter from you, do write again soon, I am with you so often in thought. I sincerely hope that you’ve had a good Sunday.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As you know, <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> was here<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and I’m very glad of it, we went together to <rs type="pers" key="520">Mendes</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle Stricker</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="776">Kee</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="571 573 575 219">both Meijjes families</rs>, and the most pleasant memory of Pa’s visit is that morning we spent together in my study, looking over my work and talking about all sorts of things. You can imagine that those days flew by and when, after bringing Pa to the station and watching the train or even only the smoke for as long as it was in sight, I came back to my room and Pa’s chair was standing there by the little desk on which the books and notebooks were still lying from the day before, even though I know that we’ll see each other again quite soon, I broke down and cried like a child.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll already have heard that <rs type="pers" key="520">Mendes</rs> made a favourable impression on <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> as well. In the evening, at <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs>’s, we saw drawings and books, including <rs type="pers" key="998">Doré</rs>’s Bible<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and <rs type="pers" key="856">Bida</rs>’s Le livre de Ruth and Histoire de Joseph.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Was in the English church this morning<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> and met <rs type="pers" key="820">Wierda</rs> upon leaving the church, who had been there too. We went for a walk together and he asked me if I’d like to come and see his room, he lives in Weteringstraat,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> about 10 minutes from Leidsestraat. I told him that for a long time I had wanted to see his room and where and how he lived, so I went along and after drinking coffee I stayed till around 3 o’clock and saw his books and heard a thing or two about his life, where he had been previously and so on, first he was in Bolsward,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> then in Haarlem and then here. He has worked hard in his life and will probably continue to do so and not give it up easily. Afterwards, at home, translated a passage from <rs type="pers" key="1672">Caesar</rs>,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> and this afternoon to <rs type="pers" key="317 318">Uncle Stricker’s</rs>, I go there rather often now that <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle</rs>
                    <anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> is out of town and now that it’s lonely again here in the house since Pa left. This evening they went to see <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs>, who isn’t any better.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I still have to congratulate you on <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs>’s birthday,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> even though it’s already been and gone, it will have been a good day, with <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> there too, I’m longing for a letter from home to hear how they celebrated that day. Anna was slightly indisposed and hadn’t yet recovered completely,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> she wrote in a letter that Pa received here. Perhaps Pa read <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs>’s letter aloud to you, which she wrote while Pa was here, it told about a visit to a sick person which sounded like something out of Adam Bede.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s foggy here today, fortunately <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> had good weather so that we could walk quite a lot.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m reminding you of that piece by <rs type="pers" key="899">Jules Breton</rs>,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> not that there’s any hurry, but try and remember it sometime.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Because in March you’ll probably make the trip again,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> won’t you, and also come here again?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan</rs> will most likely come back on Tuesday.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll certainly have a lot to do at the beginning of the year, like most people. <rs type="pers" key="820">Wierda</rs>, too, unburdened himself on that score this morning.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">For me, too, things are beginning to get more and more serious as the exam approaches.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> I’ll be glad when it grows light a bit earlier in the morning and we’re already beginning to get used to it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Did <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> remember to give you the photograph of the <rs type="pers" key="1202 1203">Maris</rs>?<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> The woodcut after <rs type="pers" key="1056">Van Goyen</rs>, Dordrecht, is hanging in its place. Went recently to see that painting again here in the museum, it is good through and through.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> The next time you come here I’d like to look through the etchings by <rs type="pers" key="990">Dürer</rs> here in the museum again,<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> as we did with <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s last time.<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s no doubt beautiful in Scheveningen on these grey days, do you still go there quite often? Perhaps it’s like that painting by <rs type="pers" key="1333">Ruisdael</rs> in the museum in The Hague. Do you have the lithograph of it that was once in the Kunstkronijk?<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> It’s really good.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How are things going at <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>’s? Very well, I hope. Have you been there recently?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m currently taking lessons from <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle Stricker</rs> once or twice a week, that is a bonus. Uncle is an expert in it, and I’m glad he could find the time to do it.<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now, old boy, a hearty handshake in thought, I’ll set to work, give my regards to your housemates, and also to <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> if you run into him, I wish you the very best, write soon, also congratulations on <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>’s birthday, even though it’s still to come,<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> and believe me ever</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Good-night, old boy, I sat up writing till 12 o’clock, a handshake in thought.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> travelled on Monday, 4 February 1878, to Amsterdam ‘to put my mind at ease a little about Vincent’s future’ (FR b965 to Theo, 2 February 1878). Before returning to Etten on Thursday, 7 February, he stopped at The Hague (FR b967). A short while later he admitted to Theo that he was not easy about Vincent’s future: ‘We can’t stop worrying about him; there is and always will be something strange about him’ (FR b967, 20 February 1878). <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote about Vincent’s progress to Theo: ‘You wrote that when he visited you [on Monday, 7 January] he was really very good, certainly he is, perhaps that will come out more when he finally has to act independently, but he is so awfully impractical, but we will hope for the best’ (FR b966, 2 February 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
      <rs type="lit" key="177">
                            <hi rend="ital">La Sainte Bible selon la Vulgate. Traduction nouvelle avec les dessins de Gustave Doré</hi>
                        </rs>. Tours 1866. This work was available in all kinds of editions, including popular ones. A Dutch edition containing 200 plates, produced under the editorial supervision of N. Beets, had appeared in 1870. See Doré, <hi rend="ital">Catalogue</hi>, pp. 148-149.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="856">Alexandre Bida</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="178">
                            <hi rend="ital">Le livre de Ruth</hi>
                        </rs>. Translated from the Holy Bible by [L.I.] Lemaistre de Sacy. Paris 1876 and <rs type="lit" key="179">
                            <hi rend="ital">L’histoire de Joseph</hi>
                        </rs>. Translated from the Holy Bible by [L.I.] Lemaistre de Sacy. Paris 1878. Both works were illustrated by Bida.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>On 10 February the <rs type="pers" key="280">Rev. William Macfarlane</rs> conducted the service in the English Reformed Church on the Begijnhof.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="820">Jan Willem Wierda</rs> lived at Weteringstraat 26, above Arend Jan Rolff’s grocer’s shop.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Bolsward is a village in the province of Friesland in the north of the Netherlands.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Most likely <rs type="pers" key="1672">Julius Caesar</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="180">
                            <hi rend="ital">De bello gallico</hi>
                        </rs> (51 <hi rend="sc">bc</hi>), an account of the campaigns to Northern Europe, which was and still is used extensively in the instruction of Latin.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan van Gogh</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
      <note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> turned 56 on 8 February.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>, who by now had been staying for some time with the <rs type="pers" key="413">Van Houten family</rs> in Hengelo, was ill and under a doctor’s supervision. All the same, she travelled to Etten for her <rs type="pers" key="526">father</rs>’s birthday (FR b966).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>As the wife of a minister, <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> visited the sick in her husband’s parish. The novel <rs type="lit" key="20">
                            <hi rend="ital">Adam Bede</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="590">George Eliot</rs> features the preacher Dinah Morris, who visits the sick. Her visits are described in an idealized manner, and she herself is ideally characterized as a person full of loving kindness.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>For Vincent’s initial request for one of <rs type="pers" key="899">Breton</rs>’s poems, <ref target="let139.xml#n-13">see letter 139, n. 13.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>The sales trip undertaken for Goupil &amp; Cie to interest booksellers and print dealers in the firm’s publications.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>Two months later <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘<rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> will write to you about Vincent, how much it will cost him to make the sacrifice, and yet Pa wrote to him so faithfully, it seems to me he must lend an ear to it. If only he passed his exam when the time comes, how it would encourage him’ (FR b993, 21 April 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>It is unclear which work by <rs type="pers" key="1202 1203">Maris</rs> this refers to.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1056">Jan van Goyen</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">View of the river before Dordrecht</hi> was part of the Dupper Collection in the Trippenhuis. See cat. Rijksmuseum 1885, p. 15, cat. no. 101, with a woodcut. The painting is now considered to be in the ‘manner of Jan van Goyen’ and bears the title <hi rend="ital">View of the Merwede before Dordrecht</hi> (Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum). <rs type="ill" key="1868">Ill. 1868</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>Numerous prints by <rs type="pers" key="990">Dürer</rs> were preserved in the Trippenhuis.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
<ab>For Theo’s visits to Amsterdam, <ref target="let132.xml#n-10">see letter 132, n. 10</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>The lithograph <hi rend="ital">Strandgezicht </hi>(Beach view) by <rs type="pers" key="1578">Adolf Carel Nunnink</rs> after <rs type="pers" key="1333">Jacob van Ruisdael</rs> appeared in <hi rend="ital">Kunstkronijk</hi> 14 (1873), NS, between pp. 96-97. <rs type="ill" key="1869">Ill. 1869</rs>. The painting <hi rend="ital">Beach view</hi> (The Hague, Royal Cabinet of Paintings Mauritshuis) is now considered to be a copy. <rs type="ill" key="406">Ill. 406</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘in a long time’ (Was it long ago that ...).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="318">J.P. Stricker</rs>, who had taken upon himself the supervision of Vincent’s study, no doubt instructed him in the principles of theology and Christianity, as well as in history; <rs type="pers" key="520">Mendes</rs> tutored him in classical languages, <rs type="pers" key="786">Teixeira de Mattos</rs> in algebra and geometry.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> would turn 23 on 17 February.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>