<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, end of June 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let168"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">168</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">146</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">167</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Etten</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>end of June 1881</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, end of June 1881.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b166 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The mention of Van Rappard’s visit and the departure of Willemien suggest that the letter was written towards the end of June 1881. Several of the drawings Van Rappard made during his visit have survived. They are dated 13, 14 and 15 June 1881. If his stay is reckoned to have lasted twelve days (cf. ‘around 12 days’, <ref target="#l-3">l. 3</ref>), he must have left Etten on Thursday, 16 June (at the earliest) or by Saturday, 25 June (at the latest). Another clue as to the date of the letter, however, is that Willemien has meanwhile gone to Weesp to work as a governess. She probably moved there shortly before taking up this position on 2 July 1881 (though the family correspondence does not reveal the actual date of her move).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0166" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000177_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000177_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000177_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000177_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0166" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000177_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000177_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000177_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000177_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Het is tijd dat ik U weer eens een woordje schrijf.</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ge moet weten dat Rappard hier is geweest, een dag of 12, en <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>nu is hij weer vertrokken.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Natuurlijk moet ge de groete <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>van hem hebben.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">We zijn zamen nog al veel uitgeweest, verscheiden malen <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>o.a<c type="kp">_</c> naar de hei bij Seppe<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> naar de zoogenaamde <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Passievaart<c type="kk">/</c> een groot moeras.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Aldaar heeft Rappard <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>een groote studie geschilderd (1 meter bij 50) waarin veel <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>goeds was<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Overigens heeft hij een stuk of 10 kleine sepia’s <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> ook in ’t Liesbosch.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Terwijl hij aan ’t schilderen was heb ik een penteekening <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>gemaakt van een andere plek in ’t moeras alwaar veel <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>waterlelies groeijen. (bij den Roozendaalschen weg.)<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wij zijn ook zamen naar Prinsenhage geweest doch <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Oom<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> lag te bed &amp; is weer niet wel.</ab>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">Rappard gaat wel vooruit in zijn werk dunkt me<c type="kk">/</c> hij <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>schijnt naar ’t geen ik van hem hoorde een goed <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>ingerigt atelier t’huis gekregen te hebben.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Nu gaat <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>hij deze week naar Loosdrecht<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> alwaar hij een maand <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>denkt te blijven. Hij werkt ook geregeld &amp; veel.</ab>
                <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb gekregen <hi rend="ital">Cassagne</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c>
                    <hi rend="ital"> Traité d’aquarelle</hi>,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>&amp; ben bezig dat te bestudeeren<c type="kk">/</c> al zou het zijn dat <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>ik geen aquarellen maakte zoo zal ik er toch nog alligt <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>veel in vinden<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. voor sepia en inkt.</ab>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">Want tot heden<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> ben ik nog maar uitsluitend met potlood <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>blijven teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> opgewerkt of uitgehaald met de pen<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>desnoods met een rietpen die breeder werkt.</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hetgeen ik geteekend heb in den laatsten tijd bragt die <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>manier van doen ook mee<c type="kk">/</c> daar het zulke onderwerpen <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>waren als waarbij veel te <hi rend="ital">teekenen</hi> was<c type="kk">/</c> ook perspectief teekenen. <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>n.l. enkele werkplaatsen hier in het dorp, een smidse<c type="kk">/</c> timmermans<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>winkel &amp; klompenmaker.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Willemien is nu vertrokken<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> &amp; dat spijt mij<c type="kk">/</c> zij poseert zeer <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>goed<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een teekening van haar<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> &amp; nog van een ander <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>meisje dat hier gelogeerd heeft. Daar heb ik een naaimachine <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>op gebragt.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> Er zijn tegenwoordig geen spinnewielen meer<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>&amp; dat is voor schilders &amp; teekenaars wel erg jammer<c type="kk">/</c> evenwel <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>er is iets voor in de plaats gekomen dat niet minder <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>pittoresk is en dat is het naaimachine<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoe staat het eigentlijk met Uw naar hier komen dezen zomer<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>is er nog kans op dat dit werkelijk gebeurt.<lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/> Ik hoop het dat er van komen zal.</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Rappard schijnt er daar te Loosdrecht een eigen bootje <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>op na te houden<c type="kk">/</c> dat is nog al gezellig<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Van Loosdrecht denkt hij naar Gelderland<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/> te gaan. <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>Hij zou u zeer graag eens ontmoeten &amp; ik heb hem <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>beloofd dat als ge kwaamt &amp; ik wist vooruit wanneer<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ik ’t hem zou laten weten omdat hij alsdan ’t zoo <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>zou zien te schikken dat hij U eens zag.</ab>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">of hij nog weer naar Parijs terug zal gaan <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>weet ik niet<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> hij sprak er in ’t geheel niet <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>van. Of dit een teeken is dat hij er niet meer over <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>denkt dan wel of integendeel il couve <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>son projet<c type="kk">/</c> dat weet ik niet<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik te rade ga met de omstandigheid dat hij pas <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>23 jaar oud is en meer dergelijke dingen<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ’t mij niet verwonderen <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>of het laatste was ’t geval.</ab>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zult hoop ik als ge eens een oogenblikje <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>disponibel hebt wel eens schrijven. Als ge soms <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>kans ziet om mij een catalogus van den Salon te <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>bezorgen dan zou ik mij daarvoor zeer recommandeeren.<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Rappard gaat naar hij mij zeide zich ook al de boeken <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>van Cassagne aanschaffen. Hij sukkelt nog met zijn <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>perspectief en ik weet geen beter geneesmiddel voor die <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>kwaal, althans als ik er zelf volkomen van mogt genezen <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>zou ik het aan die boeken te danken hebben.<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/> dat wil zeggen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>aan ’t in praktijk brengen van de theorie die er in staat. Het in praktijk <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>brengen er van kan men er evenwel niet bij koopen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>ware dat zoo er zou meer debiet<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> van zijn misschien.</ab>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>It’s time that I wrote you a few lines again.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I must tell you that <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> was here for 12 days or so, and has now left.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Naturally he sends you his regards.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">We went on a fair number of excursions together, several times to the heath at Seppe,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> among other places, and the so-called Passievaart, a huge marsh.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> There <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> painted a large study (1 metre x 50 cm), much of which was good.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> Incidentally, he made around 10 small sepias, also in the Liesbos.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">While he was painting I made a pen drawing of another spot in the marsh where many water lilies grow. (Near Roosendaalseweg.)<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">We also went to Princenhage together, but <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle</rs>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> was in bed and is unwell again.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It seems to me that <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> really is progressing in his work, from what he told me he seems to have been given a well-furnished studio at home.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> This week he’s going to Loosdrecht,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> where he intends to spend a month. He also works regularly and hard.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve received <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="922">Cassagne</rs>, Traité d’aquarelle</hi>,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and am busy studying it, even if I don’t make any watercolours I’ll probably find a great deal in it anyway, as regards sepia and ink, for example.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Because up to now<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> I’ve been drawing with pencil only, worked up or heightened with the pen,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> if necessary with a reed pen, which makes broader lines.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">That manner of working was implicit in what I’ve been drawing lately, for they were subjects which required a lot of <hi rend="ital">drawing</hi>, also drawing in perspective, namely several workshops here in the village, a smithy, a carpenter’s shop and a clog-maker.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> has left<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> and I’m sorry, she poses very well, I have a drawing of her<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> and one of another girl who stayed here. I put a sewing machine in that one.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> There are no spinning wheels<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> nowadays, and that’s a great pity for painters and draughtsmen. However, something has taken their place that is no less picturesque, and that is the sewing machine. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">What’s the situation about your coming here next summer? Is there still a chance that it’ll happen? I hope so.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> appears to keep his own boat there at Loosdrecht, that’s rather jolly.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He intends to go from Loosdrecht to Gelderland.<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> He’d very much like to meet you, and I’ve promised him that if you were to come and I knew beforehand when, I’d let him know so that he could arrange to see you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t know whether he’ll go back to Paris,<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> he didn’t even mention it. I don’t know whether this is a sign that he’s no longer thinking about it or whether, on the contrary, he’s hatching his plan.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">When I think about the circumstance of his being only 23 years old and other such things, it wouldn’t surprise me if the latter was the case.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You will, I hope, write when you have a spare moment. If you can manage to get me a catalogue from the Salon, please do so.<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> told me that he was also going to buy all of <rs type="pers" key="922">Cassagne</rs>’s books. He’s still struggling with perspective, and I know of no better remedy for that disease. If I, at any rate, am ever completely cured of it, I’ll have those books to thank for it.<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> That’s to say, the putting into practice of the theory contained in them. The putting into practice can’t, however, be purchased with the books; were it so, perhaps more would be sold.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now adieu, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>It is not known exactly when <rs type="pers" key="1306">Anthon van Rappard</rs>’s visit took place; see <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>. In the introduction to her edition of the letters, <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> quoted Van Rappard’s recollections of the visit from a letter that is now presumably lost. See <hi rend="ital">Brieven</hi> 1914, p. <hi rend="sc">xxxiv</hi>; also in Pickvance 1992, pp. 102-103. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Near Seppe, a village approximately 5 km west of Etten, <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> made the drawing <rs type="otherart" key="198">
                            <hi rend="ital">Landscape near Seppe</hi>
                        </rs>, dated ‘Seppe 14 juni’ (Utrecht, Centraal Museum). See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 70, cat. no. 57.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The Passievaart, or Pagnevaart, is between the parishes of Hoeven and Bosschenhoofd, about 5 km from Etten-Leur. The marsh in the present-day nature reserve ‘Pagnevaart’ could be the remains of an old peat canal (<hi rend="ital">RAW</hi>). Here <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> made the drawing <rs type="otherart" key="199">
                            <hi rend="ital">The Passievaart near Seppe</hi>
                        </rs>, dated ‘Seppe 13 Juni ’81’ (Utrecht, Centraal Museum). See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 32-33, 70, cat. no. 56.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The painted study is not known. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 70.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>The other known drawings by <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> which date from this period are: <rs type="otherart" key="200">
                            <hi rend="ital">The parsonage at Etten</hi>
                        </rs>, dated ‘Etten, 14 Juni ’81’ (private collection); <rs type="otherart" key="201">
                            <hi rend="ital">Country road near Princenhage</hi>
                        </rs>, dated ‘Prinsenhage-Etten 15 Juni ’81’ (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum); and <rs type="ill" key="1902">
                            <hi rend="ital">Reader</hi>
                        </rs> (Utrecht, Centraal Museum). Two other drawings (both watercolours) were possibly made during <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s stay in Etten: <rs type="otherart" key="203">
                            <hi rend="ital">Street in a village</hi>
                        </rs> and <rs type="otherart" key="204">
                            <hi rend="ital">Farmhouse with trees</hi>
                        </rs> (both Utrecht, Centraal Museum). See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 71-72, cat. nos. 58-62. The Liesbos is a wooded area east of Etten.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Van Gogh made two drawings of this spot: <hi rend="ital">Marsh with water lilies</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2335">F 845 / JH 7</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Marsh</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2336">F 846 / JH 8</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="183">Van Rappard’s parents</rs> lived at Heerenstraat, A 1173 (now Herenstraat 23 and 23 bis) in Utrecht.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>A place c. 8 km north of Utrecht, located in an area with a great deal of water.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="922">Armand Théophile Cassagne</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="212">
                            <hi rend="ital">Traité d’aquarelle</hi>
                        </rs> (1875) is a textbook treating the art of watercolour. It explains materials, the various types of paper, the use of colour, techniques, and how to approach nature subjects. The fourth part contains a discussion of sepia (Cassagne 1875, pp. 231-239).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>Van Gogh doubtless means ‘since I’ve been in Etten’, because there is certainly watercolour in several of his previous drawings.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>‘Heighten’ is a technical term meaning ‘to brighten up paint that has become dull with varnish’. Van Gogh means that he worked up the drawing with pen, i.e. ink, by elaborating on it and applying accents here and there.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>These drawings of workshops are not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>On 2 July 1881 <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> began work as a governess in the employ of the widow Adriana Maria Scheffer-Michielsen, living at Herensingel 21 in Weesp (near Amsterdam), who had five young daughters. Willemien registered as a resident of Weesp on 5 July (<hi rend="ital">GAW</hi>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>Drawings for which <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> posed are not known. Hulsker suspects that <rs type="ill" key="2337">F 849 / JH 11</rs> was made from a photograph (cf. Hulsker 1996, p. 14 and <ref target="let169.xml#n-4">letter 169, n. 4</ref>). Van Gogh seems here to be speaking of a figure study rather than a portrait. Cf. cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 32-33. <rs type="pers" key="478">Piet Kaufmann</rs> – the family’s gardener, who also posed for Vincent – recalled later: ‘Willemien, his sister, also posed for him, beneath the walnut tree in the garden’. See ‘Tuinman van dominee Van Gogh vertelt zijn herinneringen over Vincent’, <hi rend="ital">Gazet van Antwerpen</hi>, 3 December 1953.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>We do not know who this guest was. The drawing with the sewing machine is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>In the nineteenth century many peasants in rural Brabant earned part of their living spinning yarn for textile manufacturers. However, the industrialization that took place in the second half of the century caused the gradual disappearance of this cottage industry. See Van den Eerenbeemt 1977, espec. pp. 60-70.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
<ab>A province in the east of the Netherlands with large wooded areas, where Dutch landscape painters often worked.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> had spent some time in Paris (<ref target="let166.xml">see letter 166</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>The catalogue of the Salon, <hi rend="ital">Explication des ouvrages de peinture, sculpture, architecture, gravure et lithographie des artistes vivants exposés au Palais des Champs-Elysées le 2 mai 1881</hi>. Paris 1881.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
    <ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="922">Armand Cassagne</rs> treated perspective not only in the above-mentioned <rs type="lit" key="212">
                            <hi rend="ital">Traité d’aquarelle</hi>
                        </rs> (<ref target="#n-10">see n. 10</ref>) but also in various other books, such as <rs type="lit" key="213">
                            <hi rend="ital">Guide de l’alphabet du dessin</hi>
                        </rs>, <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="509">Eléments de perspective</rs>
                        </hi>, <rs type="lit" key="214">
                            <hi rend="ital">Traité pratique de perspective</hi>
                        </rs> and <rs type="lit" key="215">
                            <hi rend="ital">La perspective du paysagiste</hi>
                        </rs>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Meaning: ‘dan zouden er meer van verkocht worden’ (then more would be sold).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>