<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Brussels, on or about Wednesday, 16 February 1881.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let163"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">163</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">141</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">162</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Brussels</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Wednesday, 16 February 1881</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Brussels, on or about Wednesday, 16 February 1881.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh’s wants to become an illustrator <ref target="let162.xml">(162)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b161 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Brussel febr. 1881’. Van Gogh congratulates his parents on the birthday of Anna, which was 17 February <ref target="#l-138">(l. 138)</ref>, so he must have written this letter on or shortly before that date. The manuscript bears the number ‘16’, added later by another hand in darker ink.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0161" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000171_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000171_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000171_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000171_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000171_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0161" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000171_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000171_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000171_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000171_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000171_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000171_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Brussel febr. 1881</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Beste Pa en Moe,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Uw brief heb ik ontvangen &amp; was er blij mede <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>van wege dat ik er reeds naar had uitgezien<c type="kk">/</c> vooral <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>om reden van Pa’s ongesteldheid.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Gelukkig dat <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>het aanvankelijk beter gaat.</ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het blijft nog al voorspoedig gaan met mijn werk hoewel <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>het nog onvolkomen is en nog veel beter moet worden. <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Bij dien schilder<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> vond ik op zijn atelier eene zeer goede <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>afbeelding van een skelet. Daar die dingen betrekkelijk <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>moeielijk goed te vinden zijn vroeg ik hem of hij mij <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>het wilde afstaan voor een dag of wat om het na te <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>teekenen. Aanvankelijk maakte hij bezwaar<c type="kk">/</c> waarschijnlijk <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>omdat hij meende ik het niet zou kunnen doen of er <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>te lang werk aan zou hebben<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik hield aan om <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>het te hebben &amp; hij liet het mij toe. Dat was verl. Zondag <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>middag en zoodra ik ’thuis kwam begon ik er aan en <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Maandagavond stond het er op en tot zijn verwondering <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>bragt ik het hem reeds Dinsdag morgen terug en <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>hij vond mijn teekening goed en die is ook werkelijk <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>zoo heel kwaad niet.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Ik zal nog wel meer van <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>dien man profiteeren als hij maar tijd disponibel <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>heeft, in sommige punten en vooral in perspectief is hij goed <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>ingelicht &amp; kan ik althans nog veel van hem leeren.</ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu moet ik U iets anders zeggen dat ik gedaan heb. Zooals ik <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>U schreef heb ik omstreeks een maand geleden een broek &amp; <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>jas gekocht uit de tweede hand. Dit is mij zoo goed bevallen <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>dat ik bij denzelfden nog een jas en nog een broek heb genomen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Wel was ik min of meer met het eerstgekochte gesteld<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> maar <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>als men 2 stel heeft is het eigentlijk beter &amp; verslijt het minder <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>gaauw omdat men verwisselen kan. Ik zend U een staal <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>van het goed hierbij. En ik had ook noodig mijn ondergoed <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>aan te vullen met 3 onderbroeken en heb daarvoor gegeven f<hi rend="ss">r</hi> 2.75 per <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>stuk en bovendien kocht ik voor 4 francs een paar schoenen. <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Het was werkelijk niet overbodig dat ik dit een &amp; ander nam. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Dit een &amp; ander heeft een merkbare bres gemaakt <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>in het voor deze maand gezondene en ik zal er <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>min of meer voor moeten krom liggen, vooral omdat <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>ik den schilder 5 francs vooruitgaf voor de <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>lessen.</ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maak U niet ongerust over deze uitgave evenwel <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>en verdenk mij niet van roekeloosheid want eigentlijk <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>is veeleer het tegendeel mijn fout<c type="kk">/</c> en kon ik nog <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>meer uitgeven zou ik ligt nog spoediger opschieten en <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>vorderen.</ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Kunt U mij deze maand nog iets zenden<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>zonder dat het U zelf in benaauwdheid brengt dan <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>zou ik U dat echter wel willen vragen.</ab>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar kunt U het niet dan is er geen onmiddelijke <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>haast mede want ik sprak er een woord over met <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>den huisbaas<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> dat ik mogelijk wat zou moeten <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>schipperen deze maand en hij vindt het goed dat ik hem <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>betaal wanneer het mij gelegen komt omdat hij mij <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>nu lang genoeg kent om niet meer bepaald te <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>vorderen dat ik vooruit betaal, ten minste geen volle <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>maand vooruit.─</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Met dat bewuste pak heb ik nog een ander doel <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>dan alleen het zelf zoo lang mogelijk te dragen, <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wanneer het n.l. wat oud geworden zal zijn<c type="kk">/</c> zal <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>het mij nog op een andere wijze dienst doen. <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>U moet namelijk weten dat ik langzamerhand <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>eene kleine collectie werkmans kleeren hebben moet <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>om er modellen mede te kunnen kleeden<c type="kk">/</c> voor <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>mijn teekeningen namelijk.</ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bijvoorbeeld een Brabantsche blaauwe kiel, het <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>graauw linnen pak dat de mijnwerkers dragen en <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>hun leeren hoed<c type="kk">/</c> verder een strooien hoed en klompen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>een visscherscostuum van bruin pilo<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> met een zuidwester. <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>En zeer bepaaldelijk ook die kleeding van dat soort <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>zwart of bruin fluweel die zeer schilderachtig en <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>karakteristiek is ─ verder een rood baai buis<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> of borstrok. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>En evenzeer een paar vrouwencostumes<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>dat van de Kempen<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> &amp; de buurt van Antwerpen met <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>de Brabantsche muts en b.v. dat van Blankenberg<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> of <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Schevening of Katwijk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is echter geenszins mijn plan om dit alles mij <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>op eens aan te schaffen maar wel zeer zeker <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>langzamerhand, stuk voor stuk, bij gelegenheid, dit <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>een &amp; ander bij een te brengen. <lb n="79a" xml:id="l-79a"/>En daar men die kleeren uit de <lb n="79b" xml:id="l-79b"/>tweede hand krijgen kan is het <lb n="79c" xml:id="l-79c"/>gansch niet onbereikbaar.</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">En dit alles zal eerst goed op streek kunnen komen <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>als ik ergens voor vast een soort atelier heb.─</ab>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dit is de eenige ware manier om er te komen, <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>te teekenen naar model met de noodige costumes<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>Alleen als ik het teekenen zoo grondig en ernstig <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>opvat<c type="kk">/</c> steeds zoekende de werkelijkheid weer <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>te geven<c type="kk">/</c> dan zal ik er komen en dan is er <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>ondanks de onvermijdelijke uitgaven nog een <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>bestaan in te vinden. Want een goed teekenaar <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>kan tegenwoordig wel degelijk werk vinden en <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>naar dergelijke personen is veel vraag en <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>er zijn betrekkingen te krijgen die zeer goed <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>betaald worden. <lb n="92a" xml:id="l-92a"/>De zaak is dus zoo knap mogelijk te trachten te <lb n="92b" xml:id="l-92b"/>worden.</ab>
                <lb n="92"/>
<ab rend="indent">Te Parijs is er menig teekenaar <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>die 10 of 15 francs daags verdient, en te Londen &amp; nog <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>elders evenzeer en zelfs nog meer<c type="kk">/</c> maar <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>dit bereikt men niet op eens en zoover ben ik <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>nog geenszins, maar het kan werkelijk zoo <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>worden als ik wat zegen heb en op nieuw in <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>relatie kom met personen als de Hr Tersteeg of <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>Theo en nog meer bepaaldelijk ook met <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>goede schilders &amp; teekenaars. Maar er moet enorm <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>gewerkt &amp; gestudeerd worden, dat is de conditie.</ab>
                <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het zal U niet verwonderen als ik U zeg dat <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>ik buitengewoon sterk verlang te weten wat Theo’s <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>propositie mogelijk wezen mogt of om welligt <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>iets te vernemen van den Hr Tersteeg.</ab>
                <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>
<ab rend="indent">Want op de een of andere manier moet ik <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>toch zoo ongeveer in de Maand Maart weten 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>waaraan ik mij te houden heb &amp; hoe en waar ik <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>gedurende de lente- &amp; zomermaanden zal kunnen <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>werken.</ab>
                <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>
<ab rend="indent">En mogt ik gaandeweg aan het verdienen kunnen <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>raken<c type="kk">/</c> zou mij gansch niet onaangenaam zijn, <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>hoewel de hoofdzaak is dat ik maar vorder &amp; <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>sterker wordt in mijn teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> dan komt er later <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>nog veel teregt, hetzij het langer hetzij het korter dure.</ab>
                <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>
<ab rend="indent">Modellen kosten duur, althans betrekkelijk duur <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>en kon ik die betalen &amp; ze dikwijls hebben <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>dan zou ik veel beter kunnen werken.─ Maar dan <lb n="118a" xml:id="l-118a"/>wordt ook een atelier onontbeerlijk. <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>En dit weten zulken als de Hr Tersteeg &amp; Theo &amp; anderen <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>zeer goed<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin ik moet afwachten tot zij schrijven <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>over een of ander en intusschen doen wat ik kan.</ab>
                <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maakte nog een teekening van mijnwerkers in de <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>sneeuw die al wat beter is dan die van verleden <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>winter<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> er is meer karakter &amp; effekt in.</ab>
                <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>
<ab rend="indent">En ben ook weer aan het verzamelen van houtgravures <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>op de manier van die plakboeken zooals Theo &amp; Willemien <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>er in der tijd ook hadden. Want als ik dat wat <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>compleet heb dan kan ik er nog nut van hebben <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>want het kon zeer wel er nog op uitloopen dat <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>ik met der tijd inderdaad voor houtgravure ga werken.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>
<ab rend="indent">U moet wel weten dat de bewuste kleeren die ik <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>kocht van goed model zijn &amp; mij beter staan dan <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>iets anders dat ik mij herinneren kan, ik zeg U dit <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>omdat U zoudt kunnen meenen het iets opzigtigs <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>of ongewoons was. Vooral op de ateliers draagt <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>men deze stof<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> dikwijls.</ab>
                <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu eindig ik na groete aan allen en na <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>U gelukgewenscht te hebben met Anna’s <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>verjaardag<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> &amp; geloof mij </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>
<ab>Uw liefh<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>
<ab>Die schilder bij wien ik nu les neem heeft op <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>’t oogenblik o.a. een zeer goed sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> onder handen <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>van een visscher van Blankenberge.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-5" n="5">reden &lt; rede</note>
<note target="l-109" n="109">lente- &lt; lente</note>
<note target="l-134" n="134">omdat &lt; opdat</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Brussels, Feb. 1881</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Dear <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs>,</ab>
    <ab>I received your letter and was glad to have it, for I had already been looking forward to it, especially because of Pa’s indisposition.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> It’s fortunate that he’s starting to get better.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Things continue to go quite well with my work, although it’s still imperfect and must improve a lot. I found a very good illustration of a skeleton in that painter’s<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> studio. Because such things are fairly difficult to find, I asked him whether he’d give it to me for a day or two in order to copy it. At first he objected, probably because he thought that I wouldn’t be able to do it or that it would take me too long, but I insisted on having it and he allowed me to. That was last Sunday afternoon, and as soon as I got home I started on it, and on Monday evening it was finished, and to his surprise I brought it back to him on Tuesday morning already and he thought my drawing good, and in fact it isn’t that bad.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> I’ll profit even more from that man if only he has the time, he’s well informed on some points, especially perspective, and I can anyhow learn a lot from him.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now I must tell you about something else I’ve done. As I told you in a letter, I bought a pair of trousers and a jacket second-hand about a month ago. It turned out so well that I bought another jacket and another pair of trousers from the same man. I was of course more or less provided for by the first one, but having two suits is actually better and they don’t wear out so fast, because one can alternate between them. I herewith send you a sample of the material. And I also needed to supplement my underclothes with 3 pairs of underwear for which I paid 2.75 francs apiece, and I also bought a pair of shoes for 4 francs. I really did have to buy a few things. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> These few things have made a noticeable hole in what was sent for this month, and I’ll have to tighten my belt rather, especially because I paid the painter 5 francs in advance for the lessons.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Don’t be concerned about these expenses, though, and don’t suspect me of recklessness, for in fact the opposite is sooner my failing, and if I could spend more I’d easily progress and make headway more quickly.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you could send me some more this month<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> without inconveniencing yourselves, I’d like to ask it of you after all.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But if you can’t, there’s no immediate hurry, because I mentioned to my landlord<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> that I might find it hard to manage this month, and it’s all right with him if I pay him when it suits me, because by now he’s known me long enough not to demand absolutely that I pay in advance, at least not a whole month in advance.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards that other suit, I have another objective apart from wearing it myself for as long as possible, for the fact is that when it’s a bit older it will serve me in another way. You see, I’ll gradually need a small collection of work-clothes with which to dress the models for my drawings.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The blue smock of Brabant, for example, the grey linen suit that the miners wear and their leather hat, also a straw hat and clogs, a fisherman’s costume of brown fustian<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> and a sou’wester. And most definitely the clothing made of that kind of black or brown velvet that’s very picturesque and characteristic — furthermore, a red doublet<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> or vest. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Likewise a couple of women’s costumes, such as that of Kempen<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> and the area of Antwerp with the Brabantian cap and that of Blankenberge,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> for example, or Scheveningen or Katwijk.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">However, it’s by no means my plan to buy all of this at once, but most certainly to gather this and that gradually, piece by piece, when the opportunity arises. And because one can obtain these clothes second-hand, it’s not wholly unattainable.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And all of this can get well and truly underway only when I have some kind of studio somewhere permanent.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">This is the only true way to succeed, by drawing from a model with the necessary costumes. Only if I pursue drawing this thoroughly and seriously, always seeking to portray reality, shall I succeed, and then, despite the inevitable expenses, a living can be made out of it. Because a good draughtsman can certainly find work nowadays, and there’s a great demand for such individuals and there are positions to be had that pay very well. So the thing is to try and become as good at it as possible.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In Paris there are many draughtsmen who earn 10 or 15 francs a day, and in London and elsewhere just as much or even more, but one can’t achieve this all at once and I am by no means that far, but it could well come to that if I’m a little blessed and come again into contact with people like <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> and Theo and, more specifically, with good painters and draughtsmen. But only on the condition that a great deal of work and study be done.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It won’t surprise you if I tell you that I’m extraordinarily eager to know what Theo’s proposal could possibly be, or perhaps to hear something from <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs>.</ab>
    <ab rend="indent">Because one way or another I must know anyway sometime in the month of March 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> where I stand and how and where I’ll be able to work during the spring and summer months.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And should I gradually begin to earn some money, that wouldn’t be disagreeable at all, even though the main thing is that I progress and become better at drawing. Then much will fall into place later on, whether it takes a long time or not.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Models are expensive, relatively expensive at any rate, and if I could pay them and use them often I’d be able to work much better. But a studio then becomes indispensable. And people like <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> and Theo and others know this very well. Anyway, I’ll have to wait until they write about one thing and another, and meanwhile do what I can.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Made a drawing of miners in the snow that’s a little better than the one from last winter,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> it has more character and effect.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Am also collecting wood engravings again in the manner of those scrapbooks that Theo and <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> used to have. For if I have that a bit more complete I may well profit by it, for it could very well be that one day I’ll do work for wood engravings.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I want you to know that those clothes I bought are well cut and look better on me than anything else I can remember. I tell you this because you might think they were tawdry or out of the ordinary. This material is worn often, especially in the studios.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now I’ll close, after sending my regards to everyone and after congratulating you on <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>’s birthday,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>At the moment that painter with whom I now take lessons is making a very good painting of a Blankenberge fisherman, among other things.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>It is not known what was wrong with <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs>. He felt better on 8 February, his 59th birthday (FR b2235). </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>From the way Van Gogh said this, it seems he had already mentioned this painter in the correspondence with his parents. <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo about Vincent’s lessons: ‘he wanted to take lessons in perspective from a poor painter for 1 franc 50 per 2-hour lesson. It seems to me he should do that, and I shall write him a letter and tell him so’ (FR b2235, 14 February 1881). <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> suggested that this painter was <rs type="pers" key="1187">Adriaan Johannes Madiol</rs>, who is mentioned in <ref target="let164.xml">letter 164</ref>. See <hi rend="ital">Brieven </hi>1914, p. <hi rend="sc">xxxiv</hi>. It could not have been the other two painters with whom Van Gogh was in touch, <rs type="pers" key="1306">Anthon van Rappard</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1318">Willem Roelofs</rs>, because they were both men of means.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>This drawing is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘was ermee voorzien’, ‘kon het ermee doen’ (was provided for, could get by with).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had heard from Theo that he wanted to help out financially, and thanked him for it: ‘It is really very kind of you to want to pay part of Vincent’s expenses’. He then worked out for Theo that he had sent 95 guilders so far: ‘At the beginning of January [I sent] 40 to him, 22 January 20 guilders, 7 February 35 ... So he’s still got enough to be getting on with, but will be needing more at the beginning of March. Would it be convenient for you to take care of it then or should I do it? Tell me frankly’ (FR b2235, 14 February 1881).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>At this time the ‘employee and shoe shop owner’ <rs type="pers" key="152">Pierre Gustave Moons</rs>, who married <rs type="pers" key="122">Thérèse Kirkels</rs> on 10 September 1881, was living at boulevard du Midi 72. It is not known whether this Moons was also the landlord (<hi rend="ital">SAB</hi>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>A fabric of linen and cotton, used especially in making work clothes.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>A short, tight-fitting jacket (‘doublet’) without tails, with one or two rows of buttons, and made of thick, coarse woollen fabric (‘baize’).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>A region in the north of Belgium.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The coastal town of Blankenberge in the north-west of Belgium.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>These drawings are not known. There is a sketch of the same subject in <ref target="let156.xml">letter 156</ref>, but it dates from August 1880.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>Van Gogh means that, as a draughtsman, he may one day make designs to be used in woodcuts.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>It emerges from <ref target="let164.xml">letter 164</ref> that this was a coarse black velvet (veloutine).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> turned 26 on 17 February.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>