<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Monday, 5 August 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let146"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">146</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">124</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">145</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Etten</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 5 August 1878</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Etten, Monday, 5 August 1878.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Vincent’s preparations for the training college in Brussels <ref target="let145.xml">(145)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Anna van Gogh’s poor health <ref target="let145.xml">(145)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Theo’s stay in Paris <ref target="let144.xml">(144)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b144 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter can be dated to Monday, 5 August; in view of the corresponding details, it must have been enclosed in the surviving letter of this date written by Mr and Mrs van Gogh (FR b988).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0144" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000152_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000152_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000152_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000152_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0144" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000152_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000152_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000152_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000152_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Een woordje sluit ik bij Pa en Moe in.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Ook ik ben er weer zeer verlangend <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>naar dat er weer eens een brief van u komt. Van harte hoop ik dat <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>gij ginder het zoo goed hebt als maar mogelijk is en veel ziet &amp; hoort waar <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>men wat aan heeft. Zooeven komt er een briefkaart van D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Pietersen. <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Omstreeks half Augustus moet ik naar Brussel. Aangezien er echter <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>geen datum is bepaald en Pa en Moe het alzoo beter vinden gelijk <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>ik zelf trouwens ook<c type="kk">/</c> blijf ik nu nog hier tot na Anna’s <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>huwelijk<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> om alsdan zoodra alles is afgeloopen naar ginder te vertrekken. <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Oom Cent was van middag hier, zal U ook naar alle gedachten <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>spoedig eens schrijven. het was een kort maar aardig bezoek<c type="kk">/</c> met Tante <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Cornelie blijft het maar zeer treurig.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
  <ab rend="indent">Gisteren is Pa naar Zundert geweest &amp; Moe ging mede ─ ook Cor &amp; ik een eind <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>tot aan de Sprundelsche heide &amp; wandelden zamen terug. S’middags preekte D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Kam <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>hier voor Pa zoodat Pa &amp; Moe eens wat langer te Zundert konden blijven &amp; niet <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>zoo gehaast waren &amp; in het terugkomen nog eens te Prinsenhage konden aangaan. <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Tegen het etensuur kwamen zij terug, juist toen ik met D<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Kam nog een eind de Leursche <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>weg was opgewandeld. S’avonds was het gezellig<c type="kk">/</c> hebben toen om beurten gelezen <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>onder het theedrinken uit een boek over Paulus dat zeer mooi is. Lezen s’avonds nu &amp; dan <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>ook uit Silas Marner van Eliott, de geschiedenis van een wever.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Heb dezer dagen met Cor zamen die een gedeelte van de schets maakte een <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>teekeningetje gemaakt naar Un Dimanche matin van Emile Breton,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> met pen <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>&amp; inkt &amp; potlood<c type="kp">_</c> Wat is dat toch mooi, dat werk van hem, heeft hij <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>dit jaar iets bijzonders of ziet Gij veel van hem.</ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Schreef gisteren &amp; heden een opstel over de gelijkenis van het mostaardzaadje<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> dat <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>27 bladzijden lang is geworden, mogt er maar wat goeds in zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Morgen ochtend ga ik met Cor uit om groen te halen voor de kamer als zij <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>aanteekenen.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Morgen avond komt Johan. Maar de zuster is nog lang niet <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>zooals men haar gaarne zou zien<c type="kk">/</c> zij ziet nog soms zoo bleek en strak<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>en is nog voortdurend zoo zwak.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ware zij maar een eind verder, maar dat kunnen wij niet krijgen <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>zooals wij het zouden willen maar moeten het nemen zooals het beschikt <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>wordt. Maar, beter is het getrouwd dan geengageerd te zijn gelijk een <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>gewonen dag met dagelijksch werk beter is dan een soort van feestdag<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>is men eenmaal over de brug dan is er een knoop losgemaakt <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>&amp; zijn als het ware alle dingen nieuw geworden<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> maar voor <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>dat het zoover is is ’t een tijd van spanning, ja ik houd het er voor <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>menigmaal van angst<c type="kk">/</c> &amp; die men meestal voor zich zelven moet <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>houden en waarin anderen zoo moeielijk kunne deelen of <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>veel geruststelling kunnen geven.</ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pa en ik wandelen zooals gij denken kunt nogal eens dikwijls zamen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>in de gemeente rond of naar de Hoeve of naar de Leur, en met Cor <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>maak ik menigen togt naar de heide<c type="kk">/</c> hetzij naar de Zundertsche <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>of naar die bij Sprundel.─</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat ik niet weinig verlangend ben om te weten hoe het aldaar <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>te Brussel zijn zal kunt gij begrijpen<c type="kk">/</c> mogt het werk er <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>voorspoedig gaan &amp; ook gezegend worden.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tante Mina<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> is nog hier geweest, en beloofde nog met Oom <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>dezen zomer te zullen terugkomen, mogt dat maar gebeuren want <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>na Anna’s trouwen zal het weer stil worden hier in huis.</ab>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">De velden zijn nu zoo mooi hier<c type="kk">/</c> het koren wordt binnengehaald en <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>de aardappels worden rijp en hun loof begint te verdorren en <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>de boekweit staat heerlijk wit in bloei.─</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Oom Jan is ook nog hier geweest zooals gij meen ik reeds gehoord hebt <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>maar ’t was maar zeer kort.</ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu jongen<c type="kk">/</c> ik zit U bij ’t licht van een lantaarntje te schrijven &amp; de kaars <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>wordt wat heel kort, à dieu, heb het goed, kunt gij schrijf dan <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>eens een woordje met iets over de schilders &amp; als Gij eens iets interessants <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>hoort van den een of ander<c type="kk">/</c> maar liefst toch nog uw eigen indrukken over <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>wat dat dan ook zijn mag. Goeden nacht<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang in gedachten een <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hartelijken handdruk &amp; geloof mij steeds</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="61*" xml:id="l-61s"/>
<ab>Uw liefh.</ab>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-18" n="18">toen &lt; <hi rend="ital">Uncertain.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I’m enclosing a few words with <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs>’s letter.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I, too, am again longing very much for a letter from you to come again. I sincerely hope that you’re doing as well as you possibly can over there and are seeing and hearing much that is of benefit. A postcard just arrived from the <rs type="pers" key="605">Rev. Pieterszen</rs>. I have to go to Brussels around mid-August. As no date was stipulated and Pa and Ma think it better this way — and I too, for that matter — I’ll stay here until after <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>’s wedding<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and then leave for there as soon as everything is over. <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Cent</rs> was here this afternoon, most likely he’ll also be writing to you soon. It was a short but pleasant visit, <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt Cornelie</rs> continues to be miserable.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
  <ab rend="indent">Yesterday <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> went to Zundert and <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs> went along — as <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> and I did for a way, as far as Sprundel Heath and walked back together. In the afternoon the <rs type="pers" key="477">Rev. Kam</rs> preached here for Pa so that Pa and Ma could stay at Zundert a bit longer for once, and weren’t in such a hurry and could also stop at Princenhage on their way home. They returned around dinner-time, just when I’d walked some distance down Leurseweg with the Rev. Kam. The evening was very enjoyable, while drinking tea we took turns reading from a book about Paul which is very beautiful. In the evenings we also occasionally read from Silas Marner by <rs type="pers" key="590">Eliot</rs>, the story of a weaver.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Recently made with <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs>, who made part of the sketch, a little drawing after A Sunday morning by <rs type="pers" key="905">Emile Breton</rs>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> in pen and ink and pencil. How beautiful it is, that work of his; has he made anything special this year, or do you see much of him?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Wrote a theme yesterday and today on the parable of the mustard seed,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> which has become 27 pages long, may there be something good in it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Tomorrow morning I’m going out with <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> to fetch some greenery for the room when they register the banns.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> <rs type="pers" key="413">Joan</rs> is coming tomorrow evening. Our <rs type="pers" key="412">sister</rs>, though, is still far from being as one would like to see her, sometimes she still looks so pale and tense, and is always so weak.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If only she were further along, though we cannot have it as we should like but have to take it as it comes. However, it’s better to be married than engaged, just as an ordinary day with daily work is better than a kind of holiday, once one has crossed the bridge a knot has been untied and all things have been made new,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> as it were, but before things reach that point there’s a time of tension, many times I even take it to be fear, which one usually has to keep to oneself, in which others can hardly share or give reassurance.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As you can imagine, <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> and I quite often take walks together around the parish or to Hoeven or Leur, and <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> and I make many excursions to the heath, either to Zundert Heath or the one near Sprundel.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You can understand that I really long to know how it will be in Brussels, may the work go well and also be blessed.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="317">Aunt Mina</rs>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> was here, and promised to return this summer with <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle</rs>, may that happen, for once <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> is married things will be quiet again here at home.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The fields here are so beautiful now, the wheat is being brought in and the potatoes are ripening and their leaves are beginning to wilt, and the buckwheat has beautiful white blossoms.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="410">Uncle Jan</rs> was also here, as you’ve already heard, I believe, but only very briefly.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now, old boy, I’m writing to you by the light of a lantern and the candle is becoming very short, adieu, I wish you well; if you can, write a few words with something about the painters, and if you hear something interesting about this or that, but better still would be your own impressions of whatever you like. Good-night, accept in thought a hearty handshake, and believe me ever</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Regarding these letters, see <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna van Gogh</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="413">Joan van Houten</rs> were to be married on 22 August 1878.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt Cornelie</rs> at Princenhage, the wife of <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs>, had serious stomach complaints and was undergoing a milk cure (FR b986, b988 and b5342).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
  <ab>It is not known to which book about the apostle Paul Van Gogh refers here. See for <rs type="pers" key="590">Eliot</rs>’s  <rs type="lit" key="66">
                            <hi rend="ital">Silas Marner. The weaver of Raveloe</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let142.xml#n-14">letter 142, n. 14</ref>. </ab>
                </note>
  <note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="905">Emile Adélard Breton</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="1762">
                            <hi rend="ital">Sunday morning in winter</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let061.xml#n-3">see letter 61, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="13" vr="31-35">Matt. 13:31-35</bibleref>; <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Mark" chap="4" vr="31-32">Mark 4:31-32</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="13" vr="18-19">Luke 13:18-19</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>On Wednesday, 7 August, <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="413">Joan van Houten</rs> were to register their banns. Vincent was planning to make decorations of greenery. <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> reported to Theo: ‘Willem the gardener will bring flowers early in the morning to decorate the drawing room, and Vincent already has plans to make hanging nets etc. for them. He is always hard at work here, in the classroom, in which he is now installed.’ <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote more specifically: ‘Vincent thought of a couple of their initials in greenery, with something around them’ (FR b988, 5 August 1878).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘gespannen’ (tense).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rev" chap="21" v="5">Rev. 21:5</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> was not convinced of Vincent’s capabilities. A week later he wrote rather sombrely to Theo: ‘I have no illusions about Vincent – often I even fear that we will be disappointed again. And apart from that, there is much, very much, that is still needed. And however much one wishes to lighten the load, there are always all sorts of consequences that add to the load’ (FR b987, 31 July).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="317">Willemina Carbentus</rs>, J.P. Stricker’s wife.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>