<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Monday, 13 May 1878.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let144"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">144</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">122</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">143</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 13 May 1878</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Amsterdam, Monday, 13 May 1878.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Christoffel Vos’s illness <ref target="let131.xml">(131)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b142 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Amsterdam Mei 1878’. Two circumstances show that the letter was written on Monday, 13 May: Van Gogh cites the funeral of Rev. Pantekoek on Saturday, 11 May (cf. <ref target="#l-52">ll. 52-53</ref>), and mentions Elisabeth’s arrival at home in Etten on Sunday, 12 May, after having failed her examinations (‘yesterday was perhaps a less cheerful Sunday’, <ref target="#l-20">l. 20</ref>; see FR b977 and b978).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0142" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000150_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000150_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000150_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0142" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000150_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000150_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000150_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000150_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000150_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000150_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam Mei 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Het is tijd dat Gij weer eens een woordje van mij ontvangt, reeds schreef Pa dat gij goed <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>zijt aangekomen en reeds hebt geschreven hoe gij de eerste dagen de stad hebt doorkruist<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Niet weinig verlangend ben ik om eens te hooren wat zoo al Uwe indrukken <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>zijn van het een en het ander, en het is daarom dat ik mij aanbeveel voor <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>een woordje zoodra gij er den tijd voor vinden kunt. Wel is het dat de <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>eerste indrukken niet blijven, want wij weten het maar al te goed dat niet alles <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>goud is wat er blinkt, en dat als er een vriendelijke morgenschemering is <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>er middernacht is ook en brandende en drukkende hitte op den middag. Maar even als <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>het morgenuur een gezegend uur is en goud in den mond heeft zoo is het ook <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>met de eerste indrukken en die hebben hunne waarde al gaan zij ook voorbij<c type="kk">/</c> want <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>zij zijn het die later nog wel eens blijken juist te zijn geweest en men komt er <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>op terug<c type="kp">_</c> het eerste wat een kind aantrekt en treft<c type="kk">/</c> dat is het licht en een oud man <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>zoekt daar ook weer angstig naar. Schrijf mij dus eens wat ge zoo al in die eerste <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>dagen hebt gezien en wat alzoo er bij gedacht.</ab>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zult hebben gehoord dat Lies niet door haar examen is, en niet wel is geworden <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>en Moe haar omdat zij zoo naar huis verlangt is komen halen,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> arm meiske<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>het zal geen kleine teleurstelling voor haar zijn en voor allen t’huis en gisteren <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>mogelijk een minder opgewekten Zondag. Toch schreef Pa weder en in <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Zijn mond is dat waarheid<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> dat bij alle teleurstelling en in ieder ernstig oogenblik <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>van het leven het geloof levendiger wordt en krachtiger.</ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is hier mooi weer dezer dagen en naar alle gedachten te Parijs ook wel<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Gij zult wel spoedig gewaar worden dat het ginder s’zomers nog vrij wat <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>warmer soms is dan bij ons en Gij zult de onweersluchten zooals Bonnington <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>ze schilderde<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> ook wel zien. Het is wel een aardige buurt waar gij woont<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>als men hetzij s’morgens of s’avonds die straten daar of ook den kant van Montmartre<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>uit doorkruist dan valt menige werkplaats en menig kamertje in het oog dat doet <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>denken aan “un tonnelier” of Les couturières of andere schilderijen van Ed<c type="kp">_</c> Frère<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> en het <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>doet wel eens goed om zulke dingen te zien die eenvoudig zijn<c type="kk">/</c> als men soms heel 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wat ziet van menschen die om verschillende redenen een heel eind van <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>al wat natuurlijk is zijn afgedwaald en hun eigentlijk en inwendig leven <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>erbij verspeeld hebben<c type="kk">/</c> en ook veel <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>die in de ellende en in wat afschuwelijk is zijn geworteld, want <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>s’avonds en s’nachts ziet men er allerlei van die donkere figuren zoowel van <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>mannen als van vrouwen rondwaren waarin als het ware de schrik des <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>nachts<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> verpersoonlijkt is en wier ellende men moet rangschikken <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>onder de dingen die geen naam hebben in eenige taal.</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het gaat niet goed bij Vos<c type="kk">/</c> hij heeft weer meer dan eens bloed opgegeven<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>was er laatst op een middag toen hij op was en hand in hand met Kee<c type="kk">/</c> en zij beiden <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>in het zwart en hunne gezigten al even bleek uit het raam zaten te kijken <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>naar de Kerk<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> en de boomen aan den overkant<c type="kk">/</c> toen er een donkere <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>onweerslucht hing en de blaren en het stof zoo eigenaardig dwarrelden <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>en de straatsteenen zoo veel witter dan gewoonlijk schenen en de zwarte figuurtjes <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>van de menschen zoo veel scherper daar tegen uit kwamen, zooals voor <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>een onweer dat dikwijls het geval is. Hij is nog zooveel bleeker en <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>magerder geworden dan toen Gij hem zaagt en ziet er soms als een geest uit<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>Het is er een waar klaaghuis<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> geworden en bij Oom Stricker eigentlijk ook <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>omdat als een lid lijdt dan lijden al de leden mede<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> omdat zij er <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>eene plante mede zijn.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">Verl. week is een van de predikanten hier gestorven die door het heele <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>land zeer bekend was (Pantekoek)<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> Zaturdag was de begrafenis<c type="kk">/</c> het was <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>iets dat deed denken aan “In memoriam”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> die togt langs dat pad aan de groene kanten <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>van den Amstel, hij was vader van 6 kinderen<c type="kk">/</c> de oudste een jaar of 20.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> Een <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>zeer groote menigte volgde en men verdrong elkaar letterlijk<c type="kp">_</c> Er werd <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>gisteren in bijna alle kerken naar aanleiding hiervan gepreekt, hoorde Oom Stricker <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>onder anderen die hem van zeer nabij had gekend. Het was diens beurt <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>om in de Oude zijds Kapel te preeken<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> waar de weesjongens en <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>die van de kweekschool voor de zeevaart gewoonlijk gaan.<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-o-17"/> Er was <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>veel stemming in<c type="kk">/</c> sprak o.a<c type="kp">_</c> over het woord<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben ontroerd en wat zal ik <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>zeggen.<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-o-18"/> Het is een vreesselijk en langdurig lijden geweest dat zijn deel is geweest. Hoorde nog op een avond een zijner laatste <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>preeken en het was toen reeds duidelijk blijkbaar aan hetgeen hij zeide<c type="kk">/</c> dat Hij huiverde en <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>terugdeinsde voor iederen nieuwen dag en nacht en wel bepaaldelijk voor <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>een die volgde op de inspanning van het preeken<c type="kp">_</c> Toen reeds kon men hem <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>niet hooren zonder met hem mede te voelen als het ware en onwillekeurig <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>sidderde men want het is een donkeren weg<c type="kk">/</c> dien naar het eeuwig huis,<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-o-19"/> <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>en gelukkig is hij die<c type="kk">/</c> als die duisternis en nacht voor hem nadert<c type="kk">/</c> door de hoop op <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>een beter leven en op de opstanding zooals wij weten dat die is geschied met Maria Magdalena en <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Hem Dien zij voor den Hovenier aanzag in den hof bij het graf<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="20" xml:id="note-o-20"/> ook dan nog gesterkt wordt door <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>de hoop: wie weet wat morgen geschieden zal.<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-o-21"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zag gisteren Zijn zoon in de vroegkerk<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="22" xml:id="note-o-22"/> als men de aangezigten van <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>de menschen bij andere aangezigten vergelijken kan dan heeft het zijne <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>veel van een arend<c type="kk">/</c> vooral zoo als hij toen was getroffen door het pas gebeurde.</ab>
                <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij moet toch eens zien om nog het een of ander mooi boek te lezen ginder<c type="kk">/</c> van Michelet <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>b.v. over de omwenteling<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-o-23"/> of ook iets van Thoré of Th<c type="kp">_</c> Gauthier over Parijs en den tijd der <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>jonge schilders en schrijvers,<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-o-24"/> o Jongen wat zou ik graag eens met U <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>door de stad kruisen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoop vandaag eens een groote wandeling te maken door eene buurt waar ik <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>nog niet dikwijls geweest ben. Het huis in de Breestraat waar Rembrandt gewoond heeft heb ik nog <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>gevonden<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="25" xml:id="note-o-25"/> Gij weet wij er over spraken toen Gij hier waart.<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-o-26"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Denk om dat bewuste Sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> op de Luxembourg<c type="kk">/</c> Qui vous reçoit<c type="kk">/</c> me reçoit &amp; qui <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>me reçoit<c type="kk">/</c> reçoit Celui Qui m’a envoyé<c type="kk">/</c> en schrijf eens van wie het is.<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-o-27"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het kan in den herfst zoo prachtig mooi zijn te Parijs<c type="kk">/</c> nu daar ziet Gij in ’t eind van <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>September ook reeds iets van.</ab>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab rend="indent">Groet allen bij Soek hartelijk voor mij, ik denk nog zoo dikwijls aan een <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>togt die ik met zijne familie naar Ville d’Avray heb gemaakt. In het kerkje <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>daar gaande trof het mij dat daar ik geloof zelfs meer dan een schilderij <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>van Corot hing<c type="kp">_</c> Gij weet dat hij daar veel was<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="28" xml:id="note-o-28"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zeg ook Braat<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-o-29"/> en Mutters<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-o-30"/> goeden dag. Heb het goed en schrijf eens <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>spoedig en ontvang in gedachten een hartelijken handdruk en <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>geloof mij steeds</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
<ab>Uw zoo liefh<c type="kp">_</c> broer</ab>
                <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab>Nog moet ik U bedanken voor Uw portret,<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-o-31"/> daar ben ik zeer blij mede <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>en het is zeer goed uitgevallen. Dank er voor.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-68" n="68">een beter &lt; eene beter</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Amsterdam, May 1878</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>It’s time you received a few words from me, <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> already wrote that you’ve arrived safely and have already written how you roamed around the city the first few days.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I’m really longing to hear what your impressions are of this and that, and that’s why I urge you to write a few words as soon as you can find the time. It’s true, though, that first impressions don’t last, for we know all too well that all that glitters is not gold, and that when there is a friendly dawn there is a midnight too, and scorching and oppressive heat in the afternoon. But just as the morning hour is a blessed hour and the early bird catches the worm, so it is with first impressions, and they have their value even though they pass, for it is they which later appear to have been correct, and one comes back to them. The first thing that attracts and strikes a child is the light, and an old man also searches again fearfully for it. So write and tell me what you saw during those first few days, and what you thought.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll have heard that <rs type="pers" key="401">Lies</rs> didn’t pass her exam and has fallen ill, and that because she longed so much for home, <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs> went to fetch her,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> poor girl, it will be no small disappointment for her and for everyone at home, and yesterday was perhaps a less cheerful Sunday. <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> nevertheless wrote again, and in his mouth that is the truth,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> that with all disappointment and at every serious moment of life, faith becomes more alive and stronger.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The weather has been beautiful here the last few days, and probably in Paris too. You’ll soon notice that in the summer it’s at times rather warmer there than it is here, and you’ll probably see stormy skies like those <rs type="pers" key="881">Bonington</rs> painted.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> It’s really a nice neighbourhood where you live.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> If one roams the streets there, whether in the morning or evening, or walks in the direction of Montmartre,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> one is struck by many workshops and many rooms that recall ‘a cooper’ or The seamstresses or other paintings by <rs type="pers" key="1023">E. Frère</rs>,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> and it does one good sometimes to see such things, which are simple, as one occasionally 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> sees a good many people who for various reasons have strayed a long way from everything that is natural, thereby throwing away their true and inner lives, and also many who are rooted in misery and loathsome things, because in the evening and at night one sees all manner of those dark figures walking about, both men and women, who personify, as it were, the terror of the night,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> and whose misery must be classified among the things that have no name in any language.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs> isn’t well, he has coughed up blood again more than once. Was there recently one afternoon when he was up, sitting hand in hand with <rs type="pers" key="776">Kee</rs>, both of them dressed in black and their faces equally pale, looking out of the window at the Church<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> and the trees across the street, when there was a dark stormy sky and the leaves and the dust were whirling around in a strange way and the paving-stones looked so much whiter than usual, and the little black figures of the people stood out against them so much more sharply, as is often the case before a thunderstorm. He has become so much paler and thinner than when you saw him, and sometimes looks like a ghost. It has become a veritable house of mourning,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle Stricker</rs>’s too, in fact, for when one member suffers, all the members suffer with it,<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> for they have been planted together.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Last week one of the ministers here died who was very well known throughout the country (<rs type="pers" key="555">Pantekoek</rs>).<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> The funeral was on Saturday, it was something that reminded one of ‘In memoriam’,<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> that procession along the path by the green borders of the Amstel. He was the father of 6 children, the eldest around 20.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> A very large crowd followed, literally jostling one another. Yesterday there were sermons occasioned by the event in nearly every church. Heard <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle Stricker</rs>, among others, who had been a close acquaintance of his. It was his turn to preach in the Oudezijdskapel,<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> where the boys from the orphanage and those from the nautical college<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> usually go. There was a lot of spirit in it, spoke, among other things, of the words: Now is my soul troubled; and what shall I say?<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> It was a long and terrible suffering that was his lot. Heard one of his last sermons one evening, and even then it was clearly evident from what he said that he trembled at and recoiled from each new day and night, and especially from one that followed upon the effort of preaching. Even then one couldn’t hear him without feeling for him, as it were, and one couldn’t help shuddering, for it is a dark path, the one to his long home,<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> and happy is he who, when that darkness and night are approaching, is strengthened even then by the hope for a better life and the resurrection as we know befell Mary Magdalen and Him Whom she supposed to be the gardener in the garden by the sepulchre,<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> by the hope: who knows what shall be on the morrow?<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Saw his son yesterday at the early service,<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> if one can compare the faces of people with other faces, then his looks very much like an eagle, especially then, when he was stricken by what had just happened.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You must try to read some beautiful book or other over there, by <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>, for instance, on the Revolution<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/> or something by <rs type="pers" key="554">Thoré</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="607">T. Gautier</rs> on Paris and the time of the young painters and writers.<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-t-24"/> Oh, old boy, how I’d like to roam through the city with you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Hope to take a long walk today through a neighbourhood I haven’t seen much of yet. I found the house in Breestraat where <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> lived.<anchor n="25" xml:id="note-t-25"/> We talked about it, you know, when you were here.<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-t-26"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Don’t forget about that painting in the Luxembourg, He that receiveth you receiveth me, and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me, and write and tell me who made it.<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-t-27"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It can be so glorious in Paris in the autumn, well, you’ll be seeing something of it at the end of September.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Give my warm regards to everyone at the <rs type="pers" key="758">Soeks</rs>’, I still think so often of an excursion I made with his family to Ville-d’Avray. Going into the church there, it struck me that there was, I believe, even more than one painting by <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs> hanging there. You know that he spent a lot of time there.<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-t-28"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Bid good-day to <rs type="pers" key="305">Braat</rs>,<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-t-29"/> and <rs type="pers" key="541">Mutters</rs>
                    <anchor n="30" xml:id="note-t-30"/> too. I wish you well, and write soon, and accept in thought a hearty handshake, and believe me ever</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your most loving brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I still have to thank you for your portrait,<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-t-31"/> I’m very glad to have it, it turned out very well. Thanks for sending it.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Theo travelled to Paris on 1 May – he turned 21 that day – where he was to assist at Goupil &amp; Cie’s stand at the World Exhibition, which opened on 1 May and lasted for six months.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Around 8 May, <rs type="pers" key="401">Lies</rs> spent two days sitting her exams in English and French, but she was ill and did not pass them (FR b977).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Kings" chap="17" v="24">1 Kings 17:24</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The landscapes and townscapes painted by <rs type="pers" key="881">Richard Parkes Bonington</rs> often contain large, conspicuous clouds, such as seen in <rs type="ill" key="1674">
                            <hi rend="ital">A road</hi>
                        </rs>. <ref target="let037.xml#n-11">See letter 37, n. 11.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Upon his arrival in Paris, Theo took up residence at 46 rue de la Tour d’Auvergne, south of boulevard de Clichy, in the 9th arrondissement (FR b978).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>District in the northern part of Paris.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
  <ab>For <hi rend="ital">A cooper</hi> and <rs type="ill" key="1685">
                            <hi rend="ital">The seamstress</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="1023">Frère</rs>, <ref target="let037.xml#n-21">see letter 37, nn. 21</ref> and <ref target="let037.xml#n-20">20.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Ps" chap="91" v="5">Ps. 91:5</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Song of Sol" chap="3" v="8">Song of Sol. 3:8</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The Westerkerk.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Eccl" chap="7" vr="2-4">Eccl. 7:2-4</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="1 Cor" chap="12" v="26">1 Cor. 12:26</bibleref>. <rs type="pers" key="806">Vos</rs> was <rs type="pers" key="318">Uncle Stricker</rs>’s son-in-law.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Rom" chap="6" v="5">Rom. 6:5</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>The <rs type="pers" key="555">Rev. Frederik Carel Antonius Pantekoek</rs> died on 6 May. He was buried amid great public interest on 11 May in Zorgvlied cemetery on the River Amstel; several newspapers covered the event.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
  <ab>It is not certain which work Van Gogh is referring to here, though he assumes that Theo understands what he is talking about. It is possible that he was thinking of the well-known <rs type="lit" key="187">
                            <hi rend="ital">In memoriam</hi>
                        </rs> (1849) by <rs type="pers" key="215">Alfred Tennyson</rs>, or the poem ‘<rs type="lit" key="188">In memoriam</rs>’ by <rs type="pers" key="615">P.A. de Génestet</rs>. Cf. De Génestet<hi rend="ital"> </hi>1869, vol. 2, pp. 274-280.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="555">Pantekoek</rs> had five sons and one daughter. The eldest was Johan Marius Jacob, born on 8 July 1857.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>On Sunday, 12 May 1878, <rs type="pers" key="318">Stricker</rs> conducted the 10 a.m. service in the Oudezijdskapel.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="17" xml:id="n-17" target="#note-t-17">
<ab>The orphans were housed in the Burgerweeshuis (Civic Orphanage), located in Kalverstraat and Sint-Luciënsteeg (now the Amsterdam Museum). The ‘Kweekschool voor de zeevaart’ (Nautical College) was housed in the former Stadswerkhuis (City Workhouse) on the Buitenkant (now Gelderse Kade; on 4 May 1878, King Willem <hi rend="sc">iii</hi> laid the first stone of the new, imposing accommodations at Prins Hendrikkade 189-190).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="18" xml:id="n-18" target="#note-t-18">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="12" v="27">John 12:27</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="19" xml:id="n-19" target="#note-t-19">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Eccl" chap="12" v="5">Eccl. 12:5</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="20" xml:id="n-20" target="#note-t-20">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="John" chap="20" vr="11-18">John 20:11-18</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="21" xml:id="n-21" target="#note-t-21">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Jas" chap="4" v="14">Jas. 4:14</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="22" xml:id="n-22" target="#note-t-22">
<ab>On Sunday, 12 May, early services were conducted at 7 a.m. by the <rs type="pers" key="1708">Rev. H. Steenberg</rs> in the Noorderkerk and by <rs type="pers" key="206">L. Steinfort</rs> in the Zuiderkerk.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="23" xml:id="n-23" target="#note-t-23">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="707">Jules Michelet</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="162">
                            <hi rend="ital">Histoire de la Révolution Française</hi>
                        </rs> (1847-1853).</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="24" xml:id="n-24" target="#note-t-24">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="607">Théophile Gautier</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="189">
                            <hi rend="ital">Portraits contemporains. Littératures, peintres, sculpteurs, artistes dramatiques</hi>
                        </rs> (1874). Van Gogh did not specify which Salon reports and art reviews by <rs type="pers" key="554">E.J.T. Thoré</rs> he had in mind; he had previously sent Theo <rs type="lit" key="14">
                            <hi rend="ital">Musées de la Hollande, <hi rend="sc">ii</hi>. Musée Van der Hoop, à Amsterdam et Musée de Rotterdam</hi>
                        </rs>. Paris 1860; <ref target="let111.xml">see letter 111</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
  <note n="25" xml:id="n-25" target="#note-t-25">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs> lived from 1639 to 1658 in the house at Jodenbreestraat 6, now known as the Rembrandthuis.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="26" xml:id="n-26" target="#note-t-26">
<ab>For Theo’s visits to Vincent, <ref target="let143.xml">see letter 143</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="27" xml:id="n-27" target="#note-t-27">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="975">Jules Joseph Dauban</rs>,<rs type="ill" key="1761"> <hi rend="ital">Réception d’un etranger chez les Trappistes</hi>
                        </rs>; <ref target="let035.xml">see letters 35</ref> and <ref target="let055.xml">55</ref>; the reference is to <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="10" v="40">Matt. 10:40</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="28" xml:id="n-28" target="#note-t-28">
<ab>Regarding this trip, <ref target="let040.xml">see letter 40</ref>. On 4 March 1817, <rs type="pers" key="48">Corot’s parents</rs> bought a house in Ville-d’Avray. From 1822 onwards, this village and its environs became <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs>’s favourite places, and he returned there every year to study. See exhib. cat. Paris 1996,<hi rend="ital"> </hi>p. 16.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="29" xml:id="n-29" target="#note-t-29">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="305">Frans Braat</rs>, an employee of Goupil &amp; Cie, and Theo’s roommate (FR b995).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="30" xml:id="n-30" target="#note-t-30">
<ab>This <rs type="pers" key="541">Mutters</rs> has not been identified.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="31" xml:id="n-31" target="#note-t-31">
<ab>This probably refers to one of the portrait photographs made of Theo by a photographer (Lavieter &amp; Co.) in The Hague (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b4793). <rs type="ill" key="1879">Ill. 1879</rs>. There was also an <hi rend="ital">en face</hi> version of this photograph.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>