<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 21 January 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let201"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">201</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">171</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">200</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 21 January 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:physDesc>
                        <vg:decoration>
                            <vg:decoList xml:id="sketches">
                                <vg:decoItem n="A" xml:id="sketch-1">
                                    <vg:decoDesc>
<p>
      <hi rend="ital">Scheveningen woman sewing</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="42">F - / JH 96</rs>), letter sketch</p>
                                    </vg:decoDesc>
                                </vg:decoItem>
                            </vg:decoList>
                        </vg:decoration>
                    </vg:physDesc>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 21 January 1882.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. nos. b192 a-b V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh writes that ‘the week is over’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref> and ‘the coming week... starts tomorrow’ <ref target="#l-87">(l. 87)</ref>. Because he writes in <ref target="let202.xml">letter 202</ref> that he consulted Mauve, and also says that he wrote the present letter ‘yesterday’, this letter must date from Saturday, 21 January 1882. (The <hi rend="ital">working</hi> week ended on Saturday.)</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0192 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000218_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000218_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000218_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000218_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000218_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0192 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000218_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000218_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000218_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000218_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000218_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000218_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0192 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000219_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000219_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000219_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000219_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0192 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000219_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000219_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000219_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000219_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Nu de week om is schrijf ik U maar weer eens. <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Ik heb geregeld iederen dag model gehad van <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>s’morgens tot s’avonds en het model is goed. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Mauve is eens komen kijken &amp; de Heer Tersteeg ook <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>en daar ben ik blij om.</ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu heb ik al dien tijd enkel met waterverf gewerkt <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>en ik krijg daar hoe langer hoe meer pleizier <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>in.</ab>
                <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat zou ik graag hebben dat gij eens hier <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>waart<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou U zooveel te zeggen &amp; te vragen <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>hebben. Zoudt gij in ’t voorjaar weer <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>komen? Weet gij het niet wat vooruit.–</ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu is ’tgeen ik heb gemaakt nog niet goed <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>&amp; nog lang niet maar het is weer iets anders <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>en het is wat sterker en frisscher van kleur &amp; zonder <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>dekverf.</ab>
                <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu hoop ik dat gij mij spoedig weer eens <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>schrijft &amp; wel bepaaldelijk dat wij probeeren <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>een afspraak te maken omtrent het geld.</ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Want ofschoon ik met frs. 100 per maand voor me <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zelf wel zou kunnen rond komen<c type="kk">/</c> het is een heel <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>andere kwestie wanneer ik bovendien dagelijks <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>mijn model moet betalen en moet te eten geven <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>&amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> &amp;c. En dan de onkosten van verf<c type="kk">/</c> van <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>papier &amp;c. Ik heb het U reeds in mijn <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>vorig schrijven gezegd dat het daarvan af hangt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>of ik full speed of half speed werken kan. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>En nu ik hier eenmaal zit komen er toch <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>iederen dag allerlei kleine onkosten opdokken <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>die mij het leven niet makkelijk maken.</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb evenwel geregeld doorgezet nu <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>een tijd lang maar ik zit zonder geld <lb n="33a" xml:id="l-33a"/>nu.</ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is natuurlijk dat wanneer men zich ergens <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>installeert er op allerlei wijs kosten zijn. <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Maar wat ik er mee win is dat ik <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>gevoel dat ik vooruitga en ik zal het <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>aquarelleeren overwinnen en zelfs zoo heel <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>lang hoeft het niet te duren of mijn werk <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>is verkoopbaar.</ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">De Heer Tersteeg zelf zei daaromtrent <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>iets en als ik op kleiner formaat eens <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>gelukkig ben dan zal hij denk ik wel <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>iets nemen. En die teekening van dat oud <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>vrouwtje waarvan ik U een schets zond heb ik afgemaakt nog verder<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> en <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>den een of anderen dag gaat die wel weg.</ab>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">Geloof mij<c type="kk">/</c> ik werk, ik tob, ik blok den <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>heelen dag en met pleizier ook maar <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>nu is het er ook zoo mee dat ik erg gedecoura<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>geerd zou worden als ik niet net zoo hard <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>en nog harder kon doorwerken.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als gij er den Heer Tersteeg over schrijft <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>dan zal hij U graag crediet geven tot een <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>bedrag dat gij zelf stellen kunt en hij zelf <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>kan controleeren als hij wil waar ik het voor <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>gebruik als hij of gij mij niet <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>vertrouwt. Doch ik zou het verschrikkelijk <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>vinden als ik niet kon voortwerken op de zelfde <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wijs als nu een week of drie. Wat betreft het <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>formaat van teekeningen of de sujetten<c type="kk">/</c> graag wil <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>ik dienaangaande letten op t’geen de Hr T<c type="kp">_</c> of <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>Mauve zeggen. Ik heb nu dezen tijd eenige <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>groote onder handen genomen, omdat ik <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>coute que coute die drooge manier <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>waarop mijn studies van dezen zomer gedaan <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>zijn moet overwinnen. En nu zei Mauve <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>toch gisteren avond ofschoon hij natuurlijk <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>aanmerkingen had ook, “het begint een <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>aquarel te worden”<c type="kp">_</c> Nu als ik dat er maar <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>mee win dan reken ik dat ik noch tijd noch <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>geld verkwist. En nu ik op grooter formaat <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>eens beproefd heb de penseelsbehandeling &amp; de <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>kracht der kleuren eens te probeeren kan ik mij <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>weer eens aan kleinere wagen. Trouwens ik <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>heb er reeds twee kleine op touw maar omdat ik <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>daarmee sukkelde en ze gedeeltelijk weer heb <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>uitgesponsd<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik een heele groote onder <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>handen genomen. Waarvan ik U een schetsje stuur.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het verwondert me een beetje dat gij mij nog niet <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>weer eens geschreven hebt want gij hebt mij nog maar <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>eens geschreven sedert ik hier ben en dat nog maar <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>terloops.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab>En toch is het erg noodig dat gij mij eens spoedig schrijft. Mauve <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>is weer pas<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> hier geweest &amp; ik bij hem ook<c type="kk">/</c> hij heeft mij weer een &amp; ander gezegd. <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>En de Hr. Tersteeg is er ook geweest en heeft gesproken van dat ik eens een paar <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>teekeningen in kleiner formaat zou beginnen. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> dus ik heb voor de <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>volgende week die morgen begint werk genoeg maar ik vrees geen geld <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>genoeg want al wat ik over heb is f<c type="kp">_</c> 2.50 en nog een paar centen. <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>Wat moet ik nu doen<c type="kp">_</c> als ik naar Mauve ga of naar den Heer <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>Tersteeg en hun vroeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof zij het niet weigeren zouden. <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>Doch Mauve heeft reeds zooveel gedaan en aan den Heer Tersteeg <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>verkoop ik liever een paar kleine teekeningen als ze mij lukken <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>mogten dan dat ik hem geld te leen vraag. Althans tot <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>zoolang er geen bepaalde afspraak is omtrent hetgeen <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>waaraan ik mij te houden heb. Antwoord mij dus <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>spoedig en als gij wilt doe het een of het ander<c type="kk">/</c> stuur <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>mij wat om door te gaan of schrijf het een of ander aan <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>den Heer Tersteeg.– Ik voel Theo<c type="kk">/</c> dat er een werkkracht in 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>
                    <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>mij zit en ik doe wat ik kan om die los en vrij te <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>maken. Ik heb zorg genoeg met het tobben en scharrelen <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>met mijn teekeningen en als er al te erge zorgen bij <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>kwamen en ik de modellen niet aan kon houden dan <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>zou ik in de war raken<c type="kp">_</c> Het is wel erg dat gij er voor <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>op moet dokken doch we staan nu niet meer zoo alleen als <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>b.v. verl. winter. Nu voel ik mij op een beteren weg om <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>tot een resultaat te komen. Ik zal doen wat ik kan<c type="kk">/</c> ik zal hard <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>werken en zoodra ik ’t penseel wat in mijn magt heb nog veel <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>harder dan ik nu kan. En als wij nu flink en energiek doorzetten <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>dan is de tijd niet ver af dat gij mij niet meer hoeft te zenden. <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>Nu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> blijf gij doen wat ge kunt en ik zal ook doen <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>wat ik kan.– à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> ik reken er op dat ge spoedig schrijft<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>ge hoeft ook niet veel op eens te sturen als ik maar van week op <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>week kan doorgaan. Ontvang een handdruk in gedachten, </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Now that the week is over I’m writing to you again. I’ve had a model every day on a regular basis, from morning to evening, and the model is good. <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> came to have a look, and <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> too, and I’m glad about that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve been working all this time with watercolour only, and it’s giving me more pleasure every day.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How much I’d like you to be here, I’d have so much to tell and to ask you. Will you come again in the spring? Won’t you know a little in advance?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now, what I’ve made still isn’t good and is far from being so, but it’s again something different and it’s somewhat stronger and livelier in colour, and without body-colour.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now I hope that you’ll write to me again soon, and that we’ll definitely try to reach an agreement about the money.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Because although I’d be able to get by on 100 francs a month on my own, it’s a very different matter when I also have to pay and feed my model every day &amp;c. &amp;c. And then the cost of paint, paper &amp;c. I already told you in my last letter that this is what determines whether I can work at full speed or half speed. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And now that I’m here, all kinds of little expenses crop up every day, and they don’t make life any easier.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, for a while I carried on steadily nevertheless, but now I have no money.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s natural that when one sets up house somewhere there are all kinds of expenses. But what I win by it is that I feel I’m progressing, and I’ll master the art of watercolour, and it needn’t even take very long before my work is saleable.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> himself said something about it, and when I succeed in a small format then I think he’ll buy something. And I’ve worked more on that drawing of that little old woman I sent you a sketch of,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and one day it will be sold.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Believe me, I work, I struggle, I swot the whole day, and with pleasure, too, but as it is now I’d also become very discouraged if I couldn’t go on working just as hard or even harder. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you write to <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> about it, he’ll gladly give you credit for an amount you set yourself, and if he wants to he can check and see what I spend it on if he or you don’t trust me. But it would be terrible not to go on working as I have been the last three weeks or so. With regard to the size of the drawings or the subjects, I’ll gladly listen to what Mr T. or <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> has to say about it. I’ve been working on several large ones recently, because no matter what, I must get over that dry manner in which my studies of this summer were done. And Mauve actually said yesterday evening, although he naturally had some criticism as well, ‘it’s beginning to look like a watercolour’. Well, if I gain that much, then I reckon I’m squandering neither time nor money. And now that I’ve tried out the handling of the brush and the power of colours in a larger format, I can attempt smaller ones again. As a matter of fact, I have two small ones started, but because I was wrestling with them and sponged part of them out, I started on a really large one. Of which I’m sending you a sketch.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It surprises me a little that you haven’t written to me again, because you’ve written to me only once since I’ve been here, and then only briefly.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab>
                    <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab>And yet it’s very necessary that you write to me soon. <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> was just<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> here again and I at his place too, he again had this and that to tell me. And <rs type="pers" key="787">Mr Tersteeg</rs> was also here and talked about my starting a couple of drawings in a smaller format. Well, so for the coming week, which starts tomorrow, I have work enough but not money enough, I fear, because all I have left is 2.50 guilders and a couple of cents. What should I do now? If I were to go to Mauve or Mr Tersteeg and ask them, I don’t think they’d refuse me. But Mauve has done so much already, and I’d rather sell Mr Tersteeg a couple of small drawings, if they succeed, than ask him to lend me money. At least as long as there’s no definite agreement as to where I stand. So answer me soon and, if you will, do either one or the other: send me something to keep me going or write about it to Mr Tersteeg. Theo, I feel an energy in 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> me and I’m doing what I can to release it and set it free. I have trouble enough struggling and wrestling with my drawings, and if this were compounded by dreadful worries and I couldn’t keep the models, then I wouldn’t know what to do. It’s awful that you have to pay for it all, but we aren’t as alone as we were last winter, for example. I now feel that I’m on a better path to get results. I’ll do what I can, I’ll work hard and, as soon as I’ve mastered the brush, even harder than I’m now able to. And if we press on with vigour and energy, it won’t be long before you no longer have to send me anything. Well, old chap, keep on doing what you can and I’ll also do what I can. Adieu, I’m counting on your writing soon, you don’t have to send a lot all at once, if only I can go on from week to week. Accept a handshake in thought,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
      <ab>This watercolour of a woman knitting is not known. Cf. the letter sketch in <ref target="let200.xml">letter 200</ref>, as well as <ref target="let200.xml#n-3">n. 3</ref> to that letter.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The letter sketch at the end of the letter is <hi rend="ital">Scheveningen woman sewing</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="42">F - / JH 96</rs>), which was based on a large watercolour, <hi rend="ital">Scheveningen woman</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="3013">F 946v / JH 95</rs>), only a part of which survives. Van Gogh later painted the watercolour <hi rend="ital">Bleaching ground</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2379">F 946 / JH 158</rs>) on the back of that incomplete work.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Only one letter Theo wrote to Vincent in this period has survived (<ref target="let197.xml">letter 197</ref> of 5 January), but it would have been strange for Vincent to think it ‘brief’. Vincent’s requests for letters from Theo generally had an ulterior motive, i.e. the hope that he would send money along with the letter.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Van Gogh says in <ref target="let202.xml">letter 202</ref> of Sunday that he and <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> spoke ‘yesterday’, which must therefore have been Saturday.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>