<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 29 October 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let277"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">277</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">239</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">276</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 29 October 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 29 October 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Theo’s visit early in August <ref target="let253.xml">(253)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b261 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh writes ‘It’s Sunday again’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>. In <ref target="let274.xml">letter 274</ref> of 22 October 1882 he remarked, ‘I have the stove in place already’, and he now says, ‘Believe me, I’m glad that the stove is in place’, so this letter must date from after that Sunday. Then the remark that ‘this week’ there was a storm <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref> relates to the storm of 24 October (<hi rend="ital">KNMI</hi>). This means that the letter was written on Sunday, 29 October 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0261" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000319_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000319_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000319_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000319_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000319_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0261" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000319_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000319_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000319_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000319_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000319_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000319_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>’t Is weer Zondag &amp; weer even regenachtig als gewoonlijk. Wij <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>hebben bovendien deze week storm gehad en de blaren worden <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>dun aan de boomen. Ik verzeker U ik blij ben dat de kagchel <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>staat.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toen ik dezen morgen er eens toe kwam om mijn <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>teekeningen te rangschikken<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. de studies naar ’t model <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>van zoowat sedert uw bezoek (niet meegerekend de <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>oudere studies en ook niet wat ik in mijn schetsboek teeken)<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>toen vond ik er ongeveer een honderdtal. <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Ik noem eens een cijfer omdat ik me herinner <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>ge bij gelegenheid van Uw bezoek mij vroegt of ik <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>nog andere studies had dan die teekeningen die ge toen <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>zaagt. Ik weet niet of alle schilders<c type="kk">/</c> ook <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>zelfs die die zeer uit de hoogte op mijn werk neerzien <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>dermate dat ze ’t beneden zich achten er zelfs ook <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>maar de minste notitie van te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> meer werken <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>dan ik. Ook weet ik niet of zij een beteren <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>weg kennen dan te werken met model ofschoon <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>ze zulks m.i<c type="kp">_</c> wel wat weinig doen<c type="kk">/</c> zooals ik U wel meer <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>schreef dat ik ’t niet begrijpen kon ze niet meer model <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>namen. (Ik bedoel natuurlijk <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> lui als Mauve of <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>Israels ofschoon de laatste het m.i<c type="kp">_</c> prachtige voorbeeld geeft <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>om steeds met model te werken<c type="kk">/</c> maar meer <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>heeren als b.v. Bock &amp; Breitner.) Laatstgenoemde heb ik sedert <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>ik hem in ’t gasthuis bezocht tijdens zijn ziekte<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> volstrekt niet gezien – ik hoorde toevalligerwijs <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>er iets van dat hij leeraar aan een burgerschool<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> was geworden – ik <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>heb van hem zelf echter taal noch teeken vernomen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Deze week ontving ik een brief van Rappard<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> die zich <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>ook verwondert over de manier van doen van veel schilders <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>hier<c type="kk">/</c> en onder anderen ondervond een sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> van hem geweigerd <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>werd op Arti.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> Ik zeg maar dit<c type="kk">/</c> als zulken als <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>hij en ik voor niets geteld worden<c type="kk">/</c> is dit billijk? <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>Want ik verzeker U dat hij terdeeg werkt<c type="kk">/</c> hij was in Drenthe <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>dezen zomer en daarna heeft hij een heelen tijd gewerkt <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>in het gasthuis voor blinden te Utrecht.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik vond het wel curieus van hem eenige ervaringen te hooren <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>die zoo ten naasten bij al precies ’t zelfde zijn als de mijnen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>Enfin.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik kan zoo als ik U reeds schreef dikwijls naar U verlangen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>als ik U meer zag en we over ’t werk meer bespreken <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>konden zou ik nog tot het maken van verscheidene <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>dingen komen<c type="kk">/</c> die uit de studies die ik heb te maken <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>zouden zijn, dat geloof ik vast.</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toch – ge herinnert U dat niet lang geleden <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>ik U nog schreef (ik stuurde U toen een klein krabbeltje <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>van een aardappelmarkt): “ik moet toch weer eens <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>probeeren dat gescharrel op straat aan te pakken”<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>Daarvan zijn nu toch een stuk of 12 aquarellen het <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>gevolg<c type="kk">/</c> die ik op ’t oogenblik onder handen heb.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Zoodat <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>ik met ’t bovenstaande <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> zeggen wil dat ik niets <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>met mijn studies kan uitrigten of ze zonder doel <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>maak maar alleen dat ik geloof ik er <hi rend="ital">meer</hi> <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>mee zou kunnen uitrigten en <hi rend="ital">meer</hi> direkt doeltreffend <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>maken als ik eens meer met U overleggen kon. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>Maar wat hier ook van zij<c type="kk">/</c> ik werk toch met <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>veel pleizier dezer dagen en ik heb wel hoop er dingen <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>bij zullen zijn waar ge ook pleizier in hebben zult, <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>dan wanneer ge eens komt.</ab>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">’k Geloof dat wil men figuren maken men een warm gevoel moet <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hebben in zich zelf van wat Punch op de Kersmisplaat noemt <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Good will to all</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> n.l. dat men werkelijk liefde moet <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>hebben voor de menschen.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Ten minste hoop ik mijn best <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>te doen in zoo’n stemming te zijn zooveel mogelijk.</ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik vind het juist daarom ook zoo jammer dat het met omgang <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>met schilders niet vlot, en<c type="kk">/</c> zooals ik reeds vroeger U eens schreef<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>op een regenachtigen dag als heden men niet eens gezellig <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>bij de kagchel kan zitten<c type="kk">/</c> teekeningen of prenten zien <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>en elkaar zoodoende animeeren.</ab>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik moet U eens vragen of er van <hi rend="ital">Daumier</hi> goedkoope <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>bladen in den handel zijn, en indien ja<c type="kk">/</c> welke? Ik heb hem <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>altijd zeer knap gevonden maar het is eerst in den laatsten <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>tijd dat ik begin te vermoeden dat hij van nog grooter <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>importance is dan ik dacht. Als gij iets bijzonders weet <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>van hem of wel importante dingen van zijn <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>teekeningen kent<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf er als ge wilt eens over. <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>Ik heb vroeger ook wel caricaturen van hem gezien <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>en juist daardoor misschien een ander idee van hem gekregen <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>dan wel ’t juiste. Zijn figuren troffen mij steeds bijzonder <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>maar ik geloof dat ik maar een heel klein deel <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>van zijn werk ken en dat b.v. de karicaturen volstrekt niet het <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>gewone of voornaamste van hem is.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
    <ab rend="indent">Ik herinner mij wij erover gesproken hebben verleden jaar op den weg <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>naar Prinsenhage,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> en gij toen zeidet ge Daumier mooier vondt dan <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Gavarni en ik toen partij trok voor Gavarni en U <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>sprak over het boek dat ik over Gavarni gelezen had dat gij nu hebt<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>Maar ik moet zeggen dat ofschoon ik sedert niet minder van <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Gavarni ben gaan houden, ik begin te vermoeden dat ik slechts <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>een heel klein deel van ’t werk van Daumier ken EN IN DAT <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>GEDEELTE WAT IK VAN ZIJN WERK NIET KEN juist de dingen zitten <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>die mij (hoe zeer ik ook dat wat ik van hem ken reeds apprecieer) nog <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>het allermeest interesseeren zouden. En mij schemert nog iets <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>in de herinnering – maar ik kan ’t mis hebben – dat gij mij <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>spraakt van groote teekeningen<c type="kk">/</c> typen of portretten uit het <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>volk<c type="kk">/</c> en daar ben ik nieuwsgierig naar. Waren er meer dingen van hem zoo mooi als <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>een blad dat ik onlangs van hem vond<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="ital">les 5 âges d’un</hi> <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">buveur</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> of als dat figuur van een oud man onder den kastanjeboom <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>waar ik U reeds van sprak,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> ja dan was hij misschien de baas van <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>allen. Weet gij hieromtrent me eenige inlichting te geven. <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>Herinnert gij U nog de figuren van De Groux uit de Uilenspiegel<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>die ik vroeger gehad heb en nu helaas niet meer – wel<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>die twee bladen van Daumier die ik het laatst noem lijken <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>daarop – en kent ge er zulken meer – (de karikaturen <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>daar geef ik veel minder om) dat is mijn bedoeling. <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>Het spijt mij verschrikkelijk dat ik die de Groux en Rops<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>niet meer heb<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb ze met andere dingen in Engeland <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>weggegeven. aan Richardson<c type="kk">/</c> den reiziger van het huis G&amp;C<hi rend="ss">ie</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu kerel, en dit beloof ik U tegen dat ge komt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>behalve de aquarellen &amp; geschilderde studies zal ik U eens <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>verzoeken de moeite te nemen een portefeuille <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>met een honderdtal geteekende studies <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>door te zien – allen figuren. Ik heb die nu reeds<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>vooral als ik er eenige oude bijreken.– In den <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>tusschentijd van nu en uw komst zal ik echter trachten <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>betere in de plaats te maken voor anderen die <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>er uit kunnen en er nog meer variatie in trachten te <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>brengen. à dieu intusschen, van harte wensch ik <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>U wat voorspoed &amp; geluk toe en geloof me<c type="kk">/</c> met <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>een handdruk in gedachten</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="118*" xml:id="l-118s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-47" n="47">“ik &lt; ik</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>It’s Sunday again, and again as rainy as usual. On top of that we’ve had a gale this week and the leaves are thinning out on the trees. Believe me, I’m glad that the stove is in place.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">This morning, when I at last got round to sorting out my drawings, namely the studies from the model done since about the time of your visit (not counting the older studies nor what I draw in my sketchbook), I found about one hundred. I just mention this figure because I remember that on the occasion of your visit you asked me if I had other studies as well as the drawings you saw then. I don’t know whether all painters work harder than I do, even those who look down on my work very loftily, so much so that they consider it beneath them to take the slightest notice of it. Nor do I know whether they know a better way than working with models, although in my view they do that too little, as I’ve written to you more than once, saying that I couldn’t understand why they don’t make more use of models. (Of course I do <hi rend="ital">not</hi> mean people like <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1107">Israëls</rs>, although the latter sets an excellent example in my view by always working with a model, but more gentlemen like <rs type="pers" key="868">Bock</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="903">Breitner</rs>, say.) I haven’t seen anything at all of the latter since I visited him in hospital when he was ill<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> — by chance I heard something about his having become a teacher at a secondary school<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> — but I haven’t had the slightest sign of life from him himself. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">This week I received a letter from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> who’s also surprised by the behaviour of many painters here, and had the experience, among other things, of having one of his paintings refused at Arti.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> I say only this: if the likes of he and I are rated as nothing, is that fair? For I assure you that he works hard; he was in Drenthe this summer, and after that he worked for a long time in the hospital for the blind in Utrecht.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I found it curious to hear from him of several experiences that were roughly or exactly the same as my own. But anyway. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">As I’ve written to you before, I often long for you. If I saw more of you and we were able to discuss the work more, I could make several things that should be possible to make from the studies I have. I’m convinced of that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Still — you remember that not long ago I wrote (when I sent you a small scratch of a potato market): ‘I must have another go at tackling that bustle on the street’.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> The result is now some 12 watercolours that I’m working on at the moment.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> So I do <hi rend="ital">not</hi> mean by the above that I can’t achieve anything with my studies or that I do them without any aim, but only that I believe I could achieve <hi rend="ital">more</hi> with them and make them <hi rend="ital">more</hi> immediately effective if I could discuss things with you more often. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> But be that as it may, I do work with great pleasure these days, and I do have hope that there will be some things which you too will take pleasure in, when you next come. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I believe that if one wants to do figures one must have a warm sense within oneself of what Punch in the Christmas illustration calls <hi rend="ital">Good will to all</hi>, that is, that one must have a real love of people.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> At least I hope to do my best to be in that kind of a mood as much as possible. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">That’s exactly why I find it such a pity that I don’t get on better with painters, and, as I wrote to you in the past, that on a rainy day like today one can’t just sit cosily by the stove, look at drawings or prints and liven each other up that way.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I must ask you whether there are cheap prints by <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>
                    </hi> for sale, and if so, which. I’ve always believed him to be highly gifted, but it’s only recently that I begin to suspect that he’s of even greater importance than I thought. If you know anything special about him, or know of important things among his drawings, do write about them if you will. In the past I saw caricatures by him, and perhaps because of them got an idea about him that wasn’t the right one. His figures always struck me the most, but I believe that I know only a very small part of his work and that, for instance, the caricatures are definitely not his most typical or main work. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I remember that we talked about this last year on the road to Princenhage,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and you said then that you thought <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs> more beautiful than <rs type="pers" key="1043">Gavarni</rs>, and I took Gavarni’s side and spoke to you of the book about Gavarni that I had read and that you now have.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> But I must say that, although I still like Gavarni just as much, I begin to suspect that I know only a very small part of Daumier’s work AND THAT IN THE PART OF HIS WORK I DO NOT KNOW are the very things that would interest me most of all (however much I already appreciate what I know by him). And I also dimly remember — but I may be wrong — you telling me about large drawings, types or portraits from the common people, and I’m curious about them. If there were more things by him as beautiful as a print by him I recently found, <hi rend="ital">The 5 ages of a drinker</hi>,<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> or as that figure of an old man under a chestnut tree I told you about before,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> well, then he was perhaps the master of them all. Can you give me any information about this? Do you still remember the figures by <rs type="pers" key="1063">Degroux</rs> from the Uylenspiegel that I had in the past but not any more, alas?<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> — well, those two prints by Daumier that I just mentioned look like them —and if you know of any more like them — (I care much less about the caricatures) that’s what I’m after. I’m terribly sorry that I no longer have the Degroux and <rs type="pers" key="1326">Rops</rs>.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> I gave them away in England, along with other things, to <rs type="pers" key="636">Richardson</rs>, the traveller for the house of G&amp;Cie.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, old chap, and I promise you this for when you come, apart from the watercolours and painted studies, I’ll ask you to take the trouble to look through a portfolio with one hundred drawn studies — all figures. I have them already, especially if I include some old ones. In the interval between now and your visit, however, I’ll try to make better ones to replace others that can be left out, and try to put even more variety into them. Adieu in the meantime, I sincerely wish you good fortune and happiness, and believe me, with a handshake in thought,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>For the placing of the stove, <ref target="let274.xml#n-13">see letter 274, n. 13.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh had visited <rs type="pers" key="903">Breitner</rs> in the Municipal Hospital between 21 and 28 March 1882; <ref target="let214.xml">see letter 214</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>During the winter course of 1882-1883 <rs type="pers" key="903">Breitner</rs> taught freehand and ornament drawing for 16 hours a week in the 2nd class of the Academy of Fine Arts and Technical Science in Rotterdam. He gave his first lesson on 5 September 1882. See Hefting<hi rend="ital"> </hi>1970, p. 49 and <hi rend="ital">Brieven Breitner </hi>1970, pp. 36, 38.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This letter from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> is mentioned in <ref target="let275.xml">letter 275</ref>, which was an answer to it. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>For this refused painting, <ref target="let268.xml#n-11">see letter 268, n. 11.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>On <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs>’s work at the Institute for the Blind in Utrecht in the autumn of 1882: exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 79-80.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This unknown ‘scratch of the potato market on Noordwal’ was mentioned earlier in <ref target="let261.xml">letter 261</ref>. In that letter of 9 September Van Gogh literally wrote: ‘where I can express the bustle of workmen I see on the street or outdoors’. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>It is not known which watercolours these were. There is a good chance that one of them was <hi rend="ital">Potato market</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="341">F 1091 / JH 252</rs>) (cf. <ref target="let261.xml">letter 261</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
    <ab>For this Christmas print, <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="1369">Stirring the pudding</rs>
                        </hi> in <hi rend="ital">Punch</hi>, <ref target="let276.xml#n-1">see letter 276, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>This must have been in July 1881 when Theo was in Etten; the brothers would have visited <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs> van Gogh in Princenhage – he was not very well at that time: <ref target="let168.xml">see letters 168</ref> and <ref target="let170.xml">170</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="617 618">Jules and Edmond de Goncourt</rs> characterize <rs type="pers" key="677">Daumier</rs> as Gavarni’s ‘rival’ in <rs type="lit" key="224">
                            <hi rend="ital">Gavarni, l’homme et l’oeuvre</hi>
                        </rs> (Goncourt 1873, pp. 230, 400).</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>, <rs type="otherart" key="421">
                            <hi rend="ital">Physiologie du buveur – Les quatre âges</hi>
                        </rs> (The physiology of the drinker – The four ages), <ref target="let267.xml#n-33">see letter 267, n. 33.</ref> Van Gogh has one drinker too many.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>’s print of <rs type="ill" key="54">Ferragus</rs>, <ref target="let274.xml#n-3">see letter 274, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>In the period January 1857-July 1857, <rs type="pers" key="1063">Charles Degroux</rs> provided twelve illustrations with several <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>-like figures for the satirical weekly <hi rend="ital">Uylenspiegel, Journal des Ebats Artistiques et Littéraires.</hi> They are all reproduced in exhib. cat. Ypres 1995, pp. 149-152. See also <ref target="let273.xml#n-37">letter 273, n. 37.</ref> On this magazine: Nathalie Eeckman, <hi rend="ital">Uylenspiegel. Journal des ébats artistiques et littéraires (1856-1860). Rôle et conceptions littéraires</hi>. Louvain 1985.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1326">Félicien Rops</rs>’s illustrations for the magazine <hi rend="ital">Uylenspiegel</hi>, see Maurice Exteens, <hi rend="ital">L’Oeuvre gravé et lithographié de Félicien Rops</hi>. 5 vols. Paris 1928. Van Gogh copied Rops’s <rs type="otherart" key="422">
                            <hi rend="ital">Souvenirs. En attendant la confession</hi>
                        </rs> (Recollections. Waiting for confession) from <hi rend="ital">Uylenspiegel</hi> (29 March 1857), p. 4: <hi rend="ital">Old woman asleep (After Rops)</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="153">F XVII / JH -</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 51-52, cat. no. 5 and ill. 5a.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>Van Gogh had earlier expressed his regret at having given away wood engravings in <ref target="let267.xml">letter 267</ref>; cf. <ref target="let267.xml#n-8">n. 8</ref> there.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>