<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Thursday, 22 June 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let239"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">239</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">208</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">239</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 22 June 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Thursday, 22 June 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh is treated for gonorrhoea <ref target="let237.xml">(237)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Sien will give birth in Leiden <ref target="let224.xml">(224)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Second order for drawings from Uncle Cor <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b230 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘den Haag 22 Junij’. We assume that Van Gogh wrote this himself, despite the different handwriting in this line. This is probably due to the fact that it is a later addition for which there was little space. It is unlikely that Jo van Gogh-Bonger put the date on: she never used the spelling ‘Junij’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0230" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000271_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000271_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000271_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000271_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000271_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0230" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000271_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000271_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000271_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000271_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000271_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000271_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>den Haag 22 Junij</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2*" xml:id="l-2s"/>
<ab>Uw brief van 12 Juni met ingesloten frs. 50 heb ik in orde <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>ontvangen &amp; dank er U van harte voor. Ik antwoordde er tot <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>heden nog niet op omdat ik niet wist welken keer mijne onge<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>steldheid nemen zoude<c type="kk">/</c> die niet zoo voorspoedig beterde als de dokter <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>gedacht had. Het is heden ruim 14 dagen ik hier ben en <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>ik heb op nieuw 14 dagen vooruit moeten betalen ofschoon <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>ik welligt binnen 8 of 10 dagen als alles goed gaat <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>zal mogen vertrekken &amp; dan ook gedeeltelijk mijn geld terug <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>krijg. Nu sprak ik van morgen met den dokter en <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>vroeg hem of er iets bij gekomen was dat erg kon worden<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Neen, zei hij, maar rusthouden en nog blijven was evenwe<supplied>l</supplied> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>de boodschap. Het is niet alleen bij inspuiting gebleven <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>maar hij is met een katheter in de blaas aan ’t scharrelen <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>geweest hetwelk niet bijzonder erg amusant is.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toch zou het misschien voor zeer veel menschen heilzaam zijn als <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>zij van tijd tot tijd dat eens gedaan werden omdat <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>het een maatregel is die preventief is ten opzigte <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>van lastige kwalen die zeer zeer langzaam zich ontwikkelen. <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>Maar ik verzeker U dat ik schrikkelijk verlang naar <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>een beetje groen en wat buitenlucht want zoo’n grapje maakt <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>erg zwak en flaauw. Want ik moet bijna gedurig stil liggen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ik kan niet teekenen ofschoon ik ’t een paar maal beproefd heb<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>ik word er te koortsig van, lezen gaat nog maar ik <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>heb geen boeken meer. Enfin er zal toch wel weer een <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>eind aan komen dus nog maar wat geduld.</ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Sien is te Leiden maar voor zij bevallen is kan ik geen berigt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>van haar hebben. Wat beteekent ’tgeen wij mannen hebben <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>bij dat vreesselijke lijden dat de vrouwen bij hun bevalling moeten <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>uitstaan. In het pijnlijden zijn ze ons de baas maar in sommige andere <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>dingen winnen wij het daarentegen. Tot den laatsten dag dat <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>zij hier was kwam zij geregeld mij bezoeken en bragt mij nog wat <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>rookvleesch of suiker of brood mee<c type="kk">/</c> dat nu ophoudt en mij erg flaauw <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>maakt. Maar nu spijt het mij zoo dat ik niet op mijn beurt 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>haar nog te Leiden een hartsterking kan toestoppen die zij zeker <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>best gebruiken kon want het zijn maar slappe kostjes die men krijgt. <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Het is mij zoo’n mal gevoel niets te kunnen doen <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>en die dagen zoo leeg te zien voorbijgaan<c type="kp">_</c> Soms denk <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>ik dat ik dit of dat zal kunnen en dan valt de zwakte tegen.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het doet mij regt veel genoegen dat gij in de teekeningen die ik <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>U stuurde<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> iets zaagt – ik heb er die laatste dagen toen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>ik veel meer pijn en benaauwdheid had dan hier nog <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zoo op gesjouwd &amp; op die van C.M. ook. Want het <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>ergste was vóór ik hier in ’t gasthuis kwam<c type="kk">/</c> al lang te voren<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu moet ge weten dat ik nog een brief van Rappard heb<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Natuurlijk had ik hem dadelijk de f<c type="kp">_</c> 2.50 terug gezonden<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> en <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>ik kreeg nog daarna een antwoord van hem waarin <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>hij opnieuw het zelfde zegt van mijn teekeningen wat hij op ’t <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>atelier er van zei<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. dat vooral om de opvatting<c type="kk">/</c> het sentiment <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>en het gewilde<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> er van<c type="kk">/</c> hij er pleizier in had &amp; ze hem sympathiek <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>waren<c type="kk">/</c> dat hij mij voorstelde als ik iets dergelijks had <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>het hem eens te zenden daar hij dacht het aan den man <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>te kunnen brengen. Gij begrijpt wel dat ’t geen <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>ik het allerliefst heb is dat de menschen er wat schik in <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>hebben<c type="kk">/</c> dat doet mij zoo’n pleizier. Want het <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>is zoo ontmoedigend en uitdoovend en domperig als <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>men niet eens nu en dan hoort: dit of dat is <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>juist en gevoeld en gewild. Het wekt zoo op als <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>men merkt dat iemand werkelijk iets voelt van datgene <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>wat men getracht heeft uit te drukken. Hij had toen ook <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>pleizier in nog een paar naaktstudies.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is voor ’t eerst in verscheiden dagen dat ik weer eens <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>op zit en zoo schrijvende voel ik weer wat leven wakker <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>worden. Was ik maar in orde! Kon ik mij maar <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>installeeren zoo als ’t moest<c type="kk">/</c> wat zou ik graag hier in de zalen <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>wat studies maken. Ik leg<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-o-b"/> nu in een andere zaal met bedden <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>of kribben zonder gordijnen en vooral s’avonds of s’nachts zijn <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>er eigenaardige effekten. De dokter is net zoo als ik <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>hem ’t liefste heb<c type="kk">/</c> volstrekt geen Blom Coster<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> hij heeft veel van <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>sommige koppen van Rembrandt, een prachtig voorhoofd en <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>een zeer sympathieke uitdrukking<c type="kp">_</c> Ik hoop wat van hem af gezien <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>te hebben in dit opzigt dat ik hoop <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>met de modellen om te springen eenigzins als hij met de zieken<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>n.l. ze maar krachtig aanpakken<c type="kk">/</c> ze kort en bondig <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>precies in de positie zetten die noodig is. Het is <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>fameus zooveel geduld die man heeft om zelf de zieken <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>te wrijven<c type="kk">/</c> te smeeren<c type="kk">/</c> te hanteeren op allerlei wijs<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>oneindig flinker dan een oppasser en hoe hij er den <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>slag van heeft de scrupules weg te nemen en de luidjes <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>precies zóó te zetten als hij ze noodig heeft. Er is een <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>oud man die superbe zou zijn voor een St Gerome<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>Een mager<c type="kk">/</c> lang<c type="kk">/</c> peezig<c type="kk">/</c> bruin &amp; gerimpeld ligchaam met <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>gewrichten zoo fameus duidelijk en expressief dat men <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>er melankoliek van wordt hem niet voor model te bezitten.</ab>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik kan mij best begrijpen dat Heyerdahl in zijn schik is met <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>zoo’n belooning.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> Nu moet ik U nog mededeelen dat Pa mij <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>bezocht heeft in de eerste dagen dat ik hier was ofschoon maar <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>heel kort &amp; heel gehaast en eigentlijk heb ik over niets kunnen <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>spreken<c type="kk">/</c> ik had het bezoek eigentlijk liever op een anderen tijd gehad <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>wanneer wij van weerskanten er waarlijk meer aan hadden kunnen <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>hebben.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Het was mij nu erg vreemd en kwam mij min of meer <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>als een droom voor – gelijk trouwens deze heele geschiedenis van het <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>hier ziek liggen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Behalve Sien<c type="kk">/</c> haar moeder en Pa heb ik anders niemand gezien <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>wat eigentlijk het beste is ofschoon de dagen wel wat <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>eenzaam en melankoliek zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Ik denk soms onwillekeurig <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>dat het nu heel wat somberder en eenzamer geworden is <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>dan b.v. toen ik dezen winter het eerst bij Mauve kwam<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>Het geeft mij een steek en een benaauwd gevoel telkens <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>als ik er aan denk ofschoon ik tracht de heele gedachte <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>er aan over boord te donderen als nutteloozen <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>ballast.</ab>
                <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb van den oppasser gehoord dat Breitner <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>dezer dagen het huis verlaten heeft.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik geloof dat hier in deze klasse de dokter wat korter <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>wetten<anchor n="c" xml:id="note-o-c"/> maakt dan in de duurdere<c type="kp">_</c> Tant mieux<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>
<ab rend="indent">Misschien zijn ze hier<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> minder schroomvallig ons patienten <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>een beetje pijn te doen dan in de hoogere zalen, en b.v. steken iemand heel spoedig <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>een katheter in zijn blaas zonder veel “vormen” <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>of complimenten. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> mijns inziens tant mieux <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>en nog eens<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> ik vind het hier even aardig als in de wachtkamer <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>3e klasse. Als ik maar werken kon! maar <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>ik moet mij daaraan onderwerpen<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb een boek van <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>Dickens en mijn perspectiefboeken bij me.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoop gij nog eens schrijven zult<c type="kk">/</c> ge weet t’<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>adres is</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="116*" xml:id="l-116s"/>
      <ab rend="html" html="239_01_ol.html">Gemeente gasthuis<c type="kk">/</c> Brouwersgracht</ab>
                <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>
      <ab rend="html" html="239_01_ol.html">4<hi rend="ss">o</hi> klasse. Zaal 6 N<hi rend="ss">o</hi> 9<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>
<ab>adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk in gedachten <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>&amp; veel dank voor Uw trouwen brief <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>&amp; het ingeslotene nogmaals. Heb het <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>goed &amp; geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="121*" xml:id="l-121s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>
<ab>Ik geloof dat toen Sien weg moest ik <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>wat te zenuwachtig geweest ben en toen <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>ingestort maar er zijn wel eens momenten <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>waarin men niet altijd geheel <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>koelbloedig zijn kan. Zij legt daar <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>zoo alleen en ik wou er zoo graag eens heen want het zullen bange <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>dagen voor haar zijn.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-12" n="12">evenwe<supplied>l</supplied> &lt; <hi rend="ital">Text lost due to the edge of the paper.</hi>
                    </note>
</div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
      <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <ab>The Hague, 22 June</ab>
                <vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I received your letter of 12 June with the 50 francs enclosed in good order, and thank you sincerely for them. I haven’t replied before because I didn’t know what course my illness would take — it hasn’t improved as quickly as the doctor thought. I’ve now been here for over a fortnight and have again had to pay for a fortnight in advance, although if all goes well I’ll be allowed to leave in a week or 10 days and will then get part of my money back. This morning I spoke to the <rs type="pers" key="151">doctor</rs> and asked him if there was a complication that might become serious. No, he said, but the message was still rest and stay here. The treatment didn’t stop at instillations: he’s been rummaging about inside the bladder with a catheter, which isn’t particularly enjoyable.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But it might perhaps be good for a great many people if they underwent this from time to time, because it’s a preventive measure for troublesome conditions that develop very, very slowly. But I assure you that I long dreadfully for a little greenery and some fresh air, for a thing like this makes you very weak and faint. I can’t draw because I must lie still almost continuously, although I have tried a few times; it makes me too feverish. I can read but I’ve run out of books. Anyway, it will come to an end, so I must be patient. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs> is in Leiden, but I won’t hear any news of her until she has given birth. What does what we men have signify compared with the terrible suffering that women must endure in childbirth? They are our masters when it comes to suffering pain, but in other things we are the winners. Until the last day she was here she visited me regularly and brought me a little smoked meat or sugar or bread, which is now finished, leaving me feeling very faint. But now I’m so sorry that I can’t in turn 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> give her a tonic in Leiden, which she’d certainly welcome, for what you get there is only weak fare. I find it such an odd feeling not to be able to do anything and to watch the days passing so emptily. Sometimes I think I can do this or that, but find I’m too weak. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It pleases me greatly that you saw something in the drawings I sent<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> — I laboured so hard on them, and on those for <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M. </rs>as well, in those last days when I felt so much more pain and anxiety than here. For the worst was before I came to this hospital, long before.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now I must tell you that I’ve had a letter from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>. Of course I had immediately returned the 2.50 guilders,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> and after that I received a reply from him in which he repeats what he said about my drawings in the studio, namely that he enjoyed them and found them sympathetic, mainly because of the conception, the sentiment and the intention. He suggested that if I had something similar I should send it to him, because he thought he could find a customer for it. You do understand that what I want most is for people to enjoy my work; that gives me such pleasure. For it’s so disheartening and stifling and crushing if you don’t even occasionally hear: this or that is right and felt and meant. It’s so exhilarating when you see that someone really does feel something of what you’ve tried to express. He was also pleased by a few nude studies.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">This is the first time for several days that I’ve sat up, and as I write I feel some life stirring. If only I were cured! If only I could settle myself as I need, how I would love to do some studies here in the wards. I’m now in a different ward with beds or cots without curtains, and especially in the evening or at night there are curious effects. The doctor is just the way I like, absolutely not <rs type="pers" key="289">Blom Coster</rs>.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> He resembles some heads by <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>, a fine forehead and a very sympathetic expression. I hope to have learned something from him, in the sense that I hope to deal with models rather as he deals with patients, namely tackling them firmly, setting them shortly and sharply in the precise position required. It’s extraordinary how patient he is when rubbing, massaging and manipulating the sick himself in various ways. He’s far stronger than an orderly, and has the knack of allaying their embarrassments and positioning the people exactly as he needs them. There’s an old man who would make a superb St Jerome. A thin, tall, wiry, brown and wrinkled body with joints so outstandingly clear and expressive that it makes one sad not to have him as a model. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I can well imagine that <rs type="pers" key="1084">Heyerdahl</rs> is delighted by such a payment.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> Now I must inform you that <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> visited me the first days that I was here, although very briefly and in great haste, and I wasn’t really able to talk about anything. I would rather he had visited at another time, when it could truly have been of more good for both of us.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> Now it was very strange for me, and seemed more or less like a dream — as does this whole business of lying here being ill. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve seen no one apart from <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs>, her <rs type="pers" key="464">mother</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs>, which is in fact all for the best, though the days are rather lonely and melancholy. Sometimes I can’t help thinking that life is now considerably more sombre and lonelier than, for example, when I first visited <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> last winter. It gives me a stab of pain and an anxious feeling each time I think of it, even though I try to chuck the whole thought of it overboard as useless ballast. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I heard from the orderly that <rs type="pers" key="903">Breitner</rs> was discharged a few days ago.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I believe that here in this class the doctor gives shorter shrift than in the more expensive ones. So much the better.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Perhaps here<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> they’re less hesitant about inflicting a little pain on the patients than in the higher wards, and more ready, for example, to stick a catheter in someone’s bladder without a lot of ‘good manners’ or compliments. Well, all the better in my view, and I repeat<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> it’s as good here as in the 3rd-class waiting room. If only I could work! But I must take things as they are. I have a book by <rs type="pers" key="580">Dickens</rs> and my perspective books.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hope you’ll write again. You know the address is:</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
      <ab rend="html" html="239_01_tr.html">Municipal hospital, Brouwersgracht</ab>
      <ab rend="html" html="239_01_tr.html">4th class. Ward 6, No. 9.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Adieu, a handshake in thought, and many thanks again for your loyal letter and the enclosure. I wish you well, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I believe that when <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs> had to go I became too nervous and then broke down, but there are times when one can’t always remain cool-headed. She’s lying there so alone, and I would so like to go there because these will be frightening days for her. </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>For the treatment of Van Gogh’s illness, <ref target="let237.xml">see letter 237</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Fish-drying barn</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2377">F 940 / JH 154</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Carpenter’s yard and laundry</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2376">F 944 / JH 153</rs>), sent on 3 June; <ref target="let235.xml">see letter 235</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>For this loan on 27 May, which was repaid on 4 or 5 June, <ref target="let231.xml">see letters 231</ref> and <ref target="let236.xml">236</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘de intentie, dat wat ik ermee voor had’ (the intention, what I had in mind).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>These nude studies are not known. In 1903 M. and J.C. Couvreur acquired works by Van Gogh. Stokvis noted that: ‘They included nude drawings, which so scandalized the wife of J.C. Couvreur that they were thrown away’ (Stokvis 1926, p. 5; cf. cat. Amsterdam 1997, p. 25). Perhaps there were works from the Hague period among them.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-o-b">
<ab>Read: ‘lig’ (lie).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>A gibe<hi rend="ital"> </hi>at the doctor in the Hague, <rs type="pers" key="289">Tuimen Hendrik Blom Coster</rs>, who had treated Theo in 1877 and evidently looked too distinguished and eminent in Vincent’s eyes (for him see also <ref target="let125.xml#n-14">letter 125, n. 14</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Theo must have reported that <rs type="pers" key="1084">Heyerdahl</rs> had been awarded the Grand Prix de Florence – worth 5000 francs – for the painting <rs type="otherart" key="270">
                            <hi rend="ital">The dead child</hi>
                        </rs> (Riom, Musée Régional Folklorique d’Auvergne), which was shown at the Salon of 1882. The journal <hi rend="ital">L’Art</hi> had written about the prize. See exhib. cat. Åmot 1981, pp. 19, 58-59. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>On 14 June 1882 <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had written at length to Theo about this visit: ‘You will want to know how I found Vincent.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">On Saturday evening we received a letter from him written in the hospital in which he said that he was ill and had gone there. He had just received a package from us with a 10-guilder coin as well. He wrote in a mild tone and said that he was reassured by our letter, etc. etc.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If it had been possible for me, I would have gone on Sunday, but I had to preach in Minister <rs type="pers" key="477">Kam</rs>’s place, since he is ill. I left Roosendaal early on Monday morning. Immediately on arriving I called at the institution, but could not see the director, who is also a doctor, before 2 o’clock because he was engaged in an operation. I couldn’t see the patient either before 3 in the afternoon. Then to <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>, who was away travelling and his <rs type="pers" key="321">wife</rs> out shopping. Then to <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs>, also not at home before 1.30. Then I did speak to Mr. Tersteeg, but he knows nothing about Vincent. V. had broken off all relations, since Tersteeg had pointed out to him that it was not fitting that at his age he should be supported by his brother. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Vincent had concluded from this that Tersteeg and Mauve had urged you to not to send your contribution any more, and that idea seems to have made him agitated again. Tersteeg knew these details from you or from your letters. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">At 2 o’clock I spoke to the <rs type="pers" key="151">doctor</rs>. When I enquired about the patient, he said that his illness was catarrhal in nature, and that he appeared to be in need of rest. But he saw no objection and allowed me to go to him and to speak to him again (the doctor) after my visit. Vincent was somewhat surprised to see me, a little touchy, but I put him into a normal mood and promised to return the next day. He does not look at all wasted, his pulse is calm and otherwise quite normal. He had complaints about <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs>, that he had judged his drawings so coolly. <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> had seen them and thought them very good. That Rappard remains loyal to him and had later written to him again to encourage him. We spoke for quite a long time and then it was time for me to go to Leiden. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I told Vincent that when he was allowed to leave the hospital he could come to us to get his strength back but, while he appreciated the offer, he thought it better not to avail himself of it, because he wanted to get back to work. Yesterday morning at 10 o’clock I returned from Leiden and went to see him again. And I asked the doctor to let me know if, Heaven forbid, there was a change for the worse. Before that, however, I drove to his house, where the people said they didn’t really know where the gentleman was. He had said he was leaving the city for 14 days, but they believed he was in the hospital. They couldn’t show me his studio because they hadn’t got the key. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now I heard from him that he had heard from his <rs type="pers" key="463">model</rs> about that package we had sent. He had got my letter and the enclosure, but that letter was inside the package, so the model must have opened the package. Can there be any danger in that so-called model?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">When I left I secretly gave him a piece of paper from <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> with some ox-tongue, but not a lot, to which I added a 10-guilder coin. He had refused to take money from me. There he pays 10.50 guilders per 14 days, always in advance. He had been there eight days and he showed me his receipt. As I left I whispered to him that he must be careful with the small packet I had given him because there was something else in it (I meant that coin). He stuffed the packet under his mattress. He remains singular, and I have no great expectations. But if only he does not sink lower and lower and does not throw himself away on an unworthy person. That avoidance of people who want to help him along is an unfavourable sign. When the time came for other visitors to arrive, I noticed him looking towards the door uneasily. Can it be that he was expecting a visitor, someone that he would rather I did not meet?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Don’t say that I think the worst. I say this to no one else but you and you will understand – how I mean it, truly not to burden him, but in part out of fear. There is in him an inclination towards the lower classes, and sometimes a person can enter into an improper connection out of perversity or a sense of desolation.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You understand, though we are not now afraid of this illness turning out badly, we continue to be concerned about him and that concern has not diminished. He also talked about wanting to take another house – in the same neighbourhood – where he would have better opportunities ... What a support you are for Vincent. Bye, old chap!’ (FRb2240).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="903">Breitner</rs> was discharged from the hospital on Saturday, 17 June: <ref target="let214.xml">see letter 214</ref> and cf. <ref target="let237.xml">letter 237</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="c" xml:id="n-c" target="#note-o-c">
<ab>Variant of the expression ‘korte metten maken’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Van Gogh means in the 3rd class.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>This comparison is also found in <ref target="let238.xml">letter 238</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>In the previous letter Van Gogh not only named the title, <rs type="lit" key="243">
                            <hi rend="ital">The mystery of Edwin Drood</hi>
                        </rs>, but also spoke of ‘several volumes’ of <rs type="pers" key="580">Dickens</rs>. <ref target="let238.xml">See letter 238</ref>, also for the perspective books mentioned.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>