<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 2 July 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let242"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">242</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">210</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">242</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 2 July 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 2 July 1882.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b232 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Zondag middag’. The letter was written on the Sunday of the visit to the hospital in Leiden and the birth of Sien’s child <ref target="#l-4">(ll. 4-7)</ref>. That was Sunday, 2 July 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0232" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000274_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000274_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000274_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000274_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000274_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0232" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000274_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000274_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000274_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000274_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000274_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000274_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Zondag middag</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Zooals ik U gisteren schreef ben ik naar Leiden <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>geweest. Sien is gisteren nacht bevallen, heeft <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>eene zeer moeielijke verlossing gehad maar is <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>er Goddank evenwel levend af gekomen en <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>een bijzonder aardig klein jongentje ook.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Haar moeder en kindje en ik waren zamen er <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>naar toe gegaan – gij kunt denken dat wij <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>in groote spanning waren<c type="kk">/</c> niet wetende wat wij <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>hooren zouden toen wij in het gasthuis aan de <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>oppasseres naar haar vroegen<c type="kp">_</c>– En ontzettend <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>blijde waren toen wij hoorden: van nacht <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>bevallen..... maar gij moogt niet veel met haar <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>spreken.. Ik zal dat “ge moogt niet veel met <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>haar spreken” niet ligt vergeten want dat was “gij <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>kunt nog met haar spreken”<c type="kk">/</c> en het had evengoed kunnen <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>zijn “gij zult haar nooit meer spreken”. Theo ik <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>was zoo gelukkig toen ik haar weer zag en zij <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>lag vlak bij ’t raam dat op den tuin vol zon en groen <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>uitzag<c type="kk">/</c> en in een soort dommeling van uitputting <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>tusschen slapen en wakker zijn in<c type="kk">/</c> en toen <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>keek zij op en zag ons allen. Ah kerel zij <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>keek zoo en zij was zoo blij ons te zien en dat <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>wij toevallig zoo juist precies 12 uren nadat <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>het gebeurd was daar waren terwijl er maar 1 uur <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>in de week is men hun bezoeken mag. En zij vrolijkte <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>zoo op en was zoo in alle opzigten in een oogenblik <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>bij haar positieven en vroeg naar alles.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar wat ik niet genoeg bewonderen kan is het kind<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>in dit bijzonder opzigt dat<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon het met den <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>forceps is gehaald<c type="kk">/</c> niet in ’t minst bezeerd is <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>en in zijn wiegje lag met een soort air van <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>wereldwijsheid. Zij zijn toch knap die dokters<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Maar naar de beschrijving was het een critiek <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>geval<c type="kp">_</c> Er stonden 5 professors bij toen het gebeurde <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>en men heeft haar bedwelmd met chloroform. Voor dien <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>tijd heeft zij enorm veel uitgestaan omdat het kind <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>vast zat van s’avonds 9 tot half twee. En nu <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>is zij nog zeer pijnlijk. Maar zij vergat alles toen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zij ons zag en wist mij zelfs te vertellen dat wij gaauw <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>weer aan het teekenen zouden zijn en ik heb er volstrekt <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>niets op tegen dat haar voorspelling maar heel precies <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>moge uitkomen. Er is geen inscheuring of zoo iets <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>wat in zoo’n geval zoo heel ligt gebeuren kan<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Sapperloot ik ben er zoo dankbaar voor. Alleen <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>de sombere schaduw dreigt nog altijd en <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>meester Albert Durer wist het wel toen hij <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>de dood achter het jonge paar plaatste <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>in die prachtige ets die gij kent.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Maar wij <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>willen hopen dat de sombere schaduw maar <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>eene schaduw moge blijven die weer voorbijgaat. <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Nu Theo<c type="kk">/</c> gij weet er alles van<c type="kk">/</c> als ik Uwe hulp <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>niet gehad had dan was Sien er waarschijnlijk <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>niet meer. Nog iets – ik had Sien verzocht 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>den professor te vragen haar eens goed te onderzoeken <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>omdat zij dikwijls iets had dat men witten vloed<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>noemt<c type="kp">_</c> En hij heeft dat ook gedaan en <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>haar raad gegeven omtrent ’t geen zij te doen <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>had om geheel in orde te komen.</ab>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
<ab rend="indent">En hij zegt dat zij meer dan eens<c type="kk">/</c> vooral <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>bij haar vroegere keelziekte<c type="kk">/</c> bij een vroegere miskraam<c type="kk">/</c> en dan dezen <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>winter zeer ver weg is geweest om het hoekje <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>om te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> dat zij door en door <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>verzwakt is door een leven van onrust <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>en gejaagdheid jaren lang<c type="kk">/</c> dat <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>nu zij niet langer dat leven <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>behoeft te leiden zij van zelf teregt kan <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>komen als er niets bij komt<c type="kk">/</c> door rust<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>door versterkende middelen<c type="kk">/</c> door zeer <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>veel in de buitenlucht te zijn en door <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>geen zwaar werk te doen.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als zij uit haar vroegere misère is komt er dan <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>een heele nieuwe periode in haar leven en <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>krijgt zij haar lente<c type="kk">/</c> die voorbij is en <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>die maar bar was<c type="kk">/</c> wel niet terug maar haar <hi rend="ital">st Jansschot</hi>
                    <anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>kan des te frisscher zijn. Gij weet wel hoe <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>de boomen in ’t midden van den zomer als <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>de grootste hitte voorbij is op nieuw frissche jonge <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>scheuten maken<c type="kk">/</c> een nieuwe jonge laag <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>groen over het oude verweerde heen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zit U te schrijven bij de moeder van Sien<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>bij een raam dat op een soort hofje uitziet<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>Dat heb ik tweemaal geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> eens <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>in ’t groot en eens kleiner. C.M<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>heeft die twee en dat waren die, vooral <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>de groote, waar Rappard schik in had<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Ik zou gaarne hebben gij ze eens <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>zaagt als gij bij C.M. komt want ik wou <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>wel weten wat gij vooral van de <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>grootste denkt. Wanneer komt gij?<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik verlang erg naar U. Nu broer, <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>gij hebt het op Uw geweten dat ik <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>van daag zoo gelukkig ben dat ik <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>er van geschreid heb. Dank voor <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>alles kerel<c type="kk">/</c> en geloof me met <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>een handdruk in gedachten</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab>t. à. t.</ab>
                <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-17" n="17">spreken”<c type="kk">/</c> &lt; spreken</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Sunday afternoon</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>As I wrote to you yesterday, I went to Leiden. <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs> gave birth last night, had a very difficult delivery but thank God she survived, together with a jolly nice little <rs type="pers" key="466">boy</rs>.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Her <rs type="pers" key="464">mother</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="467">child</rs> and I went there together — you can imagine how tense we were, not knowing what we’d hear when we enquired after her from the nurse at the hospital, and how delighted we were to be told: gave birth last night..... but you mustn’t talk to her too much... I shan’t soon forget that ‘you mustn’t talk to her too much’, because that meant ‘you can still talk to her’ and might equally well have been ‘you will never speak to her again’. Theo, I was so happy when I saw her again, and she was lying right by the window with a view of the garden full of sun and greenery in a sort of exhausted drowse in between sleeping and being awake, and then she looked up and saw us all. Ah, old chap, she had such a look on her face and she was so glad to see us, and because by chance we were there exactly 12 hours after it happened, while visitors are allowed only 1 hour a week. And she was so cheered up and came to her senses in every respect in a second, and asked about everything. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But what I can’t get over is the <rs type="pers" key="466">child</rs>, in particular because although it was delivered with forceps it wasn’t the least bit harmed, and lay in its cradle with a sort of air of worldly wisdom. They’re so clever, those doctors. By all accounts it was a critical situation. There were 5 professors present when it happened, and she was given chloroform. Before that she had endured an enormous amount because the baby was stuck from 9 in the evening until half past one. And she’s still in considerable pain. But she forgot it all when she saw us, and even said to me that we’d soon be drawing again, and I have absolutely no objection if her prediction proves entirely accurate. There’s no tearing or anything, which can easily happen in such a case. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">By Jove, I’m so thankful. But the sombre shadow still threatens, and the master <rs type="pers" key="990">Albrecht Dürer</rs> knew that when he placed Death behind the young couple in the wonderful etching you know.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> But we must hope that the sombre shadow remains only a shadow that will pass. Well, Theo, as you well know, if I hadn’t had your help <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs> probably wouldn’t be here. Another thing — I asked Sien 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> to ask the professor to give her a proper examination, because she often has what they call a white discharge.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> He did so, and advised her on what she must do to be completely cured. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And he says that she had been at death’s door more than once, especially during her previous throat illness, in an earlier miscarriage, and then last winter, that she has been profoundly weakened by a life of turmoil and agitation, year after year, that now that she no longer needed to lead that life she’d recover of her own accord, provided there are no complications, with rest, tonics, plenty of fresh air and no heavy labour.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">When she’s past her old misery, there will be a completely new period in her life: she won’t get back her spring — that is over, and was cruel anyway — but her <hi rend="ital">second growth</hi> can be all the fresher. You know how, in the middle of summer when the greatest heat has passed, the trees throw out fresh young shoots, a new layer of young green over the old, faded one. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m sitting writing to you next to Sien’s <rs type="pers" key="464">mother</rs> at a window looking out on a sort of courtyard. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I’ve drawn it twice, once large and once smaller. <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M.</rs> has both and they were the ones, especially the large one, that <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> liked.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> I’d like you to see them if you visit C.M. because I would particularly like to know what you think of the large one. When are you coming? </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I long to see you. Well brother, you have it on your conscience that I’m so happy today that it made me cry. Thanks for everything, old chap, and believe me, with a handshake in thought,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>On 4 July the director of the University Hospital in Leiden registered the birth of <rs type="pers" key="466">Willem Hoornik</rs> on 2 July 1882; <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs>’s occupation was given as ‘seamstress’. When Sien married Arnoldus Franciscus van Wijk (deceased 12 March 1916) at Rotterdam on 4 September 1901, he recognised Willem as his son. Willem van Wijk, as he was known from then on, died on 4 November 1958 at Maastricht (<hi rend="ital">GAM</hi>). See also <ref target="let224.xml">letter 224</ref> and Hulsker 1993-2, pp. 41-53; cf. Wilkie 1978, pp. 181-207 (he insinuates that Van Gogh was the father).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="990">Albrecht Dürer</rs>, <hi rend="ital">The promenade</hi>, c. 1497-1498, engraving (H83, B94). <rs type="ill" key="87">Ill. 87</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>‘White discharge’ is an abnormal, profuse mucous secretion from the vagina and the womb, also known as <hi rend="ital">fluor albus</hi>. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>St John’s growth is the new growth on trees around St John’s day, i.e. 24 June.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The two drawings are <hi rend="ital">Sien’s mother’s house</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2373">F 941/ JH 146</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Sien’s mother’s house </hi>(<rs type="otherart" key="251">F 942/ JH 147</rs>); the second is the larger. Van Gogh wrote his letter in this house at Slijkeinde, corner of Breedstraat 31a.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>