<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, between about Tuesday, 12 and Sunday, 17 September 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let263"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">263</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">R12</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">264</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Anthon van Rappard</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about Tuesday, 12 and Sunday, 17 September 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:physDesc>
                        <vg:decoration>
                            <vg:decoList xml:id="sketches">
                                <vg:decoItem n="A" xml:id="sketch-1">
                                    <vg:decoDesc>
<p>
      <hi rend="ital">Four people and a baby on a bench</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="65">F - / JH 198</rs>), letter sketch</p>
                                    </vg:decoDesc>
                                </vg:decoItem>
                            </vg:decoList>
                        </vg:decoration>
                    </vg:physDesc>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, between about Tuesday, 12 and Sunday, 17 September 1882.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b8346 V/2006</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh is working on the watercolour <hi rend="ital">Four people and a baby on a bench</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2395">F 951 / JH 197</rs>) – as is also evident from the letter sketch. In <ref target="let262.xml">letter 262</ref> of 11 September he tells Theo too that he is at work on this subject. In addition, to Van Rappard he mentions the same set of three prints by Lançon that were listed in <ref target="let261.xml">letter 261</ref> (of 9 September). Because, furthermore, he says that recently he has often worked on the beach <ref target="#l-50">(l. 50)</ref> and tells Theo on 17 September ‘Have been to Scheveningen quite often lately’ (<ref target="let264.xml">letter 264</ref>), we have dated the letter between about Tuesday, 12 and Sunday, 17 September 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 8346" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001591_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001591_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001591_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001591_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001591_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 8346" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001591_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001591_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001591_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001591_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001591_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001591_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Amice Rappard,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Het doet me genoegen U bijgaande houtsneden <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>te kunnen zenden<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge zult zien echter dat <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ook deze wat gehavend zijn op de vouwen, dat <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>komt niet door ’t zenden maar veeleer door dat <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>ze zoo lang in een leesinrigting<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> dienst hebben <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>gedaan. Doch ge zult ze wel plakken kunnen <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>net als ik ’t zelf ook heel dikwijls moet doen. <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Schrijf me eens of ge hebt van Percy McQuoid <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>een vrouwen figuurtje met een licht<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> in de hand <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>op den trap van een Wapenzaal waar men een harnas <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>ziet glinsteren.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Ik meen dat ge het reeds van me <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>hebt<c type="kk">/</c> even als een meisje in ’t wit tegen een <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>boom geleund<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> doch hebt ge ’t niet zoo zal ik <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>’t U bij gelegenheid er bij voegen. Mc Quoid is <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>een van de meest gedistingueerden onder de Engelsche <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>illustrateurs. Ik denk wel ge schik zult hebben in <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>de Renouards – misschien kan ik er later <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>nog eenigen bijvoegen daar de jood<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> mij zeide <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>t’huis nog een gedeelte van den rommel tijdschriften <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>te hebben (waaruit ik deze en de mijnen nam)<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>die hij, omdat ze te veel gehavend waren, <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>niet meegebragt had<c type="kp">_</c>– Als ik tijd heb ga ik dien <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>rommel doorzoeken – wat anders geen prettig <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>karweitje is.</ab>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">De Grève des charbonniers<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> vind ik voor mij superbe<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>ik geloof dat die U ook zal bevallen.</ab>
                <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb veel moeite gedaan dingen van de mijnwerkers <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> dit en een Engelsche van een accident<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>zijn de mooisten – anders worden er weinig <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>zulke motieven gemaakt – ik wou ik zelf <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>daar nog eens studies van kon maken vroeger of later. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Schrijf me eens, als ge wilt, Rappard, <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>in vollen ernst of gij – gesteld dat ik <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>er nog eens heenging b.v. voor 2 maanden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>naar die mijnstreek in de Borinage – lust <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>zoudt hebben zamen te gaan.</ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is een tamelijk lastig landje – zoo’n <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>togt is geen pleizierreisje – maar ’t is <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>een van de dingen die ik<c type="kk">/</c> zoodra ik mij <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>nog wat sterker gevoel in het bliksemsnel <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>teekenen van lui in beweging<c type="kk">/</c> enorm graag <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zou ondernemen. wetende dat er zoo veel moois daar <lb n="43a" xml:id="l-43a"/>zou te maken zijn – en dat nog weinig of niet door anderen is geschilderd.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Omdat men echter met allerlei bezwaren te <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>kampen heeft in zoo’n streek is het niet overbodig <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>met zijn tweeën te gaan.</ab>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Nu</hi> zouden mijn omstandigheden ’t ook <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>nog niet toelaten – maar het is een <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>gedachte die diep in mij geworteld zit.</ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dikwijls werk ik in den laatsten tijd op ’t strand <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>’t zij om te teekenen t’zij om te schilderen. <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>En telkens meer trekt de zee mij aan.</ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik weet niet wat Uw ervaring is van omgang <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>met artisten hier – ik heb al meer <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>dan eens ondervonden van lui dat ze zeer <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>hatelijk op wat zij noemen “het illustratieve” begonnen <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>te schelden op een manier die mij zeer duidelijk bewees <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>dat zij volstrekt niet op de hoogte van de kwestie waren<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>volstrekt niet wisten wat er op dat gebied omgaat. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>En ook niet te overtuigen waren of liever niet <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>verkozen zich de moeite te geven zelfs naar een <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>of ander te kijken. Of als ze er naar keken <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>was ’t voor een korten tijd in hun hoofd en dan <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>weer er radikaal uit.</ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu het is mijn ondervinding van U dat gij er <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>anders over denkt.</ab>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb onlangs nog dingen gevonden van Lançon<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>een soepuitdeeling – een Rendez vous des chiffonniers<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Balayeurs de neige<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> waar ik s’nachts voor <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>opstond om ze nog eens te bekijken<c type="kk">/</c> zoo sterk <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>was de indruk die ze op mij maakten.</ab>
                <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>
<ab rend="indent">En vooral terwijl ik zelf er op sjouw om iets <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>te maken van die dingen die mij gedurig meer <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>interesseeren op straat<c type="kk">/</c> in de wachtkamer 3<hi rend="ss">e</hi> klasse<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>op ’t strand<c type="kk">/</c> in een gasthuis<c type="kk">/</c> neemt mijn respect <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>voor die groote teekenaars van het volk zooals <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>b.v. Renouard of Lancon of Doré of Morin <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>of Gavarni of Dumaurier of Ch<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Keene of <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>Howard Pyle of Hopkins of Herkomer en Frank Hol <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>en talloozen meer<c type="kk">/</c> toe.</ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Misschien gaat het U ook eenigermate zoo. <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>Enfin – wat hier ook van zij – het interesseert <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>me steeds in hooge mate dat gij op verschillende <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>sujetten sjouwt die mij ook zeer sympathiek <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>zijn en het spijt mij wel eens dat wij tamelijk ver van <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>elkaar zijn &amp; betrekkelijk weinig van elkaar merken <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>kunnen.</ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> de tijd tot schrijven ontbreekt mij, ontvang een <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>handdruk in gedachten en geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
<ab>Ziehier in groote haast een krabbel <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>van een aquarel waaraan ik doende ben.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear friend <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>,</ab>
      <ab>I’m pleased to be able to send you the enclosed woodcuts. You’ll see, though, that these too are rather tattered at the folds. That’s not because of going through the post, but because they were kept for so long in a subscription library.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> But you’ll be able to glue them together, as I very often have to do myself. Write and tell me whether you have a female figure by <rs type="pers" key="1188">Percy Macquoid</rs> holding a candle on the stairs of an armoury where the gleam of a suit of armour can be seen.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> I believe you’ve already had it from me, together with a girl in white leaning against a tree,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> but if you don’t have it I’ll send it when the opportunity arises. Macquoid is one of the most distinguished of the English illustrators. I think you’ll like the <rs type="pers" key="1292">Renouard</rs>s. I may be able to add some more later, since the Jew<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> told me he still had more of that jumble of magazines at home (from which I took these and my own) which he hadn’t brought along because they were too tattered. When I have time I’m going to look through his jumble — which isn’t a pleasant task, by the way. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think The miners’ strike<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> is superb, I believe it will please you too. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I made a big effort to get things with miners — this and an English one of an accident<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> are the best — such subjects are rarely handled, by the way. I would like to do studies of them myself sooner or later. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> Write to me if you would, <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>, in earnest whether — supposing I were to go for 2 months, say, to the mining region in the Borinage — you would like to go with me. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s quite a difficult part of the world — the journey is no pleasure trip — but it’s one of the things I would love to undertake as soon as I feel more confident about making lightning sketches of people in motion — knowing that there are such beautiful things to do there, which as yet have rarely been painted by others, if at all.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But because one has to deal with all sorts of difficulties in a region like that, there’s every reason to go together. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">At present</hi> my circumstances don’t permit it – but this is an idea that’s deeply rooted in me. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve often worked on the beach recently, either drawing or painting. And the sea attracts me more and more. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t know what your experience of getting on with artists here has been like — I’ve found more than once that people began to rail viciously against what they called ‘the illustrative’ in a manner that to me very clearly proved they had no understanding of the matter at all, were completely unaware of what’s going on in that sphere. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> And were also not to be persuaded, or rather chose not to even take the trouble to look at a few things. Or if they did look, it was in their head for a short time and then straight out again. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now my experience of you has been that you think differently.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve recently found some things by <rs type="pers" key="1146">Lançon</rs> — a soup distribution, a gathering of rag-pickers, gang of snow-shovellers<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> — which made me get up at night to take another look at them, that’s how strong an impression they made on me. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And especially while I myself toil away to make something of the things that interest me more and more on the street, in the 3rd-class waiting room, on the beach, in a hospital, my respect grows for the great portrayers of the people such as, for example, <rs type="pers" key="1292">Renouard</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1146">Lançon</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="998">Doré</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1236">Morin</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1043">Gavarni</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1197">Du Maurier</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1137">C. Keene</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1285">Howard Pyle</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1092">Hopkins</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1080">Herkomer</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1089">Frank Holl</rs> and countless others.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Perhaps this has been your experience to some extent too. Well – whatever the case — I find it highly interesting that you’re toiling at various subjects that I also think are most appealing, and sometimes I regret that we live quite far apart and can see relatively little of each other.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, I haven’t the time to write, accept a handshake in thought, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab>
                    <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Here’s a scratch in great haste of a watercolour I’m working on.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>A subscription library offered books and magazines on loan for payment. In some cases the members could take out subscriptions to a package put together by the library. Cf. in this connection the ‘Voorwaarden van Abonnement in de Leesinrichting’ of <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M. van Gogh</rs>, bookseller and art dealer (<hi rend="ital">SAAm</hi>). On this subject see the contributions to ‘Lezen in rangen en standen. Negentiende-eeuwse bibliotheken opnieuw bezien’, <hi rend="ital">De Negentiende Eeuw</hi> 24 (no. 3-4), December 2000.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘een kaars’ (a candle).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The wood engraving <hi rend="ital">The haunted armoury</hi> after a work by <rs type="pers" key="1188">Percy Thomas Macquoid</rs> appeared as the frontispiece of <hi rend="ital">The Graphic</hi> 22 (July-December 1880). Van Gogh had a copy of this. <rs type="ill" key="1088">Ill. 1088</rs>. (t*175).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
      <ab>The print <hi rend="ital">Reflections</hi> after <rs type="pers" key="1188">Percy Thomas Macquoid</rs> appeared in the special Christmas number of <hi rend="ital">The Illustrated London News</hi> of 1874 (vol. 65, nos. 1843-1844), p. 20. <rs type="ill" key="1092">Ill. 1092</rs>. It bears a striking similarity to Van Gogh’s painting <hi rend="ital">A girl in a wood</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2387">F 8 / JH 182</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The ‘book Jew’ <rs type="pers" key="294">David</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="293">Jozef Blok</rs>: <ref target="let199.xml">see letter 199</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Van Gogh is referring to the engraving mentioned in <ref target="let272.xml">letter 272</ref>, <hi rend="ital">Grève de mineurs</hi> (A miners’ strike) by <rs type="pers" key="1537">Eugène Froment</rs> after <rs type="pers" key="1329">Alfred Philippe Roll</rs> in <hi rend="ital">L’Illustration</hi> 78 (29 October 1881), pp. 288-289. <rs type="ill" key="1950">Ill. 1950</rs>. A smaller version is the engraving by <rs type="pers" key="1601">Auguste Trichon</rs> in <hi rend="ital">L’Univers Illustré</hi> 23 (12 June 1880), no. 1316, p. 373.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Probably <rs type="pers" key="999">Alfred Edward Emslie</rs>, <hi rend="ital">A colliery explosion. Volunteers to the rescue</hi>, engraved by <rs type="pers" key="1537">Eugène Froment</rs>, in <hi rend="ital">The Illustrated London News</hi> 80 (25 February 1882), unpaginated, between pp. 200-201. <rs type="ill" key="1951">Ill. 1951</rs>. In <ref target="let272.xml">letter 272</ref> Van Gogh writes about this print, again in connection with <rs type="pers" key="1329">Roll</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Van Gogh added ‘knowing that there are such beautiful things to do there, which as yet have rarely been painted by others, if at all’ later.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
      <ab>For these three prints by <rs type="pers" key="1146">Auguste Lançon</rs>, <ref target="let261.xml#n-5">see letter 261, nn. 5</ref>
                        <ref target="let261.xml#n-7">-7.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The letter sketch <hi rend="ital">Four people and a baby on a bench </hi>(<rs type="sketch" key="65">F - / JH 198</rs>) is after the watercolour with the same title <rs type="ill" key="2395">F 951 / JH 197</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>