<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 26 August 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let259"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">259</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">226</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">259</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 26 August 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Saturday, 26 August 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>The parents’ move to Nuenen <ref target="let247.xml">(247)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b248 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Zaturdag avond’. In earlier editions this Saturday was said to be 19 August 1882. Roland Dorn correctly proposed 26 August 1882, though without any supporting arguments. See exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 96 (n. 1).</p>
<p rend="indent">The gales, storms and rain ‘all this week’ which Van Gogh talks about provide support for Dorn’s thesis. From 19 August the weather became turbulent: on 21 August the wind reached force 8, on the 22nd there was a storm (force 9-10 wind and heavy rain). Extra high water was forecast for this day (<hi rend="ital">KNMI</hi>). Since Van Gogh speaks of the tempestuous waves and the fact that the water came close to the dunes <ref target="#l-143">(ll. 143-147)</ref>, this letter must date from the Saturday after the bad weather, thus 26 August 1882. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0248" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000302_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000302_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000302_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000302_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000302_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0248" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000302_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000302_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000302_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000302_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000302_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000302_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Zaturdag avond.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Ontvang mijn hartelijken dank voor Uw brief en <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>voor het ingeslotene. Zoodra ik Uw brief ontving <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>heb ik in eens nog voor zeven gulden verf gekocht <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>om weder wat voorraad te hebben &amp; de leemtes aan <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>te vullen. Wij hebben hier gedurende de geheele week <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>veel wind<c type="kk">/</c> storm<c type="kk">/</c> regen gehad, en ik ben talrijke <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>malen naar Schevening geweest om het te zien. <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>En heb er twee kleine marines van teruggebragt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>In het eene zit reeds veel zand – maar het tweede<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>toen het eigentlijk stormde en de zee tot zeer digt aan <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>de duinen stond<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik tweemaal geheel moeten <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>afschrappen om reden van de dikke laag zand die <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>het geheel bedekte. Het waaide zoo dat ik mij haast <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>niet kon staande houden en haast niet kijken <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>door het stuiven<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb het er toch zoeken op te <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>krijgen door nadat ik ’t afgeschrabt had in een klein <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>herbergje achter de duinen het er onmiddelijk weer <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>op te zetten en van daar uit weer te gaan kijken. <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Zoodat ik er toch een paar souvenirs van heb.–<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>Maar een ander souvenir is dat ik weer koude <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>heb gevat met de gevolgen die ge weet<c type="kk">/</c> die mij gedurende <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>een paar dagen nu dwingen ’thuis te blijven. <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>In dien tusschentijd heb ik eenige figuurstudies <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>geschilderd – ik stuur U twee krabbeltjes<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het schilderen van figuur trekt mij zeer aan – het <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>moet echter nog rijpen – ik moet meer het procede <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>leeren kennen – dat wat men wel eens noemt <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>“la cuisine de l'art”<c type="kp">_</c> In ’t begin zal ik veel <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>moeten afkrabben – dikwijls op nieuw beginnen – <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>maar ik gevoel ik er mee leer, en het mij een <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>nieuwen frisschen blik op de dingen geeft.</ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als gij weer stuurt zal ik wat goede marterpenseelen <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>opdoen die de eigentlijke <hi rend="ital">teeken</hi>penseelen zijn <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>naar ik merk – om een hand of profiel mee te <hi rend="ital">teekenen</hi> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>met kleur.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Ook voor fijne boomtakken &amp;c. zijn ze <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>bepaald noodig merk ik. de Lyonsche kwasten<c type="kk">/</c> al zijn ze fijn<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>maken te breede streepen of toetsen.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Mijn schilderpapier<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> is ook <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>haast op – tegen 1 Sept. zal het er nog al op aankomen om nog eenige dingen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>te nemen maar ik zal er komen met het gewone.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dan wilde ik U nog eens zeggen dat ik verschillende <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>dingen in Uw schrijven geheel met U eens ben. <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Voornamelijk dat ik ten volle toestem dat Pa en Moe <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>met al hun voor &amp; tegen personen zijn die in den <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>tegenwoordigen tijd zeer zeldzaam te vinden zijn – hoe langer <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>hoe schaarscher worden – en misschien is ’t nieuwe gaar niet<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>beter – en die men dus te meer moet apprecieeren. <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Ik voor mij apprecieer hen dan ook wel degelijk<c type="kk">/</c> alleen <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>ik vrees dat datgene waaromtrent gij hen nu voorloopig <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>gerustgesteld hebt – vooral in geval ze mij weerzagen – <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>zou terugkeeren. Zij zullen nooit kunnen vatten wat <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>schilderen is – niet het begrip krijgen dat een figuurtje <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>van een spitter – eenige voren omgeploegden grond – <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>een brokje zand<c type="kk">/</c> zee en lucht<c type="kk">/</c> serieuse motieven <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>zijn &amp; zóó moeielijk maar ook zóó mooi dat <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>het wel degelijk de moeite waard is zijn leven <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>er aan te wijden die poezij welke er in is weer <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>te geven. Tevens wanneer in vervolg van tijd<c type="kk">/</c> nog <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>meer dan nu<c type="kk">/</c> zij mij zouden zien ploeteren en <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>sjouwen op mijn werk – het weer uitkrabben en <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>veranderen – het nu eens streng vergelijken met <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>de natuur – en dan weer er eene verandering <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>in brengen zoodat zij niet precies het plekje meer <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>herkennen of het figuur – dan zal dat hun <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>steeds eene teleurstelling blijven – zij zullen niet <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>kunnen begrijpen dat het schilderen niet in eens gaat <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>en steeds weer in de gedachte vervallen “dat ik <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>het eigentlijk niet ken”<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-o-b"/> en dat echte schilders op een <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>heel andere manier zouden werken.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin ik durf mij geen illusies scheppen en vrees wel <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>het niet zal gebeuren dat Pa en Moe werkelijk opregt <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>er schik in zullen hebben<c type="kp">_</c>– Dit is geen wonder &amp; het is hun <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>schuld niet – zij hebben niet geleerd te zien zooals gij <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>en ik het geleerd hebben<c type="kk">/</c> zij kijken naar andere dingen <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>dan wij en dezelfde dingen zien we niet met dezelfde <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>oogen<c type="kk">/</c> zij wekken niet dezelfde gedachten op.</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Te wenschen zulks anders kon zijn is gepermitteerd<c type="kk">/</c> het <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>te verwachten is mijns inziens niet verstandig.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zij zullen zich moeielijk mijn gemoedsstemming kunnen <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>begrijpen en niet weten wat mij drijft als zij mij dingen <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>zien doen die hun vreemd &amp; zonderling voorkomen – ze <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>wijten aan ontevredenheid<c type="kk">/</c> onverschilligheid of nonchallance <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>als er toch iets anders in den grond ligt, namelijk <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>de lust om coute qui coute datgene na te loopen <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>wat ik voor mijn werk hebben moet. Zij hebben nu het <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>oog misschien op het “schilderen <hi rend="ital">met olieverf</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> nu <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>zal het dan eindelijk komen – en och wat zal het <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>hun tegenvallen als zij het zien zouden, vrees ik, en <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>zij er niets dan klonten verf in zullen zien – tevens<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>zij beschouwen het teekenen als een “<hi rend="ital">voorbereidende</hi> <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">studie</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> een expressie waar ik sedert jaren onuitsprekelijk <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>het land aan heb en zoo onjuist mogelijk vind. Zooals ge <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>trouwens weet. <lb n="96a" xml:id="l-96a"/>En als zij mij dat evenveel zien doen als vroeger zullen zij denken ik nog steeds aan die voorbereidende studie ben. <lb n="96"/>Enfin. Maar we willen ’t beste <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>hopen en ons best doen om hun gerust te stellen.</ab>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat ge mij mededeelt omtrent hunne nieuwe omgeving <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>interesseert mij ten hoogste. Zeer zeker zou ik <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>wat graag zoo'n oud kerkje &amp; kerkhof met zandgraven <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>en oude houten kruisen trachten te maken.</ab>
                <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoop wel dat het er eens van komen zal.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> Dan <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>schrijft ge over een stuk hei &amp; mastbosch vlak in de <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>buurt – wel<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb een altijddurend heimwee naar <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>hei &amp; masthout met de eigenaardige figuren.<lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/> Een vrouwtje dat hout sprokkelt – een boertje dat zand <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>haalt – enfin dat eenvoudige dat iets groots heeft als <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>de zee<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>
<ab rend="indent">Steeds is bij mij de gedachte om als zich de gelegenheid <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>eens voordoet – de omstandigheden er toe leiden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>mij ergens geheel buiten te vestigen.</ab>
                <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ofschoon ik hier overvloed van stof heb – het bosch<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>het strand<c type="kk">/</c> de Rijswijksche weilanden vlak bij en <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>dus ook letterlijk bij elken voetstap een motief. <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>Het zou zijn ook om reden van goedkooper wonen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>Maar er is nu op ’t moment zoover ik zie geen bepaalde <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>aanleiding en dus ’t heeft geen haast.</ab>
                <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>
<ab rend="indent">Alleen ik zeg het U om U te doen begrijpen hoe <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>sympathiek mij zoo'n landstreek is als die welke <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>gij beschrijft als de nieuwe woonplaats van Pa en Moe.</ab>
                <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik gevoel mij dezer dagen regt gelukkig door het <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>schilderen. Ik heb mij heel wat ingehouden en bepaald <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>tot het teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> juist omdat ik zooveel treurige histories 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>weet van lui die er zich onbekookt<anchor n="c" xml:id="note-o-c"/> inwierpen – het in ’t <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>procedé zochten en gedesillusioneerd wakker werden <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>zonder iets gevorderd te zijn en tot over de ooren zich in <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>de schulden gestoken hadden door de dure dingen die <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>zij verknoeid hadden. Daar heb ik van meet af aan een <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>schrik en huivering voor gehad – ik heb het teekenen beschouwd <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>en beschouw het ook nog als het eenige middel om <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>hetzelfde lot niet te deelen. En heb het teekenen lief gekregen <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>in plaats van het als een last te beschouwen. Nu echter <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>geeft, ongedacht bijna, het schilderen mij veel ruimte<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>stelt mij in staat effekten aan te grijpen vroeger ongenaakbaar<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>juist die welke mij toch après tout ’t meest sympathiek <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>zijn en ’t geeft me in veel kwesties zooveel meer licht <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>en nieuwe middelen om effekten uit te drukken <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>dat dit een en ander mij regt gelukkig maakt.</ab>
                <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het was toch zoo mooi op Schevening dezer dagen<c type="kp">_</c> De zee was vóór die <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>storm haast nog imposanter dan toen het eigentlijk storm was<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>Gedurende den storm zag men de golven veel minder en was er <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>minder een effekt als van de voren van een omgeploegd land<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>De golven volgden zoo snel op elkander dat de een den ander <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>verdrong en er ontstond door de botsing van de watermassas <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>een soort schuim als stuifzand dat het eerste plan van de zee <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>als in een soort waas hulde. Maar het was anders een <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>nijdig stormpje – te nijdiger – en als men er wat lang op <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>keek te indrukwekkender omdat het zoo weinig lawaai <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>maakte<c type="kp">_</c> De zee had een kleur van vuil zeepsop<c type="kp">_</c> Er was <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>daar op die plek een pinkje<c type="kk">/</c> ’t laatste van de rij<c type="kk">/</c> en eenige <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>donkere figuurtjes.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Er is in ’t schilderen iets oneindigs – ik <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>kan het U niet zoo uitleggen – maar juist voor het uitdrukken <lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>van stemming is het zoo heerlijk. Er zijn in de kleuren <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>verborgen dingen van harmonie of contrasten die van zelf <lb n="155" xml:id="l-155"/>medewerken, en waar men anders geen partij van trekken kan.<anchor n="d" xml:id="note-o-d"/> <lb n="156" xml:id="l-156"/>Morgen hoop ik weer eens naar buiten te kunnen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="157" xml:id="l-157"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb nog van Zola gelezen La faute de l'abbé Mouret<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> en Son Excellence <lb n="158" xml:id="l-158"/>Eugène Rougon<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> ook mooi. Een nobel figuur vind ik <lb n="159" xml:id="l-159"/>Pascal Rougon<c type="kk">/</c> de dokter – die in de verschillende werken <lb n="160" xml:id="l-160"/>voorkomt<c type="kk">/</c> echter steeds op den achtergrond. Hij is wel een bewijs <lb n="161" xml:id="l-161"/>dat hoe verdorven een ras ook zij het steeds mogelijk blijft <lb n="162" xml:id="l-162"/>door wilskracht en principes de fataliteit te overwinnen. <lb n="163" xml:id="l-163"/>Hij vond in zijn vak eene kracht die sterker was dan de <lb n="164" xml:id="l-164"/>natuur die hij van zijn familie had en in plaats van zich aan <lb n="165" xml:id="l-165"/>zijn natuurlijke neigingen over te geven ging hij een regten<c type="kk">/</c> helderen <lb n="166" xml:id="l-166"/>weg en verviel niet in dat troebele water waar al de andere Rougons <lb n="167" xml:id="l-167"/>in verzopen.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> Hij en M<hi rend="ss">me</hi> Francois<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> uit le ventre de Paris zijn mij de <lb n="168" xml:id="l-168"/>meest sympathieke figuren. Nu à dieu, ik denk veel aan U en <lb n="169" xml:id="l-169"/>dol graag zou ik U nu en dan eens zien. Ontvang een handdruk <lb n="170" xml:id="l-170"/>in gedachten en geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="170*" xml:id="l-170s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="170"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
<ab>Terwijl ik dezen schrijf heb ik nog een studie gemaakt van een jongen<c type="kk">/</c> grisaille: houtskool<c type="kk">/</c> olie en heel weinig kleur<c type="kk">/</c> alleen voor <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>den toon.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-95" n="95">het land aan heb &lt; het land heb <hi rend="ital">(cf. letter 258)</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-42" n="42">grisaille: &lt; grisaille</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Saturday evening.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Please accept my sincere thanks for your letter and the enclosure. As soon as I received your letter I bought seven guilders’ worth of paint in one go in order to have a supply in reserve and fill up the gaps. All this week we’ve had gales, storms and rain here, and I’ve been to Scheveningen many times to see it. And came back with two small seascapes. There’s already a lot of sand in the one, but with the second, when there really was a storm and the sea came very close to the dunes, I had to scrape everything off twice because of the thick layer of sand completely covering it. The wind was so strong that I could barely stay on my feet and barely see through the clouds of sand. I tried to get it down anyway by immediately painting it again in a small inn behind the dunes, after first scraping it all off, and then going out to take another look from there. So I have a couple of souvenirs after all.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> But another souvenir is that I’ve caught a cold again, with the results you know about, which now force me to stay at home for a few days. In the meantime I’ve painted some figure studies — I’m sending you two scratches.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
    <ab rend="indent">Figure painting attracts me enormously, but it still has to ripen. I need to become better acquainted with the method — what is sometimes called ‘the cookery of art’. In the beginning I’ll have to scrape off a great deal — and often make a new start – but I feel that I’m learning as a result, and that it gives me a new, fresh view of things. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When you next send, I’ll get some good sable brushes. They’re the proper <hi rend="ital">drawing</hi> brushes, I find — for <hi rend="ital">drawing</hi> a hand or profile in colour.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> For delicate tree branches, &amp;c. they’re really essential, I find. The Lyon brushes, though fine, make lines and strokes that are too broad.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> My painting paper<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> is almost finished too — by 1 Sept. I’ll also need to get some other items quite urgently, but I’ll manage with the usual. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now I wanted to tell you that I entirely agree with various things in your letter. Above all, that I absolutely concur that <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs>, with all their pros and cons, are people who are very rare in this day and age — and all the more so as time passes — and perhaps the new is by no means better — and whom one therefore ought to appreciate all the more. For my part I do indeed appreciate them, only I fear that what you have now reassured them about for the time being would come back, especially if they saw me again. They’ll never be able to grasp what painting is, never understand that a figure of a digger — a few furrows of ploughed land — a bit of sand, sea and sky, are serious subjects and so difficult, but so beautiful too that it’s well worth the trouble of devoting one’s life to depicting the poetry that’s in them. Also, whenever in the future, even more than now, they should see me slogging and toiling away at my work — scratching out and altering — now making a close comparison with nature, and then introducing a change so that they can no longer exactly recognize the spot or the figure, that will always be a disappointment to them. They’ll be unable to understand that painting isn’t done at a stroke, and they’ll always fall back on the idea ‘that I can’t really do it’, and that real painters work in a totally different way. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">In short, I dare not cherish any illusions and do fear that <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs> will never take any real pleasure in it. This is hardly surprising and it’s not their fault — they haven’t learned to see as you and I have learned. They look at different things from us, and we don’t see the same things with the same eyes; they don’t evoke the same thoughts. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">To wish that it could be different is permissible, to expect it is in my view unwise. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">They’ll find it difficult to understand my state of mind, and not know what drives me when they see me do things that seem strange and peculiar to them — will blame them on dissatisfaction, indifference or nonchalance, while the cause lies elsewhere, namely the desire, at all costs, to pursue what I must have for my work. Now they may be waiting expectantly for ‘painting <hi rend="ital">in oils</hi>’. Now it will come at last, and oh how disappointed they’ll be should they see it, I fear, seeing nothing but globs of paint in it. Besides, they regard drawing as a ‘<hi rend="ital">preparatory study</hi>’, a term I’ve detested for years and believe is as incorrect as possible. As you well know. And if they see me doing that just as much as in the past, they’ll think I’m still engaged in preparatory study. Well. But we’ll hope for the best and do our best to reassure them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">What you say about their new surroundings is most interesting. I certainly would like to try doing that kind of old church and churchyard with sandy graves and old wooden crosses. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hope it will happen one day.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> You also write about a stretch of heath and a pine-wood nearby. Well, I have an everlasting nostalgia for heath and pine-woods with the curious figures. A woman gathering wood, a peasant fetching sand — in short, that simplicity that has something grand like the sea. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I always have in mind the idea of moving to the country if an opportunity arises, if circumstances suggest it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Although I have an abundance of material here — the woods, the beach, the Rijswijk meadows close by, and thus literally a subject at every footstep. It would also be for the sake of living more cheaply. But at the moment there’s no particular reason, as far as I can see, so there’s no urgency. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I only mention it so that you’ll understand how attracted I am by a country district like the one you describe that’s <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs>’s new home.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve been made deeply happy by painting these last few days. I’ve really restrained myself and stuck to drawing, precisely because I know so many sad stories 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> of people who threw themselves into it unprepared — they concentrated on method and woke up disillusioned, without having made any progress, and got deep into debt because of the expensive things they botched. From the start I felt a fear and horror of that — I regarded and still regard drawing as the only way of avoiding the same fate. And drawing has become dear to my heart, rather than being a burden. Now, though, almost unexpectedly, painting has given me lots of room, enables me to tackle effects that used to be out of reach, especially those I find, after all, most appealing, and it gives me so much more insight into many issues and new means of expressing effects, so that all this makes me deeply happy. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s been so beautiful at Scheveningen the last few days. The sea was almost more imposing before the storm than when the storm actually arrived. During the storm the waves were less visible and there was less the effect of furrows of ploughed land. The waves followed each other so quickly that each pushed the other aside, and the collision between these bodies of water produced a sort of foam like drifting sand that shrouded the foreground of the sea in a haze. But it was a nasty little storm — all the nastier — and all the more impressive the longer you looked, because it made so little noise. The sea was the colour of dirty dishwater. At that spot there was a fishing-boat, the last in the row, and several dark figures.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> There’s something infinite about painting — I can’t quite explain — but especially for expressing a mood, it’s a joy. In the colours there are hidden harmonies or contrasts which contribute of their own accord, and which if left unused are of no benefit. Tomorrow I hope to be able to go outdoors again. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve also read <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs>’s La faute de l’abbé Mouret<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> and Son Excellence Eugène Rougon,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> also beautiful. I find Pascal Rougon, the doctor, a noble figure — he appears in various works, but always in the background. He is proof that, however corrupt a lineage may be, it’s always possible to overcome fate through willpower and principles. In his profession he found a strength that was greater than that of the nature he inherited from his family, and instead of giving in to his natural tendencies he followed a straight, clear path, and didn’t slip into the murky waters in which all the other Rougons drowned.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> He and Mme François<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> in Le ventre de Paris are the most sympathetic figures to me. Well, adieu, I think of you often and would love to see you from time to time. Accept a handshake in thought, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>While writing this I’ve done another study of a boy, grisaille: charcoal, oil and very little colour, just for the tone.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The seascape painted on 22 August, ‘when there was really a storm’, is unknown (cf. <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>). The other is <hi rend="ital">View of the sea at Scheveningen </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2390">F 4 / JH 187</rs>). See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 36-42, cat. no. 2. Dorn assumes that this latter work was done during the storm; see exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 98, cat. no. 19.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Which painted figure studies are referred to here is not known; for similar works, cf. <hi rend="ital">Fisherman on the beach</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2391">F5 / JH 188</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Scheveningen woman</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2392">F 6 / JH 189</rs>). The two ‘sketches’ are not known. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Sable brushes, the most expensive kind, are relatively soft and naturally retain a sharp point. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>‘Lyon brushes’ are made of pig hair and also have a good reputation. They were fairly new and available in various widths and hardnesses. See Carlyle 1991, vol. 1, pp. 304-305, and cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 40 (n. 10).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>For painting paper, <ref target="let255.xml#n-3">see letter 255, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘geheel niet’ (by no means).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-o-b">
<ab>Read: ‘kan’ (can).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Theo had evidently suggested the old church tower and the graveyard beside it at Nuenen as a subject. When Vincent later settled in the village, he did indeed draw and paint this location, for example in <hi rend="ital">The old church tower at Nuenen with a ploughman</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2453">F 34 / JH 459</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The old tower</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2471">F 88 / JH 490</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The old tower</hi> <hi rend="ital">in the snow</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="364">F 87 / JH 600</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">The old church tower at Nuenen (‘The peasants’ churchyard’) </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2512">F 84 / JH 772</rs>). See also <ref target="let269.xml">letters 269</ref>, <ref target="let271.xml">271</ref>, <ref target="let356.xml">356</ref>, <ref target="let361.xml">361</ref>, <ref target="let377.xml">377</ref> and <ref target="let489.xml">489</ref>. In <ref target="let502.xml">letter 502</ref> he says he has done his first watercolour of it. See also De Brouwer 2000.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="c" xml:id="n-c" target="#note-o-c">
<ab>Means: ‘onbezonnen’, ‘ondoordacht’ (rash, ill-considered).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This description relates to the seascape. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="d" xml:id="n-d" target="#note-o-d">
<ab>Means: ‘voordeel, nut van hebben kan’ (take advantage, make use of).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>The leading character in <rs type="pers" key="836">Emile Zola</rs>’s novel <rs type="lit" key="253">
                            <hi rend="ital">La faute de l’abbé Mouret</hi>
                        </rs> (1875) is Serge Mouret, a somewhat naive young priest who is inclined towards mysticism. He becomes acquainted with the innocent ‘child of nature’ Albine, who lives with her uncle Jeanbernat and spends most of her time in his beautiful garden, ‘Le Paradou’. When Mouret falls ill, he stays with Jeanbernat to recuperate. Mouret and Albine fall violently in love, and they give free rein to their passion in the garden. As time passes, however, the priest feels obliged to opt for his vocation, and he breaks off the relationship. Albine then commits suicide by stupefying herself in her sleep with an abundance of scented flowers.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs>’s novel <rs type="lit" key="254">
                            <hi rend="ital">Son Excellence Eugène Rougon</hi>
                        </rs> (1876) is about ambition and power, which govern the ups and downs in the political career of the hero of the novel during the Second Empire. Rougon held an important position but then fell from power. As the result of complicated intriguing by a former mistress whom he abandoned, he again secures high office. But she is only helping him in order to exact vengeance, and she again brings him down. Nonetheless, the novel ends with a new ministerial post for Rougon.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>The aristocratic Rougon family, who are at the core of <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs>’s cycle of novels, are marked by physical and moral decline, depravity and opportunism. As Van Gogh describes, Doctor Pascal Rougon is exceptional in his love of medicine, his austerity and his modesty. This contrast is heightened because he devotes himself to studying heredity and makes his own family one of the objects of his research. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>For Mme François in <rs type="lit" key="246">
                            <hi rend="ital">Le ventre de Paris</hi>
                        </rs>, <ref target="let250.xml#n-12">see letter 250, n. 12.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>This charcoal study of a boy is not known. For ‘grisaille’, <ref target="let255.xml#n-4">see letter 255, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>