<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, between about Monday, 6 and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let208"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">208</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">179</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">208</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about Monday, 6 and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, between about Monday, 6 and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mauve’s <hi rend="ital">Fishing boat on the beach</hi> for the Salon <ref target="let194.xml">(194)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b200 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter was certainly written after 18 February 1882, because Van Gogh refers to a letter from Theo of that date <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, and before 11 March 1882, because that was when he heard of the completion of Mauve’s painting <hi rend="ital">Fishing boat on the beach</hi>, something he was not yet aware of when writing this letter (<ref target="#l-44">l. 44</ref> and <ref target="let210.xml">letter 210</ref>).</p>
    <p rend="indent">The ‘money for this month’ which Vincent requests <ref target="#l-63">(ll. 63-64)</ref> cannot have been the money for February, because Theo had sent money on 18 February and <ref target="let206.xml">letter 206</ref> is the first to include a response to this. It must therefore refer to the March allowance, about which Van Gogh wrote on 3 March, however, evidently for the first time that month (<ref target="let207.xml#l-88">letter 207, ll. 88 ff.</ref>). It seems only natural that a subsequent letter with the same request would not have been written until at least several days later. Moreover, it certainly dates from before 11 March, because in the letter written that day Vincent told Theo that he should meanwhile have received the present letter (and <ref target="let209.xml">letter 209</ref>). Even though this does not offer an exact date, we assume that this letter was written on or about Monday, 6 March at the earliest and on or about Thursday, 9 March 1882 at the latest.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0200" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000227_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000227_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000227_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000227_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000227_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0200" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000227_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000227_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000227_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000227_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000227_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000227_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>In Uw brief van 18 Februarij ll. zegt gij: <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>“Toen Tersteeg hier was spraken we natuurlijk over je <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>en hij zeide mij dat wanneer je iets noodig had je <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>gerust bij hem kondt komen.” &amp;c.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Doch waarom is het dan dat als ik Tersteeg dezer <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>dagen vroeg om f<c type="kp">_</c> 10. hij ze mij wel gaf doch vergezeld <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>van zoo veel reproches en ik zou haast zeggen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>beleedigingen dat ik mij haast niet kon inhouden, <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ofschoon ik mij heb ingehouden.</ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zou hem de f<c type="kp">_</c> 10 in ’t gezigt gesmeten hebben <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>als ’t voor mij geweest was doch ik moest het <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>model betalen dat eene arme zieke vrouw is <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>die ik niet <hi rend="ital">mag</hi> laten wachten. Dus hield <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ik me stil.</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zal evenwel in een half jaar <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>niet meer naar Tersteeg toe gaan <lb n="17a" xml:id="l-17a"/>of met hem spreken of hem mijn werk laten zien. <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Dat zeg ik niet tegen hem maar <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>ik zeg het tegen U.</ab>
                <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>
<ab rend="indent">Waarde Theo<c type="kk">/</c> gij zegt wel “zorg dat gij <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>goede vrienden met T. blijft want hij is voor <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>ons bijna als een oudere broer”<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Doch mijn beste kerel<c type="kk">/</c> hij moge tegen U <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>vriendelijk zijn doch ik heb gedurende jaren <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>met zijn onvriendelijken en harden kant te <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>maken gehad.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hij zou gelijk hebben met mij reproches te <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>maken als ik niet werkte doch het <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>is ongepermitteerd om iemand die hard <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>werkt en aanhoudend aan een moeielijk <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>geduldwerk<c type="kk">/</c> verwijtingen te doen als: <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>“dit staat bij me vast dat gij geen artist zijt”<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>“dit weegt bij mij zwaar dat gij te laat begonnen zijt”<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>“gij moet Uw brood verdienen”.</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dan zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> halt! zacht wat.–</ab>
                <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>
<ab rend="indent">Men kan niet altijd vrienden zijn<c type="kk">/</c> men <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>moet ook wel eens twisten.</ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat betreft de schikking tusschen U en mij <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>dat ik van U geld ontvang<c type="kk">/</c> daarover <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>verlang ik op nieuw met U in tegenwoordigheid <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>van Mauve en van niemand anders te spreken, <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>bij gelegenheid van Uwe komst te s’Hage <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>die hoop ik spoedig plaats zal vinden.</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het groote sch<hi rend="ss">ij</hi> van Mauve zal weldra af <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>zijn<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> alsdan zal Mauve <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>mij op nieuw wel een en ander te zeggen <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>hebben over het aquarelleeren.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>
<ab rend="indent">Doch Tersteeg kan werkelijk niet zóó <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>praten dat men er naar werken kan. <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Het resumé van wat Mauve mij tot dusverre <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>gezegd heeft is: <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Vincent als ge teekent dan zijt ge schilder.</hi> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>En daarom heb ik op het teekenen, <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>op de proportie<c type="kk">/</c> op de perspectief gewerkt <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>en hard gewerkt nu weken lang <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>en Tersteeg apprecieert dat niet genoeg <lb n="56a" xml:id="l-56a"/>en praat maar over “verkoopbaarheid”<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>In dezen verdien ik zijn verwijtingen <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>niet – toch wil ik mij inhouden <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>omdat ik wel degelijk achting voor <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ZEd. heb <lb n="60a" xml:id="l-60a"/>en hij er niet tegen kan dat men hem tegenspreekt.– <lb n="60"/>daarom zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> over een <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>half jaar spreken we elkaar nader – <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>in een half jaar spreken we elkaar niet.</ab>
                <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als gij kunt zend mij het geld voor <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>deze maand spoedig. Ik vorder <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>met mijn werk doch ik kan niet zonder <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>of met te weinig geld werken.</ab>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab rend="indent">Met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="67*" xml:id="l-67s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab>Ik wil liever in een half jaar geen <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>middageten gebruiken &amp; op die manier <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>bezuinigen dan dat ik weer <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>nu &amp; dan f<c type="kp">_</c> 10 van Tersteeg krijg<c type="kk">/</c> vergezeld <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>van zijn reproches.–</ab>
                <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zou wel eens willen weten wat <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>de schilders zeggen zouden van zijn <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>argument “minder model nemen <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>om de goedkoopte”<c type="kk">/</c> dan wanneer<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> men <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>modellen gevonden heeft, na veel zoeken, <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>die niet te duur zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zonder model werken is de pest voor <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>een figuurschilder<c type="kk">/</c> vooral in zijn <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>eersten tijd.–</ab>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als Tersteeg U zijn verwondering te kennen gaf <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>over eenige dingen die ik ZEd<c type="kp">_</c> gezegd had dan zal <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>hij zich over dit ook misschien verwonderen doch <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>ik wenschte wel dat hij er eens over wilde <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>nadenken of hij soms niet wat te ver gaat.– <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Verleden winter verzocht ik hem om eens met Mauve over <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>mij te spreken<c type="kk">/</c> hij behandelde dat toen ook uit de hoogte <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>en schreef mij “dat kan zeker niet”. Toch kon <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>het<c type="kk">/</c> bleek het later<c type="kk">/</c> en dus Tersteeg heeft niet <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>altijd gelijk.– En als T. dat verl. winter niet zoo <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>gedecideerd gezegd had dan was ik misschien eerder met <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>Mauve in kennis gekomen.–</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-33" n="33">begonnen zijt”<c type="kk">/</c> &lt; begonnen zijt</note>
<note target="l-34" n="34">verdienen”. &lt; verdienen.</note>
<note target="l-52" n="52">Vincent <supplied>
                            <hi rend="ital">...</hi>
                        </supplied> schilder. &lt; <hi rend="ital">Written on a seperate line; emphasis added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>In your letter of 18 February you said: ‘When <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> was here we naturally spoke about you, and he told me that whenever you needed anything you could feel easy about going to him’ &amp;c.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But why, then, when I asked <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> for 10 guilders the other day, did he give it to me with so many reproaches, and I’d almost say insults, that I almost couldn’t restrain myself, though I did restrain myself.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’d have thrown the 10 guilders in his face if it had been for me, but I had to pay the model, who’s a poor, sick woman whom I <hi rend="ital">may</hi> not keep waiting. So I kept quiet.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">However, for half a year I won’t go to <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> any more or talk to him or show him my work. I’m not telling him that, but I’m saying it to you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">My dear Theo, you say ‘be sure and stay good friends with <rs type="pers" key="787">T.</rs>, for he’s almost like an elder brother to us’.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But my dear fellow, he may be friendly to you, but for years I’ve been confronted with his unfriendly and hard side.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">He would be right in reproaching me if I didn’t work, but it’s disgraceful to upbraid someone who works hard and constantly at difficult, painstaking work with such rebukes as ‘I’m absolutely certain that you’re no artist’, ‘for me it counts heavily against you that you started too late’, ‘you have to earn your bread’.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Then I say, stop! Easy does it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">One can’t always be friends, one must also quarrel occasionally.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards the arrangement between you and me, that I receive money from you, I’d like to speak to you about it again in the presence of <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> and no one else, when you come to The Hague, which will be soon, I hope.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>’s large painting will be finished soon,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and then Mauve will again have a thing or two to say to me about making watercolours. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> really cannot talk so that one can work from it. The summary of what <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> has said to me so far is: <hi rend="ital">Vincent, when you draw you’re a painter</hi>. And that’s why I’ve worked, and worked hard, for weeks now, on drawing, on proportion, on perspective, but Tersteeg doesn’t appreciate that enough, and merely talks about ‘saleability’. For this I don’t deserve his reproaches – though I’m inclined to restrain myself because I do respect His Hon., and he can’t stand being contradicted. That’s why I say, in half a year we’ll speak to each other again – for half a year we won’t speak to each other.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you can, send me the money for this month soon. I’m progressing with my work, but I can’t work without money, or with too little.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">With a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab>I’d prefer to have no midday meal for half a year and save money like that than receive 10 guilders now and then from <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs>, along with his reproaches.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’d like to know what the painters would say to his argument ‘take fewer models to economize’ at the very moment when, after much hunting, one has found models who aren’t too expensive.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Working without a model is the bane of the figure painter, especially at the beginning of his career.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent"> If <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> told you he was surprised at some of the things I’d said to His Hon., then perhaps he’ll also be surprised at this, but I wish that he’d consider whether he doesn’t sometimes go a bit too far. Last winter I asked him to speak to <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> about me. He also treated that very high-handedly and wrote to me ‘that certainly won’t be possible’. Yet it was possible, as it later turned out, and so Tersteeg isn’t always right. And if T. hadn’t said that so decidedly last winter, perhaps I’d have become acquainted with Mauve sooner.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>’s painting <rs type="ill" key="239">
                            <hi rend="ital">Fishing boat on the beach</hi>
                        </rs> was exhibited at the Paris Salon (cf. <ref target="let194.xml">letter 194</ref>). Prior to that it was on display at Goupil’s branch in The Hague (<ref target="let211.xml">see letter 211</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘juist op het moment dat’ (at the very moment that).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>