<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 22 January 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let202"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">202</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">172</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">201</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 22 January 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 22 January 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mauve gives Van Gogh advice <ref target="let192.xml">(192)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b193 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Zondag avond’. The contents of this letter suggest that it followed <ref target="let201.xml">letter 201</ref>, which was ‘written yesterday’ <ref target="#l-4">(l. 4)</ref>, i.e. Saturday, 21 January. It precedes <ref target="let203.xml">letter 203</ref> of Thursday, 26 January (in which Vincent thanks Theo for the money he sent). This means that the present letter must date from Sunday, 22 January 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0193" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000220_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000220_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000220_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000220_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000220_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0193" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000220_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000220_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000220_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000220_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000220_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000220_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Zondag avond. <hi rend="ital">Schenkweg 138</hi>
                </ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>(bij de Rijnspoor)</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab>Wel heb ik U reeds gisteren geschreven en toch<c type="kk">/</c> ik schrijf <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>er nog eens over heen. Want ofschoon ik nog wel <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>een dosis moed heb zoo is het mij toch soms moeielijk <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>om mij tegenover Mauve en Tersteeg en anderen <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>altijd goed te houden. En dat moet ik ook doen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>want ofschoon ik tegenover hen niet mij maar <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>onbezorgd houd zoo behoef ik toch hun niet alle <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>details en diepten er van mede te deelen.</ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar het gebeurt mij dikwijls genoeg dat ik met <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>de handen in ’t haar zit. Nu was ik van morgen <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>zoo beroerd dat ik naar bed ben gegaan<c type="kk">/</c> ik had <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>hoofdpijn en was koortsig van overspanning <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>omdat ik zoo opzie tegen deze week en niet <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>weet hoe ik er door zal komen. En ik ben <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>toen weer opgestaan en weer naar bed gegaan en <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>nu is het weer gezakt maar ik wilde het U toch <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>eens zeggen dat ik in mijn brief van gisteren <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>niet overdrijf. Als ik maar hard doorwerk dan <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zal het niet lang meer duren of ik verdien <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>wat met mijn werk maar tot zoolang zit ik <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>geducht in de zorg.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb betrekkelijk ook nog zoo weinig teekenbehoeften<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>of gebrekkige. Nu<c type="kk">/</c> toch voorloopig genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>mijn kist en ezel en penseelen maar b.v. <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>deze week trok mijn teekenplank zoo krom als <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>een ton omdat die te dun was en mijn <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>ezel heeft bij het verzenden naar hier ook een <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>mankement gekregen dat hinderlijk genoeg is.</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er zijn enfin een massa dingen die ik <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>nog hebben of verbeteren moet en natuurlijk hoeft <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>dat alles niet op eens maar het maakt dat van <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>dag tot dag er kleine dingen noodig zijn <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>die mij bij elkaar genomen veel zorg geven. <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Er zijn soms ook dingen aan mijn kleeren <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>te doen en Mauve heeft mij ook daaromtrent <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>al een en ander gezegd dat ik wel doen zal <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>maar dat niet alles op eens kan. Gij weet mijn <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>kleeren zijn meest vermaakte dingen van U of <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>een paar zijn er bij die gemaakt gekocht zijn en <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>van slechte stof. Dus het is niet frisch en vooral <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>met al die sjouwerij met de verf wordt het nog <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>veel moeielijker ze nog maar dragelijk te houden<c type="kp">_</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Met laarzen is het dito dito. Mijn ondergoed <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>begint ook mij te begeven<c type="kk">/</c> er zijn nog goede <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>dingen bij maar ook sommige vol lappen en dat <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>mij niet past. Gij weet wel dat het al een heelen <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>tijd duurt dat ik het niet breed heb en dan raken <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>veel dingen wrak.<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> En dan gebeurt het soms dat <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>men onwillekeurig soms<c type="kk">/</c> al is het momenteel<c type="kk">/</c> vreesselijk <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>neergedrukt wordt soms<c type="kk">/</c> juist in een tijd dat men <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>goedsmoeds is zooals ik dezer dagen werkelijk ben <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>en zelfs nu ook. En zoo was het van morgen, dat <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>zijn van die kwade uren waarin men magteloos is <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>en flaauw van overspanning. Ik geloof dat het eigentlijk <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>kwam omdat ik met Mauve had afgesproken omtrent dingen <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>die ik met het model en buiten doen zou en toen dacht ik <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>in eens.. misschien kan ik het niet doen omdat ik <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>geen cent meer hebben zal over twee dagen en dan <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>denkt M. dat ik het uit lafheid heb gelaten. En <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>nu ben ik dus nog eens opgestaan om U nog eens <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>te schrijven omdat ik geen rust had. En het doet <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>mij zoo veel hinder bij het werken als ik te veel <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>andere dingen in het hoofd heb tegen mijn zin<c type="kk">/</c> en 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>terwijl ik voor ’t model zit in de rats ben hoe ik betalen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>zal en of ik den volgenden dag zal doorgaan of niet <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>zal kunnen. En ik moet, ik moet bedaard en kalm <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>kunnen zijn bij mijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> het is toch al moeielijk <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>genoeg. En nu vooral moet ik mij goed houden <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>maar ik voelde van morgen zoo duidelijk dat <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>mijn kracht aan het bezwijken ging<c type="kk">/</c> niet mijn lust of <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>mijn moed<c type="kk">/</c> en daarom zeg ik het U nog eens<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik begrijp er alles van dat gij het zelf ook moeielijk kunt <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>hebben maar mij dunkt er is toch een afspraak te <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>maken met Tersteeg desnoods zoodat alles geregeld wordt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Nu ik op Pulchri naar ’t model kan teekenen twee avonden <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>in de week<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> zouden desnoods voortaan 4 dagen model <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>genoeg zijn en nu ik dat oud vrouwtje gevonden heb <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>behoeft dat zoo kostbaar niet te zijn als toen ik de <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>eerste dagen moest scharrelen met die en met die <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>want ik heb al verscheiden modellen gehad doch zij zijn te duur of <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>zij vinden het een te ver eind om te komen of zij maken <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>later bezwaar en kunnen niet geregeld terug komen. Maar <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>ik geloof het met dit vrouwtje goed getroffen te hebben.</ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gisteren heb ik nog een lesje gehad van Mauve over het <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>teekenen van handen &amp; gezigten<c type="kk">/</c> om die dun in de verf te <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>houden. Mauve weet het zoo goed en als hij iets zegt <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>dan doet hij het met inspanning en niet om maar wat te zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik luister er ook met inspanning naar en span mij in <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>op de praktijk. Ik heb wel gisteren nog eens tot Mauve <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>gezegd dat het zoo noodig was ik er wat bij verdiende doch ik <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>wil hem niet om geld vragen want hij geeft mij iets dat veel <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>beter is dan geld en trouwens hij heeft mij aan mijn meubels geholpen <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>en dat is meer dan genoeg. Nu ik U geschreven heb ga ik <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>morgen met goed vertrouwen weer aan den slag. Toen <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>gij dezen zomer te Etten waart<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> spraakt gij er over dat gij wildet <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>ik met waterverf zou werken<c type="kp">_</c>─ Toen zag ik er geen gat in en <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>wist niet hoe het aan te leggen. Nu begint er wat licht te <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>schemeren en ondanks alles gaat toch het zonnetje op<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu adieu Theo<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang een handdruk in gedachten en <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="103"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Sunday evening. <hi rend="ital">Schenkweg</hi> <hi rend="ital">138</hi>
                </ab>
<ab>(near the Rijnspoor)</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I may have written to you only yesterday, but I’m writing again even so. For although I still have some measure of courage, it’s sometimes difficult for me always to bear up bravely in the presence of <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> and others. And I must do so, for even though I don’t pretend to be without worries, still, I don’t have to tell them all their details and depths.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But it happens often enough that I’m at my wits’ end. This morning I felt so miserable that I took to my bed, I had a headache and was feverish from nervous exhaustion, because I dread this week so much and don’t know how I’ll manage. And then I got up again and went to bed again and now it’s subsided, but I wanted to tell you that I didn’t exaggerate in yesterday’s letter. If I only go on working hard, it won’t be long before I’ll be earning something with my work, but until then I’ve got terrible worries. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Then, too, I have relatively few drawing materials, or otherwise inadequate ones. Well, I have my box and easel and brushes, enough in fact for the time being, but this week, for instance, my drawing board warped, becoming as curved as a barrel, because it was too thin, and my easel was also damaged during shipment here, which is bothersome enough.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In short, there are heaps of things I still have to get or replace, and naturally it needn’t be all at once, but it means that nearly every day little things are necessary which, taken altogether, worry me greatly. Sometimes my clothes need things done to them, regarding which <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> has already told me a thing or two, which I’ll certainly do, though not all of it can be done at once. You know that my clothes are mostly altered things of yours, and a couple of poor-quality fabric which were bought ready-made. So they look shabby, and especially all that messing about with paint makes it much more difficult even to keep them wearable. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> With boots it’s exactly the same. My underclothes are also starting to wear out, some of them are still all right, but some are in tatters and don’t fit me. You know of course that for a long time I’ve been short of money, and then lots of things fall apart. And then it sometimes happens that one can’t help being terribly depressed at times, even if only briefly, just when one is in good spirits, as I actually have been these days and still am even. And that’s how it was this morning, it was one of those unfortunate hours when one is powerless and weak with nervous exhaustion. I believe it was actually caused by my having arranged with Mauve to do things with the model and outdoors, and then I suddenly thought... perhaps I can’t do it because I won’t have a penny in two days’ time and then M. will think that I haven’t done it through cowardice. And so I got up again to write to you again because I had no peace of mind. And it hinders me so much in my work if I have too many other things on my mind that I don’t want to think about, and 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> am in a stew while sitting in front of the model about how I’m going to pay and whether I’ll continue the next day or won’t be able to. And I must, I must be able to stay composed and calm when at work, it really is hard enough as it is. And now, especially, I must keep my wits about me, but this morning I felt so clearly that my strength was beginning to ebb, not my desire or my courage, and that’s why I’m telling you this again.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I thoroughly understand that you might also be having a hard time of it, but it seems to me that an agreement could be made with <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> if necessary so that everything would be settled. Now that I can draw from the model at Pulchri two evenings a week,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> if it’s necessary 4 days of model should be enough from now on, and now that I’ve found that little old woman, it needn’t be so expensive as it was those first few days when I was bargaining with this one or that one, for I’ve already had a number of models, but they’re too expensive or they think it too far to come, or they complain later and can’t come back regularly. But I think I’ve done well to find this woman.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yesterday I had a lesson from <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> on drawing hands and faces, on keeping the paint layer thin. Mauve knows it all so well, and when he says something, he makes an effort and doesn’t just say something for the sake of saying it, well, I also make an effort to listen and take pains to put it into practice. Yesterday I again told Mauve that it was so necessary for me to earn something on the side, but I don’t want to ask him for money because he gives me something that’s much better than money, and besides, he helped me to buy my furniture and that’s more than enough. Now that I’ve written to you, I’ll set to work again tomorrow in good faith. When you were in Etten this summer<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> you talked about wanting me to start working in watercolour. At the time I saw no way to do it and didn’t know how to set about it. Now it’s beginning to dawn on me, and in spite of everything, the sun is rising.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, adieu Theo, accept a handshake in thought, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘in slechte staat’ (in poor condition, in a bad state).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Van Gogh had indeed become an associate member of this artists’ society, evidently after <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> had put in a good word for him (cf. <ref target="let199.xml">letter 199</ref>). He is listed as no. 18 in the membership records, and paid a six-month fee of 6.25 guilders. See <hi rend="ital">Archief Pulchri</hi>, inv. no. 59-289, October 1881- September 1882, in <hi rend="ital">GAH</hi>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The figure drawing (mentioned in <ref target="let203.xml#l-121">letter 203, l. 121</ref>) of ‘<rs type="pers" key="33">Artz</rs>’s model’ was probably made at Pulchri. There are no other indications of drawings made there.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Theo had visited Etten in July 1881 (<ref target="let170.xml#n-1">see letter 170, n. 1</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Something <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> had said prompted Van Gogh to use this metaphorical expression (<ref target="let192.xml">see letter 192</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>