<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 22 October 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let274"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">274</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">237</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">274</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 22 October 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:physDesc>
                        <vg:decoration>
                            <vg:decoList xml:id="sketches">
                                <vg:decoItem n="A" xml:id="sketch-1">
                                    <vg:decoDesc>
<p>
      <hi rend="ital">Beach with people strolling and boats</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="74">F - / JH 248</rs>), letter sketch</p>
                                    </vg:decoDesc>
                                </vg:decoItem>
                            </vg:decoList>
                        </vg:decoration>
                    </vg:physDesc>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Sunday, 22 October 1882.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b259 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed ‘Zondag middag’. The only possible date is Sunday, 22 October 1882. Vincent also writes to Theo on the last Sunday of the month (<ref target="let277.xml">letter 277</ref>, which in view of the opening words ‘It’s Sunday again’ cannot be from the same Sunday). Moreover, in the present letter he remarks: ‘I have the stove in place already’; and in <ref target="let277.xml">letter 277</ref> he says: ‘Believe me, I’m glad that the stove is in place’, so this letter must be earlier than that last Sunday. He also thanks Theo for the remittance, which would have been that of the 20th. Thus Sunday, 22 October 1882 is the only possible date. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0259" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000317_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000317_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000317_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000317_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000317_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0259" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000317_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000317_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000317_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000317_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000317_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000317_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Zondag middag</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Uw brief &amp; het ingeslotene deden mij zeer veel pleizier, dat <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>behoef ik U niet te zeggen, het komt erg van pas en is mij <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>een krachtige hulp.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">We houden hier herfstweer – regenachtig &amp; kil, maar vol <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>stemming – prachtig voor figuren vooral, die op de natte straten <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>en wegen waar de lucht in weerkaatst toonig uitkomen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Het is ’t geen Mauve vooral telkens zoo mooi doet.</ab>
                <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb nog wat daardoor kunnen doen aan de <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>groote aquarel van den troep volk voor het loterijkantoor<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>en zoo pas heb ik er ook weer een van het strand begonnen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>waarvan dit <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>de compositie is.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab>Ik kan volkomen <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>overeenstemmen met <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>wat gij zegt omtrent <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>tijden die men soms <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>heeft waarin men <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>stomp schijnt voor de <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>dingen van de natuur <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>of waarin de natuur <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>niet meer tot ons schijnt <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>te spreken.</ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb dat ook dikwijls en het helpt mij wel eens als ik dan heel andere <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>dingen aanpak. ben ik stomp op landschap of lichteffekten dan grijp ik <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>de figuren aan<c type="kk">/</c> en omgekeerd. Soms is er niets aan te doen dan <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>af te wachten tot het over gaat maar menigen keer lukt het mij <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>de ongevoeligheid weg te krijgen door verwisseling van motieven, <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>waarop ik mijn attentie heb. Hoe langer hoe meer echter boeien mij <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>de figuren. Ik herinner mij vroeger een tijd gehad te hebben <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>dat het gevoel voor ’t landschap erg sterk bij me was en ik veel <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>meer getroffen werd door een schilderij of teekening waar een lichteffekt <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>of stemming van landschap goed was uitgedrukt dan door figuur<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Zelfs boezemden in ’t algemeen de figuurschilders mij meer een <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>soort tamelijk koelen eerbied in dan wel dat ik er warme sympathie <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>voor had. Ik herinner mij echter nog zeer wel in dien tijd <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>toch bijzonder getroffen geweest te zijn door een teekening van Daumier<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>een oud man onder de kastanjeboomen in de Champs Elysées (een <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>illustratie voor Balzac)<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> ofschoon die teekening zoo important niet was <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>maar ik weet wel dat het mij toen zoo bijzonder trof dat <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>er iets zoo flinks en mannelijks in de opvatting van Daumier was dat <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>ik dacht<c type="kk">/</c> het moet toch goed zijn zòò te voelen en te denken en <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>een massa dingen over ’t hoofd te zien of voorbij te gaan om zich te <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>concentreeren op zoo iets wat te denken geeft en een mensch <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>als mensch meer direkt persoonlijk aangaat dan weilanden of wolken.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">En zoo blijven mij ook steeds de figuren ’t zij van de Engelsche <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>teekenaars ’t zij van de Engelsche schrijvers om reden van hun <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>Maandagmorgenachtige nuchterheid en gewilde soberheid en proza en analyse <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>steeds aantrekken als iets dat solide en flink is<c type="kk">/</c> waar men <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>een houvast aan heeft in dagen wanneer men zich slap voelt.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Zoo onder de fransche schrijvers die van Balzac &amp; Zola evenzeer. <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>De boeken van <hi rend="ital">Murger</hi> waarover gij schrijft zijn mij nog <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>onbekend doch ik hoop wel er kennis mee te maken.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Schreef ik U reeds ik van Daudet Les rois en exil las.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>Dat vond ik wel mooi<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">De titels van die boeken trekken mij zeer aan<c type="kk">/</c> o.a<c type="kp">_</c> la bohême<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>Wat zijn wij in dezen tijd erg ver afgedwaald van la bohême <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>uit de dagen van Gavarni!<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Me dunkt er was toch in dien tijd <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>iets meer hartelijks en opgeruimds en levends dan nu<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Ik weet het echter niet – en tegenwoordig is er ook veel <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>goeds<c type="kk">/</c> of kon er zijn nog meer dan effektief ’t geval is<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>als er wat meer aaneensluiting was.</ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is op ’t oogenblik uit het raam van mijn atelier een prachtig <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>effekt. De stad met de torens en daken en rookende schoorsteenen teekent zich als <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>een donker<c type="kk">/</c> somber silhouet af tegen een horizont <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>van licht. Dit licht is evenwel slechts eene breede <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>streep<c type="kk">/</c> daarboven hangt een zware bui<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>beneden meer geconcentreerd<c type="kk">/</c> boven door <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>den herfstwind gescheurd in groote vlokken &amp; massas <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>die er af drijven. Die streep licht echter doet in <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>de sombere massa der stad hier &amp; daar de natte <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>daken glinsteren (op een teekening zou men ’t met <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>een streek dekverf uithalen) en maakt dat ofschoon <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>de massa één toon heeft men nog onderscheid ziet <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>tusschen roode pannen &amp; leijen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab rend="indent">De Schenkweg loopt door den voorgrond als een <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>glinsterende streep door het nat<c type="kk">/</c> de populieren <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>hebben geele blaren<c type="kk">/</c> de slootkanten &amp; weiland zijn diep <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>groen, figuurtjes zijn zwart<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zou het teekenen of liever trachten te teekenen indien ik niet den heelen <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>middag op figuren gesjouwd had van turfdragers<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>die mij toch nog te zeer in ’t hoofd zitten dan dat er <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>ruimte is voor iets nieuws, en er ook in moeten <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>blijven.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik verlang toch zoo dikwijls naar U en denk <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>zooveel aan U. Wat gij mij schrijft over sommige karakters <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>te Parijs<c type="kk">/</c> van artisten die met vrouwen leven<c type="kk">/</c> minder kleingeestig <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>zijn dan anderen misschien<c type="kk">/</c> wanhopend trachten iets jongs <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>te behouden<c type="kk">/</c> vindt ik wel juist gezien<c type="kp">_</c> Zulken zijn er ginder <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>en hier. Ginder is ’t misschien nog moeielijker dan <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>hier als mensch wat frischheid te behouden in het <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>huisselijk leven omdat zulks daar haast nog meer <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>tegen den stroom op werken is. Wat zijn er veel te <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>Parijs wanhopig geworden – kalm<c type="kk">/</c> beredeneerd<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>logisch en teregt wanhopig<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik las nog iets <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>van dien aard<c type="kk">/</c> o.a. omtrent Tassaert van wien ik <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>veel houd en wat mij leed deed dat het zoo met <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>hem gegaan was.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab rend="indent">Te meer, te meer vind ik elke poging in die <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>rigting waard gerespecteerd te worden. Ook geloof ik <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>dat het kan gebeuren men slage en niet moet beginnen <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>met te wanhopen – ook al verliest men ’t hier en daar <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>en ook al voelt men soms een soort aftakeling<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>toch is het zaak weer op te leven en moed te vatten <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>al komt het ook anders uit dan men aanvankelijk <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>meende. Meen ook niet dat ik met minachting op <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>personen als die ge beschrijft neerzie om reden hun leven <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>niet zou berusten op serieuse en doordachte beginselen. <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>Mijne gedachte daaromtrent is deze – <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>het resultaat moet zijn een <hi rend="ital">daad</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> niet een abstract <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>idée.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Slechts dan vindt ik principes goed en de moeite waard als zij <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>zich tot daden ontwikkelen en ik vind het goed na te denken <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>en te trachten conscientieus te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> omdat dit de werkkracht <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>van een mensch meer decideert en de verschillende daden <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>tot een geheel maakt. Ik zou van zulken als ge beschrijft <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>vinden dat zij door meer beredeneerd te doen wat ze doen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>meer vastheid zouden krijgen doch overigens prefereer <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>ik zulken verre boven menschen die met principes te <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>koop loopen zonder zich de minste moeite te geven of <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>er zelfs maar aan te denken ze in praktijk te brengen. <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>Want deze laatsten hebben aan de mooiste principes niets <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>en de eersten zijn net de lui om <hi rend="ital">dan</hi> <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>
                    <hi rend="sc">als</hi> ze er toe komen met wilskracht en nadenken te gaan leven<c type="kk">/</c> iets groots <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>te doen. Want het groote geschiedt niet bij impulsie alleen en <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>is een aaneenschakeling van kleine dingen die tot elkaar gebragt zijn<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat is het teekenen? hoe komt men er<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>’t Is een zich heenwerken door een onzigtbaren <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>ijzeren muur die schijnt te staan tusschen wat men <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">voelt</hi> en wat men <hi rend="ital">kan</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>– Hoe moet men door dien <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>muur heen komen – daar er tegen beuken niets <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>helpt. Men moet dien muur ondermijnen en <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>doorvijlen langzaam en met geduld mijns inziens<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>en ziedaar – hoe zal men aan zulk een werk <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>assidu blijven zonder zich te laten afbrengen er <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>van of afleiden<c type="kk">/</c> tenzij men nadenke en zijn leven <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>regele naar principes. En zoo als ’t met het artistieke is <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>zoo is het ook met andere dingen. En het groote is niet <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>iets toevalligs<c type="kk">/</c> het moet wel degelijk <hi rend="ital">gewild</hi> worden<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>Of oorspronkelijk in een mensch de daden tot de principes <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>of de principes tot de daden leiden moeten<c type="kk">/</c> is iets <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>wat me even ondecideerbaar schijnt en evenmin de moeite waard gedecideerd te worden als de kwestie <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>wat er ’t eerst geweest is<c type="kk">/</c> de kip of het ei.</ab>
                <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar iets positiefs en van veel gewigt acht ik het dat men <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>trachte zijn denk- en wilskracht te ontwikkelen.</ab>
                <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zeer nieuwsgierig ben ik of ge als ge vroeger of later <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>ze zien zult<c type="kk">/</c> in de figuren die ik dezer dagen maak <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>iets vinden zult. ’t Is daarmee ook al een kwestie als die <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>van de kip &amp; het ei<c type="kk">/</c> moet men figuren maken voor een eerst gevonden compositie <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>of de figuren die men afzonderlijk maakt combineeren zoo dat de compositie <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>er uit voortvloeit<c type="kp">_</c>– ’t Zal dunkt me wel op ’t zelfde neerkomen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Mits men maar werke</hi>. Ik eindig met hetgeen waarmee gij Uw brief <lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>besluit<c type="kk">/</c> dat we met elkaar gemeen hebben we er van houden om <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>achter de schermen van het tooneel te zien, of met andere woorden een <lb n="155" xml:id="l-155"/>neiging hebben om de dingen te analyseeren. Dit nu geloof ik <lb n="156" xml:id="l-156"/>juist de eigenschap is die <lb n="157" xml:id="l-157"/>men hebben moet om te schilderen – bij het schilderen of teekenen <lb n="158" xml:id="l-158"/>moet men die kracht inspannen. ’t moge eenigermate zoo zijn dat <lb n="159" xml:id="l-159"/>er als van nature iets in ons zijn moet (maar ook dat hebt gij en <lb n="160" xml:id="l-160"/>ik heb het ook – we hebben dat misschien te danken aan onze jongensjaren <lb n="161" xml:id="l-161"/>in Brabant en aan een omgeving die er veel meer dan meestal ’t geval <lb n="162" xml:id="l-162"/>is er toe meewerkte om ons te leeren denken) doch vooral<c type="kk">/</c> vooral is <lb n="163" xml:id="l-163"/>het eerst later dat het artistieke gevoel zich ontwikkelt en rijpt door werken<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="164" xml:id="l-164"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Hoe</hi> het zou kunnen dat gij een zeer goed schilder werdt weet ik niet doch dat <lb n="165" xml:id="l-165"/>het in U zit en ’t er van komen kan dat geloof ik wel degelijk<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="166" xml:id="l-166"/>
<ab rend="indent">à dieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> dank voor het gezondene en een hartelijken handdruk.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="167" xml:id="l-167"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="168" xml:id="l-168"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="169" xml:id="l-169"/>
<ab>Ik heb het kagcheltje reeds staan<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> – kerel wat wou <lb n="170" xml:id="l-170"/>ik we eens een avondje teekeningen &amp; schetsen konden <lb n="171" xml:id="l-171"/>kijken – en <hi rend="ital">houtsneden</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> ik heb weer prachtige<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="172" xml:id="l-172"/>
<ab>Ik hoop deze week weesjongens te poseeren te krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> dan zou ik misschien die teekening van weeskinderen<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> <lb n="173" xml:id="l-173"/>nog kunnen redden.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-62" n="62">dan &lt; dat</note>
<note target="l-125" n="125">te doen &lt; de doen</note>
<note target="l-145" n="145">denk- &lt; denk</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Sunday afternoon</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Your letter and the enclosure gave me very great pleasure, I don’t need to tell you that. It’s just what was needed and is a mighty help to me. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s still autumnal weather here — rainy and chilly, but full of atmosphere — especially good for figures, which show a range of tones on the wet streets and roads in which the sky is reflected. It’s what <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>, above all, does so beautifully time and again.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As a result I’ve been able to do some more to the large watercolour of the crowd of people in front of the lottery office,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and I’ve also just started another of the beach, of which this is the composition.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
                    <figure facs="zone-sketch-1" n="A"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I can agree entirely with what you say about times one occasionally has when one seems to be deadened to the things of nature, or when nature no longer seems to speak to us. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I, too, often have that, and sometimes it helps if I turn to something very different. If I’m dead to landscape or effects of light, I tackle figures, and vice versa. Sometimes there’s nothing to be done except wait for it to pass, but on many occasions I manage to get rid of the unresponsiveness by changing the subjects I’m concentrating on. I’m becoming more and more fascinated by figures though. I remember having had a time in the past when the feeling for landscape was very strong within me, and I was much more struck by a painting or drawing in which a light effect or the mood of a landscape was well expressed than by figures. In general, the figure painters even inspired in me a kind of fairly cool respect rather than warm sympathy. However, I well remember being particularly struck at the time by a drawing by <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>, an old man under the chestnut trees in the Champs Elysées (an illustration for <rs type="pers" key="591">Balzac</rs>),<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> although the drawing wasn’t that important. But I remember that it struck me so forcefully that there was something so firm and manly in Daumier’s approach that I thought: it must be good to feel and think like that and overlook or ignore a mass of things so as to concentrate on something that’s thought-provoking and appeals to a human being as a human being more directly than meadows or clouds. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And similarly the figures of either the English draughtsmen or the English writers, on account of their Monday morning-like sobriety and deliberate austerity and prose and analysis, continue to attract me as something solid and firm which gives one something to hold onto on days when one is feeling weak.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> And those of <rs type="pers" key="591">Balzac</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs> among the French writers just as much. As yet I don’t know the books by <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="716">Murger</rs>
                    </hi> you write about, but I hope to become acquainted with them.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Did I write to you before that I read <rs type="pers" key="583">Daudet</rs>’s Les rois en exil?<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> I thought it rather beautiful. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The titles of those books sound very attractive, La bohème among others.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> How far we have strayed in our age from la bohème of <rs type="pers" key="1043">Gavarni</rs>’s day!<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> It seems to me that things were a little warmer then, and more good-humoured and livelier than now. But I don’t know, and there’s also much that’s good in the present, or would be more than is actually the case if there were rather more joining together.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">At the moment a wonderful effect can be seen from the window of my studio. The city with its towers and roofs and smoking chimneys stands out as a dark, sombre silhouette against a horizon of light. The light, though, is only a broad strip; above it hangs a heavy shower, more concentrated below, above torn by the autumn wind into great tufts and clumps that float off. But that strip of light makes the wet roofs glisten here and there in the sombre mass of the city (in a drawing you would lift it with a stroke of body-colour), and ensures that, although the mass all has the same tone, you can still distinguish between red tiles and slates. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Schenkweg runs through the foreground as a glistening line through the wet, the poplars have yellow leaves, the banks of the ditch and the meadow are deep green, figures are black. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I would draw it, or rather try to draw it, if I hadn’t spent the whole afternoon toiling at figures of peat carriers<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> which are still too much in my mind for there to be room for something new, and must remain there. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I do so often long for you and think of you so much. What you write about some characters in Paris, about artists who live with women, are less petty-minded than others perhaps, try desperately to stay young, seems well observed to me. Such people exist there and here. It’s perhaps even more difficult there than here for a person to keep some freshness in domestic life, because that’s almost more of an uphill struggle there. How many have become desperate in Paris — calmly, rationally, logically and rightly desperate? I read something along these lines about <rs type="pers" key="1379">Tassaert</rs>, among others, whom I like very much, and was pained by what happened to him.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">All the more, all the more, I think every attempt in this direction is worthy of respect. I also believe that it may happen that one succeeds and one mustn’t begin by despairing; even if one loses here and there, and even if one sometimes feels a sort of decline, the point is nevertheless to revive and have courage, even though things don’t turn out as one first thought. Moreover, don’t think that I look with contempt on people such as you describe because their life isn’t founded on serious and well-considered principles. My view on this is as follows: the result must be an <hi rend="ital">action</hi>, not an abstract idea.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> I think principles are good and worth the effort only when they develop into deeds, and I think it’s good to reflect and to try to be conscientious, because that makes a person’s will to work more resolute and turns the various actions into a whole. I think that people such as you describe would get more steadiness if they went about what they do more rationally, but otherwise I much prefer them to people who make a great show of their principles without making the slightest effort to put them into practice or even giving that a thought. For the latter have no use for the finest of principles, and the former are precisely the people who, <hi rend="sc">if</hi> they ever get round to living with willpower and reflection, will do something great. For the great doesn’t happen through impulse alone, and is a succession of little things that are brought together. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">What is drawing? How does one get there? It’s working one’s way through an invisible iron wall that seems to stand between what one <hi rend="ital">feels</hi> and what one <hi rend="ital">can do</hi>. How can one get through that wall? — since hammering on it doesn’t help at all. In my view, one must undermine the wall and grind through it slowly and patiently. And behold, how can one remain dedicated to such a task without allowing oneself to be lured from it or distracted, unless one reflects and organizes one’s life according to principles? And it’s the same with other things as it is with artistic matters. And the great isn’t something accidental; it must be <hi rend="ital">willed</hi>. Whether originally deeds lead to principles in a person or principles lead to deeds is something that seems to me as unanswerable and as little worth answering as the question of which came first, the chicken or the egg.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But I believe it’s a positive thing and of great importance that one should try to develop one’s powers of thought and will. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m very curious about what you’ll think of the figures I’m doing at present, when you see them sooner or later. It’s the same with them as with the question of the chicken and the egg: should one make figures for a composition one has done first, or combine the figures made separately so that the composition flows from them? I believe it comes down to the same thing. <hi rend="ital">Just as long as one works</hi>. I end with that with which you close your letter — that we have in common a liking for seeing behind the scenes or, in other words, are inclined to analyze things. Now this, I believe, is exactly the quality one must have in order to paint — one must exercise this power when painting or drawing. It may be that there has to be something innate in us, to some extent (but that too you have, and so do I — for that we may have to thank our childhood in Brabant and a background that helped, much more than is usually the case, to teach us to think), but above all, above all, it’s only later that the artistic sense develops and ripens through working. <hi rend="ital">How</hi> you might become a very good painter I don’t know, but I certainly believe that it is in you and will come out.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Adieu, old chap, thanks for what you sent, and a hearty handshake. </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I have the stove in place already<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> — old chap, how I wish we could look at drawings and sketches for an evening sometime — and <hi rend="ital">woodcuts</hi>. I have some more splendid ones. </ab>
                <vg:whiteline/>
                <ab>This week I hope to have orphan boys to pose, then I may be able to rescue the drawing of orphan children<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> after all.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">The poor and the money</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2398">F 970 / JH 222</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The letter sketch <hi rend="ital">Beach with people strolling with boats</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="74">F - / JH 248</rs>) was done after the watercolour with the same title <rs type="ill" key="2405">F 982 / JH 247</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
      <ab>Van Gogh is possibly referring to <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>’s illustration ‘Ferragus, les deux mains sur sa canne’ (Ferragus leaning on his walking stick) for the story ‘Ferragus’ in <rs type="pers" key="591">Balzac</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="208">Histoire des Treize</rs>
                        </hi>. <rs type="ill" key="54">Ill. 54</rs>. It appeared in <hi rend="ital">Le Charivari</hi> (20 November 1846) and was included in several editions of Balzac’s <hi rend="ital">Oeuvres complètes</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Oeuvres illustrées</hi>. See Bouvy 1995, cat. no. 735 and Honoré de Balzac, <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="219">La comédie humaine</rs> <hi rend="sc">v</hi>
                        </hi>. <hi rend="ital">Etudes de moeurs. Scènes de la vie de province. Scènes de la vie parisienne</hi>. <hi rend="ital">Histoire des treize</hi>. Ed. Rose Fortassier. Paris 1977. Cf. also <ref target="let162.xml#n-2">letter 162, n. 2.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This plea for firmness and sobriety, and the words ‘Monday morning’ and ‘solid’, especially in this context, make it all the likelier that this is an allusion to the following passage at the beginning of <rs type="pers" key="534">Charlotte Brontë</rs>’s novel <rs type="lit" key="216">
                            <hi rend="ital">Shirley</hi>
                        </rs>: ‘If you think, from this prelude, that anything like a romance is preparing for you, reader, you never were more mistaken. Do you anticipate sentiment, and poetry, and reverie? Do you expect passion, and stimulus, and melodrama? Calm your expectations; reduce them to a lowly standard. Something real, cool, and solid, lies before you; something unromantic as Monday morning, when all who have work wake with the consciousness that they must rise and betake themselves thereto.’ Ed. London 1857, p. 1. Van Gogh knew the book; <ref target="let170.xml">see letters 170</ref> and <ref target="let187.xml">187</ref>. Later he writes ‘prosaic as Monday morning’ (<ref target="let341.xml">letters 341</ref> and <ref target="let342.xml">342</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>A month later Van Gogh was to read <rs type="lit" key="263">
                            <hi rend="ital">Les buveurs d’eau</hi>
                        </rs> (1854) by <rs type="pers" key="716">Henri Murger</rs>; <ref target="let288.xml">see letter 288</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="583">Alphonse Daudet</rs>, <rs type="lit" key="264">
                            <hi rend="ital">Les rois en exil – Roman parisien</hi>
                        </rs> (1879) is a novel about the royal family of Illyria, which is in exile in Paris after a revolution and waiting to return to the homeland. Their ‘race’ and ‘blood’ are exhausted, however, and the son and heir has to renounce the throne because of his poor health. Daudet describes aristocratic circles in Paris and how their show of strength is confronted by reality.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>When giving the titles by <rs type="pers" key="716">Murger</rs>, Theo would have been bound to include <rs type="lit" key="265">
                            <hi rend="ital">Scènes de la vie de bohème</hi>
                        </rs> (1851), a highly successful book with a mix of romanticism and realism. The main characters are a painter, a musician, a philosopher and a poet. The life of these bohémiens in the Quartier Latin in Paris takes shape in long dialogues and details about interiors, dress and music – it is extravagant and theatrical. At first money and romance are the central concerns, but eventually they have ‘arrived’ and they leave the free and easy ways of their younger years behind them.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Van Gogh was familiar with <rs type="pers" key="1043">Gavarni</rs>’s combination of a free way of life and a successful career as an artist from the biography <rs type="lit" key="224">
                            <hi rend="ital">Gavarni, l’homme et l’oeuvre</hi>
                        </rs> by <rs type="pers" key="617 618">Jules and Edmond de Goncourt</rs>. Meanwhile Theo had the book (<ref target="let277.xml">see letter 277</ref>). A series of lithographs entitled ‘Bohèmes’ was included in <rs type="lit" key="266">
                            <hi rend="ital">La mascarade humaine</hi>
                        </rs>, which Vincent had (<ref target="let302.xml">see letter 302</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>No figure studies of peat carriers from this period are known. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1379">Nicolas François Octave Tassaert</rs> was obsessed by death; it ‘foreshadowed his own later self-destruction by asphyxiation’. ‘In April 1874, faced with starvation and with no hope of earning a living, Tassaert committed suicide, using the same type of coal stove he had depicted in his genre scenes of the garrets of the poor’. See exhib. cat. Cleveland 1980, pp. 44-45, 311.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>Van Gogh mentions this idea several times: <ref target="let312.xml">see letters 312</ref>, <ref target="let398.xml">398</ref> and <ref target="let400.xml">400</ref>. He probably borrowed it from <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="197">Sartor resartus</rs>
                        </hi> by <rs type="pers" key="563">Thomas Carlyle</rs>, who writes ‘<hi rend="ital">The end of Man is an Action, and not a Thought,</hi> though it were the noblest’ (book 2, chapter 6). See also ‘existence was all a Feeling, not yet shaped into a Thought. Nevertheless, into a Thought, nay into an Action, it must be shaped’ (book 2, chapter 5). See Carlyle 1987, pp. 120, 112. Van Gogh must have had a copy of <hi rend="ital">Sartor resartus</hi> as early as 1875. See Pabst 1988, p. 25. For this novel, <ref target="let325.xml#n-34">see letter 325, n. 34.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Vincent had earlier suggested that Theo would be a good painter: <ref target="let211.xml">see letter 211</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>It was not unusual to dismantle stoves in the spring to give more space in a room. They were reassembled in the autumn (cf. <ref target="let218.xml">letter 218</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>Van Gogh had sent <hi rend="ital">Orphans</hi> (<rs type="sketch" key="67">F - / JH 203</rs>), the letter sketch of this unknown drawing: <ref target="let265.xml">see letter 265</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>