<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Thursday, 16 or Friday, 17 November 1882. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let283"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">283</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">245</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">286</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 16 or Friday, 17 November 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Thursday, 16 or Friday, 17 November 1882. </p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh is drawing diggers <ref target="let281.xml">(281)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b267 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter must have been written after Tuesday, 14 November, since in <ref target="let282.xml">letter 282</ref> of that date Vincent still did not know for sure whether Theo’s letter with money had been lost (cf. <ref target="#l-2">ll. 2-3</ref>). Moreover, it must have been from the same <ref target="let282.xml">letter 282</ref> that Theo learned about the loss, so that his response, to which Vincent refers in <ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref> of the present letter, could not have reached The Hague earlier than Thursday, 16 November (‘Today’). Because corresponding back and forth could have taken slightly longer, the letter is dated to Thursday, 16 or Friday, 17 November 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0267" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000327_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000327_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000327_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000327_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000327_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0267" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000327_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000327_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000327_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000327_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000327_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000327_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Heden ontving ik Uw brief waarvoor hartelijk <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>dank. Hoe bitter jammer ik het ook vind dat Uw schrijven <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>van 9 Nov. en het ingesloten biljet is weggeraakt<c type="kk">/</c> toch <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>was ik blij dat het om geen andere reden was dat Uw <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>brief wegbleef. Want dat ik verbazend ongerust <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>geweest ben kan ik U verzekeren.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Dadelijk heb ik <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>aan ’t postkantoor aangifte gedaan van ’t weg raken <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>van den brief doch men zegt men weinig hoop kan <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>geven &amp; de demarches van nasporing moeten <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>uitgaan van Parijs. Intusschen zou men onderzoeken<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>We willen hopen ’t nog teregt komt maar ik <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>durf er niet op te rekenen en ik vrees de frs 50 zijn <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>naar de maan<c type="kk">/</c> juist op een moment dat ze <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>haast onmisbaar zijn.– Primo voor ’t vorderen <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>met de proeven in lithographie. dat die welke <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>ik ’t eerst zond U eenig genoegen deed verheugt <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>me bijzonder,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> ge ontvangt bij dezen de <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">allereerste</hi> afdruk van Sorrow.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Voor Heyerdahl <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>heb ik er ook een met grooter marge bijgedaan <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>en een van de andere voor Buhot maar juist omdat ze <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>grooter zijn zoo weet ik niet of de post het aannemen zal.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>Gij kunt natuurlijkerwijs nemen welke ge wilt <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>en van welke ge wilt meer afdrukken krijgen <lb n="23a" xml:id="l-23a"/>maar de allereersten heb ik gemerkt 1<hi rend="ss">re</hi> epreuve.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ga morgen met Smulders spreken om de <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>steenen van hem te krijgen. ’k moet U <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>zeggen ik het verbazend prettig zou vinden <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>als ik er toe komen kon eens eene flinke <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>serie te maken.</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb nu Spitters onder handen<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>de teekeningen die hoop ik iets worden kunnen<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">We hebben ’t hier bar koud<c type="kp">_</c> Sneeuw <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>en vorst maar wel erg mooi.</ab>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">In het rolletje lithographien zult ge vinden <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>een teekeningetje gemaakt met neutral tint <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>op Whatman.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Mijne vraag daaromtrent <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>is deze. Zou eene teekening op deze <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>wijs gemaakt te reproduceeren zijn<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Verder<c type="kk">/</c> zouden dergelijke teekeningen <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>of dergelijke gemaakt met autographische <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>inkt door Vie moderne te gebruiken zijn.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>Ik zou U wel willen verzoeken of <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>ge me zenden kondt <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>eenige No<hi rend="ss">s</hi> Vie moderne omdat <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>ik slechts zeer enkele (’k geloof 3) bladen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>er van heb uit een zelfde<c type="kk">/</c> reeds zeer oud <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Nummer<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> en zoo gaarne mij een beter <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>en ietwat compleeter begrip zou kunnen maken <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>van wat het blad eigentlijk is.</ab>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb er hier in stad naar gezocht en <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>geen enkel N<hi rend="ss">o</hi> kunnen vinden. <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Hoe eer ik die zou ontvangen hoe liever <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>ze me zijn zouden daar ik nu juist <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>aan het zoeken ben naar de <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>verschillende procedés en de reproducties in Vie moderne mij <lb n="54a" xml:id="l-54a"/>mogelijk op den weg helpen zullen om beter te begrijpen <lb n="54b" xml:id="l-54b"/>wat men er mee doen kan<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Doch ik mag U wel eens excuus vragen <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>voor zooveel last die ik er U voor aandoe<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Deze week is Pa heel even hier geweest <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>toen hij in stad was voor eene vergadering<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab rend="indent">Rappard schrijft me over eene nieuwe serie <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>teekeningen van <hi rend="ital">Paul Renouard</hi> in <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>de Illustration over de mijnwerkers<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>Ik heb die nog niet gezien maar <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>mogt ge ze ergens in een kiosk waar <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>men “die dingen die in ’t Zuid Hollandsch <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>Koffijhuis liggen”<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> verkoopt<c type="kk">/</c> zien – toe <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>let er voor me op want ik geloof <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>dat het buitengewoon mooie dingen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>zullen zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik weet niet of ge het pedant of iets dergelijks <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>van me vinden zult als ik U zeg dat <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>het volgende me pleizier deed. de knechs van <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Smulders uit het andere magazijn op de Laan<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> hadden <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>den steen van den weesman gezien en den drukker <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>gevraagd of ze er een afdruk van konden krijgen <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>om op te hangen. Geen resultaat van <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>mijn werk zou me aangenamer zijn dan <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>dat gewone werklui zulke bladen in hun <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>kamer of werkplaats hingen. <hi rend="ital">For you –</hi> <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">the public – it is really done</hi> vind <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>ik een waar woord van Herkomer.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Natuurlijkerwijs moet een teekening artistieke waarde <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>hebben doch dit moet niet uitsluiten m.i. <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>dat de gewone passanten er iets in vinden <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>kunnen. Enfin dit allereerste blad reken ik nog <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>als niets doch dat het tot iets serieusers moge <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>worden hoop ik zoo van harte.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Door ’t verlies van de bewuste frs 50 <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>(want ik vrees ze zijn weg) hebben zoowel <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>gij als ik eene contrarieteit bij het <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>nemen van deze proeven doch <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>laat het ons niet ontmoedigen. <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Wat wou ik dat ge de onderhanden <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>zijnde teekeningen eens zien kondt<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik verzeker U dat ik toen Uw brief <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>wegbleef en ik niet wist wat toch de oorzaak <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>wezen kon<c type="kk">/</c> erg melankoliek ben geweest<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>Zeer gaarne verneem ik at your <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>early convenience iets over wat <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>ik heden zend. Verder help ik U <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>eens onthouden ge nog op <hi rend="ital">Daumier</hi> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>zoudt terug komen.– ook at your <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>early convenience want ik begrijp dat <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>ge niet altijd den tijd tot schrijven <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>hebt. adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> nogmaals <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>dank voor Uw brief en geloof me<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>met een handdruk</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="106*" xml:id="l-106s"/>
<ab>t. à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>
<ab>ik begin van avond aan het lezen <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>van <hi rend="ital">Pot bouille</hi> van Zola<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-23" n="23">a gemerkt &lt; gemerkt.</note>
<note target="l-65" n="65">zien – &lt; zien</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I received your letter today, for which many thanks. Bitterly sorry as I am that your letter of 9 Nov. and the enclosed banknote have been lost, I was nonetheless glad that it wasn’t for another reason that your letter didn’t come. For I can assure you that I was terribly worried.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I immediately reported the loss of the letter at the post office, but they say they can give little hope and that steps for tracing it must come from Paris. In the meantime they would investigate. We hope it’ll turn up but I dare not count on it, and I fear the 50 francs are down the drain, just when they’re almost indispensable — first, for making progress with the experiments in lithography. I’m really delighted that you took some pleasure in the first one I sent.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> Herewith you’re receiving the <hi rend="ital">very first</hi> impression of Sorrow.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> I’ve also enclosed one with a bigger margin for <rs type="pers" key="1084">Heyerdahl</rs> and an earlier one for <rs type="pers" key="910">Buhot</rs>, but because they’re bigger I don’t know whether the post office will accept them.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> Of course you can take whichever you like and get more impressions of whichever you like, but I’ve marked the very first ones 1re épreuve.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m going to go and talk to Smulders tomorrow to get the stones from him. I must tell you that I would find it extremely pleasing if I could get around to making a large series sometime.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m now working on Diggers — they’re the drawings I hope may amount to something.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s bitterly cold here. Snow and frost, but very beautiful for all that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the roll of lithographs you’ll find a drawing done in a neutral tint on Whatman.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> My question about it is this. Would it be possible to reproduce a drawing done in this way?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Also, would such drawings or similar ones done in autographic ink be of use to Vie Moderne?<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> I would like to ask you if you could send me some issues of Vie Moderne because I have only a very few (I think 3) prints from it from one now very old issue,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> and would so much like to have a better and rather more complete idea of what the magazine actually is. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve looked for them here in town and can’t find a single issue. The sooner I receive them the more valuable they’ll be to me, since I’m just now going into the various processes, and the reproductions in Vie Moderne may help me to get a better understanding of what can be done with them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But I ought to ask you to excuse me for all the trouble I put you to.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> was here briefly this week when he was in town for a meeting.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> writes to me about a new series of drawings of miners by <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="1292">Paul Renouard</rs>
                    </hi> in L’Illustration.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> I haven’t seen them yet, but if you happen to see them in a kiosk somewhere where they sell ‘those things that lie in the Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuisch’,<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> please keep an eye out for me, because I believe that they’ll be exceedingly fine things.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t know whether you’ll find it conceited of me or something like that when I tell you that the following gave me pleasure. <rs type="pers" key="1482">Smulders</rs>’s workmen from the other warehouse in the Laan<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> saw the stone of the orphan man and asked the printer if they could have an impression to hang up. No result of my work would be more agreeable to me than that ordinary working men should hang such prints in their room or workplace. I believe <rs type="pers" key="1080">Herkomer</rs> speaks the truth when he says <hi rend="ital">For you — the public — it is really done</hi>.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Of course a drawing must have artistic value, but in my view this shouldn’t rule out the possibility that ordinary passers-by may see something in it. Well, I regard this very first print as nothing as yet, but I hope from the bottom of my heart that it will become something more serious. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Because of the loss of those 50 francs (for I fear they’re gone), both you and I have had a setback in carrying out these experiments, but don’t let it discourage us. How I wish you could see the drawings I’m working on at the moment. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I assure you that when there was no letter from you, and I couldn’t think what the reason might be, I was very melancholy. I would very much like to hear something from you at your early convenience about what I’m sending today. I’ll also help you remember that you were going to return to the subject of <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>
                    </hi> — again, at your early convenience, for I understand that you don’t always have the time to write. Adieu, old chap, thanks again for your letter, and believe me, with a handshake,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>This evening I’ll begin reading <hi rend="ital">Pot-bouille</hi> by <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs>.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This concern is evident from <ref target="let282.xml">letter 282</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The first lithograph sent by Van Gogh to Theo was <hi rend="ital">Old man</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2408">F 1658 / JH 256</rs>); <ref target="let281.xml">see letter 281</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The lithograph <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2409">F 1655 / JH 259</rs>). The impression sent to Theo with the note ‘1re épreuve’ is in the collection of the Van Gogh Museum (inv. no. p 14 V/1962). See Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, pp. 42, 90, cat. no. 2.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
    <ab>The three known impressions of <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi> come from the estates of Theo and <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs>. The copy for <rs type="pers" key="1084">Heyerdahl</rs> is not known, nor is the impression of <hi rend="ital">Old man</hi> (‘an earlier one’) for Buhot. See Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, pp. 42, 90, cat. no. 2.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>The plural ‘very first ones’ indicates that there were a number of copies with the note ‘1re épreuve’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
    <ab>For the three known diggers from this period, <hi rend="ital">Digger</hi> <rs type="ill" key="2410">F 906 / JH 260</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="2411">F 907 / JH 261</rs> and <rs type="otherart" key="429">F 908 / JH 258</rs>, <ref target="let281.xml#n-10">see letter 281, n. 10.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This drawing is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>The fact that Van Gogh asks specifically about <hi rend="ital">La Vie Moderne</hi> is explained by an earlier letter from Theo about special transfer paper in use at the magazine; <ref target="let280.xml">see letter 280</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Which prints from <hi rend="ital">La Vie Moderne</hi> Van Gogh had in his possession at this point is impossible to determine. Sixteen sheets from this magazine survive in the estate; they include only one series of three from the same issue, namely <rs type="pers" key="1146">Auguste Lançon</rs>, <rs type="otherart" key="431">
                            <hi rend="ital">Les chinois fumeurs d’opium à Londres</hi>
                        </rs> (Chinese opium smokers in London); Auguste Lançon, <rs type="otherart" key="432">
                            <hi rend="ital">Au music-hall</hi>
                        </rs> (At the music hall) and <rs type="pers" key="1226">Jean-François Millet</rs>, <rs type="otherart" key="433">
                            <hi rend="ital">Le berger</hi>
                        </rs> (The shepherd) (t*1348 (2 prints on 1 sheet) and t*914); they appeared in <hi rend="ital">La Vie Moderne</hi> 2 (16 October 1880), no. 42.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It is odd that Van Gogh talks about a ‘very old issue’ <ref target="#l-45">(ll. 45-46)</ref>: <hi rend="ital">La Vie Moderne</hi> had only been published since 1879. He may have been thinking of another magazine.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>For this <rs type="ill" key="2009 2010 380">series of miners</rs> by <rs type="pers" key="1292">Renouard</rs>, <ref target="let284.xml#n-11">see letter 284, n. 11.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>For the ‘Zuid-Hollandsch Koffiehuis’, <ref target="let214.xml#n-9;">see letter 214, n. 9;</ref> the statement quoted was also cited in <ref target="let278.xml">letter 278</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1482">Smulders</rs>, <ref target="let253.xml#n-9">see letter 253, n. 9.</ref> Who Smulders’s workmen were is not known. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>For this quotation from <rs type="pers" key="1080">Herkomer</rs>, <ref target="let278.xml#n-7">see letter 278, n. 7.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
<ab>
      <rs type="lit" key="274">
                            <hi rend="ital">Pot-bouille</hi>
                        </rs> (1882) was the most recent novel in the Rougeon-Macquart-cycle by <rs type="pers" key="836">Emile Zola</rs>. The lead character is Octave Mouret, who moves from the provinces to an apartment building in Paris. He discovers that the other occupants lead an outwardly respectable life among the bourgeoisie, but do so to conceal their poverty, adultery or opportunism. A recurring theme is their unsympathetic behaviour towards the domestic staff. The sole exception is honest Madame Hédouin, who manages the department store <rs type="lit" key="275">
                            <hi rend="ital">Au bonheur des dames</hi>
                        </rs> and sees qualities in Mouret that can benefit her business; she decides to offer him her hand in marriage.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>