<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 23 May 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let230"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">230</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">200</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">229</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Tuesday, 23 May 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Tuesday, 23 May 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh’s plans to marry Sien <ref target="let224.xml">(224)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Sien will give birth in Leiden <ref target="let224.xml">(224)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Second order for drawings from Uncle Cor <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="4">
<p>Van Gogh wants to move to the house next door <ref target="let222.xml">(222)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b222 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>This letter is later than <ref target="let229.xml">letter 229</ref> of on or about Thursday, 18 May, because Vincent now asks again and more urgently than in that letter whether Theo has received the drawings he sent. Some time has passed between the last letter and the present one: he is drawing again, he discusses his recent illness <ref target="#l-32">(l. 32)</ref> etc. Moreover, he mentions Sien’s stay in Leiden ‘in 3 weeks or so’ <ref target="#l-17">(l. 17)</ref> – that stay was planned for mid-June (<ref target="let229.xml">letter 229</ref>). Thus <ref target="let230.xml">letter 230</ref> must have been written between 18 and 27 May (<ref target="let231.xml">letter 231</ref>), evidently with an interval of several days between the letters; so we date it to on or about Tuesday, 23 May 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0222" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000261_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000261_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000261_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000261_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000261_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0222" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000261_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000261_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000261_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000261_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000261_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000261_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Een enkel woord in <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>haast.– Hebt gij reeds ontvangen de <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>teekeningen en mijn later schrijven. <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Ik bedoel de portefeuille waar de groote Sorrow <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>in was &amp; die boomwortels<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> &amp;c.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoor Oom Cent is te Parijs – ik hoop <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>dat gij met hem maar niet over de bewuste <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>zaak hebt gesproken want gij weet hoe vreesselijk <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>zij te Prinsenhage babbelen – weinig anders te <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>doen hebbende. Zij beschouwen dit natuurlijk <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>als eene “demoralisatie” of iets dergelijks nog <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>erger. Best. als ik er maar niet naar hoef te luisteren <lb n="12a" xml:id="l-12a"/>en er niet bij ben<c type="kk">/</c> mijnentwege kunnen ze dan babbelen.</ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Van Pa en Moe ontving ik gisteren een vriendelijk <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>schrijven dat mij veel pleizier zou doen indien <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ik gelooven kon dat deze stemming zou blijven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Als ik hen echter over de zaak met X<hi rend="ss">tien</hi> spreek <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>(’t welk ik over een week of 3 – als zij naar <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Leiden is &amp; ik weg kan – wel degelijk doen zal <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>doch eerder niet) als, zeg ik, zij dit een en ander <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>weten<c type="kk">/</c> zullen zij dan ook vriendelijk spreken??? <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Het hangt echter niet van hun af en gij weet <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>genoeg hoe ik denk over de kwestie, en dat <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>aangezien ik niets doe ’t geen wettelijk ongepermitteerd <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>is en ik in ’t moreele hun competentie van oordeelen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>betwijfel<c type="kk">/</c> hunne weigering mij wel leed zou doen doch <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>ik er niet om zou kunnen stoppen of stilstaan. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben weer bezig aan de teekeningen voor C.M. <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>Zullen ze hem echter bevallen – misschien niet. <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>ik kan zulke teekeningen niet <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>anders opvatten dan als studies van <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>perspectief – en daarom maak ik ze vooral <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>om er mij door te oefenen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">Al neemt ZEd. ze niet zoo ben ik toch niet <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>rouwig om de moeite die ik er mij voor geef <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>omdat ik ze graag zelf houd en mij <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>oefen in de kwestie waar zoo oneindig veel van <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>afhangt. perspectief &amp; proportie.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben de laatste 14 dagen maar slap <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>geweest en voelde mij niet prettig. Ik heb er <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>niet aan toe willen geven en toch maar door<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>gegaan. Doch b.v. verscheiden nachten achtereen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>heb ik niet kunnen slapen en was koortsachtig &amp; <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zenuwachtig. Maar ik dwing mij zelf toch aan den <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>gang en in ’t touw te blijven want het is nu geen <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>tijd om niet wel te worden. Ik moet door – <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Christien &amp; haar moeder zijn verhuisd in eene kleinere <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>woning<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> omdat als X<hi rend="ss">tn</hi> uit Leiden komt zij <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>bij mij haar intrek zal nemen<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik ook ben<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>’t zij in beter ’t zij in erger omstandigheden.</ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is een huisje met binnenplaatsje waar <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>ik deze week een teekening van hoop te maken. <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Met den dag meer zie ik dat dezen stap <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>dien ik doe mij een interessant veld opent <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>om te teekenen en modellen te krijgen. <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Hiermee moet men toch ook rekening houden <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>als men mij beoordeelen wil. Mijn vak <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>maakt dat ik dit aandurf<c type="kk">/</c> ’t welk ik<c type="kk">/</c> had <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>ik eene andere betrekking<c type="kk">/</c> niet zou kunnen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik verlang naar Uw schrijven en hoop <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>gij er spoedig tijd voor vinden zult<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Mij dunkt gij zoudt in dezen veel <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>ten goede kunnen leiden in zoover<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dat wetende hoe de zaak in elkaar <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>zit (en hebt gij daaromtrent nog nadere <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>inlichting noodig<c type="kk">/</c> graag wil ik ze U geven <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>naar mijn opregtste &amp; beste weten) in zoover, <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>zeg ik, dat wetende hoe de vork in den steel <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>zit gij het oordeel van hen die later <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>ook als zij de klok zullen hebben hooren luiden <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>toch nog niet begrijpen zullen waar de klepel <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>hangt<c type="kk">/</c> wat zult kunnen matigen en <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>wijzigen zoodat hier geen onaangenaam<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>heden door komen.</ab>
                <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>
<ab rend="indent">Want gij zult dit wel begrijpen – ik wil <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>alle onaangenaamheden<c type="kk">/</c> praatjes<c type="kk">/</c> twist <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>vermijden zooveel mogelijk – en het is om <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>des lieven vredes wil dat ik er nog tot geen <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>mensch dan tot U over sprak, en ook <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>niet spreken zal meer dan absoluut noodig <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>is, b.v. tot Pa als we zoover zijn dat <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>zij naar Leiden is.</ab>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dit is niet iets dat ik zelf gezocht heb doch ’t is <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>mij op den weg gekomen en ik heb het aangepakt <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>en ik ben er blijde om dat het hier op handelen <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>aan komt zonder aarzelen – niet op er over <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>mediteeren. En heb U de zaak eerst van <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>den donkersten kant laten zien<c type="kk">/</c> dan valt <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>het U later hoop ik nog mede.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar – ik wenschte wel dat ik wist <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>wat te doen omtrent het atelier waarover <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>ik U schreef. Ik ben ook met eene <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>mindere woning tevreden – doch <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>eene geschiktere en doelmatiger weet <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>ik niet. En vrees eene ondoelmatiger <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>eigentlijk niet goedkooper zou wezen om <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>reden van dat ik ’t dan bij mijn werk <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>bezuren moet<c type="kk">/</c> al win ik een paar gulden s’maands <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>uit door minder huur te betalen.</ab>
                <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>
<ab rend="indent">En zou dan alligt later zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> waarom <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>heb ik dat atelier laten schieten en niet <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>meer moeite gedaan om het te krijgen.</ab>
                <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>
<ab rend="indent">Meer dan naar Uw brief verlang ik naar Uw <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>komst doch ik begrijp zulks misschien nog <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>eenigen tijd zal moeten duren. <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>Mijn hoofd staat niet erg naar schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>alleen het moet soms. Kunt gij mij nog wat <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>zenden<c type="kk">/</c> het zou goed zijn want ik heb het <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>niet makkelijk. Enfin<c type="kk">/</c> in elk geval <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>schrijf spoedig. Omtrent het atelier vooral <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>wist ik graag Uwe gedachte – het kan <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>iederen dag weg zijn.– à dieu – <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>nog eens, ontrief U niet, doch is het <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>mogelijk zend mij nog wat.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="113*" xml:id="l-113s"/>
<ab>t. à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab>En schrijf ook of gij de <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>teekeningen hebt ontvangen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-18" n="18">kan – &lt; kan</note>
<note target="l-22" n="22">denk &lt; er denk</note>
<note target="l-37" n="37">perspectief &amp; proportie. &lt; <hi rend="ital">Added later.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-103" n="103">zulks &lt; zulk</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Just a brief word in haste. Have you received the drawings and my later letter yet? I mean the portfolio with the large Sorrow in it and the tree roots<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> &amp;c.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hear that <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Cent</rs> is in Paris — I hope you haven’t discussed the matter in question with him, because you know what terrible gossips they are in Princenhage — having little else to do. Of course they regard this as a ‘demoralization’, or something even worse. Fine. As long as I don’t have to listen to them and am not present, they can gossip for all I care. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yesterday I had a friendly letter from <rs type="pers" key="526 524">Pa and Ma</rs> that would give me great pleasure if I could believe this mood would last. However, when I talk to them about the question of <rs type="pers" key="463">Christien</rs> (which I’ll definitely do in 3 weeks or so — when she’s in Leiden and I can get away — but not before), when, I say, they know about one thing and another, will they still speak kindly then??? It isn’t up to them, though, and you know well enough what I think about the matter; and since I’m not doing anything not permitted by law, and since I doubt their competence to make moral judgements, their refusal would hurt but wouldn’t make me stop or stand still. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m working again on the drawings for <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M.</rs> But will he like them? Perhaps not. I can’t see such drawings as anything other than studies of perspective — and so I’m doing them mainly to practise. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Even if His Hon. doesn’t take them I won’t regret the effort I’m putting into them, because I’d like to keep them myself and get some practice in the matter on which such an enormous amount depends — perspective and proportion.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve been rather weak for the last fortnight and haven’t felt well. I didn’t want to give in to it and carried on regardless. But I couldn’t sleep for several nights on end, and was feverish and nervy. Yet I force myself to keep going and to stay busy, for this is no time to fall ill. I must carry on — <rs type="pers" key="463">Christien</rs> and her <rs type="pers" key="464">mother</rs> have moved to a smaller house,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> because when Christien returns from Leiden she’ll move in with me, wherever I am, whether in better or worse circumstances.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s a small house with a courtyard which I hope to do a drawing of this week. With every day that passes I see more and more that the step I’m taking opens up an interesting field for me to draw and find models. People should take this into account if they want to judge me. It’s because of my occupation that I dare do this; I couldn’t do it if I had a different kind of work. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I long for your letter and hope you’ll soon find time to write. It seems to me that you can do a great deal of good in this affair in that, knowing how matters stand (and if you need further information about that, I’ll be happy to provide it as honestly as I can), in that, as I say, knowing what the position is, you’ll be able to moderate and modify somewhat the judgement of those who will later hear about the matter but still not understand exactly what it’s all about, so that it doesn’t lead to unpleasantness. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">For you will understand this — I want to avoid any unpleasantness, gossip or dispute as far as possible — and it was for the sake of peace that I said nothing to anyone except you, and shan’t say more than absolutely necessary, for instance to <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs>, until she’s in Leiden. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">This isn’t something that I’ve sought myself; I encountered it on my way and have taken it on, and am glad that what’s required here is to act without hesitation — not to meditate on the matter. And have first shown you the darkest side of the question, in the hope that it won’t look so bad later on. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But — I did wish I knew what to do about the studio I wrote to you about. I would also be content with a poorer house, but I don’t know of a more suitable and practical one. And fear that a less practical one wouldn’t really be cheaper, because then my work would suffer, even if I saved a few guilders a month by paying less rent. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And later would probably say, why did I let that studio go and not take more trouble to get it? </ab>
<ab rend="indent">More than for a letter, I long for your visit, but I understand that it may have to wait for some time. I’m not really in the mood for writing, but sometimes I have to. If you could send me a little more, it would be good, for things aren’t easy for me. Well, in any case write soon. I would especially like to know what you think about the studio — it could be gone any day. Adieu. Again, don’t inconvenience yourself, but if you can, send me a little more.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>And also write to say whether you’ve received the drawings.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This is the unknown large version of <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi> (<ref target="let222.xml#n-1">see letter 222, n. 1</ref>) and <hi rend="ital">Study of a tree</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2371">F 933r / JH 142</rs>), which were mentioned in <ref target="let226.xml">letter 226</ref> as having been sent. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh added ‘perspective and proportion’ later.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Both <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs> and her <rs type="pers" key="464">mother</rs> were registered as living at Noordstraat 16 and Slijkeinde 31. In May (the exact date is not known) the address became Slijkeinde, corner of Breedstraat 31a (<hi rend="ital">GAH</hi> and exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, pp. 50-52). For Van Gogh’s drawings of this house, <ref target="let231.xml">see letter 231</ref>. </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>