<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 27 December 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let296"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">296</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">255</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">297</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Wednesday, 27 December 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 27 December 1882.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript </p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b277 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>On 31 December Van Gogh remarks that the present letter was written before he began three days of drawing with models (<ref target="let297.xml#l-2">see letter 297, ll. 2-8</ref>). Those days were 29-31 December. His comment that he feels a need to write before the year is over shows that the letter dates from one of the last days of 1882. Based on this, we date the letter on or about Wednesday, 27 December 1882. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0277" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000344_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000344_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000344_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0277" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000344_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000344_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000344_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000344_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000344_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000344_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Eer het jaar om is<c type="kk">/</c> is ’t me behoefte U nog eens <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>te danken voor al Uw hulp en vriendschap<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Ik heb U haast niets gestuurd in geruimen <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>tijd – maar ik spaar op tegen dat ge <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>eens komt.</ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het spijt mij dat het mij dit jaar nog niet is gelukt <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>eene verkoopbare teekening te maken – <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>ik weet het werkelijk niet waar het aan <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ligt dat dit mij niet gelukt is<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik wou ge weer eens op ’t atelier waart<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>’k Geloof ik schreef het U laatst reeds<c type="kk">/</c> ik <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>ben tegenwoordig druk aan groote <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>Koppen bezig omdat ik een gevoel <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>had noodig te hebben meer intiem <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>de structuur van een schedel en het <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>in elkaar zitten eener physionomie <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>te bestudeeren.</ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het werk absorbeert mij sterk en ik vind <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>dezer dagen eenige dingen waar ik lang <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>tevergeefs naar gezocht had.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Enfin <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>als gij eens komt zult ge alles zien<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dezer dagen heb ik gedurig een lastige <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>kiespijn die soms werkt op mijn regter oog <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>en oor en waar misschien de zenuwen ook bij <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>in ’t spel zijn. Als men kiespijn heeft wordt <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>men onverschillig voor veel dingen – maar het is curieus <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>dat b.v. de teekeningen van Daumier zòò raak zijn dat men <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>er haast de kiespijn door vergeet. <lb n="29a" xml:id="l-29a"/>Ik heb weer twee bladen van hem<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="29b" xml:id="l-29b"/>“<hi rend="ital">Un train de plaisir</hi>”<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Reizigers met bleeke gezigten en zwarte <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>jassen in guur weer en die te laat <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>op ’t perron komen. Vrouwen met schreeuwende <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>zuigelingen er tusschen in<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Kent gij het boekje Croquis à la plume<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">geschreven</hi> door den teekenaar <hi rend="ital">Henri</hi> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Monnier</hi> (die M<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Prudhomme uitvond)<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Ik las daarin eene “reis in de dilligence”<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>verbazend echt<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zult nog druk in Uw inventaris <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>zitten &amp; ik houd U niet op<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>Van harte wensch ik U alles <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>goeds in ’t nieuwe jaar toe<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zullen we in ’t nieuwe jaar gelukkiger <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>zijn met het maken van verkoopbare <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>teekeningen – of het vinden van werk <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>aan een illustratie b.v.–</ab>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">Een ding blijf ik gelooven, het worstelen met <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>de natuur is geen ijdel werk, en ofschoon <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ik niet weet welk het resultaat zijn zal<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>er moet een resultaat zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik wou ge weer eens op ’t atelier <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>waart, niet omdat ik niet meer voortkan of niet <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>weet wat te doen, maar vooral daarom <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>omdat ik zoo vrees gij misschien denkt ik <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>niet vorder. En ofschoon ik nog geen definitief <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>resultaat U kan wijzen<c type="kk">/</c> gij zoudt zien <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>dat het langzamerhand zich ontwikkelt. <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>en gij zoudt zien dat ik zoek naar een <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>groote zaak.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben ’t volkomen met U eens wat <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>gij onlangs schreeft<c type="kk">/</c> “er komt een tijd <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>dat men het teekenen zoodanig meester is <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dat het formaat onverschillig wordt en <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>men de proporties zoo in ’t hoofd heeft <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>dat men even goed in ’t groot als in <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>’t klein kan werken”.</ab>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab rend="indent">Niet alleen dat ben ik met U eens doch <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>bovendien ik geloof dat men zich kan <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>en moet opwerken tot eene hoogte <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>dat men compositie<c type="kk">/</c> effekten<c type="kk">/</c> licht &amp; bruin <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>in zoover meester is dat in den kring <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>die men zich gekozen heeft men ook <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>de meest diverse motieven en sujetten <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>meester is – b.v. heden een wachtkamer <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>3<hi rend="ss">e</hi> klasse<c type="kk">/</c> morgen een regendag in een arme <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>buurt<c type="kk">/</c> een ander maal een oudmannetjeshuis<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>dan weer een kroeg of gaarkeuken kan <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>maken.</ab>
                <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoover ben ik nog niet – maar <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>misschien juist omdat ik zoek naar <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>den wortel of oorsprong van veel dingen te gelijk<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>duurt het lang<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dank voor al Uw trouwe vriendschap <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>kerel<c type="kk">/</c> die ik het heele jaar weer ondervond<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Mogt het zijn ik van mijn kant U ook <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>wat pleizier kon doen<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi rend="ital">Eens zal mij dat</hi> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">lukken</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>– In gedachten een handdruk<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>schrijf weer eens als ge een oogenblikje vinden <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>kunt – nogmaals het beste, en geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-66" n="66">werken”. &lt; werken.</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Before the year ends, I feel a need to thank you again for all your help and friendship. I’ve sent you almost nothing for a considerable time, but I’m saving up for when you come some day.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m sorry that I haven’t managed to make a saleable drawing this year — I really don’t know why it is that I haven’t managed this. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I wish you were in the studio once more. I believe I wrote to you recently that at present I’m occupied with large heads because I felt I needed to study the structure of a skull and the composition of a physiognomy more intimately. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The work is most absorbing, and the other day I found some things that I had long looked for in vain.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Anyway, you’ll see everything when you come. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The past few days I’ve had a constant, troublesome toothache that sometimes affects my right eye and ear, and may perhaps involve the nerves too. One becomes indifferent to many things when one has toothache, but it’s curious that <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs>’s drawings, for example, are <hi rend="ital">so</hi> striking that one almost forgets about the toothache. I have two more sheets by him, ‘<hi rend="ital">Excursion train</hi>’, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> passengers with pale faces and black coats in raw weather who get to the platform too late. Women with howling infants between them.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Do you know the little book Croquis à la plume <hi rend="ital">written</hi> by the draughtsman <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="712">Henry Monnier</rs>
                    </hi> (who invented Mr Prudhomme)? In it I read a ‘journey by diligence’, amazingly true to life.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll still be busy with your inventory and I shan’t hold you up. I heartily wish you the very best in the New Year. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Will we have more luck making saleable drawings in the new year, or finding work for an illustrated magazine, say? </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I continue to believe one thing: wrestling with nature is not working in vain, and though I don’t know what the result will be, there will be a result. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I do wish you were in the studio again, not because I can’t make progress or don’t know what to do, but mainly because I’m so afraid that you may think I’m not making progress. And although I can’t show you a definitive result as yet, you would see that it’s gradually developing. And you would see that I’m searching for a great thing.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I agree entirely with what you wrote recently, ‘there comes a time when one has mastered drawing to the degree that the format becomes immaterial and one has the proportions in one’s head, so that one can work just as well on a large or a small scale.’ </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Not only do I agree about that, but on top of that I believe that one can and must raise oneself to a level where one has mastered composition, effects, chiaroscuro to the extent that one can master the most diverse themes and subjects in the field one has chosen — such as today doing a 3rd-class waiting room, tomorrow a rainy day in a poor neighbourhood, another time an almshouse for old men, then a pub or a soup kitchen. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I haven’t got that far yet, but perhaps it’s a long process precisely because I search for the root or origin of many things at the same time.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Thanks for all your loyal friendship, old chap, which I again experienced the whole year long. May I, for my part, be able to give you some pleasure in turn. <hi rend="ital">One day I’ll succeed in that</hi>. In thought a handshake, write again when you can find a moment — best wishes once more, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>In this week, on 25 December 1882, <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> wrote to Theo: ‘It is a better Christmas for us this year than last, with that sad business with V. But we are getting good letters from him and always full of satisfaction with his work’ (FR b2238).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
    <ab>Given the other <rs type="pers" key="977">Daumier</rs> engravings Van Gogh acquired from <hi rend="ital">De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> and a print after <rs type="pers" key="1117">Jacque</rs> mentioned elsewhere, in this case two prints are possible candidates, namely, <hi rend="ital">Reizigers met een pleiziertrein</hi> (On a day out by train), in <hi rend="ital">De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> 2 (1865-1866), no. 21, p. 168; and <hi rend="ital">Met den pleiziertrein – Te laat!</hi> (On a day out by train – Too late!), in<hi rend="ital"> De Hollandsche Illustratie</hi> 2 (1865-1866), no. 4, p. 32. Both are in the estate. <rs type="ill" key="57">Ill. 57</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="2023">Ill. 2023</rs>. (t* 1056 and t*15). <rs type="ill" key="1954">
                            <hi rend="ital">Het eerste april-gras</hi>
                        </rs> (The first grass in April) after Jacque was on the same page as <hi rend="ital">Reizigers met een pleiziertrein</hi>; above <hi rend="ital">Met den pleiziertrein</hi> was <rs type="ill" key="51">
                            <hi rend="ital">De vier leeftijden van den drinker</hi>
                        </rs> (The four ages of the drinker). For these prints, <ref target="let267.xml#n-32">see letter 267, n. 32</ref> and <ref target="let267.xml#n-33">33</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="712">Henry Monnier</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="315">
                            <hi rend="ital">Croquis à la plume</hi>
                        </rs> (1858) consists of 28 dramatised conversations. The story ‘Un voyage en diligence’ is set ‘in the offices and in the interior of the diligence. Parents, friends, acquaintances, porters, messenger boys and idlers throng about the travellers. The horses are harnessed’ (dans les bureaux et dans l’intérieur de la diligence. Les parents, les amis, les conaissances, les portiers, les commissionaires et les oisifs se pressent autour des voyageurs. Les chevaux sont à la voiture). Ed. Brussels 1858, pp. 5-98 (quotation on p. 5).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Monnier used the figure of Joseph Prudhomme to caricature the bureaucracy. Prudhomme personifies the arrogant, puffed-up petit-bourgeois, the prototype of self-important futility, and first appears in <rs type="lit" key="316">
                            <hi rend="ital">Scènes populaires dessinées à la plume</hi>
                        </rs> (1830). He also figures in <rs type="lit" key="317">
                            <hi rend="ital">Grandeur et décadence de M. Joseph Prudhomme. Comédie en cinq actes et en prose</hi>
                        </rs>. Par MM. G[ustave] Vaez [= Jean Nicolas van Nieuwenhuysen] et H[enry] Monnier. Brussels 1853, and in <rs type="lit" key="209">
                            <hi rend="ital">Mémoires de Monsieur Joseph Prudhomme</hi>
                        </rs>. 2 vols. Paris 1857.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>