<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, Saturday, 24 June 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let240"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">240</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">R10</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">240</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Anthon van Rappard</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 24 June 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Anthon van Rappard. The Hague, Saturday, 24 June 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh is treated for gonorrhoea <ref target="let237.xml">(237)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Second order for drawings from Uncle Cor <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b8344 V/2006</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘24 Junij’. In <hi rend="ital">De brieven</hi> 1990 and Hulsker 1993-1 this letter is dated on or about 28 June. This date is no doubt based on Vincent’s remark that he has been in hospital ‘for three weeks now’ <ref target="#l-8">(l. 8)</ref>. Van Gogh was admitted on 7 June, which if we add 21 days makes 28 June. There is no reason, however, to doubt the authenticity of the dating on the manuscript. So in accordance with the letter head we date the letter Saturday, 24 June 1882, and take it that Van Gogh meant that he was in his third week. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 8344" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001589_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001589_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001589_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 8344" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001589_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001589_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001589_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001589_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001589_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001589_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Gasthuis Zaal 6 N<hi rend="ss">o</hi> 9</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>24 Junij</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Amice Rappard</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Bij dezen wil ik U danken voor Uw laatsten brief en <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>zou dit alligt eerder gedaan hebben als ik niet <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>sedert eenigen tijd uit mijn gewone doen was <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>geraakt. Ge moet n.l. weten dat ik Uw brief <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>niet ontving op mijn atelier doch in het gasthuis <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>waar ik nu 3 weken reeds ben.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> In die dagen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>was Uw schrijven mij dubbel welkom dus &amp; deed <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>’t geen gij zegt van die teekeningen die mijn waarden <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Oom weinig schenen te bevallen mij dubbel genoegen. <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Later heb ik echter nog van een ander gehoord <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>dat ze zoo slecht niet waren en dat hij het ook zoo <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>erg niet bedoeld had<c type="kp">_</c> Wat hier ook van zij, terwijl <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ik die teekeningen maakte &amp; sedert nog eenigen van die <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>zelfde soort scharrendroogerijen in de duinen<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> onder <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>anderen<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik kou gevat en daar kwam koorts <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>bij en zenuwen<c type="kk">/</c> en een &amp; ander schijnt op de <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>blaas geslagen te zijn zoodat ik niet urineeren kon <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>en ’t eindelijk zoo benaauwd kreeg &amp; zoo pijnlijk dat ik <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>naar hier gegaan ben. En zij hebben toen met een <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>katheter in mijn blaas gescharreld en zoo voorts tot dat <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ik nu weer in meer normalen toestand begin te komen, <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>wat mij veel pleizier doet. Toch ben ik er nog <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>niet van af en weet nog niet of ik spoedig weer <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>naar huis zal kunnen gaan of niet. Ik hoop het <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>nu binnen 8 dagen wel weer klaar zal zijn maar ’t moet <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>in elk geval zijn tijd hebben.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is hier in ’t gasthuis bijzonder aardig<c type="kk">/</c> ik leg<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> in eene zaal met 10 bedden <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>maar tot heden was ik niet tot teekenen in <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>staat omdat ik mij stil moest houden &amp; <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>ook nu nog is het maar weer een heel <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>flaauw en zwak begin en kan ik nog niets <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>doorzetten en er dieper in doordringen. <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Maar ik mag een uur per dag in den <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>tuin en daar ben ik gisteren weer begonnen <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>te krabbelen. En ten minste ik begin weer <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>te kijken maar in den eersten tijd was ik <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>te bedonderd om ook maar te zien.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik er uit kom zal ik nog wel een tijdje <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>het heel stillekens aan moeten leggen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat ik bijzonder moet prijzen is de behandeling <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>hier<c type="kk">/</c> als ik ooit weer ziek worden moest<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>evenmin als nu een oogenblik aarzelen naar <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>’t gasthuis te gaan<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is, mijns inziens, oneindig <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>meer praktisch dan ’t huis ziek liggen<c type="kk">/</c> ten <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>minste in omstandigheden als de mijnen. <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>In mijn gevoel ben ik nu bijna geheel beter <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>doch de knoop zit hem dáár dat door <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>mij te veel te bewegen<c type="kk">/</c> te loopen &amp;c. ik <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>onmiddelijk weer in kan storten wat mij <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>verleden week gebeurd is<c type="kk">/</c> anders was ik nu al <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>verder.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoodra ik over eenigen tijd eens weder een paar <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>teekeningen heb, b.v. van die scharrendroogerijen <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>of een hofje<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik regt gaarne U eens <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>iets zenden om het zoo mogelijk te plaatsen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>Alleen ik zal er mij niet mede haasten en <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>wachten tot er eens een beter dan gewoonlijk <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>uitvalt want ik stuur ’t dan liever aan U dan <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>weer naar Amsterdam.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Ofschoon ik wel hoop <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Amsterdam weer teregt zal komen.</ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab rend="indent">En wij moeten afspreken dat gij <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>als het U niet lukt het te plaatsen U niet <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>geneeren moet het terug te zenden en niet <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>denken moet zulks mij decourageeren zou <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>want het lukt niet in eens. Hetzij dus het <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>de fout van mijne teekening, ’t zij de <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>fout van den mogelijken liefhebber zijn mogt, laat <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>ons van weerskanten afspreken wij <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>door ’t mislukken van de proef (als ’t niet <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>lukken mogt) ons niet direkt zullen laten afschrikken. <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>Als ik weer aan den gang ben schrijf ik U wel weer <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>eens spoedig<c type="kp">_</c> Nogmaals dank voor Uw brief <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>waarvan ik de beantwoording niet langer wilde <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>uitstellen. Geloof me intusschen</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Hospital Ward 6, No. 9</ab>
<ab>24 June</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear friend <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>
                </ab>
    <ab>This is to thank you for your last letter, which I would certainly have done earlier were it not for the fact I’ve not been my normal self for some time. I must tell you your letter reached me not at my studio but in the hospital, where I’ve been for 3 weeks now.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> So your letter was doubly welcome at the time, and what you say about the drawings that seem not to have pleased my worthy <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle</rs> gave me double pleasure. Later, however, I heard from someone else that they weren’t so bad and that he hadn’t meant to be so critical. Whatever the case, while I was making those drawings and some more since, of the same sort of fish-drying barns in the dunes for instance,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> I caught a cold and then had fever and nerves as well, and it seems that one thing and another affected the bladder so that I couldn’t urinate, and in the end I was so anxious and in such pain that I came here. And they rummaged around in my bladder with a catheter and so forth, and now I’m beginning to return to a more normal condition, which pleases me a good deal. But I’m not clear of it yet, and still don’t know whether I’ll be able to go home soon. I hope it will be over within a week, but it will take some time in any event. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s very pleasant here in the hospital. I’m in a ward with 10 beds, but until today I was unable to draw because I had to lie still, and and even now I’ve made only a very faint and weak beginning and can’t pursue anything or go deeper into things. But I’m allowed in the garden for an hour a day, and there I began scrawling again yesterday. And at least I’m starting to look again, whereas at first I was too miserable even to see. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ll have to take things very quietly for a while when I leave here. Oh well.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I must say a particular word in praise of the treatment here. If I’m ever taken ill again, I shan’t hesitate for a moment, any more than I do now, before going to the hospital. It’s far more practical, in my view, than lying ill at home, at least in circumstances like mine. I feel as if I’m now almost completely cured, but the problem is that as a result of too much moving and walking &amp;c. I may have a relapse at any moment, which is what happened to me last week; otherwise I would now be well on the way. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">As soon as I have a few drawings again in a little while, of the fish-drying barns or a courtyard, for instance, I would dearly like to send you something to see if you can place it. But I shan’t be in a hurry, and shall wait until I have one better than average, because I would rather send it to you than to Amsterdam again.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> Although I do hope Amsterdam will turn out all right again.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And we must agree that if you’re unable to place it you mustn’t hesitate to send it back, and mustn’t think I’ll be discouraged, because it won’t work straightaway. So whether it’s the fault of my drawing or the fault of the possible buyer, let the two of us agree that we shan’t immediately let ourselves be frightened off by the failure of the experiment (were it not to succeed). When I’m back at work, I’ll write again soon. Thanks again for your letter — I didn’t want to put off replying to it any longer. Meanwhile believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>See <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Cf. <hi rend="ital">Fish-drying barn</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2377">F 940 / JH 154</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘lig’ (lie).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>To <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs> in Amsterdam.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>