<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Monday, 18 September 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let266"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">266</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">233</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">268</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 18 September 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Monday, 18 September 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Theo had not been repaid for a loan <ref target="let262.xml">(262)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Zuyderland is a model <ref target="let267.xml">(267)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Theo’s visit early in August <ref target="let253.xml">(253)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="4">
<p>Van Gogh is recovering from his illness <ref target="let241.xml">(241)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b255 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Because Van Gogh writes: ‘I think it very possible that you may not be able to spare the usual precisely on the twentieth. If that’s the case, I want to ask you to send whatever you can spare,’ it can be concluded that the letter was written in the week before the third monthly remittance, thus before the 20th. Moreover, Van Gogh assumes that he can still receive the money before Friday, 22 September, when he wants to pay his models <ref target="#l-5">(ll. 5-11)</ref>. Assuming that the letter, which was written late in the evening <ref target="#l-117">(l. 117)</ref>, was not posted until the following morning, the date assigned is Monday, 18 September 1882.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0255" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000313_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000313_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000313_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000313_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000313_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0255" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000313_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000313_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000313_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000313_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000313_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000313_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Terwijl ik U schrijf ben ik reeds een eind in mijn <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>laatsten gulden gevorderd<c type="kp">_</c>– Wel heb ik hoop om <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>dezer dagen van U te hooren doch in aanmerking <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>nemende wat ge mij laatst schreeft acht ik het zeer <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>wel mogelijk dat gij misschien precies op den <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>twintigsten het gewone niet missen kunt<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Voor dat geval wilde ik U verzoeken toch te sturen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>hetgeen gij disponible zoudt hebben<c type="kk">/</c> meer of <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>minder<c type="kk">/</c> al is het maar een klein gedeelte er van<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Tegen Vrijdag middag krijg ik model, een diakoniehuis <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>mannetje<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> en ik zou hem niet graag onbetaald <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>wegsturen.</ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb nog een extra uitgaaf gehad doordat mijn <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>schilderkist kapot raakte bij gelegenheid ik<c type="kk">/</c> door <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>van een hoogen kant af te springen en van daar <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>zoo snel mogelijk mijn boel te grijpen<c type="kk">/</c> uit den <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>weg moest gaan voor een schichtig paard op het <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>terrein van den Rijnspoor waar men de steenkolen <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>oplaadt.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is daar zeer mooi – ik heb de permissie <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>moeten vragen om er te schilderen daar ’t geen <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>publiek terrein is, en hoop er nu dikwijls te zijn. <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Voorloopig<c type="kk">/</c> bij die gelegenheid heb ik er de hoopen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>steenkool, waar kerels aan ’t scharrelen zijn en een <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>kar en paard stonden, geschilderd<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Verder maakte ik nog een studie van een <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>hofje met een bleek &amp; zonnebloemen.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is prachtig buiten – de blaren hebben <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>allerlei bronskleuren<c type="kk">/</c> groen<c type="kk">/</c> geel<c type="kk">/</c> roodachtig<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>alles warm en rijk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat zou ik willen ge de boel eens bij elkaar kondt <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>zien – sedert Uw bezoek heeft het atelier al een heel <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>ander aanzien. Het is waar dat ik nog al heb 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>moeten uitgeven maar er hangen nu ook heel <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>wat geschilderde studies<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het hofje en die kolenboel waren zoo mooi dat <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>ik er niet af kon blijven ofschoon ik had willen teekenen <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>deze week om reden van de verf.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zou graag hebben en ik werk er op om op mijn atelier <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zulke dingen te brengen die mij iederen morgen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>als ik ze zie het een of ander in gedachten brengen <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>van buiten. Zoodat ik dadelijk weet wat te doen <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>met den dag – en dadelijk ergens lust in heb<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>of gevoel: ik moet nog hier of nog daar eens naar <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>toe.</ab>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat betreft U eens een geschilderde studie te zenden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>ik heb daar niets op tegen – alleen voor ik het doe <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>moeten wij een paar dingen afspreken<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Iemand als Mauve – ieder artist – <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>heeft zeer zeker zijn eigenaardige kleurengamma<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Maar niemand had die den eersten dag en <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>in studies buiten gemaakt komt die niet zoo <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>direkt voor den dag<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs bij schilders die veel <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>ervarener zijn dan ik.</ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Met name de studies van Mauve<c type="kk">/</c> die ik voor <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>mij zeer mooi vind juist om hun soberheid <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>en omdat zij met zooveel trouw gemaakt zijn. <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>Toch missen zij een zeker charme dat de <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>schilderijen die er uit voortkomen hebben in <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hooge mate.</ab>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">En met mij is het nu zoo gesteld dat b.v. <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>de marine die ik ’t laatst t’huisbragt al <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>heel anders van kleur is dan de eerste of tweede <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>waarmee ik begon.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoodat uit ’t geen ik U nu zou kunnen zenden <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>gij nog over mijn koloriet geen oordeel zoudt <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>moeten vellen.</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">En als ik voor mij eigentlijk liever zou wachten <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>met zenden totdat het wat rijper zijn zal<c type="kk">/</c> is <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>zulks omdat ik geloof dat ik nog heel wat veranderen <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>zal van kleur. En van compositie ook.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat is dus het eerste en het tweede is dat <hi rend="ital">studies</hi> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>die men buiten maakt iets anders zijn dan <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>schilderijen bestemd om de wereld in te gaan. <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>Welke laatsten mijns inziens uit de studies voortspruiten <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>maar toch zeer er van mogen en zelfs moeten <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>verschillen. Want in het schilderij geeft de schilder <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>meer een persoonlijk denkbeeld en in een studie <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>is het zijn doel eenvoudig een stuk van de natuur <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>te analyseeren. ’t Zij om zijne gedachte of conceptie <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>juistheid te geven – ’t zij om eene gedachte <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>te krijgen.</ab>
                <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
<ab rend="indent">Studies dus hooren meer op ’t atelier dan in den <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>handel en moeten niet uit hetzelfde oogpunt beschouwd worden als schilderijen<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> </ab>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik denk dat gij het ook wel in dien zin zult <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>beschouwen en van zelf deze dingen in aanmerking zult nemen. <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>Schrijf er echter nog eens over hoe ge wilt ik doen <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>zal, en weet dat ik het zoo zal doen met zenden of <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>nog niet zenden als Uws inziens het beste is.</ab>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar het liefst had ik gij alles eens bij elkaar kondt <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>zien – is er mogelijkheid ge nog in den winter <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>eens komt?</ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Was dat het geval dan zou ik zeker meenen het <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>beter was ik niet zond. Enfin. Maar weet dat <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>ik op zulke dingen als ge omtrent het <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>werk zeggen zoudt met het oog op verkoopbaarheid <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>regt gaarne wil letten en ze in ’t oog houden <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>en meen niet dat ik uwe opinie ligt acht. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>Het studies maken beschouw ik als <hi rend="ital">Zaaijen</hi> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>en het schilderijen maken is oogsten<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik geloof dat men veel gezonder denkt wanneer <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>de gedachten voortspruiten uit direct contact <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>met de dingen dan wanneer men de dingen gaat <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>bekijken met het doel om er dit of dat in te vinden<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoo is het nu ook met de kwestie van koloriet<c type="kp">_</c> Er zijn <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>kleuren die van zelf mooi tegen elkaar doen – <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>maar ik doe mijn best om het te maken zoo als <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>ik het zie – voor ik er op ga werken het te <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>doen zoo als ik het voel. En toch<c type="kk">/</c> het gevoel is <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>een groot ding en zonder dat zou men niets uitvoeren<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>Soms kan ik wel verlangen naar den oogsttijd, <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>nl. naar den tijd dat ik zoo doordrongen zal zijn <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>van de studie van de natuur dat ik zelf iets scheppen <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>zal in een schilderij<c type="kk">/</c> maar anders<c type="kk">/</c> het is mij geen <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>last of iets wat ik niet graag doe<c type="kk">/</c> het analyseeren <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>van de dingen. Het is al laat – ik kan zoo slecht <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>slapen tegenwoordig – maar het is die prachtige <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>herfstnatuur die mij in ’t hoofd zit en de zorg <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>om er wat van te profiteeren.</ab>
                <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik wou echter dat ik op zijn tijd slapen <hi rend="ital">kon</hi> en doe <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>er mijn best voor want ik wordt er zenuwachtig van <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>maar niets helpt er aan.</ab>
                <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoe gaat het U toch – ik hoop zoo gij niet al te <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>veel zorgen hebt, want daar gaat men niet op <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>vooruit. Ik geloof dat als ik niet zooveel buitenlucht <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>had en minder pleizier in het schilderen ik gaauw <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>miserable zou worden. Maar buiten zijn en werken <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>aan iets dat animeert zijn dingen die de kracht <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>vernieuwen en onderhouden. Het is alleen bij tijden als <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>ik oververmoeid ben dat ik mij door en door ellendig voel <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>maar anders geloof ik dat ik wat gezondheid aangaat <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>er weer boven op zal komen.</ab>
                <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>
<ab rend="indent">à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> ontvang een handdruk in gedachten en <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>schrijf eens hoe ik doen moet<c type="kk">/</c> U een geschilderde <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>studie zenden of nog niet. En weet ik iederen dag <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>aan U denk &amp; geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="137*" xml:id="l-137s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="137*"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-15" n="15">door &lt; mij door</note>
<note target="l-17" n="17">uit &lt; ik uit</note>
<note target="l-45" n="45">gevoel: &lt; gevoel</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>As I write to you, I’m already down to my last guilder. I hope to hear from you soon but, bearing in mind what you last wrote to me I think it very possible that you may not be able to spare the usual precisely on the twentieth. If that’s the case, I want to ask you to send whatever you can spare, be it more or less, even if it’s only a small part. A model is coming on Friday afternoon, a man from the almshouse,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and I wouldn’t like to send him away unpaid. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I had some extra expenditure because my painting box got broken when I jumped from a high bank and, trying to grab my things as quickly as possible, had to get out of the way of a skittish horse in the Rijnspoor yards where they stockpile the coal.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s very beautiful there — I had to ask permission to paint there, since it’s not a public area, and now hope to be there often. Meanwhile, on that occasion I painted the mounds of coal there, where men were pottering about, and there was a horse and cart.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I also did a study of a courtyard with a bleaching ground and sunflowers.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s splendid outdoors. The leaves are all manner of bronze colours — green, yellow, reddish — all warm and rich. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I do so wish that you could see everything together — since your visit the studio has taken on a completely different appearance. It’s true that I’ve had 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> to spend quite an amount, but now there are a good number of painted studies on the walls.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The courtyard and all that coal were so beautiful that I couldn’t resist them, although this week I wanted to draw because of the paint. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I would very much like, and am working towards this, to put things in my studio that will remind me when I see them each morning of this or that outdoors. So that I immediately know what to do with the day — and immediately take pleasure in something, or have the feeling: I must still go here or there sometime. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards sending you a painted study, I have nothing against that — but before I do, we must agree on a couple of things. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Someone like <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> — any artist — undoubtedly has his own distinctive colour range. But no one had it on the first day, and in studies done out of doors it isn’t immediately apparent, even with painters who are much more experienced than I am. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Especially the studies by <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>, which I find very beautiful precisely because of their soberness, and because they’re done with such fidelity. Yet they lack a certain charm which the paintings derived from them have in great measure. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And in my case the position is that, for example, the seascape I brought home most recently is already very different in colour from the first or second I started with.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So you must make no judgement about my colour on the basis of what I can send now. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And if I would really prefer to wait until things are riper before sending, it’s because I believe I’ll change a great deal in colour. And in composition too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">So that’s the first thing, and the second is that <hi rend="ital">studies</hi> done out of doors are different from paintings intended to go out into the world. In my view the latter stem from the studies, but may, and indeed must, differ from them markedly. For in the painting the artist presents a more personal idea, and in a study his aim is simply to analyze a piece of nature. Either to give his thought or conception precision, or to arrive at a thought. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Thus studies belong more in the studio than in the trade, and shouldn’t be looked at from the same viewpoint as paintings.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, I believe that you’ll take the same view and will naturally take these things into consideration. But write and tell me what you’d like me to do, and rest assured that as regards sending or not sending yet I’ll do what seems best to you. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But what I would like most of all would be for you to see everything together — is there any possibility that you could come again in the winter sometime? </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If so, I certainly think it would be better if I don’t send. Anyway. But rest assured that I pay close attention to whatever you say about the work with a view to saleability and bear it in mind, and don’t imagine that I treat your opinion lightly. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I regard making studies as <hi rend="ital">Sowing</hi>, and making paintings as reaping.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I believe that one thinks much more healthily when the ideas arise from direct contact with things than when one looks at things with the aim of finding this or that in them. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s the same with the question of the use of colour. There are colours that are naturally beautiful seen together, but I do my best to make it as I see it, before I set to work to make it as I feel it. And yet, feeling is a big thing, and without that one would produce nothing. Sometimes I can yearn for harvest time, that is, the time when I’ll be so permeated by the study of nature that I myself will create something in a painting, yet analyzing things isn’t a burden to me or something I dislike doing. It’s already late — I sleep so badly at present — but it’s that wonderful nature of autumn that’s on my mind, and the worry about getting something out of it. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">However, I wish I <hi rend="ital">could</hi> get some sleep now and then, and do my best, for it makes me nervous, but nothing helps. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But how are things with you? I do hope you don’t have too many worries, because that doesn’t help really. I believe that I would soon be miserable if I didn’t have so much fresh air and enjoyed painting less. But being outdoors and working on something that stimulates are things that renew and sustain one’s strength. It’s only at times when I’m overtired that I feel thoroughly wretched, yet as to my health, I believe I’ll recover. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Adieu, accept a handshake in thought, and write and tell me what I should do — send you a painted study, or not yet. And rest assured that I think of you every day, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Diakoniehuismannetjes received support from the poor board of the Netherlands Reformed Congregation. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The depot where Van Gogh was working was between the line to Gouda and a branch that joined up with the Rotterdam-Amsterdam line. There were engine sheds and a workshop, and piles of coal. See exhib. cat. The Hague 1990, p. 31.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>This painting of the coal store is not known. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This painted study (cf. <ref target="#l-37">ll. 37-39</ref>) of a court is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>The recent seascape, which was also mentioned in <ref target="let264.xml">letter 264</ref>, is not known. The seascapes, which were among Van Gogh’s first painted works, were <hi rend="ital">Beach with fishing boats</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2383">F 2 / JH 173</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">View of the sea at Scheveningen</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2390">F 4 / JH 187</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>To some extent an old-fashioned view: there certainly was a separate market for ‘successful studies’. See Boime 1971.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Van Gogh made this comparison – cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="2 Cor" chap="9" v="6">2 Cor. 9:6</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Gal" chap="6" v="7">Gal. 6:7</bibleref> – earlier in a similar context, <ref target="let265.xml#n-13">see letter 265, n. 13.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>