<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Monday, 10 April 1882.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let216"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">216</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">186</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">215</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Monday, 10 April 1882</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Monday, 10 April 1882.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Vincent owes Tersteeg 25 guilders <ref target="let214.xml">(214)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b207 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>This letter precedes <ref target="let217.xml">217</ref>, in which Vincent says that he has received the money requested in this letter: ‘send what you spoke of not too late in the month’ <ref target="#l-55">(ll. 55-58)</ref>. Furthermore, in <ref target="let217.xml">letter 217</ref> he mentions having paid back the money he borrowed from Tersteeg <ref target="#l-35">(l. 35)</ref>, whereas in this letter he writes that he must still do it. He also sends a drawing <ref target="#l-3">(l. 3)</ref>, which Theo appears to have received in <ref target="let217.xml">letter 217</ref>.</p>
<p rend="indent">The fact that this letter was written after <ref target="let215.xml">letter 215</ref> emerges from <ref target="#l-47">ll. 47-48</ref>, in which Vincent returns to a topic mentioned earlier, i.e. paying back the money he had borrowed from Tersteeg (this refers to <ref target="let215.xml#l-109">l. 109</ref> in <ref target="let215.xml">letter 215</ref>). As regards the date assigned to this letter – on or about Monday, 10 April 1882 – <ref target="let214.xml">see letter 214</ref>, <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0207" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000237_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000237_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000237_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000237_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000237_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0207" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000237_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000237_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000237_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000237_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000237_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000237_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Heden heb ik per post aan U <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>verzonden 1 Teekening<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> die ik <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>U zend als bewijs van dankbaarheid <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>voor zooveel dat gij dezen anders <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>barren winter voor mij gedaan hebt. <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Toen gij verl. zomer die groote <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>houtsnee van Millet<c type="kk">/</c> “la bergère”<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>bij U hadt toen heb ik gedacht: wat <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>kan men met één enkele lijn <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>veel doen. Ik heb natuurlijker<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>wijs niet de pretentie om met een <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>enkelen omtrek zooveel te zeggen <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>als Millet. Doch evenwel heb <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ik getracht wat sentiment in dit <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>figuur te leggen. Nu hoop ik <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>maar dat deze teekening U <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>sympathiek moge zijn. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>En nu ziet ge er meteen aan dat <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>ik druk aan den slag ben. <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Nu ik er eenmaal aan begonnen <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>ben zou ik wel graag een 30 tal <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>naaktstudies maken.</ab>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bijgaand is dunkt me ’t beste <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>figuur dat ik nog geteekend heb<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>daarom dacht ik dat ik ’t U zenden <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>wilde.</ab>
                <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dit is niet de studie naar ’t model <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>en toch is het direkt naar ’t model. <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Ge moet weten dat ik twee <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>vel onderleg onder mijn papier <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>had. Nu had ik er hard op <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>gesjouwd om den contour <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>juist te krijgen en toen ik <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>de teekening van de plank <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>nam was het zeer zuiver op <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>de twee vel onderleg door<c type="shy">-</c>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>gedrukt en toen heb ik <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>’t onmiddelijk naar de <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>eerste studie opgewerkt, <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zoodat deze zelfs frisscher <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>is dan de eerste.</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">De twee anderen heb ik zelf <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>gehouden en die zou ik niet <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>graag wegdoen.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Gij zult meteen <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>hieruit zien dat het niet zonder <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>reden is dat ik U schreef ik wel wilde <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>dat het geld voor H<c type="kp">_</c>G.T<c type="kp">_</c> nog kon wachten<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ik heb het nu zelf zoo noodig en mij <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>dunkt dat hard werken met model de <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>kortste weg is om er geheel boven op <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>te komen. Het model dat ik heb is wel <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>zoo duur niet doch omdat de uitgaaf telkens <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>terug komt is het mij toch dikwijls moeielijk <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>het te betalen. Enfin schik het zoo als <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>het ’t beste is doch als het U convenieert <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>zend dan ’t geen waarvan ge spraakt niet <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>al te laat in de maand. à Dieu<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab>t<c type="kp">_</c> à. t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab>Het komt mij voor deze teekening <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>goed zou doen in eenvoudige <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">grijze</hi> passepartout<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab>’t Spreekt van zelf dat ik niet altijd <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>zoo teeken als ditmaal. Doch ik houd <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>bijzonder veel van die Engelsche teekeningen <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>die in dezen stijl<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> gedaan zijn en <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>’t is dus geen wonder dat ik het eens <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>zoo geprobeerd heb en omdat het voor <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>U was die zulke dingen <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>wel begrijpt heb ik niet geschroomd <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>wat melankoliek te zijn. Ik wou zoo <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>iets er mee zeggen als</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>
<ab>Mais reste le vide du coeur</ab> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
                <ab>Que rien ne remplira </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab>zooals in het boek van Michelet staat<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Today I sent you 1 drawing<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> by post which I’m sending to you as a token of gratitude for so much that you’ve done for me during this otherwise hard winter. Last summer, when you had that large woodcut by <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>, ‘the shepherdess’,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> I thought: how much one can do with one single line! Naturally I don’t presume to say as much as Millet with a single outline. But I’ve nevertheless tried to put some sentiment into this figure. Now I only hope that this figure is to your liking. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> And now you see at the same time that I’m hard at work. Now that I’ve started, I’d like to make around 30 studies of the nude.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The enclosed is, I think, the best figure I’ve drawn, that’s why I thought I’d send it to you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">This isn’t the study from the model and yet it’s directly from the model. You should know that I had two sheets underneath my paper. Well, I’d toiled to get the outlines right and when I took the drawing off the plank it was very cleanly impressed on the two underlying sheets 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> and then I immediately worked it up after the first study, so that this one is even fresher than the first.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve kept the other two and wouldn’t like to part with them.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> At the same time you’ll see from this that it isn’t without reason that I wrote to you that I wished the money for <rs type="pers" key="787">H.G.T.</rs> could wait, I need it so much myself now, and working hard with a model seems to me to be the quickest way of getting right on top of it. The model I have isn’t at all expensive, but because the expense recurs day after day it’s often difficult for me to pay it. Anyway, arrange it as best you can, but if it’s convenient for you, send what you spoke of not too late in the month. Adieu, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>It seems to me that this drawing would do well in a simple <hi rend="ital">grey</hi> mount.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab>Naturally I don’t always draw like this. But I’m extremely fond of those English drawings that are done in this style,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> so it’s no wonder that I tried to do the same for once, and because it was for you, who understands these things, I didn’t hesitate to be somewhat melancholy. I wanted to say something like</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>But the heart’s emptiness remains</ab>
<ab>That nothing will make full again</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>as it says in <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s book.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>As may be inferred from what follows, the drawing in question must be <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi>. The outline is an important aspect <ref target="#l-9">(ll. 9-14)</ref> and it is evidently a study of a nude; cf. <ref target="#l-23">l. 23</ref>. The following letters confirm this identification: see, for example, <ref target="let217.xml#l-69">letter 217, l. 69</ref>. Two versions of <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi> have survived (<ref target="#n-3">see n. 3</ref>). The version sent to Theo is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1226">Jean-François Millet</rs>, <hi rend="ital">La grande bergère assise </hi>(The large shepherdess seated), engraved by <rs type="pers" key="149">Jean Baptiste Millet</rs>, was in Van Gogh’s possession. The print measures 27.3 x 21.9 cm. <rs type="ill" key="267">Ill. 267</rs>. See exhib. cat. Paris 1998, pp. 121-123, figs. 36-37.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Van Gogh thus had at this time <hi rend="ital">three</hi> versions of <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi>: the actual study and two copies made by tracing over its lines hard enough to make an impression of it on two other sheets. Two of the three drawings have survived: one in pencil, with wash (<rs type="ill" key="2364">F 929 / JH 129</rs>) and one in black chalk (<rs type="ill" key="2365">F 929a /JH 130</rs>).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It is unlikely that Vincent sent Theo the last version. In the following letter he specifically mentions a ‘pencil drawing’ and advises Theo to consider applying milk as a fixative (<ref target="let217.xml#l-27">letter 217, l. 27</ref>). The hard-handed way in which he handled the paper (cf. <ref target="#l-32">ll. 32-34</ref>) indicates that this version is the original study made from the model, which he says he kept for himself. The sheet also bears traces of a grid. If such squaring was intended for the lithograph made later (<ref target="let282.xml">see letter 282</ref> ff.), this is another reason why Van Gogh would not have sent it to Theo. See also exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, pp. 62-63, 70, cat. no. 5.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Below <hi rend="ital">Sorrow</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2365">F 929a /JH 130</rs>) he wrote: ‘Comment se fait-il qu’il y ait sur la terre une femme seule – délaissé. Michelet’. (Why is there a woman alone on earth – abandoned). These words were taken from <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="12">
                            <hi rend="ital">La femme</hi>
                        </rs>; ‘délaissé’ is Van Gogh’s own addition (Michelet 1863, p. 37). Regarding the connection between the drawing and the quotation, see Soth 2004, pp. 179-180. Van Gogh quotes the same line from Michelet in <ref target="let316.xml">letter 316</ref>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The other extant version of Sorrow (<rs type="ill" key="2364">F 929 / JH 129</rs>) comes from the estate of <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs>, to whom Van Gogh must have given it as a present.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Vincent later made a larger version of the drawing, which he sent to Theo (<ref target="let222.xml">see letter 222</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>It is not impossible that Van Gogh, who at this time was reading <rs type="pers" key="617 618">Edmond and Jules de Goncourt</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="224">
                            <hi rend="ital">Gavarni, l’homme et l’oeuvre</hi>
                        </rs>, based this advice to Theo to put the drawing in a simple grey mount on a remark made by <rs type="pers" key="1043">Gavarni</rs>, who in 1852 had advised an Englishman, to whom he had sent some drawings: ‘when these drawings have arrived safely they will have to be remounted and reglazed, following the instructions I shall give you, and <hi rend="ital">edged with a simple strip of grey paper</hi>’ (‘ces dessins, arrivés à bon port, il faudra les faire recartonner et revitrer, selon les indications que je vous donnerai, <hi rend="ital">et border d’une simple bande de papier gris</hi>’). Goncourt 1873, p. 328; the italics are ours. Cf. also <ref target="let217.xml">letters 217</ref> and <ref target="let434.xml">434</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>By ‘in this style’ Van Gogh must have meant ‘likewise working with a rather heavy dose of socio-realist sentiment’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s <rs type="lit" key="133">
                            <hi rend="ital">L’oiseau</hi>
                        </rs> (‘L’hirondelle’): ‘But the heart’s emptiness remains; its emptiness remains, / And nothing will make it full again’ (Mais le vide du coeur reste, mais reste le vide du coeur, / Et rien ne le remplira) (Michelet 1861, p. 153). This is an adaptation of <rs type="pers" key="734">Friedrich Rückert</rs>’s ‘<rs type="lit" key="36">Aus der Jugendzeit</rs>’:</ab>
    <vg:whiteline/>
<ab rend="indent">Once the heart is emptied, once the heart is emptied,</ab>
<ab rend="indent">it never becomes full again.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab rend="indent">(Ist das Herz geleert, ist das Herz geleert,</ab>
<ab rend="indent">wird’s nie mehr voll.)</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>The words quoted were taken from the seventh verse. See Pabst 1988, p. 14 and cf. <ref target="let039.xml#n-2">letter 39, n. 2.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>