<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Friday, 23 February 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let319"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">319</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">269</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">322</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Friday, 23 February 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Friday, 23 February 1883.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Theo’s love for the ailing Marie <ref target="let300.xml">(300)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Alterations to the studio windows <ref target="let317.xml">(317)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b292 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter was written after the alterations were made to the windows of the studio, which were completed on or about 22 February 1883 (<ref target="let320.xml">see letter 320</ref>). Vincent thanks Theo for the remittance (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-3</ref>); this must have been the third remittance of the month, which generally arrived around the 20th (there seems to have been no question of an unusual delay). Later in the letter, moreover, he asks for the next remittance to be sent before rather than after ‘1 March’ <ref target="#l-87">(ll. 87-91)</ref>; this in a month with only 28 days. The letter must therefore date from on or about Friday, 23 February 1883.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0292" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000365_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000365_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000365_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000365_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000365_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0292" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000365_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000365_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000365_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000365_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000365_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000365_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Met een enkel woordje wilde ik U de <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>goede ontvangst van Uw brief berigten en <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>U er voor bedanken.</ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab rend="indent">En U zeggen het mij regt hartelijk verheugt dat <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>gij omtrent Uw zieke goede berigten zenden <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>kondt. Des te beter<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er zijn veel liefdes in één liefde – en ’t is weer <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>iets heel anders als de vrouw gezond wordt – en <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>dat is ook iets heerlijks<c type="kp">_</c>– Het doorgaan en volhouden <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>is ’t voornaamste<c type="kk">/</c> wie variatie wil moet trouw <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>blijven. En wie veel vrouwen wil zien moet <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>bij een en dezelfde zich bepalen. De lente vordert <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>hier goed.–</ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Op ’t moment zit ik in een ergen rommel. <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Ingesloten een krabbeltje<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> in vliegende vaart <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>gedaan bij het plaatsen van de bewuste blinden. <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>op een vodje papier. Waarom ik het U <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>zoo stuur<c type="kk">/</c> onbeteekenend als het is in zijn <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>natuurlijken toestand – Omdat ik geloof <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>dat gij er één ding duidelijk uit zien zult<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>dat ik nu op mijn atelier een heel ander <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>effekt van licht kan krijgen dan het al te <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>sterke licht van die 3 groote ramen.</ab>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Raam 1 is nu (in het krabbeltje) van onderen afgesloten en het <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>restant ook nog voor een deel.– lijkt nu de deur <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>van een kamertje in een hofje b.v.</ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Raam 2 is van boven toe en lijkt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>een venstertje waar de figuurtjes zitten<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">’t Fonds<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> links is donker want raam 3 is geheel <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>digt.</ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">Denk U ’t verschil tusschen ’t effekt van cru licht dat de <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>drie ramen op dit moment geven zouden zonder blinden <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>en gij zult genoeg begrijpen hoe men nu <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>oneindig beter werken kan. Behalve ’t invallend <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>licht kreeg men vroeger een enorme reflexie die alle <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>effekten neutraliseerde.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dikwijls was ik desperaat als ik b.v. <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>een vrouwtje zag scharrelen in een klein vertrek <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>en in ’t figuurtje een karakter en iets mysterieus <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>was dat absoluut weg ging als ik dat zelfde <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>vrouwtje op ’t atelier had.</ab>
                <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoo ook was de weesman b.v. veel mooier <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>in een donkeren gang dan op mijn atelier. <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>En zulks was erg verdrietig en de oppervlakte <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>van die 3 ramen zoo groot dat het door schermen <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>of bordpapier niet voldoende te temperen was. <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>Maar nu ben ik op weg om dat een en <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>ander te overwinnen.</ab>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hoe vormeloos het krabbeltje ook zij<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>het is direkt zoo onder het werken aan <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>de ramen naar de natuur (maar in vliegende haast) gedaan<c type="kk">/</c> en <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>zult gij er uit zien dat men leuke <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>effekten kan krijgen nu en die zeer <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>varieeren. en stuur ik het U liever <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>dan dat ik de zaak in woorden <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>expliceer.</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin het licht op ’t atelier heb ik nu betrekkelijk <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>onder den duim en kan<c type="kk">/</c> als ik in een ander huis <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>’t een of ander figuurtje heb opgemerkt<c type="kk">/</c> t’huis het <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>betrekkelijk terugvinden als ik let op de <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>verlichting en mijn licht daarnaar regel. <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>Hoe groot was de kwantiteit licht? Viel het van <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>voren<c type="kk">/</c> van achteren<c type="kk">/</c> van regts<c type="kk">/</c> van links<c type="kk">/</c> van <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>boven<c type="kk">/</c> van beneden op ’t figuur<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">’k Denk gij er schik in zult hebben als gij eens <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>komt<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab rend="indent">De kast is ook best<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">’t Is nog een lastige karwei geweest daar <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>de blinden te breed waren voor de <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>ramen en ze vertimmerd moesten <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>worden.</ab>
                <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar ’t is tot zoover klaar en <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>nu heb ik mijn volle pleizier pas <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>in ’t atelier en is het praktisch <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>in harmonie met wat ik zoek. <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>Ik krijg misschien later nog <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>een kamertje op den zolder bovendien <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>– als er weer oud hout is.</ab>
                <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
<ab rend="indent">Daar zou een zeer pittoresk en echt <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>gevalletje kunnen gemaakt worden. <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>Maar dit is bijzaak.</ab>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar het atelier is 10 maal beter. <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>Nu kost het mij echter wel <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>wat meer dan ik gedacht had daar <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>er zooveel aan de oude blinden <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>moest veranderd worden.</ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Daarom wilde ik U vragen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>aangezien ik op 1 maart iets beloofd <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>heb te betalen – als ge kunt<c type="kk">/</c> stuur <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>liever een dag vroeger dan een dag <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>later.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
<ab rend="indent">’k Wed gij U kunt begrijpen dat het <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>atelier gansch en al er door veranderd <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>is – o ik vind het zoo heerlijk – ik <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>heb er zoo met de handen in ’t haar <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>door gezeten omdat ik ’t niet goed <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>krijgen kon.</ab>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab rend="indent">’k sprak van goede berigten omtrent Uw <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>zieke – maar dat zij naar haar land<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> terug <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>zou willen – zie ik maar half heil <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>in – doch zooals gij zegt – voor zij <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>beter is valt er weinig over de toekomst te <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>zeggen.</ab>
                <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>
<ab rend="indent">Moge de lente haar goed doen.</ab>
                <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik schrijf in haast en heb <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>nog veel te sjouwen – ik ben verbazend <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>blij met de verandering van de ramen. <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>Voor zoo ver ik oordeelen kan<c type="kk">/</c> voorloopig <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>is het doeltreffend. Gij herinnert U toch <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>nog wel van Uw bezoek van dezen zomer <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>hoe het licht te cru was en niet veranderd <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>kon worden. Naar aanleiding van het <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>krabbeltje begrijpt ge alligt men nu tot <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>in ’t oneindige varieeren kan en effekten <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>welke men in kleine huisjes ziet<c type="kk">/</c> terugvinden. <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>Wat men dan vóór heeft is dat in de kleine <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>huisjes men zijn afstand niet goed nemen <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>kan om de figuren te teekenen en op <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>’t atelier wel. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>fermen handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>
<ab>Ik zal van nacht <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>waarschijnlijk zelfs wel droomen <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>van kerels in zuidwesters en oliejassen <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>waar op ’t licht valt<c type="kk">/</c> en <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>pikante kantlichtjes die den vorm <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>accentueeren doet ontstaan<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-24" n="24">(in het krabbeltje) &lt; <hi rend="ital">Added later; parentheses added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-51" n="51">(maar <supplied>
                            <hi rend="ital">...</hi>
                        </supplied> haast) &lt; <hi rend="ital">Added later; parentheses added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Just a word to report the safe arrival of your letter and to thank you for it. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And to tell you it pleases me greatly that you were able to send good news about your <rs type="pers" key="508">patient</rs>. So much the better.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">There are many loves in one love — and things are very different again when the woman regains her health — and that’s wonderful too. Continuing and persevering is the main thing; if you want variety you should remain faithful. And if you want to see many women you should confine yourself to one and the same. Spring is coming along well here. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">At the moment I’m in a complete mess. Enclosed a scratch<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> dashed off when the blinds were put in place. On a scrap of paper. Why send it to you like this, insignificant as it is in its natural state? Because I believe that you’ll see one thing clearly from it, that now I can get a light effect in my studio that’s totally different from the overly strong light of the 3 big windows. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Window 1 now (in the scratch) has its lower part closed off, and the rest too in part. Now looks like the door of a room in an almshouse, say. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Window 2 has its top part closed off and looks like a window where the figures sit.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The background on the left is dark because window 3 is completely closed. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Imagine the difference from the effect of harsh light that the three windows would give at present without blinds and you’ll well understand how one can work infinitely better now. Apart from the light coming in, there was an enormous reflection in the past that neutralized all effects. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I was often desperate when, for example, I saw a little old lady pottering about in a small room and there was a character and something mysterious in the figure that vanished completely when I had that same old lady in the studio. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Equally, the orphan man, say, was much finer in a dark passage than in my studio. And this was most regrettable, and the surface area of those 3 windows was so large that it couldn’t be dimmed sufficiently with screens or cardboard. But now I’m in the process of overcoming one thing and another. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">However formless the scratch may be, it was done immediately from nature (but in great haste) while the work on the windows was going on, and you’ll see from it that one can now obtain nice effects and vary them greatly. And I prefer to send it to you rather than explain the matter in words. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Anyway, I now have the light in the studio pretty well under control, and, if I’ve spotted a figure in another house I can re-create it fairly well at home if I pay attention to the lighting, and adjust my light accordingly. How great was the quantity of light? Did it fall onto the figure from in front, from behind, from the right, from the left, from above, from below? </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think you’ll be pleased by it when you come sometime. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The cupboard is fine too. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It was a tricky job, because the blinds were too wide for the windows and had to be altered.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But it’s finished for now, and only now do I have the full enjoyment of the studio, and it almost corresponds with what I seek. Later I may get a small room in the attic as well — if there’s some old wood again. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">A highly picturesque and distinctive thing could be made there. But this is a minor point. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But the studio is 10 times better. It’s going to cost me more now than I had thought, though, because so many changes had to be made to the old blinds. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So I wanted to ask you, since I’ve promised to pay something on 1 March, send a day earlier rather than a day later, if you can. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I wager you can understand that the studio is utterly transformed as a result — Oh, I find it such a delight — I was driven to distraction because I couldn’t get it right.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I spoke of good news about your <rs type="pers" key="508">patient</rs>, but I think it’s only half a good sign that she wants to go back to her country,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> although as you say there’s little to be said about the future until she’s better.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">May the spring do her good.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, old chap, I’m writing in haste and still have a lot of work to do — I’m immensely pleased with the changes to the windows. It’s effective for the time being, as far as I can tell. You must remember how the light was too harsh and couldn’t be altered when you visited this summer. From the scratch, you’ll probably be able to see that now one can vary it endlessly and reproduce effects one sees in small houses. The advantage that one then has is that whereas in those small houses one can’t stand back at the proper distance to draw the figures, one can in the studio. Adieu, with a firm handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Tonight I’ll probably even dream of chaps in sou’westers and oilskins on which the light falls and creates remarkable glancing lights that accentuate the form. </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This scratch showing the effects of installing the shutters is not known. Cf. in this connection the letter sketches in <ref target="let318.xml">letter 318</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘fond’ (background).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="508">Marie</rs> came from Brittany, on the north coast of France (cf. <ref target="let301.xml">letter 301</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>