<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Friday, 17 August 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let374"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">374</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">313</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">378</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Friday, 17 August 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Friday, 17 August 1883.</p>
</vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b336 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>There are five letters that were written in a period of five days as a result of Theo’s visit. We have reconstructed the course of events as follows, assuming that Theo indeed arrived in The Hague on the afternoon of Friday, 17 August (<ref target="let373.xml">see letter 373</ref>), went from there to Amsterdam and on Sunday evening or Monday returned to Nuenen. </p>
<p rend="indent">He would have visited Vincent that same Friday; during their conversation Theo must have suggested that Vincent should leave Sien. We see letter 374, which begins <hi rend="ital">in medias res,</hi> as an immediate reaction to this conversation that was delivered to Theo at the address where he was staying the same day, i.e. Friday, 17 August 1883. Vincent wishes his brother a ‘safe journey’ <ref target="#l-84">(l. 84)</ref>, which refers to Theo’s visit to Amsterdam and shows that he did not expect to see him again. But the letter was (in part) the reason for a second meeting, because the brothers spoke to each other again, most probably on Saturday, 18 August, just before Theo’s departure for Amsterdam (see also <ref target="let388.xml#l-298">letter 388, l. 298</ref>). When he got home after that meeting, Vincent immediately wrote <ref target="let375.xml">letter 375</ref>. Theo was most likely in Amsterdam on the Sunday, where he spoke to Uncle Cor (see the beginning of <ref target="let378.xml">letter 378</ref>).</p>
<p rend="indent">
  <ref target="let376.xml">Letter 376</ref> follows <ref target="let375.xml">letter 375</ref>; it was sent together with a letter to Mr van Gogh to Nuenen, where he wishes Theo a few more ‘beautiful sunsets’ <ref target="#l-181">(ll. 181-182)</ref>. <ref target="let381.xml">Letter 381</ref>, in which Vincent thanks Theo for the third remittance of the month (<ref target="let381.xml#l-*1">see ll. 1*-2</ref> and notes), must date from on or about 21 August. Since <ref target="let377.xml">letter 377</ref> comes before it (Vincent asks Theo’s opinion about <ref target="let376.xml">letter 376</ref>), we have dated <ref target="let377.xml">letter 377</ref> to Monday, 20 August. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0336" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000429_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000429_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000429_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0336" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000429_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000429_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000429_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000429_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000429_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000429_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste broer.</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Ik wenschte ge kondt inzien ik in verschillende dingen <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>consequent moet zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ge weet wat een “<hi rend="ital">erreur de point de vue</hi>” in ’t schilderen is<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>n.l. heel iets anders en veel ergers dan eene misteekening <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>van dit of dat detail<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Een enkel punt beslist de meerdere of mindere <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>helling<c type="kk">/</c> het meer regts of links zich developpeeren <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>van de zijvlakken der voorwerpen door de heele <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>compositie heen.</ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> in het leven is er iets dergelijks.</ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ’k ben een arm schilder en sta voor <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>jaren van strijd nog – in mijn dagelijksch leven <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>moet ik ’t inrigten à peu près zòò als een boeren<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>arbeider of een fabrieksarbeider het doet<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>dan is dat een vast punt waar veel dingen uit <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>volgen<c type="kk">/</c> die men dus uit zijn verband rukt als <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>men ze anders dan in ’t algemeen beschouwd. <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Er zijn schilders in andere omstandigheden die <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>anders kunnen en moeten doen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Ieder moet beslissen voor <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zich zelf.</ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik andere kansen<c type="kk">/</c> andere gegevens <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>had en er geen dingen gebeurd waren van <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>beslissenden aard<c type="kk">/</c> natuurlijk ik zoude er <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>door geinfluenceerd zijn geworden <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>in mijn doen en laten.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu echter – en à plus forte raison – wegens <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>ik<c type="kk">/</c> als er maar eenigzins kwestie zou kunnen <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>zijn van het te beschouwen als mij iets aanmatigen <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>waarop ik geen regt had<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs al had ik après tout het regt<c type="kk">/</c> maar wegens het opperen der kwestie alleen<c type="kk">/</c> ik van zelf me retireer van omgang <lb n="31a" xml:id="l-31a"/>met menschen die een zekeren stand ophouden<c type="kk">/</c> zelfs van mijn familie<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> – <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>zoo staan wij voor deze daadzaak<c type="kk">/</c> mijn vast voornemen <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>om dood te zijn voor alles behalve mijn werk.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Moeielijk is ’t me echter over die anders <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>eenvoudige gewone zaken te spreken <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>wegens ze in verband staan ongelukkigerwijs <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>tot veel dieper dingen.</ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Niets is meer “<hi rend="ital">angoisse</hi>” dan <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>een zielstrijd tusschen pligt en liefde<c type="kk">/</c> beiden <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>hoog opgevoerd.</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik U zeg<c type="kk">/</c> ik kies mijn pligt<c type="kk">/</c> weet <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>gij er alles van<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Een enkel woord dat we er over spraken op den <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>weg deed mij voelen daaromtrent in mij <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>niets is veranderd<c type="kk">/</c> dat het is en blijft een wond <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>waar ik over heen leef doch die in de diepte zit, <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>en niet heelen kan<c type="kk">/</c> over jaren zal zijn wat ’t was den eersten dag.</ab>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoop dat gij begrijpt wat ik bij mij <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>zelf voor strijd had nu pas<c type="kp">_</c>– Deze: <hi rend="ital">Quoi qu’il en soit</hi> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>(naar dat <hi rend="ital">quoi</hi>? niet vragende want ik heb het <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>regt niet het te onderzoeken) – wil ik op mijn qui vive <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>zijn eerlijk man te blijven en dubbel <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>attent op <hi rend="sc">pligt</hi>.</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Haar</hi> heb ik nooit verdacht noch verdenk ik <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>noch zal ik verdenken dat finantieele redenen <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>haar motieven waren<c type="kk">/</c> anders dan eerlijk en <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>billijk is. Zij ging zoo ver het raisonable <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>was<c type="kk">/</c> anderen overdreven. Verder echter <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>begrijpt gij ik niets presumeer omtrent liefde voor mij en <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>wat wij zeiden op den weg blijft tusschen ons. Sedert <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>zijn er dingen gebeurd die niet zouden geweest zijn <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>als op een zeker moment ik niet gestaan had voor een <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>gedecideerd neen<c type="kk">/</c> primo<c type="kk">/</c> en ten tweede voor een belofte dat ik <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>niet in haar weg zoude komen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">In haar respecteerde ik een sentiment van <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>pligt – haar heb ik nooit verdacht<c type="kk">/</c> zal ik nooit <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>verdenken van iets laags. Voor mij zelf weet <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>ik dit eene<c type="kk">/</c> dat primo ’t er op aankomt <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>niet af te wijken van wat pligt is en men met pligt <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>niet transigeeren mag.</ab>
                <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pligt is iets absoluuts. De gevolgen? <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>wij zijn er niet voor verantwoordelijk<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>voor het initiatief van pligt <hi rend="ital">doen</hi> of <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">doen</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> ja. Ziehier het lijnregt <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>tegenovergestelde aan den stelregel<c type="kk">/</c> het doel <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>heiligt de middelen.–</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">En mijn eigen toekomst is een beker <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>die niet voorbij kan gaan tenzij ik hem <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>uit drink<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dus <hi rend="ital">fiat voluntas</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet – goede reis – schrijf spoedig – maar <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>ge begrijpt hoe ik de toekomst opnemen zal<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>met sereniteit en zonder dat een trek <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>in mijn gezigt spreekt van dien strijd in de <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>allerdiepste diepte<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="88*" xml:id="l-88s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab>Gij begrijpt echter ik alles moet ontwijken <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>wat me in verzoeking zou brengen te aarzelen <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>en ik dus alles en allen vermijden <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">moet</hi> wat me <hi rend="ital">haar</hi> in herinnering zou brengen <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>kunnen. Die gedachte heeft me trouwens <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>ook dit jaar wel eens meer beslissend gemaakt <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>dan ik anders zou zijn geweest en gij ziet dat ik <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>zulks wel zóó kan doen dat niemand er ’t regte van begrijpt.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-31" n="31">me retireer &lt; ik me retireer</note>
<note target="l-31" n="31">a familie – &lt; familie</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear brother.</ab>
<ab>I wish you could understand that I must be consistent in various things. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You know what an ‘<hi rend="ital">error in the point of view</hi>’ is in painting, namely something very different from and much worse than a mistake in drawing this or that detail. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">A single point determines the steeper or gentler incline, the way the sides of the objects develop more to the right or to the left throughout the whole composition. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, there’s something similar in life. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When I say I’m a poor painter and still face years of struggle — in my daily life I have to arrange things more or less as a farm labourer or factory worker does — then that’s a fixed point from which many things follow, which are thus taken out of their context if they’re viewed other than in general. There are painters in other circumstances who can and must act differently. Everyone must decide for himself. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If I’d had other opportunities, other circumstances, and if nothing of a decisive nature had happened, of course I would have been influenced in my actions.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now, though — and with all the more reason — because I, should there be the slightest question of seeing it as me arrogating to myself something to which I had no right, even if I had the right after all, but simply because of the question being raised, I withdraw of my own accord from contact with people who keep up a certain position, even from my family<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> — thus we’re faced by this fact, my firm intention to be dead to everything except my work.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yet it’s difficult for me to speak about those otherwise simple, ordinary matters, because they’re unfortunately connected to much deeper things. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">There is no greater ‘<hi rend="ital">anguish</hi>’ than an inner struggle between duty and love, both raised to a high level.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">When I say to you, I choose my duty, you know all about it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The few words about it that we exchanged on the road made me feel that nothing has changed in me in this regard, that it is and will remain a wound which I live above but which is there deep down and cannot heal — years from now it will be what it was the first day. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hope you understand what a struggle I had with myself of late — this: <hi rend="ital">whatever happens</hi> (not enquiring about that <hi rend="ital">what?</hi> for I don’t have the right to investigate it) — I want to be on my <hi rend="ital">qui vive</hi> about remaining an honest man and being doubly attentive to <hi rend="sc">duty</hi>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I never suspected nor do I suspect nor shall I suspect <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="776">her</rs>
                    </hi> of having financial considerations as her motive, other than what was just and fair. She went as far as was reasonable, others exaggerated. Beyond that, though, you understand that I presume nothing as regards love for me, and that what we said on the road goes no further. Things have happened since that wouldn’t have taken place if at a certain point I hadn’t been faced by a firm no, firstly, and, secondly, a promise that I would keep out of her way.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I respected a sense of duty in <rs type="pers" key="776">her</rs> — I have never suspected her, shall never suspect her, of anything low. For my part I know one thing, that in the first place what matters is not to deviate from what is duty, and that one can’t compromise on duty. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Duty is something absolute. The consequences? We’re not responsible for them, but for the initiative of <hi rend="ital">doing </hi>or <hi rend="ital">not doing</hi> one’s duty, yes. Here one sees the exact opposite of the principle that the end justifies the means. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And my own future is a cup that cannot pass away from me except I drink it.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So <hi rend="ital">Thy will be done</hi>.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Regards — safe journey — write soon — but you understand how I will approach the future, with serenity and without one sign in my face betraying the struggle in the deepest depths.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>You will understand, though, that I must avoid everything that might tempt me to hesitate, and so I <hi rend="ital">must</hi> keep away from everything and everyone that might remind me of <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="776">her</rs>
                    </hi>. As a matter of fact, this year, too, that thought has sometimes made me more decisive than I otherwise would have been, and you see that I can do something like that in such a way that no one truly understands it. </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This remark and what follows relate to Van Gogh’s rejection by <rs type="pers" key="776">Kee Vos</rs> and to the estrangement between him and <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs>. These subjects had evidently been discussed during Theo's visit.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The passages ‘even ... I’ (‘zelfs ... alleen ik’) and ‘from contact ... family’ (‘van omgang ... familie’) were added later by Van Gogh.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>After ‘work’ Van Gogh crossed out the following incomplete thoughts: ‘I shall not seek relations with people, whoever they are, except for a very few. Am I wrong in that? I know too well’ (‘Relaties met menschen/ wie dan ook/ zal ik niet zoeken als de heel enkele_ Heb ik daarin ongelijk – ik ken te goed’).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="26" vr="39-42">Matt. 26:39-42</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>‘Thy will be done’ from The Lord’s Prayer; see also <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="26" v="42">Matt. 26:42</bibleref>, <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="6" v="10">Matt. 6:10</bibleref> and <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Luke" chap="11" v="2">Luke 11:2</bibleref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>