<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 10 January 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let300"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">300</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">259</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">301</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Wednesday, 10 January 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Wednesday, 10 January 1883.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Theo’s visit early in August  1882 <ref target="let253.xml">(253)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b281 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Vincent has received a letter from Theo ‘this morning’ <ref target="#l-2">(l. 2)</ref>, and he refers to his previous letter of ‘5 or 6 January’ <ref target="#l-119">(l. 119)</ref>. These letters evidently crossed, so that the date of the present letter must be shortly after 5 or 6 January. Furthermore, he is expecting the second remittance of the month and says that ‘in the last days of the 10 I am always absolutely broke’ <ref target="#l-144">(l. 144)</ref>. So the date of this letter must be on or about Wednesday, 10 January 1883.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0281" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000349_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000349_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000349_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000349_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000349_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0281" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000349_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000349_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000349_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000349_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000349_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000349_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Toen ik Uw brief heden morgen las trof het mij zeer <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>wat gij schreeft. Dat zijn van die zaken waarvan de wereld <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>somtijds zegt “wat hoeft hij zich daarmee te bemoeien”<c type="kk">/</c> en <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>toch het is niet zoozeer onze eigen daad dan wel de <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>omstandigheden die er ons toe dringen.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> En hebben <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>wij eenmaal den toestand begrepen<c type="kk">/</c> kan er een <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>medelijden wakker worden zoo grondeloos diep dat <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>wij voor ons zelven niet meer aarzelen.</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab rend="indent">En bij U – ik meen het zoo is – en wat kan ik <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>dan anders zeggen dan dat het mij voorkomt <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>wij in dergelijke gevallen onze impulsies moeten <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>volgen. Victor Hugo zegt<c type="kk">/</c> Par dessus la raison il y <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>a la conscience<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> er zijn dingen die wij voelen <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>goed &amp; waar te zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon van den kant van <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>verstand en berekening er veel onverklaarbaars <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>en duisters in blijve. En ofschoon nu in de <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>maatschappij waarin wij zijn dergelijke handelingen <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>worden beschouwd als ondoordacht of roekeloos of <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>dwaas of weet ik wat meer – wat zullen wij er <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>van zeggen indien ’t nu eenmaal met ons zoo <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>gesteld is dat de verborgen krachten van sympathie <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>en liefde in ons binnenste wakker geworden zijn<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>En zij het ook dat wij de redeneeringen welke <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>de maatschappij gewoon is aan te voeren tegen het <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>zich laten leiden door het gevoel en tegen het <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>agir par impulsion<c type="kk">/</c> niet door andere redeneeringen <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>geheel kunnen overpraten<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> – op overpraten komt <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>het ook niet op aan<c type="kk">/</c> en zoo wie het geloof in <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>een God heeft behouden hoort soms eene zachte <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>stem van het geweten welke men alsdan mischien <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wel doet te volgen met de naiveteit van <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>een kind. Zonder er met de wereld over te praten <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>meer dan men verhelpen kan.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als iemand eene dergelijke ontmoeting heeft<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>het is te voorzien hij er strijd door hebben zal<c type="kk">/</c> ook <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>vooral strijd met zich zelf omdat men soms <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>letterlijk niet weet wat men doen<c type="kk">/</c> wat men laten <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>moet. Doch is dezen strijd en zelfs die vergissingen <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>waarin men ook al eens vallen zal niet beter <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>en ontwikkelen zij niet meer dan het zich systematisch <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>buiten emoties houden. Dit laatste is wat <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>in mijn oog veel zoogenaamde esprits forts <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>in werkelijkheid esprits faibles maakt.</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ge hebt mijne sympathie in dezen en <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>is het dat<c type="kk">/</c> aangezien ik ook zelf tegenover <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>realiteiten sta en U kan vertellen wat mij <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>al zoo sedert we er ’t laatst <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>over spraken wedervaren is<c type="kk">/</c> het U wenschelijk <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>mogt zijn een &amp; ander daaromtrent te vernemen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>of wilt ge over de toekomst praten of overleggen <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>omtrent wat dan ook<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben steeds geheel <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>tot Uwe beschikking.</ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">En dat gij schrijft gij er over denkt eerlang <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>naar Holland te komen<c type="kk">/</c> is mij eene zeer <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>welkome tijding.</ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Volhouden is de groote kwestie bij liefde <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>als men eens werkelijk begonnen <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>is. Dat is als de liefde beantwoord wordt<c type="kk">/</c> want <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wordt zij gedecideerd niet beantwoord dan is het een geval <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>waarin men letterlijk absoluut magteloos wordt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Enfin. Ik dank U voor Uw vertrouwen <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>en ik ben betrekkelijk gerust omtrent de uitkomst als ik <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>er over nadenk. Zoo iets is geen “passie” want er <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>is een grondeloos diep medelijden bij in ’t spel.</ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">En ik geloof ook niet het iets is dat U voor denken over andere <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>dingen ongeschikt maakt<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> zoo iets heeft een ernstig <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>karakter dat alle faculteiten opwekt en versterkt en de 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>energie vermeerderen kan veeleer dan dat ze er op <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>verminderen zou. Zoodat ge ’t me ten goede houden <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>zult ik nog een en ander over de teekeningen <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>zeg. Dat gij den oudenmannekop<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> “echt” vondt <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>doet me zeer veel pleizier – het <hi rend="ital">model</hi> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>is fameus <hi rend="ital">echt</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> ik heb er nog meer van <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>hem. Heden een die ik geteekend heb met <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>lith<c type="kp">_</c> krijt.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Toen kwakte ik een emmer water <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>over de teekening en begon in het kletsnatte <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>te modeleeren met ’t penseel. Daardoor <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>krijgt men zeer fijne toonen als het <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>gelukt want het is een gevaarlijke manier die wel <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>eens verkeerd kan uitkomen ook. Maar als het lukt <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>heeft men een resultaat erg “non ébarbé”<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>fijne toonen van zwart die nog ’t meest op eau forte <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>gelijken. Zoo heb ik een vrouwenkop ook tegen het <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>licht in<c type="kk">/</c> dus in toon met kantlichtjes op ’t profil &amp;c.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>GIJ HEBT IMMERS HET TWEEDE ROLLETJE OOK <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>ONTVANGEN WAARIN NOG 5 KOPPEN <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>WAREN (van hier verzonden meen ik 5 of 6 Januarij) – behalve de twee eersten.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als gij die wat bij U hebt<c type="kk">/</c> geloof ik gij er hetzelfde <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>in zult vinden als in de twee eersten want er <hi rend="ital">moet</hi> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">iets</hi> van de natuur in zijn daar ik ze bepaald <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>ontworstel aan de natuur en van ’t begin tot ’t eind <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>naar het model werk. Ik heb er een groot verlangen naar <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>om U de studies te laten zien – niet omdat ik over mijn eigen <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>werk content ben doch omdat ik<c type="kk">/</c> ofschoon ik er lang niet <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>tevreden over ben<c type="kk">/</c> toch er in zie dat het in wording <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>is en er zich vanzelf iets uit ontwikkelen zal dat <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>eenig karakter zal hebben. ’tGeen me hier ’t meest <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>trof toen ik in stad kwam was b.v. de Geest en die <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>buurten. En zoo zachtjes aan krijgt het corps – <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>doch – wat een sjouwerij om zoo iets ten einde <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>te brengen.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zag heden photo’s naar teekeningen van <hi rend="ital">Barnard</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>figuren uit Dickens waarvan ik de oorspronkelijke teekeningen <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>in der tijd te Londen zag.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Er is een kracht in als in <hi rend="ital">Nicolaas</hi> <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Maas</hi> b.v. doch een geheel modern gevoel en opvatting<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>Zoo iets kan mij zoo warm maken en is mij daarom <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>zoo opwekkend omdat ik mij modellen van hier <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>voorstel zoo als zij<c type="kk">/</c> op <hi rend="ital">die</hi> wijs geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> voordoen zouden <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>en dan natuurlijkerwijs tot mij zelven zeg<c type="kk">/</c> vooruit! <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>en voortwerken tot we het Black &amp; White onder den duim <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>hebben. In de kunst en in de liefde is overeenstemming<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>het is een geslingerd worden tusschen “je l’ai depuis <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>longtemps” en “je ne l’aurai jamais”<c type="kk">/</c> zooals Michelet <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>het uitdrukt.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Zoo gaat men van melancolie tot entrain <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>en enthousiasme en zal dit steeds blijven en de <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>slingeringen alleen sterker worden. Victor Hugo <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>spreekt van “comme un phare à éclipse”<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> en <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>zoo is het er ook al mee.</ab>
                <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als het is dat gij mijn schrijven van 5 of 6 <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>Januarij nog ontvangen hebt met het tweede rolletje zoo zult <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>ge U daaruit herinneren ik reeds toen à court was. En nu <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>heden had ik huishuur te betalen en 3 modellen <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>die ik had moeten laten wachten en moest absoluut <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>verschillende teekenbehoeften hebben ook. Ik werk zeer druk <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>tegenwoordig en ik mag niet stoppen maar <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>de modellen vreten me letterlijk de ooren van ’t lijf. <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>Enfin het zou erg<c type="kk">/</c> erg wenschelijk zijn ik eens een <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>buitenkansje kon hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Zou het kunnen? Ik schroom <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>het te vragen omdat gij mij nu juist dit een en ander <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>geschreven hebt en ik zoozeer begrijp hoe gij zelf <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>er zorgen door hebt<c type="kk">/</c> welke ik respecteer en <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>medegevoel. Doch het is met mij zoo dat ik juist door <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>maar steeds door te werken wat ten achter gekomen <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>ben en ik als ik ’t geld ontvang direkt er meer dan <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>de helft van moest geven. ik <hi rend="ital">kan</hi> niet zuiniger leven dan <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>wij doen<c type="kk">/</c> wat te bezuinigen was<c type="kk">/</c> we hebben het bezuinigd maar <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>het werk breidt zich uit nu juist vooral in de laatste weken en <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>ik kan het haast niet baas meer<c type="kk">/</c> d.i<c type="kp">_</c> de kosten die er aan <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>verbonden zijn. Zou er mogelijkheid op zijn ik binnen kort <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>nog wat ontving. Ik geloof ge het begrijpen zult als gij de <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>studies ziet. Enfin, vergeef het mij dat ik er over spreek <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>maar ik kan moeielijk anders. Ik ben met de dagelijksche <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>uitgaven ten achter geraakt en dat maakt dat ik telkens <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>de laatste dagen van de 10 absoluut à sec ben. In elk geval<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">schrijf</hi> spoedig en houd U van mijne sympathie met betrekking <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>tot ’t geen waarover gij schreeft ten volle verzekerd, adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> een handdruk <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>in gedachten<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="147*" xml:id="l-147s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="147*"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-81" n="81">ébarbé”<c type="kk">/</c> &lt; ébarbé</note>
<note target="l-87" n="87">(van <supplied>
                            <hi rend="ital">...</hi>
                        </supplied> Januarij) &lt; <hi rend="ital">Added later; parentheses added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-113" n="113">“je ne &lt; je ne</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo</ab>
<ab>When I read your letter this morning I was deeply touched by what you wrote. These are matters of which the world sometimes says, ‘Why should he get involved?’, and yet it isn’t so much our own act as the circumstances that compel us to do so.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> And once we’ve grasped the situation, a compassion can be awakened that is so unfathomably deep that we no longer hesitate.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And in you — I believe it is so — and what can I say other than that it seems to me that we must follow our impulses in such cases? <rs type="pers" key="666">Victor Hugo</rs> says, ‘Over and above reason there is conscience.’<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> There are things that we feel to be good and true, although from the point of view of intellect and calculation there remains much that is inexplicable and obscure in them. And even though now, in the society in which we find ourselves, such actions are regarded as ill-considered or reckless or foolish or I don’t know what all — what shall we say once the hidden forces of sympathy and love have been awakened deep inside us? And should we be unable to use other arguments entirely to refute those that society customarily invokes against letting oneself be led by feeling and against acting impulsively — refuting isn’t the point, and he who has retained a belief in a God sometimes hears the gentle voice of conscience, which he would then be well advised to follow with the naivety of a child. Without talking about it to the outside world more than one can help. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When someone has a meeting like that, it’s to be expected that he’ll experience conflict, especially conflict with himself, because one sometimes literally doesn’t know what one should or should not do. Yet isn’t this conflict, and even the mistakes into which one will sometimes fall, better, and doesn’t it develop us more than systematically shutting out emotions? This last is what makes many so-called strong spirits in reality weak spirits, in my view.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You have my sympathy in this, and should you think it desirable, given that I too am faced by realities and can tell you what has befallen me since we last talked this over, to hear a thing or two about it, or if you want to talk about the future or confer about anything at all, I’m always entirely at your disposal.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The fact that you write that you’re thinking of coming to Holland before too long is very welcome news to me.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Persevering is the main issue in love once one has really started. That is if the love is requited, for if it’s definitely not requited then it’s a case in which one is literally absolutely powerless. Anyway. I thank you for your trust, and when I think it over I’m fairly at ease about the outcome. Such a thing isn’t ‘passion’, because an unfathomably deep compassion is involved.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Nor do I believe that it’s something that makes you unsuited to thinking about other matters; on the contrary, a thing like that has a serious nature that awakes and strengthens all the faculties, and 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> can increase energy rather than decrease it. So you won’t hold it against me if I say one or two things about the drawings. It really pleases me that you found the old man’s head<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> ‘true’ — the <hi rend="ital">model</hi> is wonderfully <hi rend="ital">true</hi>, I have more drawings of him. Today one that I drew with lithographic crayon.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> Then I tipped a bucket of water over the drawing and began to model with a brush in the soaking wet. In this way one gets very delicate tones if it works, for it’s a dangerous method that can turn out wrong on occasion. But if it works, the result is very ‘unburred’,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> delicate tones of black that most resemble an etching. In this way I also have a woman’s head, against the light, thus in tone with glancing lights on the profile &amp;c.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> YOU ALSO RECEIVED THE SECOND ROLL, DIDN’T YOU, IN WHICH THERE WERE 5 MORE HEADS (sent from here on 5 or 6 January, I think) — as well as the first two.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When you’ve had them for a while, I believe that you’ll find the same in them as in the first two, for there <hi rend="ital">must be something</hi> of nature in them, since I really wrest them from nature, and I work from the model from beginning to end. I have a great desire to show you the studies — not because I’m content with my own work but because, though far from satisfied with it, I nonetheless see that it’s taking shape, and that something will naturally develop from it that will have some character. What struck me most when I came to the city was, for instance, the Geest district and those neighbourhoods. And it’s gaining substance little by little — but what a job to see something like that through. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Today I saw photos after drawings by <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="210">Barnard</rs>
                    </hi>, figures from <rs type="pers" key="580">Dickens</rs>, the original drawings of which I saw in London at the time.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> There’s a power in them like that in <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="1185">Nicolaas Maes</rs>
                    </hi>, for example, but an entirely modern feeling and approach. That kind of thing makes me so enthusiastic and thus cheers me up, because I imagine models from here as they’d appear if they were drawn in <hi rend="ital">that</hi> way, and then naturally I say to myself, onward! and keep on working until we’ve got the hang of the Black and White. It’s the same in art and in love, one is swung between ‘I’ve had it for a long time’ and ‘I’ll never have it’, as <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs> puts it.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> So one goes from melancholy to cheerfulness and enthusiasm, and this will always remain and the swings will only get stronger. <rs type="pers" key="666">Victor Hugo</rs> speaks of ‘like a lighthouse whose beam flashes on and off’<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and that’s how it is too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you received my letter of 5 or 6 January with the second roll, you will recall that I was already running short then. And now today I had to pay the house rent and 3 models I had had to keep waiting, and I also absolutely had to have various drawing materials. I’m working very hard at present and I mustn’t stop, but the models are literally eating me out of house and home. In short, it would be very, very desirable if I could have a little extra. Would that be possible? I hesitate to ask because you’ve just written to me about one thing and another, and I understand so well how you yourself have cares as a result, which I respect and feel with you. But my position is that I’ve got a little behind precisely because I carried on working all the time, and even if I received the money now I would have to pay out more than half. I <hi rend="ital">cannot</hi> live more thriftily than we do. Where economies could be made, we’ve economized, but the work is expanding just now, particularly in recent weeks, and I’m almost losing control, of the costs involved, that is. Is there a possibility that I could receive a little more soon? I believe you’ll understand when you see the studies. Well, forgive me for raising the subject, but I have little choice. I’ve got behind with the day-to-day expenses, and that means that in the last days of the 10 I’m always absolutely broke. In any event, <hi rend="ital">write</hi> soon and be fully assured of my sympathy as regards what you write about, adieu, old chap, a handshake in thought.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Theo had confided in Vincent about his ‘dramatic’ (<ref target="let336.xml">letter 336</ref>) meeting with his beloved <rs type="pers" key="508">Marie</rs>, who was ill in body and soul (<ref target="let301.xml">letter 301</ref>). Her identity is not known. Born on the coast of Brittany (<ref target="let301.xml">letter 301</ref>), she was a Roman Catholic (<ref target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref>), childless and living alone. See also Hulsker 1990-1, pp. 127-129.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Very likely borrowed from <rs type="pers" key="666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s novel <rs type="lit" key="278">
                            <hi rend="ital">Quatre-vingt treize</hi>
                        </rs>, which Van Gogh had recently read (<ref target="let286.xml">letter 286</ref>). It does not contain the actual sentence ‘Par dessus la raison il y a la conscience’, but it describes how the character Gauvain is torn between his reason and his feelings: ‘Reasoning said one thing, feelings another; the two pieces of advice were contrary. Reasoning is only reason; feelings are often conscience; the one comes from man, the other from a higher place. That is what makes feelings have less clarity but greater force. And yet what power there is in severe reason!’ (Le raisonnement disait une chose; le sentiment en disait une autre; les deux conseils étaient contraires. Le raisonnement n’est que la raison; le sentiment est souvent la conscience; l’un vient de l’homme, l’autre vient de plus haut. C’est ce qui fait que le sentiment a moins de clarté et plus de puissance. Quelle force pourtant dans la raison sévère!). See Hugo 1965, p. 347.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘weerleggen’ (refute).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>It is impossible to say which head of a man this was. Vincent sent two to Theo (<ref target="let298.xml">see letter 298</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Which head of a man this was is impossible to say. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>For the term <hi rend="ital">non ébarbé</hi>, <ref target="let217.xml#n-2">see letter 217, n. 2.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>It is impossible to say for certain which drawing this was, but <hi rend="ital">Head of a woman</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="453">F 1005 / JH 292</rs>) is the result of a similar experiment. The ‘glancing lights’ Van Gogh talks about here are the lighter bands along her profile, where the paper has been left blank, and in the forehead, where it has been heightened with white. The face is shaded a fairly even grey (cf. the description ‘in tone’). Judging by the shadows and the fall of light, the light source is obliquely to the right of the woman. The white trim of her cap stands out clearly, despite the fact that the white body colour has turned grey. See cat. Amsterdam 1996, pp. 192-193, cat. no. 53.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>The ‘second roll’, which contained five heads, was sent with <ref target="let299.xml">letter 299</ref>; by ‘the first two’ Van Gogh means the first two studies of heads, which were sent with <ref target="let298.xml">letter 298</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>For these illustrations to <rs type="pers" key="580">Dickens</rs> by <rs type="pers" key="210">Frederick Barnard</rs>, <ref target="let235.xml#n-7">see letter 235, n. 7.</ref> Where in London and when Van Gogh saw these drawings by Barnard is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>An allusion to ‘I can do nothing about it, I cannot keep her. She has been mine for a long time and I shall never have her’ (J’ai beau faire, je ne la tiens pas. Elle est à moi depuis longtemps et je ne l’aurai jamais), in <rs type="pers" key="707">Jules Michelet</rs>’s, <rs type="lit" key="12">
                            <hi rend="ital">La femme</hi>
                        </rs> (Michelet 1863, p. 331).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
    <ab>A ‘phare à éclipse’ has not been traced in <rs type="pers" key="666">Hugo</rs>’s oeuvre, but a ‘phare à feux tournants’ does feature in the poem <rs type="lit" key="319">‘Les quatre vents de l’esprit’</rs>. See Hugo 1972, vol. 2, p. 669.</ab>
    <ab rend="indent">Van Gogh was probably mistaken about the author. <rs type="pers" key="707">Jules Michelet</rs>, who had been mentioned just before, included the phrase in both <rs type="lit" key="12">
                            <hi rend="ital">La femme</hi>
                        </rs> (but there the ‘phare à éclipse’ refers to France) and the epilogue to <rs type="lit" key="312">
                            <hi rend="ital">La sorcière</hi>
                        </rs> (1862). Since Van Gogh later gives the quotation as ‘Dieu est un phare à éclipse’ (<ref target="let691.xml">see letter 691</ref>), we take it that in the present letter too he was referring to the following passage in Michelet’s <hi rend="ital">La sorcière</hi>: ‘Gods pass, but God does not. On the contrary, the more they pass, the more He appears. He is like a lighthouse whose beam flashes on and off but which comes back brighter each time’. (Les dieux passent, et non Dieu. Au contraire, plus ils passent, et plus il apparaît. Il est comme un phare à éclipse, mais qui à chaque fois revient plus lumineux). Ed. Paul Viallaneix. Paris 1966, pp. 285-286. Cf. also Merlhès 1989, p. 108 (n. 1) and <ref target="let695.xml#n-5">letter 695, n. 5.</ref>
                    </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Van Gogh also attributed the beginning, ‘Les dieux passent, et non Dieu’, to <rs type="pers" key="666">Victor Hugo</rs> (he gave the quotation as ‘Les religions passent, mais Dieu demeure’): <ref target="let294.xml#n-6">see letter 294, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>