<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Hoogeveen, Monday, 24 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let389"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">389</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">327</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">392</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Hoogeveen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 24 September 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Hoogeveen, Monday, 24 September 1883.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b350 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Date of postmark: Monday, 24 September 1883.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>Postcard (5 cents). Postage stamps: ‘HOOGEVEEN 12-1 N / 24 SEP 83’, ‘ARRAS A <hi rend="ital">[</hi>PARIS<hi rend="ital">[?]</hi> B / 25 SEPT. <hi rend="ital">[xx]</hi>’ and ‘PARIS 3 (60) 3 / 7E/25 SEPT. 83’.<hi rend="ital"> </hi>The address reads: ‘Monsieur Th. van Gogh/ 21 Rue de Laval./ <hi rend="ital">Paris</hi>.’</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <surface n="b 0350" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000449_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000449_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000449_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000449_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
        <surface n="b 0350 V/1962" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000449_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000449_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000449_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000449_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Heden verzend ik als postpakket 3 studies welke ik hoop droog genoeg zijn<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>indien ze evenwel aan ’t vel papier dat ik er uit voorzorg opleg vastkleven<c type="kk">/</c> zoo week <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>ze af met laauw water. De kleinste vooral is erg ingeschoten<c type="kk">/</c> doe er over een <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>dag of 8 een eiwitje of over een maand een vernisje op om ze uit te halen. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Ik zend ze om U even een kijkje te laten nemen &amp; hierna beter – hoor<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb vergeten te antwoorden op wat gij omtrent zending van ’t bewuste schrijft. <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Voorloopig verzoek ik U postwissel te zenden als laatst<c type="kk">/</c> tot ik wisselkantoor <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>weet – houd echter onkosten af<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ontving schrijven van t’huis Pa onwel was geweest ten gevolge van <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>een val – moge dit maar niet serieuser zijn dan zij schreven<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Weet gij er iets naders van?–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ben afgeloopen week dieper in de turfvelden geweest<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> – prachtige <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>gevallen, ik vind het hier hoe langer hoe mooier &amp; zal wel <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>van ’t begin af er op werken hier te blijven in de streek. Want het <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>is zoo mooi hier dat tevens om het te maken nog veel studie vereischt <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>wordt<c type="kk">/</c> en doorwrocht werk slechts een juister begrip <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>van de dingen zoo als zij au fond zijn en hun ernstig<c type="kk">/</c> sober <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>karakter kan geven. Figuren ontmoette ik<c type="kk">/</c> superbe – maar <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>nog eens<c type="kk">/</c> eene natuur die zooveel noblesse<c type="kk">/</c> zooveel waardigheid en <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>ernst heeft moet met bezonkenheid en geduld en langdurig <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>werk worden behandeld. Daarom moet m.i<c type="kp">_</c> van ’t begin af aan <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>ik het niet als maar eens hier komen kijken beschouwen<c type="kk">/</c> maar <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ligt het in den aard van de zaak<c type="kk">/</c> als alles goed gaat en we wat voorspoed <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>mogen hebben<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor goed blijf. Schrijf weer eens spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>niet waar – ben wel verlangend want ondanks al ’t moois buiten <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>heb ik toch een somber gevoel. adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab>Groet Wisselingh eens voor me als ge hem ontmoet &amp; zeg eens ik hier ben.</ab>
    <vg:whiteline/>
                <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Today I’m sending a package of 3 studies which I hope are dry enough.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> However, if they stick to the sheet of paper I laid on them as a precaution, soak them off with lukewarm water. The smallest one, in particular, has sunk in a lot, go over it with the white of an egg in about a week, or some varnish in a month’s time, to lift them. I’m sending them to let you take a look, and better after this — really.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I forgot to reply to what you write about sending the you know what. For the time being would you send a postal order like the last, until I know of an exchange office — deduct expenses, though. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Received a letter from home that <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> had been unwell as a result of a fall — I hope it isn’t more serious than they say. Do you know anything more about it?<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Went further into the peat fields last week<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> — marvellous scenes, the longer I stay here the more beautiful I find it, and from the outset I’ll try to stay here in this region. For it’s so beautiful here that at the same time a great deal of study is needed to capture it, and only solid work can give a truer understanding of things as they are at bottom, and of their serious, sober nature. I came across superb figures — but again, a nature that has so much nobility, so much dignity and gravity must be treated with maturity and patience and prolonged work. This is why, in my view, from the outset I mustn’t regard it as just coming to take a look around here, but it’s in the nature of the thing, if all goes well and we’re granted a little good fortune, that I’ll stay for good. Write again soon, won’t you — I’m longing to hear, for despite all the beauty outside I still feel dejected. Adieu, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
    <ab>My regards to <rs type="pers" key="821">Wisselingh</rs> when you see him, and tell him I’m here.</ab>
                <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>It is not possible to say with any certainty which paintings were sent. <hi rend="ital">Cottages</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2446">F 17 / JH 395</rs>) comes from Theo’s collection and could therefore have been part of this shipment. However, cf. also <ref target="let406.xml#n-6">letter 406, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> told Theo on 1 October 1883 that she was sorry that he had had to hear from Vincent that <rs type="pers" key="526">Mr van Gogh</rs> had had a fall. She described the accident as follows: ‘Pa choked on a mouthful of tea while he was getting dressed and couldn’t get his breath, lost his balance and fell, hitting his nose on the frame at the bottom of the bed, the nose bled severely and Pa was light-headed for the first couple of days, all the same he preached all right twice on Sunday’ (FR b2245).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The peat had already been exhausted within the municipal boundaries of Hoogeveen. Since the area around the districts of Eleveld in the municipality of Ruinen (to the north of Hoogeveen) was being reclaimed in the 1880s, but peat was still being dug to the east of this, near Tiendeveen, Nieuweroord and Nieuwlande, Van Gogh must have been here. According to Dijk and Van der Sluis 2001, pp. 130-133, 137.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>