<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Monday, 10 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let384"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">384</idno>
    <idno type="collectedletters">322</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">387</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 10 September 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, Monday, 10 September 1883.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
    <p>Van Gogh’s plan to go to Drenthe <ref target="let379.xml">(379)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
    <p>Drawings on consignment with Uncle Cor <ref target="let378.xml">(378)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b345 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter was written one day before Van Gogh’s departure for Drenthe (<ref target="#l-3">see l. 3</ref>). He left on 11 September 1883, as the following letter <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref> shows. Consequently, the present letter dates from Monday, 10 September 1883.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0345" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000442_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000442_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000442_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0345" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000442_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000442_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000442_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000442_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000442_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000442_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Uw brief &amp; ingesl. <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>frs 100 heb ik zooeven ontvangen. <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>En ik vertrek morgen naar Hoogeveen in Drenthe. <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Van daar verder; en van daar uit zal <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>ik U een adres opgeven.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dus schrijf in geen geval meer naar <hi rend="ital">hier</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>En ik zoude U voorstellen direkt nog met <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>een woordje C.M<c type="kp">_</c> van mijn afreis te verwittigen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>wegens het<c type="kk">/</c> zoo als ge zelf zegt<c type="kk">/</c> onder de mogelijkheden <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>behoort hij mij naar hier schrijven zoude. <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Heeft hij dat reeds gedaan<c type="kk">/</c> zou ’t beste zijn <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>hij terugzending van den brief verzocht aan <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>’t postkantoor want ik<c type="kk">/</c> niet wetende precies <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>wat mijn aanstaand adres zal wezen<c type="kk">/</c> kan <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>zelf het hier aan de post of aan den huisbaas <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>eerst later opgeven.</ab>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">Vriend Rappard is ook reeds op reis en heeft Drenthe reeds <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>achter den rug<c type="kk">/</c> is bijna al op Terschelling<c type="kp">_</c> Hij schreef me <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>uit Drenthe “het land hier is zeer ernstig van stemming<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>menigmaal deden de figuren mij denken aan studies <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>van jou<c type="kp">_</c> wat ’t leven betreft<c type="kk">/</c> goedkooper kan men <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zeker nergens teregt. En den Zuidoosthoek (’t door <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>mij bedoelde terrein) houd ik voor ’t oorspronkelijkst”<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Theo bij het heengaan heb ik zeer zeker een <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>melankoliek gevoel<c type="kk">/</c> veel meer dan ’t geval zoude <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>wezen indien ik overtuigd was de vrouw energiek <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>zoude zijn en haar goeden wil niet equivoque. <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>Enfin uit een &amp; ander weet ge ’t voornaamste. <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Ik voor mij moet doorzetten of ik zou zelf <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>zinken zonder haar daardoor iets verder te brengen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>Tot dat zij uit eigen beweging meer actief wordt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>n.l. meer voortdurend in plaats van met korte vlagen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>blijft ze op èèn zelfde onvoldoend punt en al had <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>zij 3 helpers in plaats van mij<c type="kk">/</c> zouden die er niets <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>verder aan kunnen doen tenzij ze zelf meewerkte<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Maar de kinderen waar men hart voor heeft? <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Ik kon er niet alles voor doen doch indien de <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>vrouw gewild had!</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zal er echter niet heel veel over zaniken <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>want ik moet doorzetten quand même<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> voorzigtigheidshalve durfde ik ’t er niet op wagen <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>verf mee te nemen want ik zal ginder dadelijk mijn <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>goed moeten betalen als ’t komt<c type="kk">/</c> dan logement en <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>reiskosten verder. Doch als wij zoo gelukkig zijn <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>van iets te krijgen van C.M. zal ik van daar <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>uit per postpakket laten komen een en ander ik <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>heb uitgezocht<c type="kp">_</c> Hoe eer dat gebeuren kan hoe beter<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>Dus als gij iets hoort schrijf mij dan zoodra ge mijn <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>adres ginder weet<c type="kk">/</c> en natuurlijkerwijs vind ik best <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>de voorgestelde schikking (omtrent gedeeltelijk remboursement der frs 100)<c type="kp">_</c> zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> indien gij <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>à court zijt<c type="kk">/</c> wacht een gunstig moment af met <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>al datgene dat hij zou kunnen zenden.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik voor mij geloof dat C.M<c type="kp">_</c> wel eens niets zou kunnen <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>doen.</ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">In elk geval broer<c type="kk">/</c> is het energiek en heel best gezien <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>van U gij direkt dit stuurdet<c type="kp">_</c> Want dan ben ik al <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>vast ginder en kan mij orienteeren en wij 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>kunnen zeker zelf bezuinigen al komt er <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>geen hulp<c type="kp">_</c> Daarom dank voor dit en <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ik geloof het een goede maatregel zal blijken. <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Mijn plan is ginder te blijven bij voorbeeld <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>tot dat gij toek. jaar naar Holland <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>komt. Ik zou U dan ook niet willen <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>missen. Maar zoodoende zou ik er <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>net alle saizoenen zien voorbij gaan en <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>een overzigt hebben van ’t karakter der dingen <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>in die streek.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb me voorzien van een binnenlandsch <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>paspoort<c type="kk">/</c> geldig voor 12 maanden.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>Met hetwelk ik het regt heb te gaan waar <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>ik wil en te blijven in een plaats zoo lang <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>en zoo kort ’t me convenieert.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben erg blij dat ik dus voortgang kan <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>maken want zoodoende helpen we ons zelf<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>ginder reken ik 50 frs voor logies en kost<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>en de rest aan het werk<c type="kk">/</c> en dat scheelt veel <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>bij wat ik hier in de gegevenen kon doen. <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Zoo al hielpen anderen niet<c type="kk">/</c> wij zullen <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>niet stil zitten<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet want ik heb heden nog veel te <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>beredderen – schrijf dus een lettertje <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>aan C.M. – en dezer dagen ontvangt ge <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>berigt van mijn adres<c type="kk">/</c> als alles wel gaat reeds <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>morgen avond<c type="kp">_</c> adieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab>t. à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab>Gij schreeft mij onlangs “misschien zal je <hi rend="ital">pligt</hi> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>je er toe brengen om anders te doen of zoo”<c type="kk">/</c> dat is iets <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>waar ik direkt zeer over gedacht heb en <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>wegens zoo ontwijfelbaar mijn werk de demarche <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>van naar ginder gaan gebiedt<c type="kk">/</c> is mijn begrip dat <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>werk meer direkt pligt is dan zelfs de vrouw en ter wille van de laatste <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>’t eerste niet lijden mag<c type="kp">_</c> Wat verl. jaar anders was<c type="kk">/</c> daar ik <hi rend="ital">nu</hi> mijns inziens <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">juist</hi> op dat punt van Drenthe ben<c type="kp">_</c> Maar men heeft een verdeeld gevoel <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>en zou beiden willen doen<c type="kk">/</c> wat <hi rend="ital">niet kan</hi> in de gegevenen en <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>wegens ’t geld en<c type="kk">/</c> meer dan dat<c type="kk">/</c> wegens er op haar niet vast is <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>te rekenen.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-50" n="50">(omtrent <supplied>
                            <hi rend="ital">...</hi>
                        </supplied> 100) &lt; <hi rend="ital">Added later; parentheses added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I’ve just received your letter and the 100 francs enclosed. And I leave tomorrow for Hoogeveen in Drenthe. Then on from there, and from there I’ll give you an address. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So don’t write any more to <hi rend="ital">here </hi>in any event. And I would suggest you write a word to <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M.</rs> right away to inform him of my departure because, as you say yourself, there’s the possibility that he might write to me at this address. If he has already done so, it would be best if he asked at the post office for the letter to be returned for, not knowing exactly what my next address will be, I can only inform the post here or the landlord later on. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Friend <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> is also travelling, and already has Drenthe behind him and is nearly on Terschelling. He wrote to me from Drenthe ‘the country here is very earnest in mood, the figures often made me think of studies by you. As for life here, one could certainly not live more cheaply anywhere else. And I think that the south-east corner (the area I have in mind) is the most original.’<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Theo, I certainly have a feeling of melancholy on leaving, much more so than would have been the case had I been convinced that the <rs type="pers" key="463">woman</rs> would be energetic and that her good will wasn’t in doubt. Anyway, you know the gist from one thing and another. For my part I must press on or I myself will sink without getting her any further by that. Until she becomes more active of her own accord, namely more steadily instead of in short bursts, she’ll remain on the same inadequate spot, and even if she had 3 helpers in my place they wouldn’t be able to do anything about it unless she herself cooperated. But the <rs type="pers" key="466 467">children</rs> to whom one’s heart goes out? I couldn’t do everything for them, but if only the woman had been willing!</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I shan’t go on moaning, though, for I must press on nonetheless. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, to be on the safe side I didn’t dare to take paint along, for over there I’ll soon have to pay for my things when they arrive, then lodgings and more travel expenses. But if we’re lucky enough to get something from <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M.</rs>, I’ll have one or two things I’ve picked out sent there by parcel post. The sooner that can be done the better. So if you hear anything, write to me as soon as you know my address over there, and of course I agree with the proposed arrangement (regarding the partial reimbursement of the 100 francs); indeed, if you’re hard up, wait for a favourable moment before sending everything that might come from him.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I, for one, think that <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M.</rs> might just do nothing at all. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">In any event, brother, it was firm and well advised of you to send this immediately. For now I’ll be over there and able to get my bearings, and we 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> can certainly economize ourselves even if no help comes. So thanks for this, and I believe it’ll prove to be a good step. My plan is to stay there until you come to Holland next year, for instance. I wouldn’t want to miss you then. But in that way I would just see all the seasons go by and have a general view of the character of things in that region. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve equipped myself with an internal passport, valid for 12 months.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> With which I have the right to go where I will and to stay in one place for as long or as short as I please. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So I’m very glad that I can make progress, for in this way we help ourselves; over there I reckon 50 francs for board and lodging and the rest on the work, and that’s a big difference from what I was able to do here in the circumstances. So even if others won’t help, we won’t be idle. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Regards, for I still have a lot to arrange today — write a short letter to <rs type="pers" key="422">C.M.</rs> — and in the next few days you’ll receive a message with my address, by tomorrow evening if all goes well. Adieu, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>You wrote to me recently ‘perhaps your <hi rend="ital">duty</hi> will induce you to behave differently or something’. That’s something I immediately thought about a great deal, and because my work so undoubtedly demands the step of going there, it’s my understanding that work is more directly duty than even the <rs type="pers" key="463">woman</rs>, and that the former mustn’t suffer for the sake of the latter. Which was different last year, since in my view I’m <hi rend="ital">now</hi> <hi rend="ital">exactly</hi> at the point of Drenthe. But one has divided feelings and would like to do both, which <hi rend="ital">cannot be</hi> in the circumstances, both because of the money and, more than that, because she can’t be counted on. </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The south-east corner of Drenthe was an unspoilt peat moor. For the work <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> did on his journey to Drenthe and Terschelling, see exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, pp. 83-85, cat. nos. 97-106.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>This somewhat cryptic passage may be paraphrased as follows. <rs type="pers" key="422">Uncle Cor</rs> had given an advance on the drawings sent to him. If he sold enough for Vincent to be able to share in the profits, he would send the money to Theo. Vincent would like to receive this extra income, but he agrees to an arrangement evidently proposed by Theo for the repayment of the advance (which thus meant a reduction in income). He would also understand if (‘indeed’) Theo were to keep any money received from Uncle Cor for himself for some time because of his financial difficulties. Whether the advance – probably 100 francs – was sent all at once or in two parts is not known. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>At that time an internal passport was obligatory because the authorities wanted to have closer supervision of vagrants and vagabonds. The passport referred to the birth certificate, confirmed residency in a municipality and contained the holder’s description and signature.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>