<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Hoogeveen, on or about Wednesday, 26 September 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let390"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">390</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">328</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">393</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Hoogeveen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Wednesday, 26 September 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Hoogeveen, on or about Wednesday, 26 September 1883.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh looks back at the time he was with Sien <ref target="let385.xml">(385)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Loan of 25 guilders from Van Rappard <ref target="let339.xml">(339)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Theo’s visit to The Hague <ref target="let374.xml">(374)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b351 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Vincent asks Theo whether he has received the parcel of studies that was sent on 24 September <ref target="#l-190">(l. 190)</ref> (<ref target="let389.xml">see letter 389</ref>). This means that several days must meanwhile have passed. There are also references in the letter to ‘gloomy, rainy days’ and ‘pouring with rain incessantly for several days’. It rained in the last week of September: there was not a single dry day between 21 September and 1 October 1883. Since the present letter must have been written before <ref target="let391.xml">letter 391</ref> – that one dates from Friday, 28 September and Van Gogh revisits several issues in it – the present letter must have been written on or about Wednesday, 26 September 1883.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0351" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000450_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000450_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000450_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000450_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000450_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0351" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000450_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000450_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000450_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000450_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000450_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000450_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste broer</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Wegens ik eene behoefte hebbe om regtuit te spreken <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>zoo kan ik U niet verbergen dat ik overvallen ben door een gevoel <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>van groote zorg<c type="kk">/</c> gedruktheid<c type="kk">/</c> een je ne sais quoi van moedeloosheid <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>en wanhoop zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> te veel om te zeggen. En dat als ik er geen <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>troost voor vinden kan al te zeer ondragelijk me overstelpt.</ab>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik trek het mij sterk aan dat ik zoo weinig voorspoed <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>heb met de menschen in ’t algemeen<c type="kk">/</c> ik maak mij daarover <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>zeer bekommerd<c type="kk">/</c> en wel vanwege hier maar al te zeer <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>het er boven op komen en het werk doorvoeren in ’t spel is<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Het lot van de vrouw bovendien<c type="kk">/</c> het lot van mijn lief<c type="kk">/</c> arm<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>klein mannetje en het andere kind gaan mij ter harte<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Ik zou nog willen helpen en ik kan niet.</ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik sta op een moment dat ik crediet zou noodig hebben<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>vertrouwen en wat warmte<c type="kk">/</c> en ziedaar ik heb geen vertrouwen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Gij maakt eene uitzondering daarop maar juist omdat <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>het zoo alles neerkomt op U doet dat nog meer in mijn <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>geval uitkomen hoe somber alles is.</ab>
                <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>
<ab rend="indent">En als ik mijn boeltje aanzie<c type="kk">/</c> het is te armzalig<c type="kk">/</c> te <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>ontoereikend<c type="kk">/</c> te zeer uitgeput. Wij hebben hier mistroostige <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>regendagen en als ik op het hoekje zolder kom waar <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>ik mij geinstalleerd heb zoo is het daar al merkwaardig <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>melankoliek – met het licht van één enkele glazen dakpan <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>dat valt op een leege schilderkist<c type="kk">/</c> op een bos penseelen <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>waar ’t haar weinig meer van deugt<c type="kk">/</c> enfin het is <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>zóó curieus melankoliek dat gelukkig het ook een <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>genoegzaam komiek aspect heeft om er niet over te schreijen <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>maar het vroolijker op te vatten. Met dat al is het in <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>hoogst zonderlinge verhouding tot mijn plannen – in <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>hoogst zonderlinge verhouding tot den ernst van het werk <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>en – hier houd het lagchen dan ook op.–</ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat wil ik – het afgeloopen jaar is geeindigd met <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>een nog grooter tekort dan ik U wel zeide want ik <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>heb reeds meer afgedaan dan ik U opgaf <hi rend="ital">met Rappard</hi> <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">er bij</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> en zit nog vooral evenwel met Rappard en drukt die <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>mij het meest wegens het een vriend is<c type="kk">/</c> en ofschoon ik <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>op dit moment alles af deed wat ook maar eenigzins <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>urgent was zoo zit ik er mede dat voor de verf die <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>ik anders zou koopen ik nog eerst andere dien te <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>betalen<c type="kk">/</c> of liever niet durf te wagen op crediet te <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>nemen<c type="kk">/</c> wat op nieuw mij een aanmerkelijke rekening zou <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>veroorzaken over een tijd. Gij weet zelf wel hoe bij Uw <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>bezoek wij niet precies in de stemming waren om nog meer <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>te kunnen zeggen maar nu verklaar ik U wel dat den <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>Haag mij te veel is geweest en ik het scheiden al had uitgesteld <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>en uitgesteld wegens één bepaalde vaste reden<c type="kk">/</c> al was het <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>tekort onvermijdelijk als ik volhield.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat namelijk ik liever dan scheiden<c type="kk">/</c> door trouwen <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>en met haar naar buiten te gaan nog een verdere <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>poging had gewaagd<c type="kk">/</c> evenwel niet zonder U te zeggen <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>hoe de dingen stonden<c type="kp">_</c> Doch ik meende één ding<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>dat dien weg regt was<c type="kk">/</c> ook zelfs ondanks de <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>voorloopige finantieele bezwaren<c type="kk">/</c> en haar behoud had <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>kunnen zijn niet alleen doch bovendien ook voor mij <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>een einde aan veel zielstrijd zou hebben gemaakt die <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>nu ongelukkigerwijs voor me verdubbeld is. <lb n="55a" xml:id="l-55a"/>En ik had het liever <lb n="55b" xml:id="l-55b"/>maar uitgedronken zoo <lb n="55c" xml:id="l-55c"/>als het was.–</ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Indien hetzij Pa hetzij gij het zoo haddet kunnen voelen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>misschien – ik zeg niet dat ik er gelukkiger of ongelukkiger <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>door zou geweest zijn en indien de rollen omgekeerd waren geweest<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>gij in mijn plaats<c type="kk">/</c> ik in de Uwe<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet niet of ik anders hadde <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>kunnen handelen dan gij – maar misschien<c type="kk">/</c> zeg ik<c type="kk">/</c> was <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">zij</hi> er door behouden. Ik beschouw het dan ook als iets waar <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>niet van ulieden doch van mij zelf de beslissing afhing (behalve <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dat ik mij zelf niet mijn’s vaders toestemming om te trouwen kan <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>geven<c type="kk">/</c> dit een enkel punt is buiten mij<c type="kk">/</c> en heeft Pa op een <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>resolute vraag mij <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>in algemeenheden geantwoord waarin echter geen zweem van toestemmen <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>lag) en zoo heb ik beslist en wel omdat ik reeds schulden <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>had en de toekomst donker<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar deze beslissing <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>is nog geen vernieuwing en neemt niet weg de uitputting <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>die een jaar van al te veel zorgen nasleept<c type="kk">/</c> terwijl er een <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>hartewond ook als reste over blijft en een gevoel van leegte en <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>teleurstelling en melankolie – zoo makkelijk niet te genezen<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Ik ben dus nu wel hier<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb dus wel ook in het <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>finantieele het te kort haast gedekt en over een tijd <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>zal dat geheel gedekt kunnen zijn en de natuur is <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>hier wel prachtig en gaat mijn verwachting te boven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>Doch verre ben ik er van daan om reeds weder <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>goed geinstalleerd te zijn en op streek want het is naar de natuur <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>dat ik U een kijkje op mijn zoldertje laat nemen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hadde ik alle dingen vooruit geweten<c type="kk">/</c> ik had verl. <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>jaar toen zij uit het gasthuis kwam met de vrouw naar hier <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>moeten trekken<c type="kk">/</c> dan ware er geen tekort gekomen en dan <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>waren we nu ook wel niet gescheiden want zij is minder <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>schuldig aan haar verkeerd doen dan haar familie<c type="kk">/</c> die <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>zeer gemeen geintrigueerd heeft<c type="kk">/</c> quasi <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>vóór<c type="kk">/</c> au fond tegen haar. Intusschen<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb wel eens <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>getwijfeld of b.v. de moeder niet nog weer door een pastoor<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> ook werd <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>gerugsteund, want er is van hun kant te veel gedaan om de vrouw <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>te influenceeren dan dat ik het verklaren kan. Te meer omdat ik nog <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>niets heb vernomen van haar ofschoon ik vóór mijn heengaan haar <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>gezegd heb dat ik aan den timmerman naast ons<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> mijn adres zou <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>opgeven zoodra ik dit zelf weten zou<c type="kk">/</c> hem dit gestuurd heb met verzoek <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>het haar te zeggen en toch nog niets vernomen dan juist van dien timmerman <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>dat zij al haar goed (meer dan ze meebragt après tout) heeft gehaald.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu begrijpt gij wel ik op het punt van haar lot in zorg <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>ben ofschoon ik geloof dat als zij <hi rend="ital">eenvoudig</hi> in den nood <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>zat zij wel geschreven zou hebben doch nu zal er iets scheefs <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>achter zitten. Gij begrijpt mijn <hi rend="ital">stemming</hi> daaronder<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>ik vrees eenigzins dat de familie haar zegt: hij zal wel <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>schrijven en dan.... <lb n="100a" xml:id="l-100a"/>hebben we hem <lb n="100b" xml:id="l-100b"/>onder den duim<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="100*" xml:id="l-100s"/>enfin zij presumeeren dan <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>op mijn zwakheid en in dien val loop ik <hi rend="ital">niet</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>En heden schrijf ik niet aan haar doch aan den <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>timmerman dat hij moet zorgen zij mijn adres <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>weet<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zal <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> het eerst schrijven aan haar <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>en <hi rend="ital">als</hi> zij schrijft wel zien hoe het eigentlijk staat. <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>Wanneer ik bepaald zou trachten te helpen is als haar <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>familie haar geheel verstiet<c type="kk">/</c> en is het zoo dat zij van haar <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>familie geholpen wordt<c type="kk">/</c> begrijp ik er genoeg van dat zij <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>het te veel eens is en al lang geweest is met die dan dat ik er verder mee <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>te maken zou mogen of kunnen hebben.– <hi rend="ital">Of</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> heb ik gedacht<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="110a" xml:id="l-110a"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">als</hi> er een pastoor achter zit wordt ze zóó geholpen doch op conditie van met mij niets te maken te hebben en is dat reden van haar zwijgen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik wil echter zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> zóóver ben ik nog niet dat ik <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>rusten kan bij de gedachte van scheiding<c type="kk">/</c> tot nog toe <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>heb ik veel<c type="kk">/</c> veel zorg over haar lot juist omdat zij mij <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>in het duister laat daaromtrent<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu dan bovendien overstelpten mij dezer dagen <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>sombere gevoelens over het vervolg en ook omtrent den <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>miserabelen staat van mijn uitrusting in zake schilderbehoeften<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>de onmogelijkheid om de noodigste<c type="kk">/</c> nuttigste dingen <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>te doen zoo als het eigentlijk moest<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>
<ab rend="indent">Indien ik het konde bekostigen zoo zoude ik wegens het <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>mij reeds dadelijk blijkt dat er hier zoo veel moois is<c type="kk">/</c> mijn goed <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>dat nog ginder te s’Hage staat laten komen<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> en ik zou hier of dezen <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>zelfden zolder voor atelier inrigten (door een beetje meer licht er te maken) <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>of een ander lokaal opscharrelen. En dan<c type="kk">/</c> ik zoude <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>al mijn gereedschap willen opfrisschen en aanvullen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>Ik wenschte dat ik eens door en door goed <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>zulks kon doen en als ik bij iemand zooveel <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>vertrouwen kon vinden als dat<c type="kk">/</c> zoo ware mijn <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>grootste zorgen bedaard. Maar of het komt alles <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>op U neer of ik vind er niemand voor die mij <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>vertrouwt<c type="kk">/</c> is het kringetje waarin mijn gedachten <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>ronddraaien en uitweg zie ik niet.–</ab>
                <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>
<ab rend="indent">Een schilder die geen middelen heeft van zich zelf<c type="kk">/</c> hij <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>kan er niet komen zonder een soms betrekkelijk <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>groot crediet bij de menschen<c type="kk">/</c> een crediet dat niet <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>alleen het schildersvak eischt doch dat het <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>schoenmakers-<c type="kk">/</c> timmermans-<c type="kk">/</c> smidsvak evenzeer <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>zoude eisschen<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof noch meer noch minder<c type="kk">/</c> als men <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>zich installeeren of op nieuw ergens vestigen moet.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is met dit regenweder vooral<c type="kk">/</c> waarvan nu nog maanden <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>ons voor de borst staan<c type="kk">/</c> dat ik zeer de handen gebonden heb<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>En dan<c type="kk">/</c> wat wil ik – soms nemen mijn gedachten een vorm <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>aan – ik heb gewerkt en bezuinigd en toch schuld niet <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>kunnen ontwijken<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben de vrouw trouw geweest en toch in <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>ontrouw vervallen<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb intrigues gehaat en toch <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>heb ik noch crediet noch bezitting hoegenaamd. Ik acht niet ligt <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>Uw trouw<c type="kk">/</c> integendeel<c type="kk">/</c> maar veeleer vraag ik mij zelf af of <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>ik U niet moet zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> laat mij schieten want wij komen <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>er niet – het is te veel voor één en er is geen kans om <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>verlichting te krijgen van anderen kant – is zulks geen <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>bewijs genoeg dat wij het overgeven moeten?</ab>
                <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>
<ab rend="indent">O kerel ik ben zoo melankoliek geworden – ik ben in <lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>een prachtig land<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb lust<c type="kk">/</c> ja absolute behoefte <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>aan werk – tevens<c type="kk">/</c> ik ben absoluut de klus <lb n="155" xml:id="l-155"/>kwijt om te weten hoe wij het te boven zullen komen <lb n="156" xml:id="l-156"/>als ik denk dat mijn boeltje in allermiserabelsten <lb n="157" xml:id="l-157"/>staat is en ik zonder atelier of iets hier zit en <lb n="158" xml:id="l-158"/>overal zal gegêneerd zijn tot ik zulks kan verbeteren<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="159" xml:id="l-159"/>De modellen<c type="kk">/</c> zij willen niet als er omstanders bij zijn en <lb n="160" xml:id="l-160"/>dat is het ergste bezwaar waarom een atelier wenschelijk is<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="161" xml:id="l-161"/>Ik heb nu hetzelfde gevoel dat ik had toen ik in den Haag het atelier <lb n="162" xml:id="l-162"/>opzette – “als ik het niet doe gaat het zeker niet”<c type="kp">_</c> En ik <lb n="163" xml:id="l-163"/>heb ook nu<c type="kk">/</c> gegeven den Haag<c type="kk">/</c> geen spijt ik in die gegevens zoo <lb n="164" xml:id="l-164"/>deed als ik deed<c type="kk">/</c> alleen ik wou dat ik 1 1/2 jaar vroeger hier was <lb n="165" xml:id="l-165"/>gekomen en hier een atelier opgezet in plaats van ginder.</ab>
                <lb n="166" xml:id="l-166"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pa schreef mij of hij mij helpen wilde doch ik heb niets laten blijken <lb n="167" xml:id="l-167"/>van zorgen en hoop dat gij Pa dienaangaande ook maar niets <lb n="168" xml:id="l-168"/>zegt<c type="kp">_</c> Pa heeft zijn eigen zorgen en heeft er maar zorgen <lb n="169" xml:id="l-169"/>te meer over als hij iets er van weten zou dat alles niet voor den <lb n="170" xml:id="l-170"/>wind gaat. Zoo schreef ik Pa slechts dat alles mij hier bijzonder <lb n="171" xml:id="l-171"/>was meegevallen<c type="kk">/</c> wat ook volkomen waar is voor zoo ver <lb n="172" xml:id="l-172"/>de natuur aangaat. Zoolang ’t mooi weer was voelde <lb n="173" xml:id="l-173"/>ik een &amp; ander niet doordat ik zooveel moois zag<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="174" xml:id="l-174"/>maar nu het weer aanhoudenden stortregen werd sedert eenige <lb n="175" xml:id="l-175"/>dagen zie ik meer hoe ik eigentlijk vast zit en gegêneerd <lb n="176" xml:id="l-176"/>ben. Wat te doen. Zal ’t met der tijd verergeren of <lb n="177" xml:id="l-177"/>verbeteren. Ik weet er niets van maar dat ik magtig <lb n="178" xml:id="l-178"/>miserable me voel is niet af te schudden.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="179" xml:id="l-179"/>
<ab>In every life some rain <hi rend="ital">must</hi> fall</ab> <lb n="180" xml:id="l-180"/>
                <ab>And days be dark and dreary<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="180*" xml:id="l-180s"/>
<ab>dat is wel zoo<c type="kk">/</c> dat <lb n="181" xml:id="l-181"/>het niet anders kan<c type="kk">/</c> doch vrage<c type="kk">/</c> kan het aantal dark &amp; dreary <lb n="182" xml:id="l-182"/>days niet soms wat al te groot worden? Ik heb toch weer <lb n="183" xml:id="l-183"/>model gehad in de schuur doch met zeer lastig licht<c type="kp">_</c> enfin <lb n="184" xml:id="l-184"/>wat te doen is weiger ik niet te doen doch <hi rend="ital">kan dat wat</hi> MOET <lb n="185" xml:id="l-185"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">in de gegevenen?</hi> En dezen brief is een verzuchting om ruimte <lb n="186" xml:id="l-186"/>en als de winter zóó moest zijn als deze dagen was ik er slecht aan <lb n="187" xml:id="l-187"/>toe. Het is toch mooi<c type="kk">/</c> ja bijzonder mooi met den regen<c type="kk">/</c> doch hoe te werken<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="188" xml:id="l-188"/>hoe als men al te veel mankeert? adieu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> ik wou dat alles teregt <lb n="189" xml:id="l-189"/>kwam doch we zouden meer vertrouwen bij anderen noodig hebben<c type="kk">/</c> anders <lb n="190" xml:id="l-190"/>vrees ik gaat het niet. Ik hoop spoedig van U te hooren. <hi rend="ital">hebt ge studies ontvangen</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="191" xml:id="l-191"/>
<ab rend="indent">met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="191*" xml:id="l-191s"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="191**" xml:id="l-191ss"/>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-46" n="46">tekort &lt; te kort</note>
<note target="l-64" n="64">enkel &lt; enkele</note>
<note target="l-137" n="137">schoenmakers-<c type="kk">/</c> timmermans-<c type="kk">/</c> smidsvak &lt; schoenmakers timmermans smids vak</note>
<note target="l-173" n="173">doordat &lt; door dat</note>
<note target="l-185" n="185">
                        <hi rend="ital">gegevenen?</hi> &lt; <hi rend="ital">gegevenen</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear brother,</ab>
<ab>Because I have a need to speak frankly, I can’t hide from you that I’m overcome by a feeling of great anxiety, dejection, a <hi rend="ital">je ne sais quoi</hi> of discouragement and even despair, too much to express. And that if I can find no consolation for it, it might all too easily overwhelm me unbearably.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It really bothers me that I have so little success with people in general, I’m very concerned about this, and all the more so because rising above it and getting on with the work is at stake here. The fate of the <rs type="pers" key="463">woman</rs>, moreover, the fate of my sweet, poor little <rs type="pers" key="466">lad</rs> and the other <rs type="pers" key="467">child</rs>, cut me to the quick. I’d still like to help and I can’t.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m at a point where I need credit, trust and some warmth, and you see there’s no trust in me. You’re an exception to this, but precisely because everything falls on you it makes it even more apparent how dismal everything is in my case.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And if I look at my things, they’re too poor, too inadequate, too much exhausted. We’re having gloomy, rainy days here, and when I come into the corner of the attic where I’ve installed myself it’s all remarkably melancholy there — with the light from one single glass roof tile that falls on an empty painting box, on a bundle of brushes with few decent bristles remaining, well it’s <hi rend="ital">so</hi> curiously melancholy that luckily it also has a funny enough side not to weep over it but to regard it more cheerfully. But even so, it’s in a very strange relationship to my plans — in a very strange relationship to the seriousness of the work, and — this is where the laughing stops.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">What else can I do? — last year ended with an even bigger deficit than I told you, for I’ve already paid off more than I mentioned to you, <hi rend="ital">including <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>
                    </hi>, and still however owe Rappard above all, and that worries me the most because he’s a friend, and although at this moment I’ve paid off everything that was in the slightest bit urgent I’m faced with the problem that I still have to pay for other things before the paint that I would otherwise buy, or rather I don’t dare take it on credit, which would again cause me a considerable bill in time. You know yourself how we weren’t exactly in the mood to be able to say more during your visit, but I tell you now that The Hague has been too much for me, and I had already put off and put off the separation for one particular specific reason, even though the deficit was inevitable if I persisted. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">This was that, rather than separating, I would have risked one more attempt by marrying <rs type="pers" key="463">her</rs> and going to live with her in the country, although not without telling you how things stood. But I believed one thing, that this was the right course, even despite the temporary financial drawbacks, and that not only could it have been her salvation but would also have put an end to great inner struggle for me, which has now, unhappily, doubled for me. And I would rather have seen it through to the bitter end.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If either <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> or you had been able to feel it thus, perhaps — I don’t say that I would have been happier or unhappier as a result, and if the roles had been reversed, you in my place, I in yours, I don’t know whether I would have been able to act other than as you did — but perhaps, I say, <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="463">she</rs>
                    </hi> would have been saved because of it. I therefore regard it as something where the decision depended not on you two, but on myself (except that I can’t give myself my father’s consent to marry, this single point is beyond me, and in response to a determined question Pa answered me in generalities in which, however, there was no hint of consent), and so I decided, because I already had debts and the future was dark. But this decision is not yet a renewal, and doesn’t take away the exhaustion that a year of too many cares brings in its train, while I’m also left with a wounded heart and a feeling of emptiness and disappointment and melancholy — not so easy to cure. I may be here now, and may almost have covered the financial deficit, and in a while it could be entirely covered, and nature is wonderful here and exceeds my expectations. Yet I’m far from being comfortably settled again and getting on, because the little glimpse of my attic I’m giving you is drawn from life.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If I’d known all these things in advance, I would have moved here with the <rs type="pers" key="463">woman</rs> last year when she came out of hospital, then there would have been no deficit and then we wouldn’t be separated now, for she’s less guilty of her wrongdoing than her family, who have intrigued very meanly, ostensibly <hi rend="ital">for</hi> her but fundamentally against her. Meanwhile, I’ve sometimes wondered, for instance, whether the <rs type="pers" key="464">mother</rs> wasn’t also being backed in turn by a <rs type="pers" key="1760">priest</rs>,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> because too much has been done on their part to influence the woman for me to explain. All the more so because I’ve still heard nothing from her, although before I left I told her that I would give the <rs type="pers" key="472">carpenter</rs> next door<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> my address as soon as I knew it myself; I sent it to him and asked him to tell her, and I’ve still heard nothing, except just from this carpenter that she’s collected all her things (more than she brought with her, after all). 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now you understand that I’m concerned about <rs type="pers" key="463">her</rs> fate, although I believe that if she were <hi rend="ital">simply</hi> in need she’d have written, but now there must be something wrong behind it. You will understand my <hi rend="ital">feeling</hi> about it, I rather fear that the family is saying to her: he’ll surely write and then... we’ll have him under our thumb — in short they’re presuming on my weakness and I am <hi rend="ital">not</hi> going to walk into that trap. And today I’m writing not to her but to the <rs type="pers" key="472">carpenter</rs> to tell him that he must make sure she knows my address, but I will <hi rend="ital">not</hi> write to her first, and <hi rend="ital">if</hi> she writes will see how things actually stand. When I would definitely try to help is if her family were to cast her off entirely, and if it’s the case that her family is helping her, I understand well enough that she’s too much in agreement with them, and has been for a long time, so that I may not or cannot have anything more to do with it. <hi rend="ital">Or</hi>, I’ve thought, <hi rend="ital">if</hi> there’s a priest behind it, she’s being helped but only on condition that she has nothing more to do with me, and that’s the reason for her silence.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But I’ll say that I haven’t yet got <hi rend="ital">so</hi> far that I can resign myself to the idea of separation, at present I’m still very, very concerned about <rs type="pers" key="463">her</rs> fate, precisely because she’s leaving me in the dark about it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And over and above all this, I’ve been overwhelmed these past few days by sombre feelings about the future, and also about the miserable state of my equipment as far as painting materials are concerned, the impossibility of doing the most essential, most useful things as they really should be done.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Since I can already see straightaway that there’s so much beauty here, if I could afford it I would send for my things that are still there in The Hague,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> and I would either fit up this same attic here as a studio (by letting a bit more light in) or look for another place. And then I’d like to renew and replenish all my equipment. I wish that for once I could do this really thoroughly, and if I could find someone who would trust me that far, my greatest concerns would be allayed. But either everything falls on you or I find no one who trusts me, this is the circle in which my thoughts revolve, and I see no way out.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">A painter who has no means of his own can’t get by without sometimes rather large credit with people, credit that not only the profession of painter requires, but that the professions of cobbler, carpenter, smith would equally require, I believe no more nor less, if they had to set themselves up or re-establish themselves somewhere. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s above all in this rainy weather, of which we have months ahead of us, that my hands are really tied. And then, what else can I do? — sometimes my thoughts take on a form — I’ve worked and economized and still not been able to avoid debt, I’ve been faithful to the woman and yet lapsed into disloyalty, I’ve abhorred intrigues and yet I have virtually no credit or possessions. I don’t regard your trust in me lightly, on the contrary, but I rather wonder whether I shouldn’t say to you, forget about me for we won’t get there — it’s too much for one, and there’s no chance of getting any relief from another quarter — is this not proof enough that we should give up?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Oh, old chap, I’ve become so melancholy — I’m in magnificent countryside, I have a desire, indeed an absolute need to work — at the same time I’m absolutely at a loss as to how we’re going to get on top of it, when I think that my things are in the most miserable state and I’m here without a studio or anything, and will be embarrassed everywhere until I can improve matters. The models — they refuse to pose if there are bystanders around, and this is the greatest difficulty that makes a studio desirable. I have the same feeling now as I did when I set up the studio in The Hague — ‘if I don’t do it, I’ll certainly not be able to manage’. And even now, given The Hague, I don’t regret that I did as I did in those circumstances, only I wish I had come here 1 1/2  years earlier and set up a studio here instead of there.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> wrote to me saying that he wanted to help me, but I didn’t let him know anything about my worries, and I hope that you won’t say anything to Pa on this subject either. Pa has his own worries, and would only have even more worries were he to find out that things aren’t going well. So I merely wrote to Pa that everything turned out much better than I expected, which is also perfectly true as far as nature is concerned. As long as the weather was good I wasn’t aware of things because I saw so much that was beautiful, but now that it’s been pouring with rain incessantly for several days I increasingly see how I’m actually stuck here, and I’m embarrassed. What’s to be done? Will things worsen or improve with time? I don’t know, but I feel really miserable and can’t shake it off.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>In every life some rain <hi rend="ital">must</hi> fall</ab>
<ab>And days be dark and dreary<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>that is true, it cannot be otherwise, yet I wonder if the number of dark and dreary days can’t sometimes get too great? Nevertheless, I’ve had a model again in the barn, but in very trying light. After all, I don’t refuse to do what can be done, but <hi rend="ital">can I do what </hi>MUST<hi rend="ital"> be done in the circumstances?</hi> And this letter is a sigh for space, and if the winter has to be like these days, I would be in a bad way. It’s beautiful, though, indeed extremely beautiful in the rain, but how does one work, how when one lacks too much? Adieu, old chap, I wish everything would turn out all right, but we need more trust from other people, otherwise I fear it won’t work. I hope to hear from you soon. <hi rend="ital">Did you receive studies?</hi>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">With a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This is probably <rs type="pers" key="1760">W.A. van Berkel</rs>, who was priest of the Hague ‘Boschkant’ from 1875 to 1890 and died in 1899. See Visser 1973, p. 39.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Most likely <rs type="pers" key="472">Willem Kiesenberg</rs>: <ref target="let241.xml">see letters 241</ref> (in which there is mention of a carpenter who is the house-owner’s foreman) and <ref target="let315.xml">315</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Van Gogh had stored his things in The Hague, in the attic of the house where he had been living; <ref target="let382.xml">see letter 382</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Variant of the closing lines of the poem ‘<rs type="lit" key="358">The rainy day</rs>’ from <rs type="pers" key="696">Longfellow</rs>’s collection <hi rend="ital">Ballads and other poems</hi>: ‘Into each life some rain must fall, / some days must be dark and dreary’. See Longfellow 1886-1891, vol. 1, p. 69.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>These studies were sent on 24 September: <ref target="let389.xml">see letter 389</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>