<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Nieuw-Amsterdam, on or about Friday, 26 October 1883.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let399"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">399</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">334</idno>
    <idno type="brieven1990">400</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee> Theodorus van Gogh and  Anna van Gogh-Carbentus </vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nieuw-Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Friday, 26 October 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theodorus van Gogh and Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Nieuw-Amsterdam, on or about Friday, 26 October 1883.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b357 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter dates from after 17 October (the death of Johanna Tak which Van Gogh refers to, <ref target="#l-3">l. 3</ref>) and after several stormy days <ref target="#l-77">(l. 77)</ref>, which occurred between 16 and 21 October (<hi rend="ital">KNMI</hi>). In part because it was probably Mr van Gogh who wrote ‘27 Oct. 83’ in the top right corner – he most likely sent the letter on to Theo that day – we have dated the letter on or about Friday, 26 October 1883. In <hi rend="ital">Brieven </hi>1914 Jo van Gogh-Bonger took the date written in the other hand.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0357" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000460_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000460_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000460_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0357" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000460_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000460_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000460_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000460_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000460_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000460_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste Ouders</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Uwe brieven heb <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>ik ontvangen en dank U er wel voor.</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het overlijden van Nicht Anna Tak trof mij <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ook<c type="kk">/</c> ja er kon wel spoedig iets gebeuren<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Ik heb wel eens gedacht zij niet heel gelukkig was<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>of liever<c type="kk">/</c> voor mij zelf twijfel ik daar geen oogenblik <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>aan<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik geloof men met een bankier moeielijk <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>gelukkig kan zijn<c type="kk">/</c> in den tegenwoordigen tijd minder <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>dan ooit<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> U zult zeggen<c type="kk">/</c> dat is niet zoo – maar <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ik heb nu eenmaal zekere gedachten daaromtrent <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>in verband met den gang van alle zaken<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er is een zekere sfeer waar men liefst buiten <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>moet blijven mijns inziens<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Om van iets anders te spreken – de lui van het <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Heike bedrogen elkaar en of dat hier nooit gebeurt <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>zoude ik niet durven verzekeren.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Maar van de <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>lui van het Heike geloof ik zij ook al bewezen men <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ondanks het elkaar eventueel bedriegen<c type="kk">/</c> ondanks <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>het als van zelf sprekend beschouwd wordende daarvan<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>zoo’n bevolking toch au fond zeer eendragtig is <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>in ’t groot beschouwd. Het Heike vond ik een merk<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>waardig voorbeeld van energie<c type="kk">/</c> die huisjes elk <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>met een stukje groen land<c type="kk">/</c> dat arme troepje <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>zamen strijd voerende tegen de onvruchtbaarheid <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>der heide – ik ontken hun fouten niet doch <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>zij vallen mij geenszins ’t allereerst in ’t oog. Zoo <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>hier had ik er nog niet over gedacht of de lieden <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>elkaar bedrogen<c type="kp">_</c> Nu ik er over denk<c type="kk">/</c> wel – <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>waarschijnlijk zal dat wel eens gebeuren – maar <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>in ’t algemeen is het geen mij treft datzelfde <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wat ik in ’t klein in ’t Heike zag<c type="kp">_</c>– Hier is het <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>uitgebreider en interessanter en heeft nog meer <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>karakter<c type="kp">_</c>– Iets minstens zoo mooi en ordelijk <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>als een mieren nest of een bijenkorf. Ziedaar <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>de dingen in ’t groot – voor mij bewonderenswaardig <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>zoo als ze zijn – en hoe ze zouden kunnen wezen – 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>ik wil niet tegenspreken van beter – maar <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>zooals gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> ik zie hier zooveel positief goeds <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>reeds dat ik mij maar stil houd om er aanmerking <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>op te maken<c type="kk">/</c> vooral daar ik nog geenszins bij <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>magte ben toevalligheden van karakterfouten <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>te onderscheiden<c type="kp">_</c> Ik moet voor ik daartoe kom <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>er nog meer van zien<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> als ik tegenover elkaar stel eene <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>stadsbevolking en deze<c type="kk">/</c> zoo aarzel ik geen <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>oogenblik te zeggen deze heibewoners of <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>veenarbeiders mij beter voorkomen. Ja dan <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>komt het verschil mij enorm voor<c type="kk">/</c> al bedriegen <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ze hier elkaar niet minder dan op ’t Heike zelfs<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>maar ik zeg niet dat ze dat doen<c type="kk">/</c> ik weet het <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>nog niet<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik sprak onlangs met den man bij wien ik <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>woon<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> die ook zelf boert<c type="kk">/</c> over iets soortgelijks<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>Toevalligerwijs wegens hij vroeg hoe het in <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Londen gesteld was<c type="kk">/</c> hij had daar zoo veel van <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>gehoord<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zeide tot hem dat voor mij <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>een eenvoudige boer die <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">werkte en dacht bij zijn werk</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="ital">de</hi> beschaafde <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>man was – dat zulks altijd zoo geweest is<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>altijd zoo blijven zal<c type="kk">/</c> dat op het land men <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>hier &amp; daar er een ziet in wien men ziet wat dat <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>is<c type="kk">/</c> en in stad men onder de heele<c type="kk">/</c> heele <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>zeldzame allerbesten enkele lui vindt <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>die op heel verschillende wijs bijna precies <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>even nobel zijn<c type="kp">_</c> Doch dat mijns inziens het <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>daar bij blijft en dat in ’t algemeen op ’t land <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>men meer kans heeft een redelijk wezen te <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>ontmoeten dan in stad<c type="kp">_</c>– En verder dat ik <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>meende dat hoe meer men bij de groote steden kwam<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>hoe verder men in het donker van <hi rend="ital">on</hi>beschaving <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>en domheid en slechtheid kwam<c type="kp">_</c>– Hij zeide dat <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>eigentlijk ’t hem ook zoo voorkwam<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er <hi rend="ital">is</hi> een onderscheid en buiten <hi rend="ital">is</hi> het rustiger<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>vrediger<c type="kk">/</c> iets beter; ook al bedriegen <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>ze elkaar<c type="kk">/</c> ze doen ’t zóó erg niet als <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>in stad<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="76*" xml:id="l-76s"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bij afwisseling hebben wij <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>hier mooie<c type="kk">/</c> heldere herfstdagen &amp; stormachtige dito<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Eigentlijk vind ik de laatsten ’t mooist<c type="kk">/</c> al gaat <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>dan het buiten werken bezwaarlijker<c type="kk">/</c> al is het soms <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>zelfs gansch niet te doen<c type="kp">_</c> Toch<c type="kk">/</c> er door loopen <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>en een studie die men op een mooien dag <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>gemaakt heeft verschilderen overeenkomstig <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>wat men bij regen buiten ziet<c type="kk">/</c> is te doen &amp; <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>bevind ik me goed bij. Maak U over <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>mijn gezondheid niet ongerust<c type="kk">/</c> ik zorg er voor <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>en zelfs voel ik me in dezen eersten tijd hier <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>beter dan in de laatste paar maanden te s’Hage <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>toen ik veel last had van zenuwachtigheid &amp;c. <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>En dat is geheel gecalmeerd. Men kan mijns <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>inziens nergens beter denken dan bij een <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>boerenhaard waar een oude wieg met <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>een kindje bij staat – &amp; men door ’t venster <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>een fijngroen korenveldje ziet en het waaien <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>der elzenboschjes<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben nog al veel achter de ploegers <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>tegenwoordig &amp; moet daar weer heen. <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>Gegroet beste ouders – mijn overjas is <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>best in orde<c type="kk">/</c> de borstrok is heerlijk<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>
<ab rend="indent">geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="99*" xml:id="l-99s"/>
<ab>Uw liefh<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-74" n="74">beter; &lt; beter</note>
<note target="l-80" n="80">loopen &lt; loopende</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Parents</rs>,</ab>
<ab>I received your letters and I thank you for them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The death of Cousin <rs type="pers" key="770">Anna Tak</rs> touched me too; yes, it could have happened at any time.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I sometimes thought that she wasn’t entirely happy, or rather, for my part I don’t doubt it for a moment. I think it must be difficult to be happy with a banker, less than ever nowadays.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> You will say that it isn’t so — but I just happen to have certain ideas about it in regard to the way of all businesses.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">There’s a certain sphere that it’s better to keep out of, in my view.</ab>
    <ab rend="indent">To change the subject — the people of Het Heike cheated one another, and I wouldn’t swear that it never happens here.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> But as to the people of Het Heike, I believe that they have shown that, despite the way they may have cheated one another, despite this being taken for granted, when it comes down to it people like that are very united, taken as a whole. I found Het Heike a remarkable example of energy; the little houses each with a patch of green land, that poor little band battling together against the barrenness of the heath — I don’t deny their faults, but they’re by no means the first things that strike me. I had never thought about whether the people cheated one another here. Now that I come to think of it, well — it probably does happen sometimes — but generally what strikes me is the same as I saw on a small scale in Het Heike. It’s more spacious here and more interesting, and has more character. Something at least as attractive and orderly as an ants’ nest or beehive. So there you have things writ large — I find them admirable as they are — and as to how they might be — 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> I won’t deny that they could be better — but, as I said, I already see so much positive good here that I refrain from commenting, particularly since as yet I’m by no means able to distinguish coincidences from character flaws. I’ll have to see more before I can do that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, if I compare the population of a city and these people, I don’t hesitate for one moment in saying that these heathland people or peat workers seem better to me. Yes, the difference seems to me to be enormous, even if they cheat one another no less than on Het Heike, although I don’t say that they do, I don’t know yet.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I recently spoke about something of the kind to the <rs type="pers" key="195">man</rs> I lodge with,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> who also farms — by chance, because he asked me what it was like in London, he’d heard so much about it. I told him that, to me, a simple peasant who <hi rend="ital">worked and thought while he was working</hi> was the civilized man — that this has always been so, will always remain so, that here and there in the country one sees someone in whom one sees what that is, and in the city one finds a few among the very, very rare excellent people who are almost exactly as noble in a very different way. But that in my view it goes no further, and that generally speaking one has more chance of meeting a reasonable human being in the country than in the city. And also that I thought that the more one went to the big cities, the more one went into the darkness of <hi rend="ital">un</hi>civilization and stupidity and wickedness. He said that it actually appeared the same to him. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">There <hi rend="ital">is </hi>a difference, and in the country it <hi rend="ital">is</hi> quieter, more peaceful, something better; even if they do cheat one another, they don’t do it as badly as in the city.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">We have, by turns, beautiful, clear autumn days here and stormy ditto.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Actually I find the latter the most beautiful, even though they make it more awkward to work outdoors, even though it’s sometimes completely impossible to do so. All the same, going out and reworking a study one has made on a fine day in accordance with what one sees outdoors in the rain can be done, and it satisfies me. Don’t worry about my health, I’m taking care of myself, and in these early days here I’m even feeling better than in the last few months in The Hague, when I was much troubled by nervousness &amp;c. And that has calmed down altogether. In my view, there’s nowhere one can think better than by a peasant hearth, with a baby in an old cradle beside it — and where one can see through the window a delicate green wheatfield and the alder bushes waving.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m following the ploughmen a great deal at present and must get back there. Regards, dear <rs type="pers" key="524 526">parents</rs> — my overcoat is perfectly all right, the undervest is splendid.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Van Gogh’s cousin <rs type="pers" key="770">Johanna Elisabeth Tak-Van Gogh</rs>, Uncle Jan van Gogh’s daughter, died on 17 October 1883 in Middelburg at the age of 39. She was married to the merchant banker <rs type="pers" key="771">Jan Tak</rs>. The cause of her death is not known; the announcement of her death in the <hi rend="ital">Middelburgsche Courant</hi> of 17 October 1881, placed by her husband, states that she died ‘after several days’ suffering’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>From 1883 to 1888 there was an economic recession that resulted in unemployment and poverty.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Het Heike (St. Willibrorddorp) lies around 3 km to the south-west of Etten. The alleged general treachery of the people there must have been raised in the letter from <rs type="pers" key="526 524">Pa and Ma</rs>, possibly to warn Vincent against the people in his own surroundings.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The lodging-house keeper <rs type="pers" key="195">Hendrik Scholte</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>It had been stormy from 16 to 21 October, whereas the preceding and subsequent days were fine (<hi rend="ital">KNMI</hi>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Evidently Vincent’s <rs type="pers" key="524 526">parents</rs> had sent him a parcel of useful items.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>