<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Saturday, 16 June 1883. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let355"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">355</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">294</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">357</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>The Hague</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Saturday, 16 June 1883</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. The Hague, on or about Saturday, 16 June 1883. </p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh’s visit to Van Rappard’s studio <ref target="let344.xml">(344)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b317 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>In the time between <ref target="let353.xml">letter 353</ref> of on or about 15 June 1883 and this letter, Van Gogh began work on the planned drawing of a row of diggers <ref target="#l-15">(ll. 15-16)</ref>. He has worked on it for at least one day and ‘last night’ <ref target="#l-17">(ll. 17-20)</ref>. He also asks Theo to send the third remittance ‘earlier’ if possible <ref target="#l-85">(l. 85)</ref>. There would be no point in this unless the letter reached Paris by 18 June at the latest. Accordingly, we have dated it on or about Saturday, 16 June 1883. </p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>Enclosed with this letter for Theo to read was the latest letter from Van Rappard to Van Gogh; <ref target="#l-3">see l. 3</ref>. This letter is not known.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0317" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000398_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000398_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000398_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000398_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0317" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000398_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000398_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000398_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000398_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Kort nadat ik mijn brief aan U verzond ontving <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>ik een karakteristiek schrijven van Rappard dat ik U <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>eens ter lezing wilde sturen omdat gij hem toch van vroeger <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>kent<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> &amp; nu in den laatsten tijd hem niet hebt ontmoet. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Wat ik U schreef van dat ik vond hij zooveel verbeterd was<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>(ofschoon ik hem vroeger ook goed vond) zult gij denk ik <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>in dezen brief (aan den serieusen toon in ’t algemeen zoo) <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>wel zien. Werkelijk zijn teekeningen zijn verduiveld <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>mooi en ’t is eerlijk werk wat hij maakt.</ab>
                <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin lees den brief eens, ik vind het zoo’n flinke <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>opvatting van de dingen. Stuur me later den brief <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>weer eens terug.</ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Had U nog iets te vertellen – ik schreef U over mijn <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>plan voor een groote teekening<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> – wel<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ik heb er aan begonnen nog denzelfden dag dat <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>ik U schreef<c type="kk">/</c> juist ook omdat ik door dien brief van <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>R. werd geanimeerd. Ik heb er sedert aan <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>doorgewerkt en heeft het me zoo geabsorbeerd <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>dat ik zelfs haast den heelen afgeloopen nacht <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>er aan zat te werken<c type="kp">_</c> Ik kreeg er oog op <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>en wou doorzetten.</ab>
                <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb ’t nog veranderd in eenvoudigen <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>compositie<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. enkel een rij spitters<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Ik heb 7 figuren daarvan geschetst<c type="kk">/</c> 5 mannen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>en twee vrouwen<c type="kp">_</c> De overigen worden <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>kleiner op ’t tweede plan. ’t Is geloof ik <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>de krachtigste teekening die ik nog gemaakt heb <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>en betreffende de opvatting zoo zijn mijn gedachten <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>daaromtrent dergelijk als R. in zijn brief het <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>zegt. Ik net als hij kom tot de manier van <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>sommige Engelschen zonder aan hen te denken <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>om ze te imiteeren<c type="kk">/</c> maar waarschijnlijk daarom <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>omdat ik in de natuur door soortgelijke dingen <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>word aangetrokken en die slechts door betrekkelijk <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>weinigen gemaakt worden<c type="kk">/</c> en men dus als men <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>ze maakt een manier zoeken moet om wat men <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>voelt weer te geven en eenigzins bezijden de gewone <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>regels gaan om het uit te drukken wat men wil. <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>(Net als Rappard op zijn teekening in kwestie allerlei machines in <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>werking heeft geteekend die anders haast <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>geen mensch zou durven attaqueeren en <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>buiten ’t geen men als pittoresk <hi rend="ital">gewoon</hi> <hi rend="ital">is</hi> te beschouwen <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zijn<c type="kp">_</c>)<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Weet ge hoe de teek. v<c type="kp">_</c> Rappard is<c type="kk">/</c> ’t is net als of men <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>een beschrijving van een fabriek door Zola of Daudet <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>of Lemonnier zou lezen.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> In zijn brief heb ik nog een <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>passage aangestreept – die over <hi rend="ital">teekenende</hi> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">schilderen</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> Wel<c type="kk">/</c> ’t komt toch ongeveer op ’t zelfde <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>neer wat ik verl. jaar tegen sommigen zeide die <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>mij zeiden<c type="kk">/</c> schilderen is teekenen met kleur<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>waarop ik antwoordde<c type="kk">/</c> Nu ja<c type="kk">/</c> juist<c type="kk">/</c> en ’t teekenen in Black &amp; White <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>is eigentlijk schilderen in wit &amp; zwart<c type="kp">_</c> <hi rend="ital">Zij</hi> zeiden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>schilderen is teekenen – ik<c type="kk">/</c> teekenen is schilderen. <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>Maar toen was ik nog te zwak in mijn factuur <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>dan dat ik ’t in wat anders dan woorden kon <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>zeggen &amp; nu zeg ik ’t in woorden minder en <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>meer zwijgend in werk.</ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab rend="indent">Sedert ge me schreeft over Uw betrekkelijk in <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>finantieele moeielijkheden zijn<c type="kk">/</c> heb ik werkelijk <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>met een soort woede gewerkt<c type="kk">/</c> dag en nacht<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>’t Is nu de vijfde groote die ik op touw heb <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>gezet of eigentlijk zesde want de mestvaalt deed ik <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>twee keer<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> En wat al studies er voor noodig zijn <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>zult ge zien als ge komt.</ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als R. <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> met drukinkt heeft geteekend<c type="kk">/</c> ik heb het <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>hier en daar <hi rend="ital">wel</hi> gedaan. doch wat hij zegt is <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>waar – hij werkt in een witten passepartout en <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>dan lijkt ’t zwart zwarter<c type="kk">/</c> ik werk in een bruinen passepartout <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>met een zwarten binnenrand waarvan ’t zwart juist <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>zeer diep is gemaakt om de teekening helder <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>te houden. Wat betreft dat de Engelschen geen drukinkt <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>zouden gebruiken heeft hij mis betrekkelijk<c type="kp">_</c> Want zij voeren <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>de teekeningen op juist door soms enorme krachten <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>te gebruiken waar de grootste krachten van fusain nog <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>zeer helder door worden. Die krachten worden verkregen door <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>drukinkt of autographische inkt of lampblack<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> of neutraltint <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>&amp; andere zwarten uit de waterverf. ’t Moet U niet verwonderen dat ik in <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>korten tijd er zooveel opzette. bij ’t composeeren van een teekening haast nog meer dan <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>bij schilderen speelt het denken en het dóórdenken een rol en bevind ik voor mij me <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>er goed bij b.v. zoo als nu op de laatste een dag en halve nacht door <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>te zetten. Maar op die wijs kan men productief worden ook – <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>’t absorbeert dan ook enorm.– Maar juist als men zoo door ’t werk sterk <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>getrokken wordt moet men er aan blijven tot men er om zoo te zeggen <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>bij neervalt. Ik ben absoluut à sec<c type="kk">/</c> als ge kunt <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>stuur wat vroeger<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik zal van nacht wel weer weinig <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>slapen door de teekening. Maar ’t is heel gezellig met <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>een pijpje s’nachts als alles stil is<c type="kk">/</c> en het morgen worden en <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/> opgaan van de zon is goddelijk. Nu kerel<c type="kk">/</c> als ge kunt <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>stuur spoedig. Voorspoed in alles<c type="kk">/</c> adieu<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab>t. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="90*" xml:id="l-90s"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-43" n="43">zijn<c type="kp">_</c>) &lt; zijn</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Shortly after I sent my letter to you I received a characteristic letter from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> which I wanted to send to you to read because you used to know him<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and haven’t seen him recently. I think you’ll see in this letter (from the serious tone in general) what I wrote to you about my finding him so much improved<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> (although I thought he was good in the past too). His drawings are really devilishly good, and what he does is honest work.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Anyway, read the letter, it seems to me such a robust attitude to things. Send the letter back to me later.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Had something else to tell you — I wrote to you about my plan for a large drawing<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> — well, I began work on it the same day I wrote to you, precisely because <rs type="pers" key="1306">R.</rs>’s letter made me enthusiastic. I’ve carried on working on it ever since, and it has so absorbed me that I even worked on it through almost the whole of last night. I got my eye in and wanted to push on.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve changed it into a simple composition, namely just a row of diggers. I’ve sketched 7 of the figures, 5 men and two women. The remainder will be smaller in the background. It is, I believe, the most forceful drawing I’ve done so far, and as regards the approach, my thoughts on that subject are similar to what <rs type="pers" key="1306">R.</rs> says in his letter. Like him, I arrive at the manner of some of the English without thinking of them in order to imitate them, but probably because I’m attracted by such things in nature and they’re done by relatively few, and so if one does them one must find a way to depict what one feels and go somewhat wide of the normal rules to express what one wants. (Just as in the drawing in question Rappard drew all kinds of machines in operation which otherwise almost no one would dare to tackle, and which are beyond what’s <hi rend="ital">normally</hi> thought of as picturesque.)<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Do you know what <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>’s drawing is like? It’s as if one were reading a description of a factory by <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="583">Daudet</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="688">Lemonnier</rs>.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> I’ve marked a passage in his letter — the one about <hi rend="ital">painting like drawing</hi>. Well, it comes down to about the same as what I said last year to some who said to me, painting is drawing with colour, to which I replied, Yes, exactly, and drawing in Black and White is in fact painting in white and black. <hi rend="ital">They</hi> said, painting is drawing — I, drawing is painting. But then I was still too weak in my execution to be able to say it in something other than words, and now I say it less in words and more silently in work.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Since you wrote to me about your being in relative financial difficulties, I’ve really worked day and night in a kind of fury. I’ve now started work on the fifth large one, or rather the sixth, because I did the dung-heap twice.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> And when you come you’ll see the number of studies required for them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="1306">R.</rs> has <hi rend="ital">not</hi> drawn with printer’s ink, but I <hi rend="ital">have</hi> here and there. But what he says is true — he works in a white passe-partout and then the black seems blacker; I work in a brown passe-partout with a black inside edge which is a very deep black, precisely in order to keep the drawing clear. As for the English not using printer’s ink, he’s quite wrong. For they work the drawings up precisely by using tremendous strengths sometimes, which still make the greatest strengths of charcoal very clear. These strengths are obtained through printer’s ink or autographic ink or lampblack<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> or neutral tint and other blacks from watercolour. You shouldn’t be surprised that I’ve done so many in a short time. Thinking and thinking through plays a role in composing a drawing almost more than in painting, and for my part I feel fine if I carry on as now, for instance, with this last one for a day and half a night. But in this way one can become productive too — it’s tremendously absorbing. But precisely when one is so strongly drawn by the work, one must continue with it until one is fit to drop, so to speak. I’m absolutely broke, send somewhat earlier if you can. I won’t sleep much tonight again because of the drawing. But it’s very pleasant with a pipe at night when everything’s quiet, and the dawn and the sunrise is glorious. Well, old chap, send soon if you can. Good fortune with everything, adieu.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Theo and <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> had got to know each other in Paris; <ref target="let160.xml#n-6">see letter 160, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>For Van Gogh’s high opinion of <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs>, see for example <ref target="let343.xml">letters 343</ref>, <ref target="let344.xml">344</ref> and <ref target="let347.xml">347</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>This is the planned drawing of potato lifting; <ref target="let353.xml">see letter 353</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> was working on a drawing of a forge in which rollers could probably be seen. Cf. exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 82, cat. nos. 94-95.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Van Gogh admired the naturalism and realism of the writers named; they did not idealize the hard reality of a factory or workshop.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Besides the drawing of diggers on which he is working, Van Gogh means the five large drawings he had done in recent weeks: <hi rend="ital">Peat diggers in the dunes</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2437">F 1031 / JH 363</rs>), a sand quarry (‘workmen labouring’), two versions of the refuse dump and a scene at the coal yard at Rijnspoor station. Except for the first, these drawings are not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Lamp-black, which contains a fine-grained, deep black pigment.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>