<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Saturday, 15 and about Wednesday, 19 March 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let438"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">438</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">363</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">442</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about Saturday, 15 and about Wednesday, 19 March 1884</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Saturday, 15 and about Wednesday, 19 March 1884.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mrs van Gogh’s broken leg <ref target="let423.xml">(423)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b396 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>On 10 March Vincent responded hotly to a letter from Theo (<ref target="let436.xml">letter 436</ref>) and he is now surprised that he has still not had a reply from Theo. He also complains ‘that you don’t have the usual yet again this month’ <ref target="#l-82">(ll. 82-83)</ref>. This remark in any event puts the letter before <ref target="let440.xml">letter 440</ref>, which was written on or about 20 March. On the other hand, some days must have elapsed since <ref target="let436.xml">letter 436</ref>, because Van Gogh had expected a reply to it <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref>. We therefore date the present letter between about Saturday, 15 and about Wednesday, 19 March 1884.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>There are two painters’ names and the name of a collector, probably in Theo’s handwriting, on p. [1r:4].</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0396" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000520_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000520_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000520_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000520_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000520_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0396" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000520_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000520_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000520_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000520_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000520_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000520_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>het heeft mij een beetje <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>verwonderd dat ik van U niet heb gehoord. <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Omdat ge schrijft: “indien ’t je niet convenieert <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>te wachten<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf mij per ommegaande”<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>
<ab rend="indent">Goed<c type="kk">/</c> ik schreef U terug dat wat betreft <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>’t convenieeren langer te wachten<c type="kk">/</c> inderdaad <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>me dit geenszins deed – doch antwoord <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>kreeg ik daar minder direkt op<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mijn brief was juist er over dat waar <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>er iets wat al te traînants begon te komen m.i. in onze <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>vriendschap<c type="kk">/</c> dit niet opwekkend was &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> wat <lb n="11a" xml:id="l-11a"/>ik niet hoef te repeteeren.–</ab>
                <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bezuiniging nu is dit zeer zeker niet <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>want tijd is ook geld en waar men <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>zelfs op verf moet wachten is de zuinigheid <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>meest radicaal<c type="kk">/</c> ABSURD zelfs in mijn oog<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Doch weet gij het voor U zelf – mijn zaken <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>après tout zijn de uwen niet – en als <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ge niet van zelf begrijpt<c type="kk">/</c> wat zal ik mijn <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>geduld en mijn tijd verliezen er over te <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>zaniken<c type="kp">_</c>– Ge kunt evenwel van mij niet <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>verwachten dat zoolang er een beetje fut in <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>me zit ik vrede neme met meer en <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>meer verslappen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ge moet U maar goed oefenen in <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>dat systeem van de omzigtigheid <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>en de fatsoenlijkheid en wat dies meer <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>zij<c type="kk">/</c> dan zult ge ’t wel ver brengen; <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>in de mediocreteit juist – wel te <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>verstaan – <hi rend="sc">Dat</hi> leidt <hi rend="sc">daartoe</hi> en <hi rend="ital">regelregt</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Niet omdat ik dat zeg – maar omdat <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>als men zijn oogen opendoet en zich <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>de moeite geeft eens rond te kijken <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>het tienduizendmaal te zien is<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoor echter dat Uw vriend Braat ziek is <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>geworden – (wat ik hem altijd eigentlijk heb gevonden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>het korte tijdje dat ik hem eenigzins kende)<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>is het U daardoor door ’t hoofd gegaan<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> enfin <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>wat er ook van zij<c type="kk">/</c> wees zoo goed mij <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>op mijn laatsten brief te antwoorden en <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>inlichting te geven in hoever ge al dan <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>niet het in dien zin wilt veranderen<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het gaat met Moe geleidelijk vooruit<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="44*" xml:id="l-44s"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab>Bij gewone goede verstandhouding zou ’t <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>geheel buiten kwestie zijn te stipuleeren men <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>in elkaars privé zaken niet zich mengen zal <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>en als ge een greintje <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>warmte voor mijn werk hadt zoudt ge niet <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>absoluut het laten liggen. En nog meer <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>schrijf ik zoo als ik schrijf om U een beetje <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>te laten voelen hoe ge koud geworden zijt <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>voor wat we zamen ondernamen met goeden <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>moed en hoe bovendien er te veel koud fatsoenlijke <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>politiek in Uw leven insluipt<c type="kk">/</c> dan wel <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>omdat ik aan de meerdere of mindere <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>beslistheid eener afspraak veel waarde hecht<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>Den grond der kwestie is een elkaar <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>begrijpen of niet begrijpen – een zaak <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>van kou of van warmte voor elkaar<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>En dat wat Zola zegt over traineeren vind <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>ik even waar als gij – dat dooft energie <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>uit<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Doch resteert iets er bij te <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>vragen<c type="kk">/</c> waar ligt dat traineeren aan<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>Ik voor mij<c type="kk">/</c> die liever buiten ben dan in den stad<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>verlang volstrekt niet er naar om met U te breken<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>doch zoo als ’t nu gaat<c type="kk">/</c> indien ik al werk ik dag <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>in dag uit<c type="kk">/</c> zie dat ik met U niet vorder<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>ik kan dat niet uitstaan en zie er in een verwaarloozen <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>van mijn eigen zaken waarvoor later après tout <hi rend="ital">ik</hi> <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>verantwoordelijk zou zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Wilt gij er voor zorgen <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>– en voorzeker ge zijt daartoe in de gelegenheid – dat 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>mijn werk gezien wordt door die lui die<c type="kk">/</c> indien <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>niet nu dan toch later<c type="kk">/</c> er de liefhebbers voor moeten <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>worden – best – dan kan ik er mijn hart van <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>af trekken en occupeer mij slechts met het schilderen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Het <hi rend="ital">zoo</hi> laten liggen als ge doet – <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>is NEGLIGENCE<c type="kp">_</c>– Wilt ge dit pedant <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>van me vinden – dat moet ge voor U zelf <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>uit maken – maar ik vind hier U zelf wat pedant waar ’t niet te <lb n="81a" xml:id="l-81a"/>pas komt.</ab>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Juist uit de zaak dat deze maand <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>nu ook weer gij het gewone niet hebt – <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>moogt ge wel eens nadenken dat wij er <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>met ons zoo groot te houden <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>niet komen zullen<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Had ik het zoo<c type="kk">/</c> dat niet met den dag meer <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>ik voelde ik er wat bij noodig heb<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zou ik <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>mijn studies stil voor me zelf houden<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zoo als Rappard doet<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar gij zegt zelf <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>dat wij niet in Rappards geval zijn – en met dat <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>al raak ik maar meer en meer in ’t naauw<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb van daag mijn 9<hi rend="ss">de</hi> geschilderde studie van een wever <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>’t huis gebragt<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> – schilderen kost geld en waar ik op verf moet <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>wachten<c type="kk">/</c> zooals me telkens gebeurt<c type="kk">/</c> verlies ik tijd – en – <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>allons – als ge er wat warm voor waart zouden we <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>hebben wat er noodig is<c type="kp">_</c>– En wat voor impressie <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>moet het wel maken indirekt op anderen als <hi rend="ital">gij zoo doet</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>Voorzeker dit is weinig geschikt om eenig vertrouwen <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>op te wekken<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-27" n="27">brengen; &lt; brengen</note>
<note target="l-70" n="70">ik kan &lt; kan</note>
<note target="l-80" n="80">voor U zelf &lt; voor Uw zelf</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>It surprised me a little that I haven’t heard from you. Because you write: ‘if it isn’t convenient for you to wait, write to me by return’.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Very well, I wrote back to you that as far as being convenient to wait longer, it indeed certainly wasn’t — but I got a less direct response to that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">This is precisely what my letter was about — that where our friendship was really beginning to flag in my view, this wasn’t stimulating &amp;c., which I don’t need to repeat.</ab>
    <ab rend="indent">Now this is most certainly not economizing, for time is money too, and when one even has to wait for paint, that is economizing at its most radical, even ABSURD, to my mind. But you should know this for yourself — my affairs aren’t yours, after all — and if you don’t understand it as a matter of course, why should I waste my patience and my time harping on about it? However, you can’t expect me to put up with more and more slackening as long as there’s a bit of spirit in me. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Go on and train yourself well in that system of prudence and respectability and suchlike, then you’ll go far, precisely in mediocrity — you understand — <hi rend="sc">That</hi> leads <hi rend="sc">to it</hi>, and<hi rend="ital"> directly</hi>. Not because I say so — but because it can be seen ten thousand times if one opens one’s eyes and takes the trouble just to look around.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hear that your friend <rs type="pers" key="305">Braat</rs> has fallen ill, though — (which I always thought he was anyway, the short time I knew him at all). Did it slip your mind because of that?<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Anyway, be that as it may, be so good as to answer my last letter and give me information about the extent to which you do or don’t want to change it in that way.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs> is making gradual progress. Regards.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab>In normal good relations it would be utterly out of the question to stipulate that we shouldn’t interfere in each other’s private affairs, and if you had a speck of warmth for my work you wouldn’t totally neglect it. And I write as I write more to get you to feel a little how you’ve become cold to what we undertook together in good heart and how, moreover, too much coldly decent politics is creeping into your life than because I attach great value to whether an agreement is more or less fixed. The essence of the question is whether we understand each other or not — a matter of coldness or warmth towards each other. And I find what <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs> says about dragging things on as true as you do — it extinguishes energy.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> Yet there remains something more to ask — what is the cause of this dragging on? For my part, I, who would rather be in the country than in a city, have absolutely no desire to break with you. But as things are going now, when I see that I still get nowhere with you even though I work day in and day out, I can’t stand it and see in it a neglect of my own affairs for which later, after all, <hi rend="ital">I</hi> would be responsible. If you were prepared to see to it — and you most certainly have the opportunity — that 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> my work is seen by those who should become enthusiasts of it, if not now then in any event later — very well — then I can stop worrying about it and occupy myself solely with painting. Doing nothing with it <hi rend="ital">like that</hi>, the way you do — is NEGLIGENCE. If you want to think this pedantic of me — that’s up to you — but I think you yourself rather pedantic here, where it isn’t appropriate.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">From the very circumstance that you don’t have the usual yet again this month — you might like to consider that we won’t cope by keeping up such appearances.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Were it not the case that I feel more strongly by the day that I need something more, I would keep my studies quietly to myself.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> does. But you say yourself that we’re not in Rappard’s position — and with all that I’m becoming more and more hard pressed.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Today I brought home my 9th painted study of a weaver<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> — painting costs money, and when I have to wait for paint, as I keep having to do, I waste time — and — come on — if you were a little enthusiastic about it, we’d have what’s needed. And what sort of an impression must it make, indirectly, on other people when <hi rend="ital">you behave like this</hi>? It’s certainly hardly likely to create much confidence.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>At this time Theo was assisting the seriously ill <rs type="pers" key="305">Frans Braat</rs>, who worked for Goupil (FR b2962. Letter from <rs type="pers" key="306">Pieter Kornelis Braat</rs> to Theo van Gogh, 13 April 1884). Theo and Frans were in lodgings together in 1878 (<ref target="let144.xml#n-29">see letter 144, n. 29</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh may be alluding here to the dragging on of the relationship between the husband and wife in <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="342">Thérèse Raquin</rs>
                        </hi>, who want to leave each other but nevertheless do not do it: ‘And they stayed out of cowardice and dragged wretchedly on in the horror of their existence.’ (Et ils restaient par lâcheté, ils restaient et se traînaient misérablement dans l’horreur de leur existence.) See Zola 1966-1970, vol. 1, p. 653 (chapter 30).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>It is not possible to be sure exactly which painted study of a weaver this is. Nine are known, including the following three from this period: <hi rend="ital">Weaver </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2451">F 26 / JH 450</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Weaver </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2452">F 162 / JH 457</rs>), and <hi rend="ital">Weaver and a spinning wheel</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2462">F 29 / JH 471</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>