<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Saturday, 25 October 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let467"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">467</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">383</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">469</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Saturday, 25 October 1884</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Saturday, 25 October 1884.</p>
</vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b417 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh says that Van Rappard ‘will be staying for another week’ <ref target="#l-6">(ll. 6-7)</ref>. Since it seems that he left on Saturday, 1 November 1884, we have dated the letter on or about Saturday, 25 October 1884. This must therefore be the letter to which Mrs van Gogh was referring in her letter to Theo of Monday, 27 October 1884, when she said that Vincent had written to him recently. (FR b2260)</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0417" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000556_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000556_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000556_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000556_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000556_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0417" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000556_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000556_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000556_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000556_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000556_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000556_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Ziehier een paar kleinere photos naar <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>de studies waar ge reeds de grooteren van hebt<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Ik stuur ze omdat ik wil dat – <hi rend="ital">als</hi> ’t eens <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>voorkomt – ge iets van me kunt laten zien<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Rappard is nog altijd hier en blijft nog wel <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>een week<c type="kk">/</c> daar ’t werk hem buitengewoon vlot<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Hij maakt spinsters en verscheiden studiekoppen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>heeft reeds een stuk of 10 studies gemaakt <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>die ik allen mooi vind<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">We hebben zamen nog al gepraat over het <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>impressionisme – ik <hi rend="ital">geloof</hi> dat gij zijn werk <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>daaronder zoudt rangschikken<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch hier in <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>Holland is het moeielijk er uit wijs te worden <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>wat het impressionisme eigentlijk wil zeggen<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Maar en hem en mij ook interesseert het zeer <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>wat het streven van tegenwoordig is<c type="kp">_</c>– En zeker <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>is het dat er onverwachte nieuwe opvattingen <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>beginnen te komen. Dat schilderijen weer <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>in heel anderen toon beginnen geschilderd te <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>worden dan eenige jaren geleden.</ab>
                <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het laatst wat ik gemaakt heb is een <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>nog al groote studie van een populierenlaan <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>met de geele herfstblaren<c type="kk">/</c> waar de zon <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>hier en daar schitterende plekken maakt <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>op de afgevallen blaren op den grond<c type="kk">/</c> die <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>afgewisseld worden door de lange slagschaduwen <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>der stammen.–<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Aan ’t eind van den weg een boerenhuisje <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>en de blaauwe lucht er boven <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>tusschen de herfstblaren door<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik geloof dat over een jaar – dat <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>jaar doorbrengende ook weer met veel en <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>aanhoudend schilderen – ik van manier <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>van schilderen en van kleur nog veel <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>zal veranderen en dat ik eer nog iets <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>somberder dan lichter zal worden<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>Het werk van Rappard is ook in een veel <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>lagere gamma nog geworden<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">De koppen die hij schildert tegenwoordig <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>herinneren als effekt aan <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>zekere studiekoppen van Courbet b.v.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>Maar ’t wordt verduiveld goed<c type="kk">/</c> dat kan <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>ik U verzekeren.</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">Door een en ander ik besprak met hem <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>kan ’t wel wezen ik liever hier blijf <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>en hier doorwerk dan naar elders <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>ga<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik heb door zijn bezoek weer eens <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>nieuwe idees voor mijn <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>eigen werk gekregen en heb zooveel dingen <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>in mijn hoofd die ik graag maken zou<c type="kk">/</c> dat <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>après tout ik moeielijk kan uitstellen <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>er direkt op door te gaan.</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bovendien wou ik voor Nieuwejaar mijn <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>verfrekeningen in ’t evene brengen en <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>kan het geen extra uitgaven lijden. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Want als ik naar Antwerpen ging zou <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>ik natuurlijk er veel willen werken <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>en zou er modellen voor noodig hebben <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>die ik vrees voor ’t moment te duur zouden <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>uitkomen.</ab>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">Doch in ’t algemeen raad Rappard het <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>mij ook aan om niet nu direkt <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>maar na nog eenige maanden hier <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>geschilderd te hebben het te doen en <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>te trachten er een pied à terre te <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>krijgen om nog naaktstudies te <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>maken.</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Doch als ik eerst nog eens een 30tal <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>koppen hier schilder zal ik meer van <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Antwerpen kunnen profiteeren – en aan <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>die 30 koppen begin ik nu<c type="kk">/</c> of liever <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>ben ik reeds begonnen met een groote <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>buste van een herder.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>
<ab rend="indent">Rappard heeft dezen zomer in <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>Drenthe en op Terschelling datzelfde <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>gedaan en het heeft hem een heel <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>eind doen opschieten<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb pas gezien een reproductie van <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>L’Hermitte – le cabaret – <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>twee werklui en eene vrouw<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> kent gij <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>dat<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dezer dagen hebben R. en ik groote <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>togten gemaakt en huis aan huis bij <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>de menschen binnengegaan – we <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>hebben enorm veel moois gezien<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>juist door de prachtige herfsteffekten<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>En ook nieuwe modellen ontdekt. <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>Misschien zullen er nog wel enkele <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>andere schilders ’t volgend jaar eens in deze <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>streek komen. Ik wou dat wel want <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>men moet niet al te lang aan een <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>stuk zijn <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>zonder eens schilders te zien.</ab>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin – wat dat betreft – ik zal <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>nog wel nieuwe kennissen krijgen <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>eer ’t veel verder is in elk geval<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet, ook van Rappard<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-63" n="63">niet &lt; er niet</note>
<note target="l-89" n="89">zullen &lt; zulen</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Here are a couple of smaller photos of the studies of which you already have the larger ones.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I’m sending them because — <hi rend="ital">should</hi> it ever come to it — I want you to be able to show something of mine. <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> is still here and will be staying for another week since the work is going extraordinarily well. He’s making women spinning and various studies of heads, has already made 10 studies or so, all of which I consider fine.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">We’ve talked together quite a lot about Impressionism — I <hi rend="ital">think</hi> that you would classify his work as that. But here in Holland it’s hard to work out what Impressionism is actually trying to say.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> But both he and I are greatly interested in what the present aim is. And it’s certain that unexpected new ideas are beginning to emerge. That paintings are once again beginning to be painted in very different tone from a few years ago.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The last thing I made is a rather large study of an avenue of poplars with the yellow autumn leaves, where the sun makes glittering patches here and there on the fallen leaves on the ground, which are interspersed with the long shadows cast by the trunks.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">At the end of the road a peasant cottage, and the blue sky above it between the autumn leaves.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think that in a year’s time — having spent that year once again painting a great deal and constantly — I’ll change my manner of painting and my colour a great deal, and that I’m likely to become slightly more sombre rather than lighter. The spectrum of <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>’s work has also become much lower.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The heads that he’s painting at present are reminiscent in their effect of certain studies of heads by <rs type="pers" key="962">Courbet</rs>, say.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> But it’s becoming devilish good, that I can assure you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Because of one thing and another I discussed with him, it may well be that I prefer to stay here and carry on working here rather than go somewhere else. As a result of his visit I’ve again got new ideas for my own work, and have so many things in my head which I’d like to make that, after all, I can’t easily postpone getting on with them right away.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Besides, I want to settle my paint bills before the New Year, and can’t afford any extra expenditure. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> Because if I went to Antwerp I’d obviously want to do a lot of work and would need models for it, which I fear would work out too dear for the moment.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But in general <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> advises me not to do it right away, but after having painted here for another few months, and to try to get a pied-à-terre to make nude studies.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But I’ll be able to benefit more from Antwerp if I first paint another 30 heads here — and I’m starting on those 30 heads now, or rather I’ve already started with a large bust of a shepherd.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> has done the same in Drenthe and on Terschelling this summer, and it has helped him to make a good deal of progress.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve just seen a reproduction of a <rs type="pers" key="1179">Lhermitte</rs> — The inn — two workmen and a woman,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> do you know it? 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The last few days <rs type="pers" key="1306">R.</rs> and I have been on some long excursions, and visited people house by house — we’ve seen lots of beautiful things, just because of the magnificent autumnal effects. And also discovered new models. Perhaps a few other painters might come to this region next year. I wish they would, because one shouldn’t go for too long without ever seeing any painters.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well — as to that — I’ll get new acquaintances before too long in any event.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Regards, from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> too.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>These ‘larger’ photographs are not known. See for the photographs sent prior to this: <ref target="let463.xml">letters 463</ref> and <ref target="let465.xml">465</ref>. Small <hi rend="ital">cartes de visite</hi> of works that were part of the decoration for <rs type="pers" key="449">Hermans</rs> had already been enclosed with <ref target="let466.xml">letter 466</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Little is known of the work that <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> did during his stay in Nuenen. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 90.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Van Gogh – like many of his fellow-countrymen – remained ignorant about Impressionism for a long time: <ref target="let288.xml#n-4">see letter 288, n. 4</ref> and Tempel 1999.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Avenue of poplars in autumn</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2488">F 122 / JH 522</rs>). The work measures 99 x 66 cm.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>It is impossible to tell which of <rs type="pers" key="962">Courbet</rs>’s numerous studies of heads Van Gogh has in mind here. Cf. Pierre Courthion, <hi rend="ital">Tout l’oeuvre peint de Courbet</hi>. Paris 1996.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>See for this ‘large bust’ of a shepherd <ref target="let466.xml#n-4">letter 466, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>A reproduction of a charcoal drawing after <rs type="pers" key="1179">Léon Augustin Lhermitte</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Le cabaret, dit à tort Intérieur de ferme</hi> (The inn, wrongly called Farm interior), 1881 (private collection) was printed as a supplement in <hi rend="ital">La Vie Moderne</hi> 4 (20 May 1882), between pp. 320-321. <rs type="ill" key="211">Ill. 211</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>