<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Wednesday, 22 October 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let466"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">466</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">382</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">468</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Wednesday, 22 October 1884</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Wednesday, 22 October 1884.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Set of decorations for Hermans <ref target="let453.xml">(453)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
</vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b416 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter follows <ref target="let465.xml">letter 465</ref> of 9 October: the photographs of the decorations for Hermans promised in it are sent with the present letter. Van Gogh moreover describes in <ref target="let467.xml">letter 467</ref> the outings he and Van Rappard have been going on together ‘the last few days’ <ref target="#l-83">(ll. 83-84)</ref>, which suggests that it has been several days since Van Rappard’s arrival in mid-October. Furthermore, Van Rappard has so far been able to paint four studies, while by about 25 October he had meanwhile done ‘10 studies or so’ (<ref target="let467.xml">letter 467</ref>). Since Jo van Gogh-Bonger gave the date as 22 October in <hi rend="ital">Brieven</hi> 1914, and she may have had a postmark to go on, we have dated the letter Wednesday, 22 October 1884.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0416" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000555_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000555_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000555_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0416" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000555_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000555_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000555_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000555_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000555_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000555_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Ziehier nog een paar <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>cartes de visite om U een idee <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>te geven van die decoratie voor <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Hermans – waarvan dit twee <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>doeken zijn.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Rappard is hier dezer dagen, en <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>laat U groeten.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Hij heeft een heel <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>mooie studie van een meisjeskop <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>gemaakt en een van een <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>boerenerf<c type="kk">/</c> en twee kleinen <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>van ossekarren<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> En er moeten <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>er nog verscheiden bij komen <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>waar hij plan op heeft.</ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben werkende aan een figuur <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>van een herder met grooten mantel <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>om – die van ’t zelfde formaat is als <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>de spinster.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">En overigens een studie <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>van twee <hi rend="ital">Knotwilgen</hi> met de <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>geele blaren van populieren <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>er achter en een kijkje over <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>de velden.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is buitengemeen <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>mooi hier dezer dagen <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>met de herfsteffekten<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>Over 14 dagen zullen <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>we de echte chûte des feuilles <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>hebben – als al wat aan de <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>boomen zit er in enkele <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>dagen afvalt.</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik met dien herder wat voorspoed <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>heb zal ’t een figuur worden waar <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>iets van het <hi rend="ital">heele oude Brabant</hi> in <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>zal zitten<c type="kp">_</c>– Enfin hij is nog <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>niet klaar en we zullen zien hoe <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>hij wordt<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ge hadt wel eens een woordje <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>kunnen antwoorden op wat ik U laatst <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>schreef – komt me voor – al was ’t alleen wegens ’t uw <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>eigen idees zou wakker maken welligt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>ik voor mij – ondanks veel oud en <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>nieuw verdriet – twijfel hoe langer <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>hoe minder aan mijn toekomst<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>en wat mijn werk en zelfs ook <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>wat mij zelf betreft.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toch weet ik dat in beide opzigten <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>ik veel strijd zal hebben – dat en <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>mijn werk en ik zelf tegenkanting <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>zullen krijgen<c type="kk">/</c> een slechten indruk <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>zullen maken in <hi rend="ital">veel</hi> gevallen <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>doch <hi rend="ital">niet in alle</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">En wat mijn werk betreft<c type="kk">/</c> met den dag <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>meer wordt ik feller er op <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>en krijg ik een opgewektheid terug <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">als was ik 20 jaar</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik moet dan ook doorzetten ik <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>eens naar Antwerpen ga – <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>in der tijd<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> heb ik dikwijls genoeg <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>dingen verkocht die door authoriteiten <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>onverkoopbaar waren verklaard. <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>Als ik in der tijd iets <hi rend="ital">wou</hi> verkoopen <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dan sprong ’t niet altijd af als <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>ik eenmaal het wilde dat iemand <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>dit of dat nemen zou.</ab>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab rend="indent">En misschien hebt gij gelijk dat <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>ik zelf maar voor mijn werk <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>een weg moet zoeken en mijn eigen <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>handelaar worden. Enfin.</ab>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="70*" xml:id="l-70s"/>
<ab>b. à t.</ab>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Here are a couple more <hi rend="ital">cartes de visite</hi> to give you an idea of that decoration for <rs type="pers" key="449">Hermans</rs> — of which these are two canvases.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> is here at the moment and sends you his regards.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> He’s made a very fine study of a girl’s head and one of a farmyard, and two small ones of ox-carts.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> And various others that he’s planning should follow.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m working on a figure of a shepherd wearing a greatcoat — which is the same size as the woman spinning.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And apart from that a study of two <hi rend="ital">Pollard willows</hi> with the yellow leaves of poplars behind them and a view across the fields.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s extraordinarily beautiful here at the moment with the autumnal effects. In a fortnight we’ll have the real fall of the leaves — when everything that’s on the trees falls in a few days.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If I have some luck with the shepherd, it will be a figure that will have something of the <hi rend="ital">very old Brabant</hi> in it. Anyway, it isn’t finished yet, and we’ll see how it turns out.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You could have dropped me a line in reply to what I wrote to you recently — it seems to me — even if it was only because it might shake up your own ideas, perhaps. For my part — despite much old and new sorrow — I have less and less doubt about my future, both as to my work and even as to myself. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">All the same, I know that I’ll have many a struggle in both respects — that both my work and I myself will meet with resistance, will make a bad impression in <hi rend="ital">many</hi> cases, but <hi rend="ital">not in all</hi>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And as to my work, I become keener on it by the day, and I’m regaining my high spirits <hi rend="ital">as if I were 20</hi>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">So I must see to it that I go to Antwerp sometime — often enough in the past<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> I’ve sold things that authorities declared unsaleable. If I <hi rend="ital">wanted</hi> to sell something in the past then it didn’t always fall through if I really wanted someone to take this thing or that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And perhaps you’re right that I should just find a way for my work myself, and become my own dealer. Anyway.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Regards.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The two photographs – which have survived as ‘cartes de visite’ – are of <hi rend="ital">Ploughman and a woman planting potatoes</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2483">F 172 / JH 514</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Shepherd with flock of sheep</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2485">F 42 / JH 517</rs>). See exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 177, cat. nos. 62-63. From the former we can see that shortly after his painting of the ploughman (which is under <hi rend="ital">Cottage with tumbledown barn and a stooping woman</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="3024">F 1669 / JH 825</rs>) (<ref target="let453.xml#n-10">see letter 453, n. 10</ref>) Van Gogh must have decided to do it again and add a female figure.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh’s <rs type="pers" key="524 526">parents</rs> were very pleased to have <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> staying with them to distract Vincent and divert his mind from his proposal to <rs type="pers" key="267">Margot</rs>. On Monday, 27 October 1884 Mr van Gogh wrote to Theo: ‘But there’s no getting away from it because of what Vincent asked Margot our relationship with people changed. They don’t come to see us because they don’t want to meet him, at least our neighbours, and we have to say that they’re right. Now that Rappard is here it is something of a distraction for Vincent’ (FR b2258).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Virtually no works made by <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> during this stay in Nuenen are known. <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="558">Portrait of a girl</rs>
                        </hi> (Rotterdam, Museum Boijmans Van Beuningen) may have been done in Nuenen, but it could equally well have been painted in Drenthe or Terschelling, where Van Rappard was working before he went to Nuenen. See exhib. cat. Amsterdam 1974, p. 90.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
    <ab>Van Gogh mentions two paintings of women spinning: a large one measuring about 100 x 75 cm. (<ref target="let449.xml">see letter 449</ref> ff and <ref target="let463.xml#n-1">463, n. 1</ref>), and a smaller one that he wants to do after Theo has told him the size of a frame (<ref target="let451.xml">letter 451</ref>). That plan may have resulted in the picture that is under <hi rend="ital">The parsonage garden in the snow</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2492">F 194 / JH 603</rs>). <rs type="ill" key="2129">Ill. 2129</rs>. This woman spinning measures 59 x 78 cm.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If Van Gogh is referring to the second of these here, the ‘shepherd’ could be the picture that is under <hi rend="ital">Still life with a brass cauldron and jug</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2527">F 51 / JH 925</rs>), <rs type="ill" key="2130">Ill. 2130</rs>., since the dimensions of this canvas are similar: 65.5 x 80.5 cm. This shepherd is most probably the same as the ‘large bust of a shepherd’ (<ref target="let467.xml#l-73">letter 467, ll. 73-74</ref>). See also exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, p. 172.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>This study of two pollard willows is not known. Although it was previously thought that Van Gogh was talking about <hi rend="ital">two</hi> studies here – the second being ‘a view across the fields’ – the description does in fact refer to a single work. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, pp. 68-69 (n. 4).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>In the 1869-1876 period when Van Gogh was selling art at Goupil’s.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>