<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Monday, 12 and about Thursday, 15 May 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let446"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">446</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">368</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">449</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about Monday, 12 and about Thursday, 15 May 1884</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Monday, 12 and about Thursday, 15 May 1884.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Invitation to Van Rappard to come to Nuenen <ref target="let441.xml">(441)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Mrs van Gogh’s broken leg <ref target="let423.xml">(423)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Aunt Bertha Pompe-Van Gogh had been operated on for breast cancer <ref target="let444.xml">(444)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b402 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The letter must have been written in May, since Theo had written about the Salon, which opened on 1 May <ref target="#l-88">(l. 88)</ref>. Vincent says that he had delayed thanking Theo for his letter and the enclosed money, which he must have received at the beginning of the month. As he explains that he had been busy ‘this last fortnight’ arranging a new studio, and the previous letter was written on 30 April 1884, the present one must date from mid-May. Van Rappard is expected ‘at the end of this week’ <ref target="#l-39">(ll. 39-40)</ref>; he actually arrived on or about 17 May. We have therefore dated the letter between about Monday, 12 and about Thursday, 15 May 1884. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0402" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000530_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000530_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000530_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000530_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000530_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0402" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000530_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000530_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000530_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000530_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000530_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000530_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Reeds te lang heb ik gewacht met het <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>beantwoorden van Uw laatsten brief – &amp; ge zult zien <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>hoe het kwam<c type="kp">_</c>– Laat ik beginnen met te zeg<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>gen dat ik U dank voor Uw schrijven en <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>voor ingesloten f<hi rend="ss">rs</hi> 200.- En dan zal ik <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>U mededeelen dat ik van daag net zoo wat <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>klaar ben met het in orde brengen van een <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>ruim<c type="kk">/</c> nieuw atelier dat ik gehuurd heb. <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Twee kamers – een groote en een kleine – en suite<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Hierdoor zat ik nog al in de drukte deze <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>laatste 14 dagen. Ik geloof ik er heel <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>wat prettiger zal werken kunnen dan in ’t vertrekje <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>t’huis<c type="kp">_</c>– En heb wel hoop gij als ge ’t zien zult <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>den maatregel goed zult keuren dien ik ge<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>nomen heb<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb overigens in den laatsten tijd druk door<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>geschilderd aan den grooten Wever<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> – waarover <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ik U laatst sprak – en ook een doek aangezet <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>van het torentje dat ge kent<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat ge over den Salon<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> schrijft vind ik zeer <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>belangrijk<c type="kp">_</c> Wat ge over <hi rend="ital">Puvis de Chavannes</hi>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> zegt <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>doet me <hi rend="ital">heel veel</hi> pleizier gij zijn werk zòò ziet<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>en in ’t apprecieeren van zijn talent ben ik het <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>volkomen met U eens.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">En wat de coloristen aangaat – het is met mij <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>après tout zoo als met U – ik kan in een Puvis de <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>Chavannes me verdiepen en toch neemt dat niet <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>weg ik voor het landschap met koeijen van Mauve <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>en de schij<hi rend="ss">en</hi> van Israels<c type="kk">/</c> het zelfde zou voelen wat <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>gij er voor voelt<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat mijn eigen kleur aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> ge zult in mijn <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>werk van hier <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> het zilverachtige vinden <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>maar veeleer bruine toonen (Bitume<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> b.v. en Bistre)<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> – die ik niet <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>twijfel of sommigen zouden me kwalijk nemen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Maar ge zult wel zelf zien als ge komt<c type="kk">/</c> wat er van is<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Ik heb zoo druk geschilderd dat in den laatsten tijd <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>ik geen enkele teekening er tusschen door gemaakt <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>heb<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Van Rappard heb ik berigt dat hij einde van deze <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>week komt<c type="kk">/</c> wat me veel pleizier doet<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>Ik heb wel idee hij dit jaar nog eens voor <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>iets langer terug zal komen bovendien<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hij brengt een aantal teekeningen mee van mij<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> die ik U <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>dan direkt zal toe zenden.</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">Misschien zal – <hi rend="ital">over een tijdje</hi> – ik zelf ’t met <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>U eens zijn dat door de verandering van verl. jaar<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>mijn positie is verbeterd en die verandering goed <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>was<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Iets weemoedigs zal het echter mij altijd blijven <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>dat ik toen iets heb moeten opgeven wat ik <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>toen nog wel verder had willen <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>doorvoeren<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het gaat m.i. met Moe heel goed – zij is <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>gisteren in mijn nieuw atelier <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>geweest in haar wagentje<c type="kp">_</c> Het loopen komt <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>bij<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> doch den ouden dag contrarieert aanmerkelijk <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>de vorderingen er in<c type="kk">/</c> die nu wel geregeld <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>voortgaan doch evenwel niet zoo spoedig als men wel <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>zou denken ’t geval kon zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb het in den laatsten tijd hier gezelliger <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>gehad met de menschen hier dan in het begin<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>wat mij veel waard is want men heeft er <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>zoo bepaald behoefte aan zich eens wat <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>afleiding te kunnen geven<c type="kk">/</c> en waar men <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>te zeer eenzaam zich voelt lijdt het werk <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>er altijd door<c type="kp">_</c>– Men moet er zich echter misschien <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>op prepareeren die dingen niet altijd blijven<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar ik heb er toch goeden moed in – het komt mij <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>voor dat de menschen te Nunen in ’t algemeen beter zijn dan die te <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>Etten of Helvoirt – er is meer sinceriteit hier – <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>althans dat is mijn impressie nu ik er een tijd ben geweest. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>De lui gaan wel uit van een dominésstandpunt in hun <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>doen en laten – dat wel – maar zóó dat ik voor mij <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>geen scrupule heb mij daarnaar een beetje te schikken<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>En het Brabant dat men <hi rend="ital">gedroomd</hi> heeft<c type="kk">/</c> daar <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>komt de werkelijkheid soms al heel digt bij.</ab>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mijn oorspronkelijk plan van in Brabant me te <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>vestigen – dat in duigen viel – ik moet bekennen <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>dat het mij weer op nieuw sterk aantrekt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Doch wetende hoe zoo iets ineen kan storten<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>moeten we zien of het al dan niet illusie <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>zou zijn. Enfin voorloopig heb ik genoeg <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>te doen. Ik heb nu weer de ruimte om <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>met model te kunnen werken.</ab>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab rend="indent">En betreffende hoe lang het duren zal<c type="kk">/</c> er <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>is geen peil op te trekken.</ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu gegroet – de salon zal U zeker wel <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>veel te doen geven maar tevens toch ook <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>een interessanten tijd zijn.</ab>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nogmaals dank voor het gezondene dat <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>trouwens door deze verandering mij ook wel noodig <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>was. Ik hoop dat gij er U mee zult kunnen <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>vereenigen als ge ziet hoe ik het heb ingerigt<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">à dieu<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
<ab>Groeten van allen t’huis en <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>zij vragen of ge hun niet eens schrijft<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>Pa is te Breda geweest<c type="kk">/</c> met Tante Bertha ging het goed <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>en ’t verband was er afgenomen.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-29" n="29">schij<hi rend="ss">en</hi> van &lt; schij<hi rend="ss">en</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-72" n="72">dominésstandpunt &lt; dominés standpunt</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I’ve already left it too long before answering your last letter — and you’ll see how it came about. Let me start by saying that I thank you for your letter and for the enclosed 200 francs. And then I’ll tell you that today I’ve just about finished arranging a spacious new studio I’ve rented. Two rooms — one large and one small — en suite.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I’ve been rather busy because of it this last fortnight. I believe I’ll be able to work a good deal more pleasantly there than in the little room at home. And hope that you’ll approve the step I’ve taken when you’ve seen it.</ab>
    <ab rend="indent">By the way, of late I’ve continued working hard on the large Weaver<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> — which I mentioned to you recently — and also started a canvas of the little tower you know.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think what you write about the Salon<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> is very important. What you say about <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>
                    </hi>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> gives me <hi rend="ital">very great</hi> pleasure that you see his work thus, and I’m in complete agreement with you in appreciating his talent. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And as regards the colourists — it’s after all the same with me as with you — I can immerse myself in a <rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>, and yet that doesn’t alter the fact that I should feel the same for <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>’s landscape with cows and Israëls’s paintings as you feel for them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards my own colour, in the work I’m doing here you’ll find <hi rend="ital">not</hi> silvery but rather brown tones (Bitumen,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> for instance, and Bistre)<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> — which I don’t doubt some people would take amiss of me. But you’ll see for yourself what it’s like when you come. I’ve been so busy painting that recently I haven’t made a single drawing between times.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve heard from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs> that he’s coming at the end of this week, which pleases me greatly. What’s more, I have the idea that this year he’ll come back again for a little longer.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He’s bringing a number of drawings of mine,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> which I’ll then send you right away.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Perhaps — <hi rend="ital">in a while</hi> — I’ll agree with you that my position has improved because of the change last year,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> and that that change was good. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It will always be a sadness to me, though, that I had to give something up then that I’d have liked to pursue further at the time.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="524">Ma</rs> is doing very well, in my view — yesterday she came to my new studio in her bath chair. Walking is getting better, although old age considerably frustrates her progress, which continues regularly now, although not as fast as one might think could be the case.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve recently been getting on better with the people here than at the outset, which is worth a great deal to me, for one has a definite need to be able to give oneself a little distraction, and when one feels too lonely the work always suffers in consequence. One must, however, perhaps prepare oneself that these things won’t last for ever.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But I’m in good heart — it seems to me that the people in Nuenen are generally better than those in Etten or Helvoirt — there’s more sincerity here — at least that’s my impression now that I’ve been here a while. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> People do take a sanctimonious position in what they do — that’s true — but in such a way that for my part I have no scruples about going along with it a bit. And reality sometimes comes very close to the Brabant that one has <hi rend="ital">dreamt</hi>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">My original plan of settling in Brabant — which fell to pieces — I must confess is attracting me strongly again. Yet knowing how something like that can collapse, we have to see whether or not it would be an illusion. Anyway, I have enough to do for the time being. I now have the space again to be able to work with a model.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And as to how long it will last, there’s no telling.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, regards — the Salon will certainly give you plenty to do, but at the same time also be an interesting time.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Thanks again for what you sent, which I really needed because of this change, by the way. I hope you’ll be able to agree with it when you see how I’ve fitted it out.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Adieu, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Regards from everyone at home, and they ask whether you won’t write to them sometime. <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> has been to Breda; <rs type="pers" key="502">Aunt Bertha</rs> was doing well and the dressing had been taken off.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Van Gogh had been given the mangle room in a small shed behind the house to use as a studio. He complained about the inadequacy of this space in <ref target="let440.xml">letter 440</ref>. He rented his new studio from the Catholic sacristan <rs type="pers" key="667">Johannes Schafrat</rs> and his wife <rs type="pers" key="668">Adriana Schafrat-Van Eerd</rs> in their house at Heieind (district F, no. 540), next door to St Clement’s Church. A year later Van Gogh went to live there (<ref target="let501.xml">see letter 501</ref>). The rent was 75 guilders a year. <rs type="pers" key="475">Anton Kerssemakers</rs> drew a floor plan of this studio in 1914 (FR b1423). <rs type="ill" key="2121">Ill. 2121</rs>. Schafrat’s widow can be seen in a photograph of the corner of the attic in the sacristan’s house where Van Gogh slept. See Stokvis 1926, p. 17. It has been suggested that Van Gogh had meanwhile had another studio behind the parsonage, but nothing has been found that might substantiate this. See De Brouwer 1984, pp. 38-41 and cat. Amsterdam 1997, pp. 13-18.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Probably <hi rend="ital">Weaver</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2467">F 30 / JH 479</rs>), which Van Gogh had referred to in <ref target="let445.xml">letter 445</ref> and was later to have photographed; <ref target="let463.xml">see letters 463</ref> and <ref target="let465.xml">465</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
                    <ab>The version of the Nuenen tower Van Gogh refers to here must have been a smaller study than the one about which he wrote in <ref target="let452.xml">letter 452</ref>: ‘have also been working again on the old tower in the fields in the evening; I’ve made a larger study of it than my previous ones — with the wheatfields around it’ (<ref target="let452.xml#l-13">ll. 13-17</ref>). The one in the present letter was therefore probably <hi rend="ital">The old tower at dusk</hi>, which has wheatfields (<rs type="ill" key="2477">F 40 / JH 507</rs>) and measures 35 x 47 cm. The ‘larger study’ must be <hi rend="ital">The old tower</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2471">F 88 / JH 490</rs>), which measures 47.5 x 55 cm.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
        <ab>The Paris Salon, which opened on 1 May.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
        <ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1286">Pierre Puvis de Chavannes</rs> exhibited <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="323">Le bois sacré</rs>
                        </hi> (The sacred grove): <ref target="let483.xml#n-2">see letter 483, n. 2.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
    <note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
        <ab>A dark brown pigment prepared from asphalt, resin and linseed oil.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
        <ab>A brown pigment prepared from common soot.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
        <ab>See for the twelve drawings by Van Gogh that <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> had at this time: <ref target="let441.xml#n-6">letter 441, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>This remark must refer to Van Gogh’s departure from The Hague and the parting of the ways with <rs type="pers" key="463">Sien</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘wordt beter’ (coming along, getting better).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>