<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Sunday, 6 and about Sunday, 13 January 1884. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let420"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">420</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">361</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">437</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about Sunday, 6 and about Sunday, 13 January 1884</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, between about Sunday, 6 and about Sunday, 13 January 1884. </p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b394 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>In <hi rend="ital">De brieven</hi> 1990 this letter was dated on or about 11 March 1884. However, it fits more logically at the beginning of the year – Van Gogh looks back on the previous year <ref target="#l-58">(l. 58)</ref>. In any event it was certainly written before March, as is clear from <ref target="#l-51">ll. 51-52</ref>: ‘I would wish it to remain the usual until March’. It precedes <ref target="let422.xml">letter 422</ref>, which dates from about 15 January 1884. In that letter Van Gogh wrote about how things should proceed in terms of Theo’s financial contributions, and what changes might possibly take place in that regard from March onwards. The use of the notion of ‘disorder’ in <ref target="let420.xml#l-46">letter 420 (l. 46)</ref> and ‘disorderliness’ in <ref target="let422.xml#l-10">letter 422 (l. 10)</ref> is a further indication that the two letters were written at around the same time. Since Van Gogh is somewhat less fierce in <ref target="let422.xml">letter 422</ref> and promises to send watercolours, we think that the present letter preceded that one. This means that it then follows <ref target="let419.xml">letter 419</ref> of around 4 January, and this is in line with what it says at the beginning of the letter: Van Gogh now writes in a calm tone (while he says that he was rather rash in the previous letter). It is not possible to say for certain whether there was yet another letter at the beginning of January or whether that was <ref target="let419.xml">letter 419</ref>, which crossed Theo’s in the post. For all these reasons we believe that <ref target="let420.xml">letter 420</ref> dates from between about Sunday, 6 and about Sunday, 13 January 1884. See also Dorn in exhib. cat. Vienna 1996, pp. 154 (n. 1), 162 (nn. 2-3).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0394" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000517_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000517_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000517_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000517_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000517_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0394" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000517_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000517_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000517_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000517_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000517_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000517_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Uw brief ontvang ik daareven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Misschien doordat Uw brief kruistte een <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>schrijven van mij in denzelfden toon als hetgeen <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>heden door U wordt beantwoord<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> zult gij <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>zien dat ik hier spreek in eene andere <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>stemming dan de overijling door U <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>verondersteld<c type="kp">_</c>– Juist omdat ik bedaard <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>zeg wat ik zeg<c type="kk">/</c> al zij het niet den toon welken <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>zoo dagelijks wordt gebezigd (hier is het een ernstige zaak)<c type="kk">/</c> kan ik geen <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>gebruik maken van Uw welwillendheid om <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>het als “in haast” gesproken te beschouwen<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>Juist <hi rend="ital">die</hi> opvatting van U (dat ik in haast en <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>zonder nadenken zou gesproken hebben) is mij <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>bewijs genoeg wij hier staan op een <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>punt waar meer woorden ons niet verder <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>zouden brengen en vind ik het goed we deze <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>kwestie laten rusten.</ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zegt gij <hi rend="ital">moet</hi> komen op het finantieele. <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>Ik ook.</ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Broer<c type="kk">/</c> weet ik herhaal wat ik vroeger zeide, <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zonder verandering, betreffende dat gij mij nobel <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>hebt geholpen – en dat:</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab>money <hi rend="ital">can</hi> be repaid<c type="kk">/</c> but not kindness such as yours<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab>Maar – ziehier wat ik wil en wat gij in <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>mij billijken zult dat ik wil.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik moet een maatregel nemen zóó dat <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>ik hebbe wat ik heb.</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik bedoel dat ik slechts <hi rend="ital">dat</hi> geld accepteeren <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>kan ’t welk<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-o-b"/> ik zonder iemands opinie <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>te behoeven te vragen mede doen kan wat <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>ik goedvind<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb liever frs 100 per maand er <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>vrij mee zijnde<c type="kk">/</c> dan frs 200 er niet geheel <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>vrij mee zijnde<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>
<ab rend="indent">Indien in zienswijs wij het meer eens <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>waren zoo zoude ik een accoord als het <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>tot heden tusschen U en mij afgesprokene <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>verreweg ’t beste achten.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar bij te veel verschil van zienswijs<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>bij te weinig elkaar begrijpen is een <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>accoord als het tusschen U en mij afgesprokene <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>niet bestaanbaar of verstandig<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>Veronderstellende dat après tout en Uw <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>en mijn karakter vermijden willen <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>wanorde of eclats<c type="kk">/</c> zoo zullen wij het <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>breken stil en bedaard – maar beslist <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>zóó dat noch op U noch op mij aanmerking <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>van dwaasheid of overijling kan worden <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>gemaakt.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zoude wenschen tot Maart het <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>bleef bij ’t gewone<c type="kp">_</c>– Dat zal <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>mij in staat stellen alles te betalen wat <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>ik te betalen heb en van nog een en ander <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>mij wat te voorzien van benoodigdheden. <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>Eerste maatregel van orde die moet <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>behartigd worden.</ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het laatste jaar<c type="kk">/</c> n.l. 83<c type="kk">/</c> was een hard<c type="kk">/</c> triest <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>jaar voor mij en vooral ook ’t einde triest<c type="kk">/</c> bitter &amp; bitter. <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>Goed<c type="kk">/</c> daar komen we niet op terug<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Na Maart zijn wij van weerskanten <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>vrij. Doch indien voor een tijd <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>nog gij aan Pa eenige <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>tegemoetkoming kondt geven <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>wegens ik niet te zeer tot last wil zijn<c type="kk">/</c> zoo <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>is dit wijs en goed m.i. Doch dit zij dan <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>tusschen Pa en U<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zal dan desnoods er iets bij <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>gaan doen<c type="kp">_</c> Wat<c type="kk">/</c> kan me niet eens veel <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>schelen<c type="kk">/</c> alleen <hi rend="sc">niet</hi> met U in een zelfden <hi rend="sc">handel</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> Alleen weet het wel dat <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>ik het beslist meen<c type="kk">/</c> staande tegenover <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>de daadzaak dat wij blijkbaar verder <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>voortgaande het niet genoegzaam eens zouden kunnen <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>blijven<c type="kk">/</c> ik er op werken zal van U geen 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>gunsten in den vorm van geld meer te <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>accepteeren<c type="kk">/</c> waar die in mijn levensopvatting <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>mij niet geheel vrij laten kunnen.</ab>
                <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij zult zeggen gij laat <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>mij vrij – ja maar er is toch een <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>zekere gêne<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">En liever heb ik <hi rend="ital">minder</hi> bij een ander <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">als ik in dingen die niemand anders</hi> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">raken dan mij persoonlijk alleen</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">après tout niet vrij ben</hi>.</ab>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij moet hier niet in zien dat ik <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>met U niet meer te doen wil hebben<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>het tegendeel is waar – gij zijt <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>handelaar<c type="kp">_</c> goed<c type="kk">/</c> als ik iets verkoopbaars <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>maak in uw oog zoo wil ik het zelfs <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>liever aan U dan aan een ander verkoopen <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>doch het moet eene schikking zijn zóó <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>dat mijn positie er niet scheef door <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>wordt. dus een verkoopen wil ik wel degelijk in den letterlijken zin<c type="kp">_</c> Gij kunt ook dit opvatten <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>net precies zoo als ge wilt<c type="kk">/</c> ik geloof <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>dat wat ik zeg verstaanbaar is.</ab>
                <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik dank U voor Uw schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> ik apprecieer <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>er veel dingen in. Gegroet en geloof me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab>b. à v.</ab>
                <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-10" n="10">zaak) &lt; zaak</note>
<note target="l-42" n="42">afgesprokene &lt; afgesproken  <hi rend="ital">Compare l. 38.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-51" n="51">ik het &lt; het</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I just received your letter. Perhaps because your letter crossed a missive of mine in the same tone as the one you replied to today, you’ll see that I’m speaking here in a mood other than the rashness you assume. Precisely because I calmly say what I say, albeit not in the tone that’s used every day (this is a serious matter), I can’t avail myself of your generosity in regarding it as having been spoken ‘in haste’. It is <hi rend="ital">this</hi> very view of yours (that I must have spoken in haste and without reflection) that is proof enough for me that we’re now at a point where more words wouldn’t get us any further, and I think it right that we let this matter rest.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You say you <hi rend="ital">have</hi> to speak about the finances. So do I.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Brother, know that I repeat what I said before, without change, about how you have helped me nobly — and that:</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>money <hi rend="ital">can</hi> be repaid, but not kindness such as yours.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>But — this is what I want, and what you would approve of my wanting. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I must take measures such that I have what I have.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I mean that I can only accept <hi rend="ital">that</hi> money that I can do with as I see fit without having to ask anyone’s opinion.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I would rather have 100 francs a month and free use of it, than 200 francs and not entirely free use of it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If we were more of one mind in our views, I would consider an arrangement like the one agreed between you and me up till now to be far and away the best.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But where there’s too much difference in views, where there’s too little understanding each other, an arrangement such as the one agreed between you and me isn’t viable or wise. Supposing that, after all, both your character and mine want to avoid disorder or commotions, then we’ll break it off quietly and calmly — but definitely in such a way that neither you nor I can be criticized for folly or rashness. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I would wish it to remain the usual until March. That will enable me to pay everything I have to pay, and to provide myself with a few things by way of materials. First order of business that has to be dealt with.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The last year, namely ’83, was a hard, sad year for me, and the end particularly sad, bitter and bitter. Well, we won’t refer to that again. After March we are free on both sides. But if you could still give <rs type="pers" key="526">Pa</rs> some contribution for a while, because I don’t want to be too much of a burden, that would be wise and good in my view. But this must be between Pa and you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Then, if necessary, I’ll find something to do on the side. I don’t much care what, only <hi rend="sc">not</hi> with you in the same <hi rend="sc">trade</hi>. Only be aware that I definitely mean it, facing the fact that we evidently couldn’t remain sufficiently in agreement were we to go on any further, I’ll try not to 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> accept any more favours in the form of money from you, since they can’t leave me completely free in my approach to life.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll say that you leave me free — yes, but there’s still a certain awkwardness.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And I would rather have <hi rend="ital">less</hi> from someone else,<hi rend="ital"> if I am not, after all, free in things that touch no one other than me personally</hi>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You mustn’t take this to mean that I want nothing to do with you any more, the opposite is true — you’re a dealer. Very well, if I make something saleable in your view, I would even rather sell it to you than to someone else, but it must be an arrangement such that my position doesn’t become false as a result, so I really do want a sale in the literal sense. You can take this, too, just exactly as you like, I think that what I say is understandable.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I thank you for your letter, I appreciate many things in it. Regards, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read. ‘geschreven’ (written).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This was not the first time Van Gogh had quoted this line, originally from <rs type="pers" key="215">Tennyson</rs>: <ref target="let413.xml#n-4">see letter 413, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-o-b">
<ab>Read: ‘waar’ (with which).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Since June 1882 the agreement had been that Vincent would receive a fixed sum of 50 francs from Theo three times a month and that he would keep his brother up to date with his progress by sending him works that he had done. Theo was free to keep what he wished; Vincent believed that he was entitled to them (cf. <ref target="let265.xml">letter 265</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>