<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Anton Kerssemakers. Nuenen, between Thursday, 1 and about Thursday, 8 January 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let478"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">478</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">-</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">481</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Anton Kerssemakers</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between Thursday, 1 and about Thursday, 8 January 1885</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Anton Kerssemakers. Nuenen, between Thursday, 1 and about Thursday, 8 January 1885.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b878 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh writes ‘at the start of 85’ <ref target="#l-88">(l. 88)</ref> and he sends Kerssemakers his best wishes for the New Year; he also announces that he will be back in Eindhoven ‘on Sunday’ <ref target="#l-60">(l. 60)</ref>. We therefore assume that the letter was written before one of the first Sundays in 1885: Sunday, 4 or Sunday, 11 January. We have consequently dated the letter between Thursday, 1 and about Thursday, 8 January 1885.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0878" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001172_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001172_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001172_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001172_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001172_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0878" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001172_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001172_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001172_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001172_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001172_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001172_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mijnheer,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Met genoegen heb ik Uwe nieuwe <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>stillevens gezien<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> vooral dat met een keulschen pot en <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>flesch augurken<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> En die twee vorigen zijn er <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ook door verandering aan ’t fonds<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> beter op geworden. <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Evenwel – in ’t algemeen zijn toch ook bij deze <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>wederom de schaduwpartijen mijns inziens nog <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>niet pittig van kleur genoeg. Met een woord <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>wilde ik U zeggen dat ik het er op zal trachten <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>te schikken 3 dagen achtereen bij U te <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>komen schilderen – als U zulks goedvindt. <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>We kunnen zoodoende die kwestie eens <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>goed beetnemen. Want anders zou ik <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>vreezen dat onwillekeurig U telkens weder tot <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>de zelfde resultaten zoudt komen. Ik zeg <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>daarom<c type="kk">/</c> laat ons er een dag of 3 aan <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>wijden<c type="kk">/</c> omdat de kwestie van clair obscur <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>en kleur en diepen toon in de schaduw een eeuwig moeielijke <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>kwestie is<c type="kp">_</c>– En ’t beter of minder goed <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>geschilderd zijn eener studie – de artistieke <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>waarde er van – juist voor een zeer <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>aanmerkelijk deel afhangt van de behandeling <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>der schaduwpartijen.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Ik zal U zeggen <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>wat ik gevoel bij ’t bekijken uwer studies <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>zoo als ze nu zijn.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben er spoedig op uitgekeken <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>en ik zou wenschen juist de schaduw<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>partijen mijn oog langer trokken. <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>Mysterieuser waren<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dit moet U niet verwonderen – en U moet <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>het mij niet kwalijk nemen als ik er telkens <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>over spreek – onder ons<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Om ’t clair obscur goed te krijgen moet <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>men niet alleen veel schilderen doch ook <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>wel degelijk veel zien schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> en sommige <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>dingen van theorie<c type="kk">/</c> van licht en kleur <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>weten. Ik maak me sterk dat als <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>we nog eens goed zamen geschilderd hebben<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>U zelf zult inzien dat op ’t oogenblik <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>nog dingen door U worden over ’t hoofd <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>gezien die als U eenmaal er oog op krijgt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zullen maken het schilderen U <hi rend="ital">nog veel</hi> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">meer</hi> zal interesseeren. Enfin – er <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>zal nog meer <hi rend="ital">ziel</hi> in komen<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu spijt het me betrekkelijk dat ik zoo gebonden <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>ben aan mijn modellen hier – ik kan niet <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>zoo makkelijk weg als dit najaar<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">s’Winters kan ik personen te poseeren krijgen <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>die ik niet<c type="kk">/</c> of althans bezwaarlijker kan krijgen als zij buiten werk <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>hebben op ’t veld<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik werk overigens met almagtig veel <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>pleizier dezer dagen want ik schilder veel <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>liever figuur dan iets anders.– dan – <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>die vrouwenkoppen van hier met de witte <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>mutsen – het is moeielijk – maar het <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>is zoo eeuwig mooi<c type="kp">_</c>– Juist van clair <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>obscur – het wit en een gedeelte van ’t <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>gezigt in de schaduw is zoo fijn van toon.</ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik weet niet precies wanneer ik er een dag of <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>drie zal kunnen uitbreken doch zal U een <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>briefkaart sturen zoodra ik kan. Zondag <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>kom ik overigens ook nog even aan en <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>zou dan wel een meter van dat doek van <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>Bayens<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> willen mede nemen<c type="kk">/</c> daar mijn doek op is.</ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik voorzie wel echter dat juist hoe beter ’t U <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>gaat en hoe meer U vordert met ’t schilderen<c type="kk">/</c> hoe <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>minder pleizier U er misschien van wege zekere <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>Eindhovenaars voor zult ondervinden. Doch tevens <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>naar ’t me voorkomt weegt <hi rend="ital">het pleizier van</hi> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">iets te kunnen maken</hi> ruimschoots op tegen <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>zekere hatelijke critiek. Overigens hoe <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>meer men schildert hoe minder men tijd en lust <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>heeft er naar te luisteren<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoop Zondag a.s. U een portefeuille <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>houtgravuren te brengen waarbij U wel <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>dingen zult vinden die U zullen interesseeren<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
<ab rend="indent">Onder ons gezegd – dat stilleven dat U geencadreerd <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>heeft maakt op mij den indruk onjuister van <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>teekening te moeten wezen dan de meeste anderen. <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>In dit opzigt dat ik durf veronderstellen U verzuimd <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>heeft de proportie van de breedte der groep in <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>zijn geheel voldoende te vergelijken bij de hoogte<c type="kk">/</c> en <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>gevolgelijk de verhouding der voorwerpen onderling <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>laat nog al te wenschen over. Het <hi rend="ital">meten</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> daar hangt <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>zoo enorm veel van af en als U er dadelijk op let <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>in ’t begin<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="ital">wint U veel tijd uit</hi> tegen <hi rend="ital">later</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> als <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>de moeielijker motieven – b.v. een kop – te maken <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>zullen wezen.</ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik schrijf U eens om U in ’t begin van 85 te <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>verzekeren dat het niet uit onverschilligheid is ik <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>dezer dagen niet zooveel ben gekomen, doch dat <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>integendeel ik ’t er voor houd dat als U ’t heele jaar 85 <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>zoo doorwerkt<c type="kk">/</c> U in één jaar meer zult vorderen <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>dan menig ander in 3 jaar. Dus met mijn <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>beste wenschen voor 85 – met de meeste <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>achting</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="95*" xml:id="l-95s"/>
<ab>Uw dr.</ab>
                <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear Sir,</ab>
<ab>I looked at your new still lifes with pleasure,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> particularly the one with a Cologne pot and jar of gherkins.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> And those two previous ones have also been improved by change to the background. However — nonetheless, in general, in these ones too, the colour in the shaded passages is again still not lively enough, in my view. I wanted to drop you a line to tell you that I’ll try to arrange matters so that I can come and paint with you for 3 days in a row — if you approve. That means we can really tackle this question. Because otherwise I fear that you wouldn’t be able to help getting the same results again every time. So I say, let’s devote 3 days or so to it, because the question of chiaroscuro and colour and deep tone in the shadow is an eternally difficult question. And whether or not a study is painted better or less well — its artistic value — depends to a very considerable extent on the treatment of the shaded passages.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> I’ll tell you what I feel when looking at your studies as they are now. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve soon seen enough, and I’d wish that the shaded passages in particular drew my eye for longer. Were more mysterious.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">This shouldn’t surprise you — and you mustn’t take it amiss of me if I repeatedly speak of it — between ourselves.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In order to get the chiaroscuro right, one must not only paint a lot but also really see a great deal being painted, and know some things about theory, about light and colour. I’m sure that once we’ve really painted together again you’ll see for yourself that at the moment you’re still overlooking things which, once you learn to see them, will mean that painting will interest you <hi rend="ital">much more even</hi>. In short — there will be even more <hi rend="ital">soul</hi> in it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, what I regret about this is that I’m so tied to my models here — I can’t get away as easily as I could in the autumn.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the winter I can get people to pose whom I can’t get when they have work out in the fields, or only with more difficulty. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Anyway, I’m working with almighty pleasure these days, for I would much rather paint figures than anything else. Then — the heads of these women here with the white caps — it’s difficult — but it’s so eternally beautiful. It’s precisely the chiaroscuro — the white and the part of the face in shadow, that has such a fine tone.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t know exactly when I’ll be able to get away for three days or so, but I’ll send you a postcard as soon as I can. I’m coming over for a while on Sunday anyway, and would like to take a metre of that canvas from <rs type="pers" key="260">Baijens</rs>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> with me, since my canvas is used up.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I do foresee, though, that the better you do and the more you progress with your painting, the less pleasure you may experience from it because of certain Eindhoven folk. But at the same time it seems to me that <hi rend="ital">the pleasure of being able to make something</hi> amply outweighs certain spiteful criticism. Anyway, the more one paints, the less time and inclination one has to listen to it. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Next Sunday I hope to bring you a portfolio of wood engravings in which you’ll find things that will interest you.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent"> Between ourselves — that still life which you framed makes an impression on me of being less correct in the drawing than most of the others. In this respect, that I dare suppose that you neglected sufficiently to compare the proportion of the width of the group as a whole with the height, and consequently the relationship between the objects leaves something to be desired. <hi rend="ital">Measuring</hi>, that’s what such a tremendous amount depends on, and if you really pay attention to it at the outset, <hi rend="ital">you’ll save a lot of time</hi> <hi rend="ital">later</hi>, when there will be the more difficult subjects — such as a head — to make.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I write this to you to assure you, at the start of 85, that it’s not out of indifference that I haven’t come so much recently, but that on the contrary I consider that if you keep working like this for the whole of the year 85, you’ll make more progress in one year than many others in 3 years. So with my best wishes for 85 — yours respectfully</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your servant</ab>
<ab>Vincent </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Van Gogh had started painting still lifes in Eindhoven with <rs type="pers" key="475">Kerssemakers</rs> and others in November 1884: <ref target="let469.xml">see letter 469</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>This still life by <rs type="pers" key="475">Kerssemakers</rs> is not known. Kerssemakers later recalled his dealings with Van Gogh: ‘He used to come to Eindhoven on Sunday mornings, and if he didn’t find me at home he would go to the Harmonie where we had a crowded drinking table between 12 and 2. When the company saw him come in with his hairy Ulster and rough cap, there was stifled laughter, and they said to me: off you go, Toon, there’s your friend. Then of course I abandoned the company and went to sit with him, or we went to my house together.’ Letter from Anton Kerssemakers to Albert Plasschaert, Eindhoven, 27 August 1912 (FR b3038).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘fond’ (ground).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>After reading <rs type="pers" key="546">Blanc</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="403">Les artistes de mon temps</rs>
                        </hi> Van Gogh sought to conquer the rendering of <hi rend="ital">chiaroscuro</hi> and turned to such deep colours as dark blue, dark green and dark brown. See cat. Amsterdam 1999, p. 80.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="260">Wed. J.L. Baijens &amp; Zonen</rs>, a shop selling artists’ supplies, glass, pewter ware, floor covering etc., at number 302 (now 18) Rechtestraat, district C, in Eindhoven.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>