<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 16 September 1884.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let457"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">457</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">376</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">459</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Tuesday, 16 September 1884</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Tuesday, 16 September 1884.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Margot Begemann is in Utrecht <ref target="let456.xml">(456)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b410 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh drops Theo ‘another line about it’ in which he explains his thoughts on Margot Begemann’s condition more clearly. The present letter is consequently a direct continuation of <ref target="let456.xml">letter 456</ref> and must have been written on the same day as that one or shortly thereafter. Hence the dating of on or about Tuesday, 16 September 1884.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0410" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000539_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000539_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000539_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000539_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000539_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0410" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000539_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000539_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000539_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000539_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000539_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000539_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>ik schrijf U er nog een woordje <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>over heen, om U te zeggen dat ik wel hoop <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>heb de patient er boven op komt – ofschoon <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>ik wel voorzie de gevolgen in den vorm <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>van zenuwlijden en serieus en langdurig <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>kunnen blijken. Veel – heel veel, hangt <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>hier af van omstanders en familie – die <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>eigentlijk geen beter dienst kunnen <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>bewijzen dan haar vriendelijk te behandelen <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>als ware er niets gebeurd<c type="kk">/</c> of als ze dat niet kunnen <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>maar te zwijgen. Ik heb van daag van haar <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>zelf uitvoerige berigten gehad en haar broer<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>vertelt mij hij ook berigt heeft gehad<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er zijn hier gevaren van <hi rend="ital">twee</hi> kanten <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>Theo – aan den eenen kant dat een crisis <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>van zenuwlijden zich vormt en losbarst als <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>b.v. zenuwzinkingkoorts of hersenontsteking. <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Van den anderen kant bestaat er een gevaar <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>voor melancolia of mania religiosa<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>Nu echter<c type="kk">/</c> wegens de patiente direkt behandeld <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>is geworden bij ’t eerste verschijnsel<c type="kk">/</c> wijl <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>verder zij in een milieu is on ne peut <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>plus geschikt voor iemand<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-o-b"/> in haar toestand tot zich zelf te brengen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>als logee – in ’t privé – bij een dokter <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>die zij reeds van lang kent, hem en zijne <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>vrouw – om deze redenen is er hoop 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>
                    <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>dat een crisis in een of anderen vorm <hi rend="ital">kan</hi> worden gecoupeerd <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>of afgeleid of geneutraliseerd door tijdige <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>oppositie – dat het met een sisser <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>afloopt<c type="kk">/</c> een sisser in den vorm <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>van een tijdlang onder die behandeling <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>blijven en dan weer gecalmeerd in <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>haar gewone doen terug keeren.</ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat dit mij sterk agiteert evenwel, die heele <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>geschiedenis, zult gij begrijpen als ik U zeg <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>hoe juist in dien brief dien ik heden ontving <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>ze zegt “dat niemand van haar familie haar <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>eigentlijken gemoedsstrijd begrijpt<c type="kk">/</c> dat zij <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>probeert om zich af te leiden maar dat <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>zij niet goed kan en meestentijds stil <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>in haar kamer zit met een boek of een <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>of ander dat ze van mij heeft gekregen”<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik weet waarachtig niet hoe met de familie <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>B. te doen – die waren eerst zeer <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>onaardig tegen haar – en zelfs <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>op den dag van haar vertrek lang niet allen <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>lief of zelfs alleen maar goed – ofschoon ze ’t eigentlijke niet eens wisten<c type="kp">_</c> Ik heb toen <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>door intermediair van haar broer hare <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>zusters<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> doen weten dat ik <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>bepaald hun den raad moest geven hunne 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>zuster <hi rend="ital">satisfactie te geven voor ongegrond</hi> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">wantrouwen en zekere ongegronde verdenkingen</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">welke te uiten primo voorbarig</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c>
                    <hi rend="ital"> tweedens</hi> <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">de plank mis</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c>
                    <hi rend="ital"> derdens nagels aan de doodkist</hi> <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">der patiente waren</hi>.– Dit heeft in <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>zooverre gewerkt dat hare zusters in <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>de laatste<c type="kk">/</c> hare schoonzuster<c type="kk">/</c> de vrouw van <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>Louis<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> in de eerste plaats<c type="kk">/</c> een schrijven gestuurd <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>hebben aan de patiente<c type="kk">/</c> dat van toon heel wat sympathieker <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>en heel wat zachter en beter was dan hunne <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>eerste uiting. Louis B. zelf<c type="kk">/</c> die de eenige <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>der familie is die het naadje van de kous van het gif <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>weet – ofschoon anderen soupçonneeren – <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>doch juist tegengesproken worden door mij en <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>door Louis – die iets meer weten – Louis B<c type="kp">_</c> zelf <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>heeft van ’t begin af aan praktisch flink <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>en jegens haar sympathiek gehandeld. <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>U aangaande<c type="kk">/</c> als ooit iemand van wie soupçonneeren later <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>U zou uithooren of gij iets weet <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>van poging tot suicide<c type="kk">/</c> houd U dan maar <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>leuk<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="c" xml:id="note-o-c"/> Doch dit zal trouwens <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>niemand doen<c type="kk">/</c> tenzij <hi rend="ital">misschien</hi> ooit <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Pa of Moe<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>
                <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ge begrijpt wel goed dat als ik U <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>schreef ’t me denken deed aan een <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>passage uit M<hi rend="ss">m</hi> Bovary – <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>er hier niets is dat met de <hi rend="ital">tweede</hi> <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>M<hi rend="ss">m</hi> B<c type="kp">_</c>, over wie ’t boek eigentlijk is, <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>te maken heeft – doch alleen de <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">eerste</hi> M<hi rend="ss">m</hi> Bovary<c type="kk">/</c> van wie bijna niets <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>staat dan dat eene<c type="kk">/</c> hoe en waarom <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>zij stierf – op ’t hooren van een slechte <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>tijding betreffende haar vermogen.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
                    <hi rend="sc">Hier</hi> was de oorzaak tot desperatie <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>niet een slechte tijding betreffende <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>haar vermogen maar de wijze <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>waarop men haar verweet dat zij <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">te oud</hi>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> was en dat soort van zaken. <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>Enfin – binnen kort betrekkelijk<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>over een dag of 14 of 3 weken<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>zal ’t zich wel decideeren of er <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>al dan niet nog eene gevaarlijke zenuwziekte <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>zich openbaart.–</ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet – ik ben altijd nog erg <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>ontdaan hierover. Tot Pa en Moe <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>moet ge er maar niet over spreken<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
<ab>t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I’m dropping you another line about it, to tell you that I do have hopes that the <rs type="pers" key="267">patient</rs> will get over it — although I do foresee that the consequences in the form of nervous problems could prove both serious and prolonged. Much — very much, depends on onlookers and family — who could actually do her no greater service than to treat her kindly as if nothing had happened or, if they can’t do that, just keep silent. I’ve had a long message from her today, and her <rs type="pers" key="268">brother</rs>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> tells me he’s heard too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">There are dangers from <hi rend="ital">two</hi> sides here, Theo — on the one hand that a nervous crisis develops and flares up as, say, a nervous breakdown or brain fever. On the other hand there’s a danger of melancholia or religious mania. Now, though, because the <rs type="pers" key="267">patient</rs> was treated immediately after the first symptom, while furthermore she’s in a setting that couldn’t be more suitable for bringing a person in her condition back to her senses — as a guest — in private — with a <rs type="pers" key="110">doctor</rs> she’s known for a long time, him and his <rs type="pers" key="111">wife</rs> — for these reasons there’s hope 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/> that a crisis in one form or another <hi rend="ital">can</hi> be forestalled or averted or neutralized by timely opposition — that it will blow over in the end, blow over in the form of continuing with this treatment for a while and then returning, calmed, to her normal life.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You will understand that this greatly agitates me, though, this whole episode, when I tell you how, in the very letter I received today, <rs type="pers" key="267">she</rs> says ‘that no one in her family understands her real mental struggle, that she’s trying to distract herself but that she can’t, and most of the time sits in her room with a book or something or other that she has got from me’.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I really don’t know how to deal with the <rs type="pers" key="273">B. family</rs> — they were very unkind to <rs type="pers" key="267">her</rs> at first — and even on the day she left by no means all of them were affectionate or even just good — although they didn’t actually know the truth. I then let her <rs type="pers" key="270 271 272">sisters</rs>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> know through her <rs type="pers" key="268">brother</rs> that I absolutely had to advise them to give their 
    <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> sister <hi rend="ital">satisfaction for unfounded mistrust and certain unfounded suspicions, expressing which was firstly premature, secondly wide of the mark, thirdly nails in the patient’s coffin</hi>. This worked in so far as in the first place her sister-in-law, <rs type="pers" key="269">Louis’ wife</rs>,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> and in the last place her sisters, have sent a letter to the <rs type="pers" key="267">patient</rs>, which was a good deal more sympathetic in tone and a good deal gentler and better than their first utterance. Louis B. himself, who’s the only one in the family who knows all the ins and outs of the poison — although others suspect — but are contradicted by me and by Louis — who know rather more — from the outset Louis B. himself has acted resolutely and sympathetically towards her. As for you, if anyone who suspects were ever to question you as to whether you know anything about an attempted suicide, just stay cool. But anyway, no one will, except <hi rend="ital">possibly</hi> <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa or Ma</rs> sometime.
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You do understand that when I wrote to you that it reminded me of a passage from Mme Bovary — this has nothing to do with the <hi rend="ital">second</hi> Mme B., whom the book is actually about — but only the <hi rend="ital">first</hi> Mme Bovary, about whom there is virtually nothing except that one thing, how and why she died — upon hearing bad news about her fortune.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> <hi rend="sc">here</hi> the cause of desperation wasn’t bad news about <rs type="pers" key="267">her</rs> fortune, but the way they accused her of being <hi rend="ital">too old</hi>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and that sort of thing. Anyway — in a relatively short time, in about a fortnight or 3 weeks, it will become clear whether or not a dangerous nervous disease will manifest itself.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Regards, I’m still very upset by this. You’d better not mention it to <rs type="pers" key="524 526">Pa and Ma</rs>.</ab>
    <vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="268">Louis Begemann</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘Godsdienstwaanzin’ (religious mania).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-o-b">
<ab>Read: ‘Om iemand’ (for bringing someone).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The unmarried sisters who lived with <rs type="pers" key="267">Margot Begemann</rs> in the house called ‘Nune Ville’ at no. 24 Berg – the house next door to the Van Goghs’ parsonage – were <rs type="pers" key="270">Lutgera Wilhelmina</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="271">Wilhelmina Johanna</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="272">Amalia Polixena Rosina</rs> Begemann.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="268">Louis Begemann</rs> was married to <rs type="pers" key="269">Maria Suzanna Lelyvelt</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="c" xml:id="n-c" target="#note-o-c">
<ab>Means: ‘doe dan maar net of je van niets weet’ (just pretend you know nothing).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
    <ab>See for the ‘first Madame Bovary’ in <rs type="pers" key="596">Flaubert</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="406">Madame Bovary. Moeurs de province</rs>
                        </hi>: <ref target="let456.xml#n-7">letter 456, n. 7.</ref> By ‘the second’ Van Gogh means Emma Bovary, the protagonist of the novel. She was Charles Bovary’s second wife. Emma finds no satisfaction in her dull, stifling marriage and embarks on intimate relationships, firstly with Rodolphe, later with Léon, but these only provide short-lived solutions. Dream and reality are irreconcilable. Eventually Emma gets into debt, sees her life as hopeless and commits suicide by taking arsenic.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="267">Margot Begemann</rs> was 43.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>