<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Friday, 9 March 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let583"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">583</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">467</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">585</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Arles</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Friday, 9 March 1888</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Friday, 9 March 1888.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Efforts to interest Tersteeg in modern art <ref target="let580.xml">(580)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Gauguin’s illness <ref target="let581.xml">(581)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b507 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh writes: ‘this morning the weather has changed and has turned milder’. Following a period of cold and the mistral, after a slight improvement on 8 March the weather became considerably milder on 9 March (<hi rend="ital">Météo-France</hi>). We have therefore dated the letter Friday, 9 March 1888.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>Van Gogh enclosed <ref target="let581.xml">letter 581</ref> from Gauguin with this letter.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0507" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000683_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000683_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000683_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000683_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000683_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0507" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000683_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000683_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000683_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000683_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000683_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000683_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>à la fin des fin voilà <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>que ce matin le temps a changé et <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>s’est adouci – j’ai donc déja eu occasion <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>d’apprendre ce que c’est que ce mistral<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>aussi. J’ai fait plusieurs courses dans <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>les environs mais toujours il était <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>par ce vent impossible de rien faire<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Le ciel était d’un bleu dur avec un <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>grand soleil brillant qui a fait fondre <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>à tant soit peu près<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> toute la quantité <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de neige – mais le vent était si froid et <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>si sec qu’on en avait la chair de poule. <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>Mais néamoins j’ai vu de bien belles <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>choses – une ruine d’abbaye sur une colline <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>plantée de houx<c type="kk">/</c> de pins<c type="kk">/</c> d’oliviers gris<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>Nous attaquerons cela sous peu j’espère<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Maintenant je viens de terminer une <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>étude comme celle qu’a Lucien <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Pissaro de moi mais cette fois ci c’est <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>des oranges.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Cela fait jusqu’ici huit <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>études que j’ai<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Mais cela ne compte <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>pas<c type="kk">/</c> comme j’ai pas encore pu travailler <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>bien à mon aise et au chaud<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">La lettre de Gauguin que j’avais <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>l’intention de t’envoyer mais que <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>je croyais momentanément avoir <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>brûlee avec d’autres papiers<c type="kk">/</c> l’ayant <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>retrouvée après<c type="kk">/</c> je te l’envoie ci-inclus<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Seulement je lui ai déjà écrit <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>directement et je lui ai envoié <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>l’adresse de Russell ainsi que j’ai <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>envoyé celle de Gauguin à Russell <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>afin qu’ils puissent<c type="kk">/</c> s’ils veulent<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>se mettre en rapport directement<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Mais comme pour beaucoup d’entre <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>nous – et surement nous serons <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>de ce nombre nous mêmes – l’avenir <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>est encore difficile<c type="kp">_</c>– Je crois bien <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>à la victoire finale<c type="kk">/</c> mais les artistes <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>en profiteront ils et verront ils des <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>jours plus sereins?–</ab>
                <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’ai acheté de la grosse toile ici et <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>je l’ai faite préparer pour les effets <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>mats<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> je puis avoir tout maintenant <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>à peu près au prix de Paris<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Samedi soir j’ai eu la visite <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>de deux peintres amateurs 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>dont l’un est épicier – et vend aussi <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>les articles de peinture – et l’autre <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>est un juge de paix qui a l’air bon <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>et intelligent.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Malheureusement je n’arrive guère <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>à vivre à meilleur compte qu’à Paris<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>il faut que je compte 5 fr. par jour.</ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je n’ai pour le moment encore rien trouvé <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>en fait de pension bourgeoise mais cela <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>doit sûrement exister pourtant.</ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab rend="indent">Si à Paris le temps s’adoucit aussi cela <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>te fera du bien<c type="kp">_</c>– Quel hiver!</ab>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je n’ose pas rouler mes études encore car <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>cela n’a guère séché et il y a des empâtements <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>qui ne seront pas vite secs<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je viens de lire Tartarin sur les Alpes <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>qui m’a énormement amusé<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">Est ce que ce sacré Tersteeg t’a écrit<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>cela fera toujours du bien – va<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab rend="indent">S’il ne répond pas<c type="kk">/</c> il entendra parler <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>de nous tout de même et nous ferons <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>de façon qu’il n’y aie pas à redire <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>sur nos actions.– Par exemple <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>nous enverrons à M<hi rend="ss">me</hi> Mauve un tableau <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>en souvenir de Mauve<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> avec une lettre <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>de nous deux aussi dans laquelle<c type="kk">/</c> si Tersteeg <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>ne répond pas<c type="kk">/</c> nous ne dirons pas un mot contre 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>lui mais nous ferons sentir que nous ne <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>meritons pas qu’on nous traite comme si <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>nous étions des morts<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin, il est probable que Tersteeg n’aura <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>pas de parti pris contre nous en somme.</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ce pauvre Gauguin n’a pas de chance<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>je crains bien que dans son cas la convalescence <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>soit encore plus longue que la quinzaine <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>qu’il a dû passer au lit<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nom de dieu quand est ce que l’on verra <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>une génération d’artistes qui aient des <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>corps sains. A des moments je suis <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>vraiment furieux contre moi-même <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>car il ne suffit pas du tout de n’être <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>ni plus ni moins malade que d’autres<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>l’ideal serait d’avoir un temperament fort <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>assez pour vivre 80 ans et avec ça un sang <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>qui serait du vrai bon sang<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
<ab rend="indent">On s’en consolerait pourtant si on sentait <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>qu’il va y venir une génération d’artistes <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>plus heureux.</ab>
                <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’ai voulu t’ecrire tout de suite que <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>j’ai esperance que l’hiver soit maintenant <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>passé et j’espère qu’il en sera de même <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>à Paris. Poignee de main<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab>b. à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-41" n="41">sereins?– &lt; sereins –</note>
<note target="l-49" n="49">peinture – &lt; peinture</note>
<note target="l-93" n="93">sentait &lt; senterait</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Now at long last, this morning the weather has changed and has turned milder — and I’ve already had an opportunity to find out what this mistral’s<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> like too. I’ve been out on several hikes round about here, but that wind always made it impossible to do anything. The sky was a hard blue with a great bright sun that melted just about all the snow — but the wind was so cold and dry it gave you goose-pimples. But even so I’ve seen lots of beautiful things — a ruined abbey on a hill planted with hollies, pines and grey olive trees. We’ll get down to that soon, I hope.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> Now I’ve just finished a study like the one of mine <rs type="pers" key="1267">Lucien Pissarro</rs> has, but this time it’s of oranges.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> That makes eight studies I have up to now.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> But that doesn’t count, as I haven’t yet been able to work in comfort and in the warm. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The letter from <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> that I had intended to send you but which for a moment I thought I had burned with some other papers, I later found and enclose herewith.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> But I’ve already written to him direct and I’ve sent him <rs type="pers" key="1334">Russell</rs>’s address as well as sending Gauguin’s to Russell, so that if they wish they can make direct contact.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> But as for many of us — and surely we’ll be among them ourselves — the future is still difficult. I do believe in a final victory, but will artists benefit from it, and will they see more peaceful days?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve bought some coarse canvas here and I’ve had it prepared for matt effects,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> I can now get everything, more or less, at Paris prices.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">On Saturday evening I had a visit from two amateur painters, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> one of whom is a <rs type="pers" key="3">grocer</rs> — and also sells painting materials — and the other a justice of the peace who seems kind and intelligent.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Unfortunately I’m hardly managing to live more cheaply than in Paris, I need to allow 5 francs a day.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">For the moment I haven’t found anything like a boarding-house, but there must surely be some.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If the weather also gets milder in Paris it will do you good. What a winter!</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I daren’t roll up my studies yet because they’re hardly dry, and there are some areas of impasto that won’t dry for a while.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve just read Tartarin sur les Alpes, which I greatly enjoyed.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Has that bloody man <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> written to you? That’ll do us good anyway — don’t worry.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If he doesn’t reply, he’ll hear people talking about us all the same, and we’ll make sure he has nothing to fault in what we do. For example, we’ll send <rs type="pers" key="321">Mrs Mauve</rs> a painting in memory of <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> with a letter as well from us both in which, if Tersteeg doesn’t reply, we won’t say a word against 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> him but we’ll make it understood that we don’t deserve to be treated as though we were dead.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In fact, it’s likely that <rs type="pers" key="787">Tersteeg</rs> won’t be predisposed against us after all.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">That poor <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> has no luck, I do fear that in his case convalescence will take longer than the fortnight he had to spend in bed.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">For Christ’s sake, when are we going to see a generation of artists with healthy bodies? Sometimes I’m really furious with myself because it isn’t good enough to be iller or less ill than others, the ideal thing would be to have a strong enough constitution to live for 80 years and along with that, blood that was real good blood.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But we could take comfort if we felt that a generation of more fortunate artists was going to come along.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I wanted to write to you straightaway that I’m hopeful winter’s over now and I hope it will be the same in Paris. Handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The mistral is a cold, dry katabatic wind from the north-west or north, which blows in the Rhône valley and the coastal regions of south-east France.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Conflation of the expressions ‘à peu près’ and ‘tant soit peu’, which both mean ‘almost’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The medieval abbey of Montmajour on the plain of La Crau, about five km to the north-east of Arles. Van Gogh often worked in the immediate vicinity of the abbey and depicted it in several works.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The study with the oranges is <hi rend="ital">Basket of oranges</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2567">F 395 / JH 1363</rs>). In Paris Van Gogh had exchanged his <hi rend="ital">Basket of apples </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2558">F 378 / JH 1340</rs>) for several wood engravings by <rs type="pers" key="1267">Lucien Pissarro</rs> (FR b886).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>These eight studies are: <hi rend="ital">An old woman of Arles</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2561">F 390 / JH 1357</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Landscape with snow</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2564">F 290 / JH 1360</rs>), <hi rend="ital">View of a butcher’s shop</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2563">F 389 / JH 1359</rs>) (<ref target="let578.xml">see letter 578</ref>); a study, possibly <hi rend="ital">Bowl of Potatoes </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2568">F 386 / JH 1365</rs>) (<ref target="let580.xml">see letter 580</ref>); <hi rend="ital">Landscape with snow</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2562">F 391 / JH 1358</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Sprig of almond blossom in a glass </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2565">F 392 / JH 1361</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Sprig of almond blossom in a glass with a book</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2566">F 393 / JH 1362</rs>) (<ref target="let582.xml">see letter 582</ref>); and the <hi rend="ital">Basket of oranges</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2567">F 395 / JH 1363</rs>) referred to above.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>This was <ref target="let581.xml">letter 581</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Van Gogh was trying to persuade <rs type="pers" key="1334">Russell</rs> to buy a work from <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> (see also <ref target="let582.xml">letter 582</ref>). As far as we know, Gauguin and Russell never got in touch. Merlhès suggests that Gauguin was too proud to approach Russell. <hi rend="ital">Correspondance Gauguin</hi> 1984, p. 474 (n. 242).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Van Gogh means canvas with a ground that absorbs surplus oil, producing a matt effect. See Peres <hi rend="ital">et al.</hi> 1991, pp. 26-27. He painted <hi rend="ital">Avenue of plane trees </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2569">F 398 / JH 1366</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">The Gleize bridge with washerwomen</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2570">F 396 / JH 1367</rs>) on this type of canvas.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>The grocer was <rs type="pers" key="3">Jules Armand</rs>, ‘épicier-droguiste’, 30 rue du Quatre-Septembre. Stokvis mentions a Madame J. Armand, the widow of a grocer who was an amateur artist, ‘where Vincent occasionally bought what he needed’. Coquiot calls her ‘the widow of a colourman, where Vincent bought supplies the first few days’. See Stokvis<hi rend="ital"> </hi>1929, p. 4, and Coquiot<hi rend="ital"> </hi>1923, p. 164.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Jules Armand was the first known owner of <hi rend="ital">Marcelle Roulin</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="668">F 440 / JH 1639</rs>). In the Museon Arlaten in Arles there is a portrait of an Arlésienne, signed ‘J. Armand 1889’. We know from the local newspapers that he regularly exhibited his work in the window of the Bompard fils’ wallpaper shop at 14 place de la République, under the name Armand-Ronin. The official deeds give his name as Jean Auguste Armand; on the electoral roll and in address books it is Jules Armand; Ronin was the maiden name of his wife Joséphine (ACA).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">At this time there were two justices of the peace in Arles: <rs type="pers" key="146">Paul Marre</rs> for the western canton, and <rs type="pers" key="84">Eugène Giraud</rs> for the eastern canton (<hi rend="ital">L’indicateur marseillais 1888</hi>). We do not know which of the two was an amateur artist. In May 1888 Van Gogh went to see Giraud about a dispute with his <rs type="pers" key="755">landlord</rs>; <ref target="let609.xml#n-1">see letter 609, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="583">Alphonse Daudet</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</rs>
                        </hi> (1885), like <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="459">Tartarin de Tarascon</rs> </hi>(1872), is a satirical novel that mocks the men of southern France, and particularly the inhabitants of Tarascon. The central character, Tartarin, a self-proclaimed lion-hunter and the president of the Tarascon mountain climbing association – whose members have never been further than the foothills of the Alpilles – goes to Switzerland to conquer the highest peaks in the Alps and strengthen his position as president before the elections. Tartarin is a know-it-all, who tries to rescue himself from embarrassing situations that he himself has caused.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="323">Mauve</rs> died on 5 February. Around 30 March, in response to his death, Van Gogh painted <hi rend="ital">Pink peach trees (‘Souvenir de Mauve’)</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2577">F 394 / JH 1379</rs>) and decided to give it to Mauve’s widow, <rs type="pers" key="321">Jet Mauve-Carbentus</rs>. <ref target="let590.xml">See letter 590</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>