<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Wednesday, 24 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let566"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">566</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">458</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">569</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Antwerp</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Wednesday, 24 February 1886</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, on or about Wednesday, 24 February 1886.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Plan to move to Paris <ref target="let555.xml">(555)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Plan to study with Cormon <ref target="let556.xml">(556)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b498 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh says: ‘I’m writing to you once more, because in any event my time here is almost up’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>); he was assuming that he would leave Antwerp at the end of February. He ends by asking Theo to write soon. This request would only make sense if the letter was written by Thursday, 25 February 1886 at the latest. Because it is also after <ref target="let565.xml">letter 565</ref> of about 22 February, we have dated the present letter on or about Wednesday, 24 February 1886.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0498" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000674_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000674_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000674_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000674_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000674_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0498" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000674_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000674_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000674_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000674_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000674_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000674_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>ik schrijf U nog een keer, omdat mijn <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>tijd hier in elk geval haast om is &amp; dezer dagen <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>ik terug moet. De tijd van buiten kunnen <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>werken zal met de minste verandering van <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>weer er kunnen wezen<c type="kk">/</c> en dus<c type="kk">/</c> als het moest &amp; <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>gij perse het wilt<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik althans niet geheel <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>vruchteloos in Brabant zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Doch wat daar <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>ook van zij<c type="kk">/</c> ik blijf steeds U animeeren <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>liever door te zetten met het plan van Cormon <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>en hetgeen ik voor mij daaraan zoo gaarne <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>zou willen laten voorafgaan<c type="kk">/</c> nog een tijd antiek <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>blijven teekenen.–</ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het begint<c type="kk">/</c> verbeeld ik me<c type="kk">/</c> wat te vorderen met <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>mijn gezondheid. in zoover dat ik mijn voedsel <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>iets beter begin te kunnen verdragen. Maar <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>het blijft steeds toch twijfelachtig en den eenen <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>dag ongelijk aan den anderen.</ab>
                <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb weer een teekening klaar van antiek<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>en sedert ik U schreef de leeraar indirect <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>zich had uitgelaten dat hij het zoo bar niet had gemeend<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>heb ik niets meer met hem gehad en zelfs <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zeide hij dat mijn teekening van vandaag haast <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>geen verandering noodig had van proportie 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>en in ’t geheel geen van toon<c type="kp">_</c>– Dus ik <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>zou haast durven hopen dat ik met Cormon<c type="kk">/</c> hoe <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>hij ook zij<c type="kk">/</c> het ook wel schipperen zal en dat geeft <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>mij des te meer ’t verlangen er te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>Enfin – als het mij wat meeloopt met mijn <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>gezondheid hoop ik wel te vorderen van ’t jaar<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Ik blijf ook steeds meenen dat er nog <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>wel wat te doen te vinden is<c type="kk">/</c> al is <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>het in dat opzigt mij niet voorspoedig gegaan<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Doch mijn tijd is ook erg ingenomen door <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>het werk aan de akademie<c type="kp">_</c>– Naar wat ik hoor <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>van ’t geen lui eventueel verkoopen<c type="kk">/</c> is dat <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>telkens portret<c type="kp">_</c>– Er moet een mooie tentoonstelling <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>van impressionisten zijn in Brussel.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ziet ge<c type="kk">/</c> sedert ik hier gezien en gehoord heb <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>van andere lui die op figuur zich concentreeren<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>hoe zij het aanlegden – en weet<c type="kk">/</c> het zijn allen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>zulken die meer te verteeren hebben dan ik – dan <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>hebben zij steeds zich van de modellen op een <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>of ander atelier in stad zich bediend – juist <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>ter wille van de kosten.– En tevens heeft men op <lb n="44a" xml:id="l-44a"/>die manier correctie en ziet men anderen werken<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu onwillekeurig kom ik telkens op ’t idee <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>wij misschien reeds wel twee of twee en een half 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>jaar eer dezen maatregel hadden dienen <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>te nemen<c type="kk">/</c> reden te meer het ditmaal <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>niet op den langen weg te schuiven<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Antwerpen is mij goed bevallen – <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>après tout. Natuurlijk wou ik dat ik <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>er gekomen was met die ondervinding er<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>van die ik nu weet op ’t moment ik er van daan <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>ga. Maar als dat kon waren de dingen <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>makkelijker en men begint met overal <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>er groen in te komen.– Ik hoop echter <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>wel na tijd &amp; wijle Antwerpen terug te zien <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>want er is iets vrij’s en artistieks in het leven <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>hier<c type="kk">/</c> als men het zoekt<c type="kk">/</c> welligt meer dan elders. <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>Verder<c type="kk">/</c> men ziet er allerlei lui<c type="kk">/</c> Engelschen<c type="kk">/</c> franschen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>duitschers<c type="kk">/</c> Belgen<c type="kk">/</c> en dat geeft afwisseling<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>Als er een stad is die op Parijs lijkt dan <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>is het veeleer Antwerpen dan Brussel<c type="kk">/</c> in alle dingen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>Vooreerst omdat het een centrum is voor lui van <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>alle nationaliteiten<c type="kk">/</c> tweedens ter wille <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>van de zaken en derdens ter wille van dat er animo is <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>en men er zich amuseert.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als de cursus aan de akademie doorging <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>dan zou ik ook graag nog blijven<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar ongelukkig is daar voor Mei niets meer <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>dan de concoursen<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> en de dag klas voor antiek en <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>raken ook die op zijn eind.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu heb ik Antwerpen zeker niet in zijn <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>fleur gezien want naar men algemeen hoort <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>is het er anders nog veel geanimeerder en <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>zijn er nu twee crisissen te gelijk die <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>drukken<c type="kk">/</c> vooreerst de algemeene<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> en dan <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>de naweeën van de tentoonstelling<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> nog <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>bovendien<c type="kk">/</c> in den vorm van talrijke frauduleuse <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>of gewone bankroeten.</ab>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Denk er nog eens goed over of we <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>niet een combinatie kunnen vinden die <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>’t mogelijk make ik reeds voor Juni in <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>Parijs zij. Ik zou het zoo gaarne willen <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>omdat ik geloof dat het voor zooveel dingen <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>beter ware<c type="kk">/</c> die ik U reeds noemde.</ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Waar ik nog wel bij mag zeggen dat wij <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>dunkt me zooveel beter overleggen kunnen wat <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>het nemen van een atelier tegen Juni betreft<c type="kk">/</c> indien wij <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>reeds van te voren beiden in Parijs waren en <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>poolshoogte konden nemen van vóór of tegen. <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>Enfin. Schrijf me weer spoedig<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-48" n="48">reden &lt; rede</note>
<note target="l-87" n="87">wij &lt; wij wij</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I’m writing to you once again, because in any event my time here is almost up and I have to go back one of these days. The time when one can work outdoors could be upon us with the slightest change in the weather and so, if I have to and if you’re absolutely set on it, at least my being in Brabant wouldn’t be entirely fruitless. Yet be that as it may, I still continue to urge you rather to go ahead with the <rs type="pers" key="944">Cormon</rs> plan and what, for my part, I would so much like to precede it — a further period continuing to draw plaster casts.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">My health, I fancy, is beginning to improve a little in so far as I’m beginning to be able to digest my food somewhat better. But it’s still uncertain all the same, and one day’s unlike another.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve finished another drawing of a plaster cast,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and since I wrote and told you that the <rs type="pers" key="1351">teacher</rs> had indirectly let it be known that he hadn’t meant to be so harsh<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> I haven’t had any more trouble with him, and he even said that the drawing I did today needed virtually no change in proportion 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> and none at all in tone. So I’d almost dare hope that I’ll also be able to get on with <rs type="pers" key="944">Cormon</rs>, whatever he may be like, and that makes me long to be there all the more. Anyway — if I’m fortunate with my health, I hope to make progress this year. I also still continue to think that it will be possible to find work to do, although things haven’t gone very well for me in this respect. Still, my time is very much taken up by the work at the academy. From what I hear about what people sometimes sell, it’s usually portraits. There must be a good exhibition of Impressionists in Brussels.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You see, since I’ve seen and heard how they set about it from other fellows here who concentrate on the figure — and bear in mind they’re all such as have more to spend than I — they’ve always used the models in some studio or other in town — precisely because of the cost. And this way one gets correction and one sees others working at the same time.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now I can’t help keep getting the idea that we should perhaps have taken this step 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> a good two or two and a half years ago — all the more reason not to put it off it this time. In the end, Antwerp suited me well. Of course I wish I’d come here with the experience of it that I have now, at the moment I’m leaving. But if that were possible, things would be easier, and one always begins by coming in green. I hope, though, to come back to Antwerp sometime, because there’s something free and artistic about the life here, if one looks for it, perhaps more than anywhere else. What’s more, one sees all sorts of people, English, French, Germans, Belgians, and that makes for variety. If there’s a city that resembles Paris, then it’s Antwerp rather than Brussels, in all respects. Firstly because it’s a centre for people of all nationalities, secondly because of business, and thirdly because there’s gusto and people enjoy themselves.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’d be happy to stay if the course at the academy were continuing.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But unfortunately there’s nothing there until May except for the competitions<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> and the day class for plaster casts, and those are coming to an end too. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And I’ve certainly not seen Antwerp at its best now, for from what one generally hears it’s usually much livelier still, and now there are two crises depressing it at the same time — firstly the general one,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and then on top of that the aftermath of the exhibition, too,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> in the shape of numerous fraudulent or common bankruptcies.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Think carefully about whether we couldn’t find a combination that would make it possible for me to be in Paris before June. I’d like it so much, because I believe that it would be better for so many reasons, which I’ve already told you.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">To which I may also add that it seems to me that we could discuss taking a studio by June so much better if we were both already in Paris beforehand and could size up the pros and cons of the situation. Anyway. Write to me again soon, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The reference is too general to allow us to determine which drawing of a plaster cast this is. <hi rend="ital">The discus thrower</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="644">F 1364e / JH 1080</rs>) dates from this period.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>See for this clash with <rs type="pers" key="1351">Siberdt</rs>: <ref target="let563.xml">letter 563</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
    <ab>The third exhibition of Les Vingt, which ran from 6 February to 7 March 1886 in Brussels, where several Impressionists exhibited, <rs type="pers" key="1222">Monet</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1293">Renoir</rs> among them, was the initial introduction of Impressionism in Belgium. See for this exhibition: Susan Marie Canning, <hi rend="ital">A history and critical review of the Salons of Les Vingt, 1884-1893</hi>. Diss. The Pennsylvania State University 1980, pp. 98-136; and exhib. cat. Brussels 1993, p. 30.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>See for the competitions: <ref target="let557.xml#n-3">letter 557, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>On this crisis, <ref target="let556.xml#n-1">see letter 556, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>The World Exhibition, which ran in Antwerp from 2 May to 2 November 1885, may indeed have been ‘a product of the economic crisis’, but contrary to what Van Gogh asserts, it was a financial and artistic success. See exhib. cat. Antwerp 1993, p. 133.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>