<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Monday, 15 June 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let508"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">508</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">412</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">511</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 15 June 1885</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, Monday, 15 June 1885. </p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Van Gogh sends a small crate of paintings to Paris <ref target="let506.xml">(506)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Portier’s opinion of <hi rend="ital">The potato eaters</hi> <ref target="let494.xml">(494)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b450 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh refers to a forest fire ‘yesterday’ (<ref target="#l-7">l. 7</ref>). Since this happened on Sunday, 14 June (<ref target="#n-3">see n. 3</ref>), this letter must have been written on Monday, 15 June 1885.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0450" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000602_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000602_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000602_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0450" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000602_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000602_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000602_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000602_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000602_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000602_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Ge zult dezer dagen naar <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>alle gedachten het kistje hebben ontvangen.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>ik wilde U nog zeggen dat ik nog een <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>soortgelijk geval heb<c type="kk">/</c> namelijk een <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>wit leemen hut<c type="kk">/</c> het formaat <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>iets meer in de breedte<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gisteren heb ik een grooten boschbrand bijgewoond <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>op een snikheeten achtermiddag.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> het was <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>een bosch midden op een kale heivlakte <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>en het gezigt was zeer eigenaardig, door <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de verbazende massas zwarten en witten rook die regt naar boven stegen. <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>Het vuur heeft zich echter bepaald bij <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>de heide<c type="kk">/</c> de dennennaalden en dorre takken<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>De stammen bleven staan<c type="kp">_</c>– </ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben druk doende aan de figuurteekeningen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>ik zal er echter een 100tal moeten maken <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>vóór ik dezelfde schilderen zal<c type="kk">/</c> daar het me <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>zoodoende geld en tijd uithaalt<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik geloof ik ze ronder en voller zal krijgen dan <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>vroeger.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik ben echter absoluut zonder geld <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>en weet haast niet hoe de maand door <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>te komen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bij tijden kan ik er mistroostig <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>om worden dat het altijd maar blijft<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>niets verkoopen.</ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toch<c type="kk">/</c> ik ga door en verhard er <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>me tegen in.</ab>
                <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>
<ab rend="indent">Anderen hebben ’t ook verdragen<c type="kp">_</c> </ab>
                <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Gegroet</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab>Is er in Mei geen N<hi rend="ss">o</hi> van l’Lhermitte <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>geweest?<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zeg het nog eens – werk <hi rend="ital">tegen</hi> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">de onverschilligheid in</hi> – het volhouden is <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>niet makkelijk – maar wat makkelijk <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>is beteekent ook weinig<c type="kp">_</c>– </ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het schilderen van het boerenleven is iets wat <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>goed <hi rend="ital">blijft</hi> en het gevecht dat anderen wonnen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">gaat nog steeds door</hi> en op nieuw kan men <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>het winnen. Wel verre van dat er te veel <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>boerenschilders zouden zijn – mijns inziens <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>ware ’t beter als er nog honderden bij konden <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>komen<c type="kp">_</c>– 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is geen kwaad idee dat men in <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>Frankrijk de mairies decoreeren gaat <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>met motieven uit het landleven zoo als <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>er een aantal schilderijen op den salon waren<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Ik geloof wel dat dit nog verder <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>doorgevoerd zal worden<c type="kp">_</c>– </ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar – nog beter is het dat de <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>boerenschilderijen <hi rend="ital">in de huizen</hi> komen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>in de illustraties en andere reproducties direkt <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>onder ’t volk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is dan ook slechts voorbijgaande als <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>ik decouragement gevoel.</ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik hoorde van t’huis dat gij hun iets <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>geschreven hadt over Serret<c type="kk">/</c> van dat <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>die zeide ik verzekerd kon zijn van zijn <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>sympathie &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c>– Is Serret een schilder<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>een handelaar of een liefhebber? tot heden <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>weet ik dat niet<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> ik heb Germinal<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>in ’t kistje van de schilderijen willen doen <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>doch was ten slotte bang het er tusschen in <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>zou vallen en beschadigen. Ik doe het <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>in een volgend echter, of retourneer <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>het per post. ik vind het prachtig<c type="kp">_</c>– </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-61" n="61">sympathie &lt; symathie</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>In all likelihood you’ll have received the little crate in the last few days.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I wanted to tell you that I have another similar thing, a white wattle-and-daub cottage, the size slightly more in the width.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yesterday I was at a large forest fire on a sweltering afternoon.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> It was a wood in the middle of a bare stretch of heath, and the sight was very singular because of the amazing masses of black and white smoke that were rising straight up. The fire confined itself to the heather, the pine needles and dry branches, though. The trunks remained standing.</ab>
<ab rend="indent"> I’m very busy with the figure drawings; however I’ll have to make 100 or so before I paint them, since that will save me time and money.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I believe I’ll get them rounder and fuller than before.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I have absolutely no money, though, and scarcely know how to get through the month.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">From time to time I can become dispirited that it will always just stay the same, selling nothing.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Still, I carry on and steel myself against it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Others have borne it, too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Regards</hi>.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Wasn’t there a contribution by <rs type="pers" key="1179">Lhermitte</rs> in May?<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I say it again — work <hi rend="ital">against indifference</hi> — perseverance isn’t easy — but things that are easy mean little.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Painting peasant life is something that <hi rend="ital">remains</hi> good, and the fight that others won <hi rend="ital">is still going on</hi> and one can win it again. Far from there being too many peasant painters — to my mind it would be better if there could be hundreds more.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s not a bad idea that in France they’re going to decorate the town halls with subjects from rural life, like a number of the paintings that were at the Salon.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> I do think that this will be taken still further.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But — it would be even better for the peasant paintings to come <hi rend="ital">into the houses</hi>, straight to the people, in the illustrated magazines and other reproductions.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">So when I feel discouragement it’s only in passing.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I heard from home that you’d written something to them about <rs type="pers" key="1354">Serret</rs>, about how he said I could be assured of his sympathy &amp;c. Is Serret a painter, a dealer or an art lover? As of today, I don’t know.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> I wanted to put Germinal<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> in the crate with the paintings, but in the end was afraid it might fall in among them and be damaged. I’ll put it in the next one, though, or return it by post. I think it magnificent.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
      <ab>See for this consignment: <ref target="let504.xml#n-4">letters 504, nn. 4</ref>
                        <ref target="let504.xml#n-7">-7</ref> and <ref target="let507.xml#n-1">507, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Cottage</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2519">F 91 / JH 809</rs>), which Van Gogh compares to <hi rend="ital">The cottage</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2513">F 83 / JH 777</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>In the afternoon of Sunday, 14 June a forest fire raged between Nuenen and Geldrop, according to the report in the <hi rend="ital">Provinciale Noordbrabantsche en ’s-Hertogenbossche Courant</hi> of 18 June. <rs type="pers" key="57">Driek Dekkers</rs>, who was ten years old at the time, witnessed Van Gogh helping with the fire-fighting efforts until late into the evening. See exhib. cat. ’s-Hertogenbosch 1987, p. 95, and De Brouwer 1984, p. 92.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Van Gogh had set himself this goal as a result of what he had read in <rs type="pers" key="613">Gigoux</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="407">Causeries sur l’artistes de mon temps</rs>
                        </hi>. <ref target="let506.xml">See letter 506</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
      <ab>See for <rs type="pers" key="1179">Lhermitte</rs>’s <rs type="ill" key="213">
                            <hi rend="ital">The lovers (‘Idyll’)</hi>
                        </rs>: <ref target="let502.xml#n-19">letter 502, n. 19.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Van Gogh got this from <rs type="pers" key="700">Mantz</rs>’s article ‘<rs type="lit" key="582">Le Salon <hi rend="sc">i</hi>
                        </rs>’; <ref target="let502.xml#n-10">see letter 502, n. 10.</ref> Mantz writes: ‘They resolved, not without reason, to decorate the town halls, and they thought that several of the rooms in municipal buildings, particularly those for Marriages, might be improved by paintings. They also judged that the citizens would be delighted by the sight of rural things’ (On a résolu, non sans raison, de décorer les mairies, et l’on a pensé que plusieurs salles des édifices municipaux, particulièrement celle des Mariages, pourraient être embellies par des peintures. On a même jugé que les citadins seraient réjouis par le spectacle des choses rurales) (p. 1).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Theo had mentioned the painter <rs type="pers" key="1354">Serret</rs> in an undated letter (of about 1 June 1885) to his <rs type="pers" key="524">mother</rs>: ‘I do so hope that Vincent will settle down eventually. One <hi rend="ital">cannot</hi> expect him to become altogether like an ordinary person, but the best thing is just to let him do as he wants, and perhaps see the good in him. I showed his work again to an old painter (Serret’s his name) who has seen and experienced a great deal in his life and has a good heart and a clear head. He told me that he could see in his work that it was done by someone who had been working for a relatively short time, but he found a great deal that is good in it. He even said that if he kept on working and could manage to work out his idea, he held out the prospect that he would surpass <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>, who as you know was one of the greatest painters that ever was, in expression. But speaking of success with the public, he thought that that would go slowly, very slowly. But, he went on, if it might please him, tell him that he has <hi rend="ital">my </hi>sympathy entirely. So we must wait and see, and if he produces good work, which great men think is good and admirable, try to forgive him his peculiarities in everyday life. I regard the money I give him as payment for his work and as such he earns it. Perhaps it will take a long time, but one day it will be valuable, only I wish it was soon so that people would regard him in a different light from the way they do now’ (FR b939). </ab>
<ab rend="indent">We do not know whether Serret was a dealer as well as an artist – his name does not appear in Goupil’s sales ledgers.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>The novel <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="413">Germinal</rs>
                        </hi> by <rs type="pers" key="836">Emile Zola</rs>, which Theo had sent: <ref target="let505.xml">see letter 505</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>