<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 22 June 1885. </title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let509"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">509</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">413</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">512</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Monday, 22 June 1885</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Monday, 22 June 1885. </p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Serret’s reaction to Van Gogh’s work <ref target="let508.xml">(508)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b451 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Vincent asked for money in his previous letter of 15 June (<ref target="let508.xml">letter 508</ref>). In the present letter he thanks Theo for the money he sent, which ‘enables me to work at the end of the month’ <ref target="#l-2">(ll. 2-3)</ref>. It is not possible to say how many days have elapsed between the two letters. We assume that Theo sent the extra money – which meant that the monthly allowance gradually crept back up to 150 francs again – around the twentieth; we have therefore dated the letter on or about Monday, 22 June 1885.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0451" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000603_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000603_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000603_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000603_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000603_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0451" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000603_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000603_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000603_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000603_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000603_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000603_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Dank voor Uw brief en het ingeslotene dat <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>juist is wat ik bedoelde en me in staat stelt het eind van <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>de maand te werken zoo als in ’t begin van de maand<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het deed me veel genoegen te vernemen dat Serret <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>de schilder is van wien ge reeds vroeger dingen schreeft <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>die ik ook wel degelijk onthouden had, maar de naam <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>was me ontschoten<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Ik zou U veel meer willen <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>schrijven dan ik doen zal in dezen brief, maar <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>tegenwoordig als ik ’t huis kom<c type="kk">/</c> staat mijn hoofd <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>slecht naar schrijven als ik den heelen dag in <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de zon heb gezeten. Wat betreft hetgeen Serret <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>zegt<c type="kk">/</c> ik vind het zelf ook – ik schrijf hem eens <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>een woordje omdat ik wel vrienden met hem <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>wou worden. Ik werk zoo als ik reeds schreef <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>dezer dagen druk aan figuurteekeningen<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> – <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>ik zal die sturen juist vooral met het oog op <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Serret<c type="kk">/</c> om hem te laten zien dat het ensemble van een figuur en <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>den vorm mij verre van onverschillig is<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ziet gij Wallis ooit<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> kan de aquarel van de verkooping<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>soms iets voor hem zijn, als het voor Wisseling iets ware <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>dan neemt hij haar nog eer<c type="kp">_</c>– Aan Wisseling heb <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>ik eens een paar koppen gegeven<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> en ook nu pas hem <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>die lithographie<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> gestuurd. Maar omdat hij geen half woord <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>zelfs antwoordde<c type="kk">/</c> geloof ik dat als ik iets stuurde ik slechts een <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>beleediging zou krijgen<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik had het nu pas weer dat ik van Rappard<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>met wien ik toch jaren goed ben geweest<c type="kk">/</c> na <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>in een maand of 3 niets van hem gehoord te <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>hebben in eens een brief krijg zóó uit de <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>hoogte en zoo vol beleedigingen en naar <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>het mij voorkwam zoo blijkbaar geschreven <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>nadat hij in den Haag geweest was<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>dat ik zoo goed als zeker weet ik hem <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>als vriend voor goed kwijt ben<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is juist omdat ik eerst in den Haag<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>dat is in mijn eigen land<c type="kk">/</c> het heb geprobeerd<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>dat ik volle regt en aanleiding heb al die <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>beroerdigheid te vergeten en aan iets anders <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>te denken buiten zijn eigen land.</ab>
                <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gij kent Wallis goed<c type="kk">/</c> dus misschien kondt ge <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>het eens ter sprake brengen naar aanleiding <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>van die aquarel, doch handel naarmate er gelegenheid <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>is. Als ik wat verdienen kon met mijn werk<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>als we wat vasten grond<c type="kk">/</c> al was het weinig – <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>onder de voeten hadden <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>om te kunnen blijven bestaan – en <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>als dan ooit de lust om werkman te <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>worden bij U een vorm aannam – laat <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>me zeggen om duidelijk te zijn – 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>op de manier van b.v.<c type="kk">/</c> behoudens <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>alle onderscheid in leeftijd &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> – Hennebeau <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>in Germinal – wat zoudt ge dan nog <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>schilderen kunnen<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> De toekomst <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>is toch altijd anders dan men denkt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>dus men kan nooit met zekerheid het <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>weten<c type="kp">_</c>– De schaduwzijde van het <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>schilderen is dat men als men <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>zijn schilderijen niet verkoopt<c type="kk">/</c> toch <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>geld moet hebben voor verf en model <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>om verder te komen. En die schaduwzijde <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">is</hi> leelijk. Maar anders – het schilderen <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>en m.i. bepaald het boerenschilderen <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>geeft gemoedsrust<c type="kk">/</c> al heeft men veel gescharrel <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>en beroerdigheid aan den <hi rend="ital">buitenkant</hi> van het leven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>Ik bedoel<c type="kk">/</c> het schilderen is een <hi rend="ital">t’huis</hi> en <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>men heeft niet dat <hi rend="ital">heimwee</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> dat eigenaardige <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>wat Hennebeau had.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Die passage die ik toen nog opschreef<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>heeft mij erg getroffen omdat letterlijk <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>haast ik in der tijd zoo’n verlangen <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>had om iets te zijn als een hannikenmaaier<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>of polderwerker<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">En dat ik bleu was van de <hi rend="ital">verveling</hi> van <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>de beschaving. Het <hi rend="ital">is</hi> beter<c type="kk">/</c> men <hi rend="ital">is</hi> gelukkiger <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>als men – maar zoowat letterlijk – dat ten <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>uitvoer brengt – men voelt zich werkelijk <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>althans leven<c type="kp">_</c>– En het is <hi rend="ital">iets</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> s’winters goed <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>in de sneeuw<c type="kk">/</c> in den herfst goed in de geele blaren<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>in den zomer goed in ’t rijpe koren<c type="kk">/</c> in de <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>lente goed in ’t gras te zijn<c type="kp">_</c> het is <hi rend="ital">iets</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>altijd met de maaiers en de boerenmeiden te <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>zijn<c type="kk">/</c> s’zomers met de groote lucht er boven<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>s’winters onder de zwarte schouw<c type="kp">_</c>– En te voelen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>dat is altijd geweest en dat zal altijd zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Men moge dan op stroo slapen<c type="kk">/</c> roggebrood eten<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>welnu men is er op den duur gezonder door<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zou meer willen schrijven maar – <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>zooals gezegd<c type="kk">/</c> mijn hoofd staat niet naar <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>schrijven en ik wilde hier nog een woordje <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>voor Serret insluiten dat ge maar eens lezen <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>moet<c type="kk">/</c> daar ik er in schrijf over wat <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>ik wilde sturen binnen kort<c type="kk">/</c> juist vooral omdat <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>ik Serret mijn bepaalde figuurstudies eens wil <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>laten kijken. Gegroet,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="94*" xml:id="l-94s"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>
<ab>Serret moge ’t met U eens zijn dat goede dingen maken en <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>verkoopen geheel afgescheiden zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– Toch is er niets <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>van aan<c type="kp">_</c>– Toen Millet gezien werd eindelijk door ’t publiek<c type="kk">/</c> zijn werk bij elkaar – toen <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>was het publiek en te Parijs en te Londen <hi rend="ital">enthousiast</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>– En wie waren het geweest <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>die in ’t licht hadden gestaan en Millet geweigerd – de handelaars – de <hi rend="ital">kenners</hi> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>zoogenaamd &amp;c.–<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Ik vraag U<c type="kk">/</c> zou een Mouret zoo iets gezegd hebben<c type="kk">/</c> om <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>over handel te blijven spreken?<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-24" n="24">ik slechts &lt; slechts</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Thanks for your letter and the enclosure, which is exactly what I meant and enables me to work at the end of the month just as at the beginning of the month.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I was very pleased to hear that <rs type="pers" key="1354">Serret</rs> is the painter about whom you had previously written things that I had really remembered, but the name had escaped me.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I’d like to write much more to you than I will in this letter, but when I get home nowadays I’m really not in the mood for writing when I’ve been sitting in the sun all day. As to what Serret says, I think so too — I’ll drop him a line, because I’d like to become friends with him. As I already told you, these days I’m hard at work on figure drawings<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> — I’ll send them specifically with an eye to Serret, to show him that I’m far from indifferent to the unity of a figure and the form.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Do you ever see <rs type="pers" key="818">Wallis</rs>?<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> Might the watercolour of the auction<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> be something for him? If it were something for <rs type="pers" key="821">Wisselingh</rs>, then better he should take it. I once gave Wisselingh a couple of heads<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and also just sent him the lithograph.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> But because he didn’t send so much as a word in reply, I think that all I’d get would be an insult if I sent something.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It just happened to me that, having not heard anything from him in 3 months or so, I suddenly got a letter from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Rappard</rs>, with whom I’ve been on good terms for years, so supercilious and so full of insults and, it seemed to me, so obviously written after he’d been in The Hague that I’m as good as certain that I’ve lost him as a friend for good.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s precisely because I tried it first in The Hague, that’s to say my own country, that I have every right and reason to forget all that unpleasantness and to think of something else outside my own country.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You know <rs type="pers" key="818">Wallis</rs> well, so perhaps you could bring it up sometime apropos of that watercolour, but act as the opportunity arises. If I could earn something with my work, if we had some firm ground, even a little — under our feet, to be able to go on living — and if ever the desire to become an artisan took shape in you — let me say to make it clear — 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> in the manner of, say, discounting all the differences in age &amp;c. — Hennebeau in Germinal — what you would be able to paint then!<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> Still, the future’s always other than one thinks, so one can never know for sure. The drawback to painting is that if one doesn’t sell one’s paintings one still has to have money for paints and models to make progress. And that drawback <hi rend="ital">is</hi> ugly. But otherwise — painting and, to my mind, particularly painting peasant life, gives peace of mind, even though one has a lot of scraping along and wretchedness on the <hi rend="ital">outside</hi> of life. I mean painting is a <hi rend="ital">home</hi>, and one doesn’t have that <hi rend="ital">homesickness</hi>, that peculiar thing that Hennebeau had.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The passage I copied out then<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> struck me very much because, almost literally at that time, I had just such a longing to be something like a grass-mower<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> or polder worker.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And I was sick of the <hi rend="ital">boredom</hi> of civilization. It <hi rend="ital">is</hi> better, one <hi rend="ital">is</hi> happier if one puts it into effect — but pretty much literally — at least one feels really alive. And it is <hi rend="ital">something</hi> to be deep in the snow in winter, to be deep in the yellow leaves in the autumn, to be deep in the ripe wheat in the summer, to be deep in the grass in the spring. It is <hi rend="ital">something</hi> to always be with the mowers and the peasant girls, in summer with the big sky above, in the winter by the black fireplace. And to feel -– this has always been so and always will be. One may sleep on straw, eat rye bread — well then, in the long run one is the healthier for it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’d like to write more but — as I said — I’m not really in the mood for writing, and I wanted to enclose a note for <rs type="pers" key="1354">Serret</rs>, which you must just read, since I write in it about what I wanted to send before long, especially because I want to let Serret see my particular figure studies. Regards,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
                    <rs type="pers" key="1354">Serret</rs> may agree with you that making good things and selling are quite separate. But there’s no truth in that. When the public saw <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs> at last, his work collected together — then the public in both Paris and London was <hi rend="ital">enthusiastic</hi>. And who was it who had stood in the way and rejected Millet? — the dealers — the so-called <hi rend="ital">experts</hi> &amp;c.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> I ask you, would a Mouret<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> have said something like that, to keep talking about business?</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Theo had written about <rs type="pers" key="1354">Serret</rs> at the end of November 1884; <ref target="let408.xml">see letter 408</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh told his brother in <ref target="let502.xml">letter 502</ref> that he had started drawing figures again.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Theo frequently did business with the art dealer <rs type="pers" key="818">Thomas Wallis</rs> (<hi rend="ital">Getty, Goupil Ledgers</hi>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Sale of building scrap </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2511">F 1230 / JH 770</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>We do not know which drawings of heads Van Gogh gave <rs type="pers" key="821">Van Wisselingh</rs>. The art dealer had come to see him in September 1883 (<ref target="let351.xml">letter 351</ref>); Van Gogh was very much occupied with drawing heads between October 1882 and March 1883.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">The potato eaters </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2135">F 1661 / JH 737</rs>). We do not know which one <rs type="pers" key="821">Van Wisselingh</rs> had. It may be the impression that the Gemeentemuseum (The Hague) acquired through J.H. de Bois in 1929. Cf. Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, p. 98.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This insulting letter from <rs type="pers" key="1306">Van Rappard</rs> is <ref target="let503.xml">letter 503</ref>. By the remark that Van Rappard had ‘so obviously’ been in The Hague before he wrote, Van Gogh is insinuating that he had been influenced by <rs type="pers" key="787">H.G. Tersteeg</rs> and his colleagues, with whom relations had broken down since the spring of 1882; <ref target="let208.xml">see letters 208</ref> ff.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Hennebeau is the director of the mines in Montsou in <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs>’s novel <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="413">Germinal</rs>
                        </hi>. He had previously lived in Paris, where he worked ‘with strict honesty, did not speculate, remained at his post, like a soldier’ (d’une honnêteté stricte, ne spéculait point, se tenait à son poste, en soldat’). Once he becomes director, his marriage breaks down and in his unhappiness he throws himself into his work; this is described in several passages, for example: ‘With every catastrophe in his life, he took refuge in the strict execution of orders received, he made the military discipline under which he lived, his reduced portion of happiness’ (A chaque désastre de son existence, il se réfugiait dans la stricte exécution des ordres reçus, il faisait de la discipline militaire où il vivait, sa part réduite de bonheur). See Zola 1960-1967, vol. 3, pp. 1305, 1450.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>The passage from <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="413">Germinal</rs>
                        </hi> in <ref target="let506.xml">letter 506</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>A ‘hannekemaaier’ is a grass-mower, an agricultural labourer of German origin.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
      <ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="737">Sensier</rs> gives some examples of the good reception given to <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>’s works towards the end of his life, including at the Exposition Universelle of 1867 and at the Paris sale in 1873. See Sensier 1881, pp. 301, 358. ‘Enthusiastic’ here is probably a reference to the article ‘<rs type="lit" key="582">Le Salon</rs>’ by <rs type="pers" key="700">Mantz</rs> from which Van Gogh had already quoted in <ref target="let506.xml#n-16">letter 506, n. 16</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Octave Mouret, a character in <rs type="pers" key="836">Zola</rs>’s cycle <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="417">Les Rougon-Macquart</rs>
                        </hi>, marries Mrs Hédouin, who manages the department store <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="275">Au bonheur des dames</rs>
                        </hi>. He is an ambitious entrepreneur and his modern shops are successful. Van Gogh referred to him elsewhere, specifically in <ref target="let463.xml">letters 463</ref> and <ref target="let464.xml">464</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>