<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Thursday, 6 August 1885.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let524"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">524</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">419b</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">526</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Nuenen</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 6 August 1885</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Nuenen, on or about Thursday, 6 August 1885.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Theo’s visit to Nuenen <ref target="let510.xml">(510)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b459 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>It appears that the letter was written while Theo was staying in Nuenen, immediately after he and Vincent had talked – at least if we take ‘conversation’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>) literally, and going by the present tense. The atmosphere between the brothers is icy, something that can also be inferred from <ref target="let525.xml">letter 525</ref>. We assume that the present letter was written in the heat of the moment, immediately after they talked, and that it may even have been handed to Theo in person before he left Nuenen. As far as we know, he went on 7 August. On Thursday, 6 August Theo wrote to tell Andries Bonger that he wanted to accept his invitation to come to Amsterdam: ‘I hope to arrive in Amsterdam tomorrow, Friday, evening at 8 o’clock and I hope to find you in good health’ (FR b889, 6 August 1885). Since <ref target="#l-13">ll. 13-14</ref> in the next letter to Theo <ref target="let527.xml">(527)</ref> give cause to assume that it was the first letter after Theo’s departure, we have dated the present letter on or about Thursday, 6 August 1885.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0459" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000615_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000615_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000615_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000615_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000615_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0459" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000615_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000615_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000615_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000615_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000615_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000615_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Hetgeen in ons gesprek mij <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>zeer desoleert is dat waar ik zeg dat ik <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>vrees het dit jaar er voor U spannen zal<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>gij antwoordt: “dat ge merkt ik dit graag zien zou”<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>“dat ge wel ziet ge op mij geen staat kunt maken”<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>“dat ge wel weet ik U stront voor dank retourneeren zou”<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Dit is niet zoo en het desoleert mij dat <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>gij het zoo ziet<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mijn wenk is deze geweest:– beschouw het <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>schilderzaakje van mij niet als een ballast <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>en behandel het niet stiefmoederlijk<c type="kk">/</c> om reden <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>dat het een <hi rend="ital">bootje</hi> kan blijken in een <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>catastrophe waar ’t groote schip vergaat<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>Mijn wenk is en blijft – laat ons <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>dat bootje in goeden staat en zeilvaardig <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>houden althans<c type="kk">/</c> hetzij de storm kome hetzij <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>mijne ongerustheid ongemotiveerd blijke. <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Op het oogenblik ben ik een vaartuigje <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>dat gij op sleeptouw hebt en dat bij wijlen <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>als ballast slechts U voorkomen kan<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Dat trouwens – als ballast – ge kunt <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>achterlaten door het touwtje los te snijden indien ge begeert<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>Maar ik<c type="kk">/</c> die van mijn kleine schuit de <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>schipper ben<c type="kk">/</c> vraag in dit geval<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>wel verre van loskapping van het sleeptouw<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>dat mijn schuitje worde gekalefaterd <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>en geapproviandeerd<c type="kk">/</c> opdat in tijd <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>van nood het beter dienst moge kunnen <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>doen.–</ab>
                <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>
<ab rend="indent">Betwijfelt ge nu de goede trouw <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>van dit verzoek<c type="kk">/</c> dan kan ik er <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>mijnerzijds niets anders aan doen <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>dan stelliger het te herhalen<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>Want ik merk dat aan den kant van <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>de verfrekening mijn eigen schuitje <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>hier &amp; daar lek wordt<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik stop die lekken zooveel ik kan <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>echter en verlies mijn koelbloedigheid <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>nog niet.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Ben ook niet desperaat. <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">Maar waar we misschien beiden in</hi> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">den zelfden storm zullen zijn</hi> spreek <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>ik stellig en naar ik meen in ons <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>beider belang<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Uw antwoord op mijn vraag kan ik aldus <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>resumeeren: “’t kan zijn er storm komt maar <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>ook in dat geval<c type="kk">/</c> reken niet op hetzij kalefatering <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>hetzij proviand en weet ik genoodzaakt kan <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>wezen door drang van omstandigheden juist <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>het sleeptouw te kappen”<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Dit</hi> antwoord<c type="kk">/</c> maar slechts voor zoover er <hi rend="ital">niet</hi> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">bijkomt</hi> eene verdenking van mijn goede trouw<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>kan ik me voor gezegd houden<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar – door dezen brief roep ik nog eens U toe <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>dat mijn verzoek om versterking in ons beider <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>belang kan blijken te zijn en ik het niet <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>uit egoisme alleen doe<c type="kk">/</c> gelijk ge veronderstelt. <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Dat in geval van storm ik <hi rend="ital">in alle geval wil</hi> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">maar misschien ook kan</hi> U van eenig nut en dienst <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>wezen<c type="kk">/</c> maar dat zulks onmogelijk wordt in <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>geval mijn eigen schuit (wat ik echter zoek <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>te voorkomen) nog vóór het moment in kwestie <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>vol water loopt<c type="kp">_</c>– <hi rend="ital">Dat</hi> zoek ik echter <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>zelf wel te voorkomen maar toch zou ik <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>U niet toeroepen zonder noodzakelijkheid<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>Bang in gevaar ben ik ook niet maar ik <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>zoek bereid te zijn tegen dat de nood aan den <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>man komt evenwel.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Komt het U nu ongemotiveerd voor dat ik <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>er op aandring langzamerhand <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>mijn<c type="kk">/</c> maar ik zou liever zeggen <hi rend="ital">ons</hi>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> schilderzaakje de kern te laten worden <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>van zaken die we zamen verder ondernemen <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>konden<c type="kk">/</c> ik voor mij dring er op aan toch <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>dat het iets worden kan en zal als we genoegzaam <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>eendragtig kunnen blijven.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als ik niet dezelfde idees heb als gij<c type="kk">/</c> verdenk me <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>niet van kwade trouw of enfin lage bedoelingen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>het zij jegens U het zij jegens t’huis<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Jegens t’huis doe ik niets wat ik niet ’t regt <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>heb te doen<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik absoluut en voor altijd mijzelf <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>buiten hun zaken houd<c type="kp">_</c>– Geen raad vraag of opdring<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>ten eenemale op mijn eigen gebied blijf – en ook zelfs <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>mijn gevoelen over hunne zaken voor mij houde<c type="kk">/</c> daar <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>we elkaars belangen toch niet begrijpen<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
<ab rend="indent">En jegens U spreek ik nu en zal ik verder <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>spreken als iemand wiens zaken in de schilderijen <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>zijn tot een ander iemand wiens zaken in de schilderijen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>en op het andere gebied <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">kom ik niet in</hi>.</ab>
                <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>
<ab rend="indent">En de kwestie die ik begon met U te bespreken <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>is deze<c type="kk">/</c> dat al is er nog zoo veel malaise <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>en al moeten we beiden er ons veel moeite <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>voor getroosten<c type="kk">/</c> we energiek de hand moesten <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>zien te houden aan het schilderzaakje dat <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>zoowel van U als van mij hoort. Ik <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>zeg<c type="kk">/</c> het kan een boot zijn die U eventueel <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>in den storm van dienst kan wezen<c type="kk">/</c> al <hi rend="ital">wensch</hi> <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>ik den storm evenmin als gij dien wenschen kunt.</ab>
                <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="99*" xml:id="l-99s"/>
<ab>b. à. t.</ab>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>What very much distresses me in our conversation is that when I say that I fear it will be tight for you this year, you reply: ‘that you observe that I’d like to see that’, ‘that you see very well that you can’t rely on me’, ‘that you know very well that I would be returning you no thanks for your pains’. This is not so, and it distresses me that this is how you see it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">My suggestion has been this — don’t regard my little painting business as dead weight and don’t treat it harshly, for the reason that it could prove to be a <hi rend="ital">little boat</hi> in a disaster when the big ship is lost. My suggestion is and remains — let’s at any rate keep that little boat in good condition and ready to sail, whether the storm comes or my anxiety proves to be unfounded. At the moment I’m a little vessel which you have in tow and once in a while can only seem to you to be dead weight. Which, by the way — as dead weight — you can leave behind by cutting the rope if you want to. But in this case I, who am the skipper of my small craft, ask 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> that far from having the tow-rope cut, my little craft should be caulked and provisioned so that it may do better service in time of need.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Should you doubt the good faith of this request, then for my part I can do nothing but repeat it more emphatically. For I notice that on the side of the paint bill, my own little craft is springing leaks here and there.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m plugging these leaks as much as I can, though, and am not yet losing my cool-headedness.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Am not desperate either. <hi rend="ital">But since we’ll perhaps both be in the same storm</hi>, I speak emphatically and, I believe, in both our interests.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I can sum up your answer to my question thus: ‘there may be a storm coming but, even in that case, don’t count on either caulking or provisions, and be aware that I may be compelled by the force of circumstances to cut the tow-rope’.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> I can take <hi rend="ital">this</hi> answer as a warning, but only in so far as it’s <hi rend="ital">not accompanied</hi> by suspicion of my good faith.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But — by means of this letter I cry out to you again that my request for reinforcement may prove to be in both our interests, and I’m not doing it just out of selfishness, as you assume. That in the event of a storm, I <hi rend="ital">in all events am willing but perhaps also able</hi> to be of some use and service to you, but that this will be impossible in the event that my own craft fills with water (which I’m trying to prevent, though) before the moment in question. I’m trying to prevent <hi rend="ital">that</hi> myself, though, but still I wouldn’t cry out to you without necessity. I’m not afraid in the face of danger either, but nonetheless I try to be prepared in case disaster strikes.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If it seems to you unfounded that I urge that we should gradually let my, but I would rather say <hi rend="ital">our</hi>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> little painting business become the heart of a business that we could go on to undertake together, for my part I insist that it can and will become something if we can remain sufficiently united.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If I don’t have the same ideas as you, don’t suspect me of bad faith or base intentions anyway, either towards you or towards those at home. I do nothing to those at home that I have no right to do, since I absolutely and always keep out of their affairs. Don’t ask for or urge advice, keep entirely to my own territory — and even keep my feelings about their affairs to myself too, since we don’t understand one another’s interests anyway.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And to you I speak now, and will go on speaking, as someone whose business is in paintings to someone else whose business is in paintings, and <hi rend="ital">I will not intrude on</hi> the other territory.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And the question that I started to discuss with you is this: even if the slump is severe, and even if we both have to take great trouble, we must see to it that we keep an energetic hand on the little painting business that belongs to you as well as to me. I say, it might be a boat that could possibly be of service to you in the storm, although I <hi rend="ital">wish</hi> for the storm as little as you can wish for it.</ab>
<ab>Regards,</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>
  <ref target="let523.xml">Letter 523</ref> to <rs type="pers" key="371">Furnée</rs> is an example of Van Gogh’s efforts to find a solution to the problem of his outstanding paint bills.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh added ‘but ... <hi rend="ital">our</hi>’ (‘maar ... <hi rend="ital">ons</hi>’) later.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>