<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Sunday, 14 February 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let562"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">562</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">453</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">564</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Antwerp</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 14 February 1886</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
    <p>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Sunday, 14 February 1886.</p>
                        <note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
                            <p>Vincent sends <hi rend="ital">Chérie</hi> bu Edmond de Goncourt (<ref target="let559.xml">559</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                        <note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
                            <p>Plan to move to Paris (<ref target="let555.xml">555</ref>)</p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b493 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>See for our dating of Sunday, 14 February 1886: <ref target="let559.xml">letter 559</ref>, <hi rend="ital">Date</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0493" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000668_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000668_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000668_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000668_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000668_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0493" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000668_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000668_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000668_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000668_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000668_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000668_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>ik schrijf U dezer dagen dikwijls &amp; dikwijls hetzelfde<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>maar zie er een bewijs in dat ik èèn ding vooral in t’hoofd heb – <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>de noodzakelijkheid om dien tijd figuurteekenen aan te klampen. <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>Verder – het is egoist als ge wilt – ik wil mijn gezondheid <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>gerestaureerd hebben. Mijn impressie over den tijd dat ik hier <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>ben geweest verandert ook niet – betrekkelijk valt het mij zeer tegen <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>wat ik hier heb gemaakt – maar mijn idees zijn er gewijzigd en <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>verfrischt en dat was het eigentlijk doel dat ik met het naar hiergaan <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>heb voorgehad. Waar echter wat mijn gezondheid betreft ik <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>gemerkt heb dat ik er te veel op vertrouwde en dat ofschoon <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de kern nog goed is ik maar een ruine ben van wat ik <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>had kunnen wezen – Zoo zou het mij geenszins ver<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>wonderen indien gijzelf ook evenzeer dat <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>sterker leven dat mij werd voorgeschreven zoo <hi rend="ital">uitdrukkelijk</hi> <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">mogelijk</hi> noodig hadt.</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Vergis ik me hierin niet<c type="kk">/</c> dan geloof ik zoo dat wij niet <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>te spoedig zamen kunnen zijn<c type="kk">/</c> en ik blijf bezwaar <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>zien in een verblijf buiten. Want al is er de lucht <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>opwekkend<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou er de afleiding en gezelligheid van <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>de stad missen. Waar wij indien we zamen waren nog <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>zoo veel meer aan zouden kunnen hebben.–</ab>
                <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat U betreft<c type="kk">/</c> ik zou er niet over verwonderd zijn indien <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>– mag ik het nu zeggen zoo als ik het denk – het <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>bureauleven U teveel gemecaniseerd had<c type="kk">/</c> laat <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>ons zeggen wel een paar jaar<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">En veel subtiele en fijner en artistieker <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>intelligentie wat gesteriliseerd was<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>Nu hebben we echter juist noodig die weer op te <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>frisschen en te doen herleven. En indien wij <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>nu binnen kort veel meer zamen waren <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>zou ik U in dingen teleurstellen<c type="kk">/</c> ja zeker<c type="kk">/</c> maar <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>niet in alle en niet in manier van kijken<c type="kk">/</c> geloof <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>ik. Ik wil aan ’t begin van ons spreken over <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>een &amp; ander U wel zeggen dat ik wou wij over niet al <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>te langen tijd beiden op de een of andere wijs <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>eene vrouw voor vast hadden. Omdat zulks hoog <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>tijd wordt. en omdat wij indien wij daar heel <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>lang mee wachten er niet beter bij zouden varen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>Toch – dat alles in bedaardheid. Maar het is zoowat <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>het eerste vereischte van sterker leven.– En ik <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>noem het omdat daarin wij een enorme moeielijkheid <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>welligt zullen te overwinnen hebben. En waar veel <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>van afhangt. En ik breek bij dezen daar ’t ijs eens over<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>wij zullen er altijd op terug komen moeten.–</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">En in den omgang met vrouwen leert men zoo veel <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>voor de kunst juist. Jammer dat men met ’t geen <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>men gaandeweg leert niet gaandeweg jong blijft. <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>Maar ware dat zoo<c type="kk">/</c> zou het leven te mooi zijn<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hebt gij de bewuste inleiding van Cherie van de Goncourt <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>gelezen?<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> De massa werk die die lui afgedaan hebben is <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>iets kolossaals als men ’t nagaat.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is zulk een lumineus idee<c type="kk">/</c> het gemeenschappelijk <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>werken en denken<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">En ik vind dagelijks bewijzen voor de stelling dat <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>een groote reden van veel misères onder de artisten <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>gelegen is in hun onderlinge verdeeldheid<c type="kk">/</c> in het niet <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>zamenwerken<c type="kk">/</c> in het niet goed zijn voor elkaar maar valsch<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>En als wij nu verstandiger werden in dat opzigt<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>twijfel ik geen oogenblik of binnen een jaar tijd waren <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>we op een beteren weg en gelukkiger.</ab>
                <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het werk wil mij niet erg vlotten maar ik forceer het ook <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>niet omdat het me eigentlijk zoo veel mogelijk is verboden<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>En ik mij wou reserveeren voor dien eersten tijd te <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>Parijs<c type="kk">/</c> als die het eerst voor de hand mogt liggen zonder <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>nog een tusschenperiode<c type="kk">/</c> tenzij dan van die eene maand. <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>Want ik wou er graag frisch komen.</ab>
                <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het was vandaag – zondag – haast een lentedag – ik heb <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>van morgen alleen een groote wandeling gemaakt overal<c type="kk">/</c> door de <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>stad<c type="kk">/</c> in ’t park<c type="kk">/</c> langs de boulevards. Het was zulk weer dat buiten <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>denkelijk men voor ’t eerst de leeuwrik zal hebben gehoord.</ab>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab rend="indent">En enfin er was iets van opstanding in de stemming.–</ab>
                <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>
<ab rend="indent">Toch wat is alles gedrukt van stemming in de zaken en in <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>de menschen.– ik geloof niet dat het overdrijven is als men de diverse <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>greves<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> &amp;c<c type="kp">_</c> van overal donker inziet.– Voor latere <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>geslachten zijn ze zeker niet nutteloos want <hi rend="ital">dan</hi> zal ’t een <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>gewonnen zaak zijn. Maar voor nu is het natuurlijk voor iedereen <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>die zijn brood moet vinden in zijn werk donker genoeg<c type="kk">/</c> te meer <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>omdat we wel voorzien kunnen ’t van jaar tot jaar al erger en <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>erger zal worden<c type="kp">_</c>– De werkman tegen den burger – <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>is even gemotiveerd als voor honderd jaar de <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>tiers etat tegen de twee anderen.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> En ’t best is te zwijgen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>want de burgers hebben de fataliteit niet mee en we <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>zullen er meer van beleven. we zijn nog lange na niet aan ’t eind. <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>Zoo al is ’t lente – hoeveel duizenden en duizenden <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>loopen er in desolatie.</ab>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik zie net zoo goed als de beste optimist de leeuwrik <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>die opstijgt in de lentelucht.–</ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar ik zie ook het jonge meisje van 20 jaar pas<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>dat gezond had kunnen zijn en – de tering onder de leden <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>heeft – en misschien nog voor ze aan een ziekte sterft <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>in ’t water springt.–</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
<ab rend="indent">Als men altijd in gezelschap is comme il faut en onder <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>eenigermate gegoede burgers<c type="kk">/</c> merkt men dat misschien zoo <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>niet – maar als men zoo als ik een aantal jaren <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>met de la vache enragée gedineerd heeft<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> dan is het <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>niet weg te cijferen dat de groote misère een <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>daadzaak is die gewigt in de schaal legt<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab rend="indent">Genezen moge men niet kunnen<c type="kk">/</c> of redden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>maar men kan het toch meevoelen en er in deelen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>Corot<c type="kk">/</c> die toch sereniteit had als iemand ze had<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>die toch waarlijk de lente wel voelde<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>was hij niet al zijn leven eenvoudig als een werkman <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>en zoo gevoelig voor al de miseres van anderen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>en wat mij trof in een levensbeschrijving van hem – toen <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>hij al zeer oud was in 70-71 keek hij zeker ook <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>nog in de heldere lucht maar – hij bezocht tevens <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>de ambulances waar de gekwetsten lagen te creveeren<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>Laten illusies weggaan – maar wat <hi rend="ital">blijft</hi> is <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>het sublieme – als men aan <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>alles zou twijfelen<c type="kk">/</c> men twijfelt niet aan <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>lui zooals Corot en Millet en Delacroix<c type="kp">_</c> En ik <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>vind dat in momenten als men niet <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>meer geeft om de natuur<c type="kk">/</c> men nog wel geeft <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>om de menschen.</ab>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <hi rend="ital">Kunt</hi> gij mij deze maand nog wat sturen<c type="kk">/</c> ’t zij <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>veel ’t zij weinig maar al was het maar vijf francs<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>laat het dan niet<c type="kk">/</c> en kan het niet dan kan het <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>niet<c type="kp">_</c>– Ik ben wel erg verlangend om Uw <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>beslissing te weten of desnoods gij goed zoudt <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>vinden ik tegen zoowat 1 April reeds naar Parijs <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>kwam.– In elk geval<c type="kk">/</c> schrijf me daar spoedig <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>over<c type="kp">_</c>– Gegroet<c type="kk">/</c> met een handdruk<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="122*" xml:id="l-122s"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-23" n="23">– mag &lt; mag</note>
<note target="l-38" n="38">er &lt; wij er</note>
<note target="l-41" n="41">daarin &lt; daar in</note>
<note target="l-47" n="47">niet &lt; men niet</note>
<note target="l-55" n="55">reden &lt; rede</note>
<note target="l-108" n="108">
                        <hi rend="ital">blijft</hi> is &lt; <hi rend="ital">blijft</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I write to you often these days and often the same, but see it as proof that I have one thing on my mind above all — the need to embark on that period of figure drawing. Moreover — you may call it selfish — I want to have my health restored. My impression of the time that I’ve been here doesn’t change either — in a way I’m very disappointed with what I’ve done here — but my ideas have changed and been refreshed, and that was actually the goal I had in mind in coming here. As far as my health is concerned, though, I’ve observed that I relied on it too much and that, although the core is still good, I’m just a ruin of what I might have been. So it wouldn’t surprise me in the slightest if you were also in just as much need <hi rend="ital">in the strongest possible terms</hi> of that better way of life that was prescribed for me.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If I’m not mistaken in this, then I believe that we can’t be together too soon, and I continue to see drawbacks to a stay in the country. For although the air there may be invigorating, I would miss the distractions and sociability of the city. From which we could benefit so much more still if we were together.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As for you, I shouldn’t be surprised if — if I may now speak as I find — office life had mechanized you too much, let’s say for a good few years. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And a very subtle and more refined and more artistic intelligence was somewhat sterilized. Now, though, that’s what we need to revive again and bring back to life. And were we to be together much more in the near future, I’d disappoint you in things for sure, but not in everything and not in my way of looking at things, I believe. I want to tell you at the start of our conversation about one thing and another that I wish that before too long we could both have acquired a wife, one way or another. Because it’s high time, and because we’d be no better off if we were to wait a long while to do it. Anyway — all that quite coolly. But it’s pretty much a prerequisite for living better. And I mention it because we may perhaps have a huge difficulty to overcome in this respect. And on which much depends. And I’m just breaking the ice about it here; we’ll always have to come back to it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And in relationships with women one learns so much specifically about art. Pity that as one learns by degrees, so by degrees one ceases to be young. But were that not so, life would be too good.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Have you read that introduction to Chérie by <rs type="pers" key="617">De Goncourt</rs> yet?<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> When one looks at it, the mass of work those fellows got through is colossal. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s such a brilliant idea, working and thinking in concert.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And every day I find evidence supporting the proposition that a major reason for many misfortunes among artists lies in the discord between them, in not cooperating, in being nasty, not kind, to one another. And now if we were wiser in this respect, I don’t doubt for a moment that  we’d be on a better path and happier in a year’s time.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m not getting on very well with the work but I’m not forcing it either, because to all intents and purposes it’s actually forbidden me. And I want to save my strength for that initial period in Paris, should that be the most obvious thing to do first, without an intervening period except, then, for that one month. For I’d like to arrive there fresh.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Today — Sunday — it was almost a spring day — this morning I went for a long walk on my own, all through the city, in the park, along the boulevards. It was such weather that in the countryside one would probably have heard the lark for the first time.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And in short there was something of a resurrection in the atmosphere.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">All the same, how depressed the mood is in business and among the people. I don’t think it’s exaggerating when one takes a gloomy view of the various strikes<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> &amp;c. everywhere. They certainly aren’t worthless for later generations, because <hi rend="ital">then</hi> the cause will have been won. But for now, of course, it’s gloomy enough for everyone who has to earn his living, all the more so since we can foresee that it will get worse and worse from year to year. The working man against the bourgeois — is as justified as the third estate against the other two  a hundred years ago.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> And the best thing is to keep quiet, because the bourgeois don’t have fate on their side, and we’ll experience more of it. We’re by no means at the end yet. So although it’s spring — how many thousands and thousands are walking around desolate?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I see just as clearly as the greatest optimist the lark ascending in the spring sky.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But I also see the young girl of barely 20, who could have been healthy and  has contracted consumption — and perhaps will drown herself before she dies of a disease. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">When one is always in respectable company and among reasonably well-to-do citizens, one may perhaps not notice it so much — but when, like me, one has been through very hard times, then it’s impossible to ignore the fact that great hardship is a factor that weighs in the balance.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">One may not be able to cure or save, but one can nonetheless sympathize and share in it. <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs>, who had serenity if anyone did, who truly felt the spring, wasn’t he as simple as a working man and thus sensible of all the misfortunes of others all his life? And something that struck me in a biography of him — when he was already very old in 70-71, he certainly still looked up into the clear sky, but — at the same time he visited the ambulances where the wounded lay dying.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> Illusions may fade — but what <hi rend="ital">endures</hi> is the sublime — if one were to doubt everything, one wouldn’t doubt fellows like Corot and <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="982">Delacroix</rs>. And I think that in moments when one doesn’t care about nature any more, one still cares about people.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you<hi rend="ital"> can</hi> send me a bit more this month, be it a lot or be it little, but even if it’s only five francs, don’t neglect to do it, and if you can’t, you can’t. I’m really looking forward to hearing your decision as to whether for your part you would approve if I were to come to Paris as early as somewhere around 1 April. In any event, write to me about it soon. Regards, with a handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
    <ab>See for this preface to <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="422">Chérie</rs>
                        </hi>: <ref target="let550.xml#n-12">letter 550, nn. 12</ref> and <ref target="let550.xml#n-13">13.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>One of the recent major strikes was the Decazeville strike which had taken place in January.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The working class, <ref target="let539.xml#n-4">see letter 539, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Means: ‘nauwelijks iets gegeten heeft’ (has eaten virtually nothing).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Van Gogh is referring to <rs type="pers" key="616">Gustave Geffroy</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="443">La vie de Corot</rs>
                        </hi>, in which he writes ‘War is declared. <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs> refuses to move away from Paris and even expresses the wish to go to the ramparts and buys himself several guns. Physical fatigue stops him. So he works and makes money from anything to help bring relief from the misery of the siege. He goes round the ambulances and hospitals, emptying his hands and his pockets.’ (Survient la déclaration de guerre. Corot refuse de s’éloigner de Paris, et même il manifeste le désir d’aller aux remparts et s’achète plusieurs fusils. La fatigue physique l’arrête. Il travaille alors et fait argent de tout pour venir en aide aux misères du siège. Il parcourt les ambulances, les hôpitaux, vide ses mains et ses poches.) Printed in Corot 1946, p. 68. In <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="552">Corot. Souvenirs intimes</rs>
                        </hi> <rs type="pers" key="1809">Dumesnil</rs> described how the painter contributed financially to help the wounded in Paris during the Franco-Prussan War (see Dumesnil 1875, p. 88).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>