<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Tuesday, 19 or Wednesday, 20 January 1886.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let553"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">553</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">445</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">556</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Antwerp</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Tuesday, 19 or Wednesday, 20 January 1886</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Antwerp, Tuesday, 19 or Wednesday, 20 January 1886.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b485 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>The record of Van Gogh’s enrolment for <hi rend="ital">drawing </hi>dates from Monday, 18 January. He says in this letter: ‘I’ve already drawn there 2 evenings’ <ref target="#l-57">(l. 57)</ref>, which means it is either the evening of Tuesday, 19 (after the second drawing lesson) or Wednesday, 20 January.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0485" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000657_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000657_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000657_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000657_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000657_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0485" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000657_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000657_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000657_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000657_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000657_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000657_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Waarde Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Wilde U schrijven dat Verlat <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>eindelijk mijn werk heeft gezien en toen <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>hij de twee landschappen zag en het stilleven <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>die ik van buiten<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> medebragt<c type="kk">/</c> zeide hij – “ja maar <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>dat gaat me niet aan” – toen ik hem de <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>twee portretten<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> liet zien<c type="kk">/</c> zeide hij – dat verandert<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>als ’t figuur is kunt ge komen<c type="kp">_</c>– Zoo dat ik <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>dus morgen ga beginnen met in de schilderklas <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>aan de akademie te gaan werken.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Terwijl ik bovendien <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>Vinck (een leerling van Leys van wien ik dingen in <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>de manier van Leys zag, middeneeuwsch) heb <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>gesproken om s’avonds wat antiek te teekenen.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik geloof dat ik met geen van die twee <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>dingen kwaad kan – en ligt kan ik er <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>hetzij voor ’t schilderen ’t zij voor ’t teekenen <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>iets opdoen wat me nuttig kan zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– En <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>in alle geval is het een poging om in kennis <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>te komen met lui. Er werken in de <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>schilderklas en in de teekenklas verscheiden <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>lui van mijn leeftijd<c type="kk">/</c> zag ik in ’t voorbijgaan<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>En zeker als ik met Verlat of Vinck of wie dan ook wat vrienden mogt worden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>zou het mij wat model uithalen. <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>Enfin – dat is vooral het praktische van de <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>zaak.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik moet verder naar twee lui <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>toe ter wille van portretten<c type="kk">/</c> wat daar <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>van komen zal weet ik niet<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>
<ab rend="indent">’t eene is een affaire om twee portretten van <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>een paar zeer mooie meiden te maken – typen met <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>heel donkere oogen<c type="kk">/</c> donker haar – twee zusters <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>die veronderstel ik gemainteneerd worden<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">En het andere is een portret van een <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>getrouwde vrouw<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar ik zeg U<c type="kk">/</c> er is nog niets <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>vast en het kan mislukken<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik weet echter wel dat ik desnoods bereid zou <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>zijn ze voor niets te maken<c type="kk">/</c> juist om me <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>te oefenen.–</ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar, als ge denkt dat ik hetzij daar hetzij <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>elders aan huis moet gaan werken enz<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>het is noodig ik wat doe aan <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>mijn kleeren want ik heb de mijnen twee <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>jaar gedragen en vooral in den laatsten <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>tijd hebben ze geleden. Al was het een pak <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>van b.v. frs 40 ware reeds voldoende<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">En ik moet ook geprepareerd zijn om<c type="kk">/</c> als <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Verlat zegt dat ik dit of dat me moet aanschaffen <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>van schildergerij<c type="kk">/</c> er bij te kunnen.–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>
<ab rend="indent">Daarom.– Tracht mij nog zoo als ik <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>het U vroeg frs 50 te sturen<c type="kk">/</c> dan kan ik <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>de maand rondkomen en zou een <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>nieuwe broek &amp; vest me direkt aanschaffen en <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>de jas in februarij<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het is hier geducht koud, en ik voel <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>me lang niet altijd lekker<c type="kk">/</c> maar <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>enfin als het schilderen gaat komt <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>dat er zoo erg trouwens niet op aan<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik heb 2 avonden reeds ginder geteekend, <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>en ik moet zeggen dat ik geloof het juist <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>voor het maken van b.v. boerenfiguren heel <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>goed is de antieken te teekenen<c type="kk">/</c> mits <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>s.v.p<c type="kp">_</c> niet als ’t gewoonlijk gaat<c type="kp">_</c>– De teekeningen <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>die ik er zie vind ik eigentlijk allen fataal <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>slecht – en radicaal verkeerd. En ik weet wel <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>dat de mijne glad anders is – wie ’t nu bij <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>’t regte eind heeft moet de tijd maar leeren. <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>Gevoel van wat een antiek beeld is <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>hebben ze goddomme <hi rend="ital">geen van allen</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik die in jaren lang geen goede moulure <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>der antieken gezien heb – en die ze hier <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>hebben zijn zeer mooi – en die in die jaren <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>steeds het levend model onder de oogen heb <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>gehad – ik sta verbaasd over 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>de almagtige kennis en juistheid van sentiment <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>van de ouden nu ik het eens goed terugzie<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>– Toch is het te voorzien dat de akademische <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>heeren mij van ketterij zullen beschuldigen <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>maar – que soit<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>
<ab rend="indent">Kon ik met Verlat wat vorderen<c type="kk">/</c> zou ik <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>wel willen. ik vind veel van wat hij <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>maakt en hard en verkeerd van kleur en – <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">verf</hi> – maar <hi rend="ital">ik weet dat hij zijn</hi> <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">goede dagen heeft ook</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>– Dat hij b.v. <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>een beter portret schildert dan de rest <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>grootendeels. En dus wij zullen zien<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Ik blijf mij opgewekt gevoelen ondanks alles<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>juist door dat het mij goed doet in allerlei toestanden <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>tegenovergesteld aan buiten te komen<c type="kk">/</c> en <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>het zou wel kunnen zijn dat ik hier t’huis raakte<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin<c type="kp">_</c>– Maar doe Uw best mij eens spoedig <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>te schrijven en waarachtig het is noodig dat <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>ik die frs 50 nog heb voor de maand. Ik kom <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>er anders niet en de dingen zijn te urgent.</ab>
                <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
<ab rend="indent">Gegroet<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab>b<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-67" n="67">goddomme &lt; godome</note>
<note target="l-89" n="89">Uw &lt; U</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Wanted to tell you that <rs type="pers" key="1420">Verlat</rs> has seen my work at last, and when he saw the two landscapes and the still life that I brought with me from the country,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> he said — ‘yes, but that doesn’t concern me’ — when I showed him the two portraits,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> he said — that’s different, if it’s the figure you can come. So I’m going to begin tomorrow by starting work in the painting class at the academy.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> While I’ve moreover arranged with <rs type="pers" key="1419">Vinck</rs> (a pupil of <rs type="pers" key="1176">Leys</rs>’s by whom I saw things in the manner of Leys, medieval) to draw some plaster casts in the evening.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t think I can go wrong with either of these two things — and I can probably learn something there that could be useful to me, be it for painting, be it for drawing. And in any event it’s an attempt to get to know people. I saw in passing that there are several people of my age working in the painting class and in the drawing class. And certainly if I were to become a little friendly with <rs type="pers" key="1420">Verlat</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="1419">Vinck</rs> or whomever, it would save me money for models. Anyway — that’s mainly the practical side of the matter. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I also have to go to two people with a view to portraits; I don’t know if anything will come of it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">One is a matter of making two portraits of a couple of very pretty girls — types with very dark eyes, dark hair — two sisters who, I imagine, are being kept.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And the other is a portrait of a married woman. But I tell you, nothing is settled yet and it could fall through.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I do know, though, that if need be I’d be prepared to do them for nothing, just so that I can practise.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But, when you think that I’ll have to go and work either there or elsewhere at someone’s home etc., I’ll have to do something about my clothes, because I’ve been wearing mine for two years and they’ve suffered, particularly recently. If it were just a 40-franc suit, say, it would be good enough.</ab>
<ab rend="indent"> And if <rs type="pers" key="1420">Verlat</rs> says that I have to purchase some painting gear or other, I also have to be prepared to do that too. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Accordingly. Try, as I asked you, to send 50 francs, then I can get by till the end of the month and would buy myself a new pair of trousers and waistcoat at once, and the jacket in February.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s dreadfully cold here, and I often feel far from well, but anyway, as long as the painting’s going, that doesn’t really matter.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve already drawn there 2 evenings, and I have to say that that I think it’s very good to draw plaster casts, particularly for doing peasant figures, for instance, but not, please, as it’s usually done! I actually find all the drawings I see there hopelessly bad — and fundamentally wrong. And I know that mine are totally different — time will just have to tell who’s right. Damn it, <hi rend="ital">not one of them</hi> has any feeling for what a classical statue is.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I, who haven’t seen a good cast of a classical piece for years — and the ones they have here are very fine — and who have always had live models in front of me in those years — I’m astounded by 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> the ancients’ immense knowledge and aptness of sentiment now that I really see it again.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> Anyway. All the same, it’s to be expected that the academic gentlemen will accuse me of heresy, but — so be it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’d like to make some progress with <rs type="pers" key="1420">Verlat</rs> if I could. I find much of what he does both hard and wrong in colour, and — <hi rend="ital">paint</hi> — but <hi rend="ital">I know that he also has his good days</hi>. That, for instance, he paints a better portrait than most of the others. And so we’ll see. I continue to feel cheerful in spite of everything, precisely because it does me good to be in all sorts of circumstances so unlike the country, and it could well be that I found myself at home here.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Anyway. But do your best to write to me soon, and it’s really necessary that I have that extra 50 francs for the month. I won’t manage otherwise, and things are too urgent.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Regards.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours truly,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
    <ab>The paintings Van Gogh brought with him from Nuenen were an unknown ‘mill’, <hi rend="ital">Avenue of poplars</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2538">F 45 / JH 959</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Still life with Bible</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2535">F 117 / JH 946</rs>). <ref target="let542.xml#n-3">See letter 542, nn. 3</ref>
                        <ref target="let542.xml#n-5">-5.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>One of the portraits was probably <hi rend="ital">Portrait of an old man</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2541">F 205 / JH 971</rs>). The second portrait may have been one of the portraits of women referred to in <ref target="let550.xml">letter 550</ref>. Cf. <ref target="let552.xml#n-9">letter 552, n. 9.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Van Gogh had enrolled at the Koninklijke Academie van Beeldende Kunsten on Monday, 18 January. The Certificate of Registration only refers to his enrolment in the evening ‘Classical Statues’ drawing class (FR b1495; illustrated in cat. Amsterdam 2001, p. 14, ill. 5). There is no record of his having attended the ‘Figure’ painting class that <rs type="pers" key="1420">Verlat</rs> taught during the day, but that course was virtually at an end anyway, as we learn from <ref target="let555.xml">letter 555</ref> (Antwerp, Bibliotheek Koninklijke Academie, Register 1885-1891, inv. no. 289). His fellow student Victor Hageman recounted his recollections of Van Gogh’s arrival at the Academy to the biographer Louis Piérard; Van Gogh burst into the Academy like a bomb, and his clothes – a blue stockman’s smock and a fur cap – and his furious manner of painting and drawing caused a sensation. See Louis Piérard, ‘Van Gogh à Anvers’, <hi rend="ital">Les Marges</hi> 13 (1914), pp. 47-53 and <hi rend="ital">Verzamelde brieven</hi> 1973, vol. 3, pp. 159-162.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>The history painter <rs type="pers" key="1419">Frans Kasper Huibrecht Vinck</rs> studied with <rs type="pers" key="1176">Henri Leys</rs> around 1866 and was very much influenced by him. He was an instructor at the Academy, associated with at least the grade three course, of which the subject ‘Shaded drawing of ornaments of different styles and of the bust’ (‘Dessin ombré d’ornements de différents style et de buste’) was a part. The <hi rend="ital">Jaarlijksch Verslag</hi> lists <rs type="pers" key="587">E. Dujardin</rs> as the teacher for these drawing lessons, but it can be inferred from <ref target="let555.xml">letter 555</ref> that Van Gogh had spoken to Vinck himself. See <hi rend="ital">Koninklijke Academie der Schoone Kunsten te Antwerpen. Academisch Jaar 1885-1886. Jaarlijksch Verslag</hi>. Antwerp 1886, and cat. Amsterdam 2001, p. 13 (n. 22).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>These two women were discussed in <ref target="let550.xml">letter 550</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>This passage may have been prompted in part by reading ‘<rs type="lit" key="585">Sur une Vénus</rs>’ by <rs type="pers" key="708">Guy de Maupassant</rs> in the most recent <hi rend="ital">Gil Blas</hi>, that of 12 January 1886 (we know from <ref target="let552.xml">letter 552</ref> that Van Gogh read this magazine). In it Maupassant wrote lyrically about the <hi rend="ital">Syracuse Venus</hi> (3rd century BC.), with her voluptuous curves: ‘Never has the human form seemed more wonderful yet more disturbing to me … It is at the same time a symbol and the faithful expression of a reality … It is a woman’s body which expresses all the true poetry of a caress’ (Jamais la forme humaine ne m’est apparue plus admirable et plus troublante ... Elle est en même temps un symbole et l’expression exacte d’une réalité ... C’est un corps de femme qui exprime toute la poésie réelle de la caresse). See also <ref target="let557.xml#n-10">letter 557, n. 10,</ref> and Sund 1992, pp. 150-152, where the classical statue and Maupassant’s response to it are linked to some of Van Gogh’s drawings of this period.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>