<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Emile Bernard. Arles, between Wednesday, 19 and Tuesday, 25 September 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let684"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">684</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">B16</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">688</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Emile Bernard</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Arles</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between Wednesday, 19 and Tuesday, 25 September 1888</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Emile Bernard. Arles, between Wednesday, 19 and Tuesday, 25 September 1888.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Exchange of portraits with Bernard and Gauguin <ref target="let680.xml">(680)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Bernard’s military service <ref target="let575.xml">(575)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>New York, Thaw Collection, The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>On 18 September Vincent told Theo about receiving a letter from Bernard (<ref target="let682.xml">see letters 682</ref> and <ref target="let683.xml">683</ref>). Those letters, however, give no indication that he had already replied, which increases the likelihood that this one had not yet been written. He did tell Theo about his reply in <ref target="let687.xml">letter 687</ref> of 25 September. There are no further clues to help us pinpoint the date more accurately, so we have dated the present letter between Wednesday, 19 and Tuesday 25 September 1888.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <surface n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="684_1r.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="684_1rt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="684_1rR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="684_1rRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="684_1rRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="684_1rL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="684_1rLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="684_1rLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
        <surface n="Sheet number 1 not found." xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="684_1v.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="684_1vt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="684_1vL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="684_1vLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="684_1vLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="684_1vR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="684_1vRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="684_1vRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher copain Bernard.</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Merci de ta lettre<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>mais ce qui m’etonne un peu c’est de t’entendre <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>dire “oh pour faire le portrait de Gauguin <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>pas moyen!”<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Pourquoi pas moyen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>bêtises tout cela. Mais je n’insiste <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>pas et aussi categoriquement nous <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>ne parlerons plus de cet échange<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Alors même pour lui de son côté <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Gauguin n’y a même pas songé à faire <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>le tien<c type="kp">_</c>– Voila des portraitistes<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>cela vit si longtemps à côté l’un <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>de l’autre et cela ne s’entend pas <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>pour poser l’un pour l’autre et <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>cela se separera sans s’être mutuellement <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>pourtraicturé. Bon! je n’insiste <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>pas<c type="kp">_</c>– Et je le repète<c type="kk">/</c> il n’est plus <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>question de l’echange.</ab>
                <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’espere bien un jour alors faire <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>ton portrait et celui de Gauguin <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>moi-même<c type="kk">/</c> la première fois que <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>nous tomberons ensemble. <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>ce qui ne peut manquer d’arriver.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">De ces jours ci je vais faire le portrait <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>de ce sous-lieutenant des zouaves dont <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>je t’ai parlé qui va maintenant partir <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>pour l’Afrique.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pourquoi ne m’as tu point répondu <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>au sujet de tes projets quant à <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>ton service militaire.</ab>
                <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maintenant parlons un peu de <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>ce que tu dis que tu y songes à <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>venir passer l’hiver à Arles.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Moi je me suis installé ici expres d’une <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>facon à pouvoir caser quelqu’un en <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>cas de besoin<c type="kp">_</c> Si Gauguin vient <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>pourtant<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                    <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/> Il ne s’est pas catégoriquement <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>dédit encore<c type="kk">/</c> dans tous les cas.</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mais même si je pouvais te loger je ne <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>vois pas que tu puisses bien te nourrir <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>ici à moins de 3 francs par jour. <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>et j’aimerais mieux dire 4 francs. <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>Naturellement nous pourrions faire<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>en cas de dèche<c type="kk">/</c> bien des repas à bon <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>marché à l’atelier<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="ital">certes</hi> on peut economiser de cette facon<c type="kk">/</c> tout de même <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>la vie ici<c type="kk">/</c> je te le dis<c type="kk">/</c> revient un peu plus <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>chère qu’à Pont Aven où je crois que tu payes<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>n’est ce pas<c type="kk">/</c> fr<c type="kp">_</c> 2.50 par jour seulement et <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>cela pour le tout. logement compris.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Et si ce qui te tenterait le plus – faire de <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>la peinture dans les bordels – ce qui certes est <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>excellent – ne pouvait pourtant pas ici se <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>faire à l’oeil<c type="kp">_</c>– Attends donc pour cela <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>jusqu’à que tu aies ton uniforme<c type="kk">/</c> les soldats <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>y peuvent là-dedans ici et ailleurs un tas <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>de choses à l’oeil. Moi par exemple <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>– il est vrai que je viens de faire cette etude <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>de<hi rend="ital"> </hi>café de nuit<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> – mais cela<c type="kk">/</c> quoique ce soit <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>une maison de passe et que de temps à autre <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>on y voit une putain atablée avec son type – <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>moi dis je – je n’ai pas encore pu faire <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>un bordel proprement dit <hi rend="ital">justement à cause de ce que</hi> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">cela me coûterait plus d’argent que je n’en aie nécessairement pour</hi> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">le faire un peu bien et sérieusement</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>Et que je m’abstiens de le commencer avant <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>que je me sente assez solide quant au <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>porte monnaie pour pouvoir le mener à <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>bonne fin<c type="kk">/</c> ce tableau. Maintenant <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>je ne dis pas. Nous irions prendre <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>des bocks là-dedans<c type="kk">/</c> nous y ferions <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>des connaissances<c type="kk">/</c> nous travaillerions <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>moitié d’imagination<c type="kk">/</c> moitie avec un <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>modèle<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> Et si nous voulions je ne <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>dis pas que cela ne soit pas possible <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>de le faire. Mais moi pour un<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>maintenant je suis <hi rend="ital">pressé pour rien</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>Les projets cela rate si souvent et les meilleurs <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>calculs qu’on fait; tandis qu’en profitant <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>des hasards et en travaillant au jour le <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>jour sans parti-pris on fait un tas de choses <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>imprévues<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je ne peux donc aucunément t’engager <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>à venir ici dans le but expres – sans aucun doute <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>excellent – de faire des bordels. Je le repète<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>une fois soldat tu auras une occasion splendide <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>pour cela et dans ton propre interêt tu ferais <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>peut être bien d’attendre jusqu’à que tu aies ton uniforme<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mais mon cher copain Bernard je <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>veux être bien clair et net à te dire<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>viens donc passer ton temps en Afrique<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>Le midi t’enchantera et te fera grand <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>artiste<c type="kk">/</c> Gauguin lui-même doit sa <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>supériorité au midi.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Moi je regarde <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>le soleil plus fort d’ici depuis des mois et <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>des mois maintenant. et le resultact est que ce qui reste surtout <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>debout pour moi<c type="kk">/</c> cette experience faite<c type="kk">/</c> au point de vue de la <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>couleur<c type="kk">/</c> c’est Delacroix et Monticelli<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>ces peintres qu’actuellement on dit à tort <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>être des romantiques purs<c type="kk">/</c> des gens <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>d’imagination exagérée<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin mais <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>vois tu<c type="kk">/</c> le midi qui a été fait si sèchement par <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>Gerome et Fromentin<c type="kk">/</c> à partir déjà d’ici est essentiellement <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>un pays dont on ne saurait interpreter le <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>charme intime que par la couleur de coloriste<c type="kp">_</c> J’espere <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>que tu m’écriras de nouveau bientôt. je n’ose prendre sur moi d’engager <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>qui que ce soit à venir ici<c type="kk">/</c> si quelqu’un vient de son propre mouvement <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>c’est ma foi son affaire mais pour <hi rend="ital">recommander</hi> la chôse<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>jamais je ne le ferai<c type="kp">_</c> Pour moi je reste ici et naturellement cela <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>me ferait bien plaisir que tu passerais l’hiver ici<c type="kp">_</c> Poignée <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>de main<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="110*" xml:id="l-110s"/>
<ab>t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="110*"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-70" n="70">bocks &lt; bochs</note>
<note target="l-78" n="78">fait; &lt; fait</note>
<note target="l-95" n="95">ce &lt; Ce</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear old <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>.</ab>
<ab>Thanks for your letter, but what surprises me a little is to hear you say, ‘Oh, no way of doing <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s portrait!’<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Why no way? That’s all rubbish. But I’m not pressing the point, and so we categorically won’t mention that exchange any more. So even Gauguin, for his own part, hasn’t even thought of doing yours. Here you have portraitists, living for so long side by side and they don’t agree on posing for each other and they’ll separate without having portrayed each other. Well! I’m not pressing the point. And I repeat, there’s no longer a question of an exchange.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">So I really hope to do your portrait and <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s myself one day, the first time we get together. Which is bound to happen. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">One of these days I’m going to do the portrait of that second <rs type="pers" key="515">lieutenant</rs> of Zouaves whom I’ve spoken to you about, who’s now on the point of leaving for Africa.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Why haven’t you replied to me about your plans regarding your military service?</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now let’s talk a little about what you say, that you’re thinking of coming to spend the winter in Arles.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> I’ve deliberately set myself up here in such a way as to be able to fit someone in if necessary. If <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> comes, however.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> He still hasn’t categorically said no, in any case.</ab>
<ab>But even if I could put you up, I don’t see that you could feed yourself well here for less than 3 francs a day. And I’d prefer to say 4 francs. Naturally, in the case of being broke, we could make many meals cheaply at the studio, <hi rend="ital">certainly</hi> we could save that way; all the same, living here, I tell you, comes a bit dearer than in Pont-Aven, where I believe you’re paying, aren’t you, only 2.50 francs a day, and that’s for everything. Lodging included. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And what if the thing that would tempt you the most — painting in the brothels — which is certainly excellent — couldn’t after all be done here for free? Wait for that until you have your uniform, then; here and elsewhere, soldiers can do a whole lot of things in it for free. I, for example — it’s true that I’ve just done that study of a night café<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> — but that, although it’s a house of assignation, and from time to time you see a whore sitting there at a table with her fellow — I myself, I say, I haven’t yet been able to do a brothel as such, <hi rend="ital">precisely because it would cost me more money than I’m forced to have, to do it reasonably well and seriously. </hi>And because I refrain from beginning it before I feel sufficiently sure, as far as the wallet goes, of being able to complete that painting properly. Now, all right. We’d drink some glasses of beer in there, we’d meet people there; we’d work half from the imagination, half with a model.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> And if we wanted to, I’m not saying that it might not be possible to do it. But I for one, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> I’m <hi rend="ital">not in any hurry for anything</hi>, now. Projects so often fall through, and the best calculations you make; while by taking advantage of chance, and working from day to day without bias, you do a whole lot of unforeseen things.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">So in no way can I encourage you to come here with the express purpose – excellent, without any doubt — of doing brothels. I repeat, once you’re a soldier, you’ll have a splendid opportunity for that, and in your own interest you would perhaps do well to wait until you have your uniform.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But, my dear old <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, I want to be very clear and plain in saying to you, do come and spend your time in Africa. The south will delight you and make you a great artist; <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> himself owes his superiority to the south.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> I’ve been looking at the stronger sun down here for months and months now. And the result is that, from the point of view of colour, what remains more than anything for me, having gained the experience, is <rs type="pers" key="982">Delacroix</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1240">Monticelli</rs>, those painters who nowadays are wrongly said to be pure romantics, people of exaggerated imagination. But anyway, do you see, the south, that was done so drily by <rs type="pers" key="1044">Gérôme</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1019">Fromentin</rs>, is from this place on essentially a region whose intimate charm could only be interpreted by a colourist’s colour. I hope that you’ll write to me again soon. I daren’t take it upon myself to encourage just anyone to come here; if somebody comes of his own accord, well, that’s his business, but as far as <hi rend="ital">advising </hi>the thing, I’ll never do it. For myself, I’m staying here, and naturally it would please me greatly if you were to spend the winter here. Handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>A letter from Van Gogh to <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, written between the preceding letter and this one, has been lost; <ref target="let680.xml#n-4">see letter 680, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="515">Milliet</rs> the Zouave was introduced to <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> in <ref target="let628.xml">letter 628</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Van Gogh suspected that <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>’s plan to come to Arles was a ‘whim’, so in <ref target="let682.xml">letter 682</ref> he advised Theo not to offer Bernard, who was perhaps thinking of taking <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s place, any sort of contract.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>It would appear that Van Gogh did not finish this sentence. After ‘pourtant’ he originally wrote: ‘ou si un autre viendrait a sa place’ (‘or if someone else were to come in his place’), but then crossed it out.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>This study, which Van Gogh painted at the beginning of September, and which, judging by his choice of words, he must have mentioned in the lost letter, was <hi rend="ital">The night café</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>This passage reflects the ideas of <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>, who were constantly urging Van Gogh to work from memory and the imagination. He followed their advice to the extent of undertaking a few experiments.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>Van Gogh is referring to <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s stay in tropical Martinique between May and October 1887.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>