<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Pont-Aven, Monday, 1 October 1888.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let692"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">692</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">GAC 33</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">697</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Paul Gauguin</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Pont-Aven</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 1 October 1888</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Pont-Aven, Monday, 1 October 1888.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Exchange of portraits with Bernard and Gauguin <ref target="let680.xml">(680)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Gauguin coming to Arles <ref target="let602.xml">(602)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b848 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh received this letter on 3 October 1888, as we learn from <ref target="let695.xml">letter 695</ref> of the same date. On the assumption that a letter from Pont-Aven took two days to reach Arles, we have dated the present letter Monday, 1 October 1888.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>A letter (now lost) from Bernard to Van Gogh was enclosed with this letter (<ref target="let694.xml">see letter 694</ref>).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0848" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001137_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001137_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001137_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001137_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001137_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0848" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001137_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001137_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001137_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001137_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001137_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001137_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Nous avons accompli votre désir, d’une <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>autre façon il est vrai mais qu’importe <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>puisque le résultat est le même. Nos <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>2 portraits.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> N’ayant pas de blanc <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>d’argent j’ai employé de la céruse <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>et il pourrait bien se faire que <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>la couleur descende et s’alourdisse<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Du <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>reste ce n’est pas fait au point de vue de <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>la couleur exclusivement. Je me sens <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>le besoin d’expliquer ce que j’ai voulu <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>faire<c type="kk">/</c> non pas que vous ne soyez apte à <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>le deviner tout seul mais parceque je <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>ne crois pas y être parvenu dans mon <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>oeuvre<c type="kp">_</c>– Le masque de bandit mal <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>vêtu et puissant comme Jean Valjean<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>qui a sa noblesse et sa douceur <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>intérieure. Le sang en rut <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>inonde le visage et les tons de forge en feu <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>qui enveloppent les yeux 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>indiquent la lave de feu qui <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>embrase notre âme de peintre. <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>Le dessin des yeux et du nez <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>semblables aux fleurs dans les tapis <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>persans résume un art abstrait <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>et symbolique<c type="kp">_</c>– Ce petit fond <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>de jeune fille avec ses fleurs <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>enfantines est là pour attester <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>notre virginité artistique<c type="kp">_</c>– Et ce <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Jean Valjean que la societé opprime<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>mis hors la loi, avec son amour<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>sa force, n’est-il pas l’image <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>aussi d’un impressioniste aujourd’hui. <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>Et en le faisant sous mes traits <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>vous avez mon image personnelle <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>ainsi que notre portrait à tous<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>pauvres victimes de la societé<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>nous en vengeant en faisant le <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>bien – ah! mon cher Vincent <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>vous auriez de quoi vous divertir 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>à voir tous ces peintres d’ici <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>confits dans leur mediocrité <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>comme les cornichons dans le <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>vinaigre. Et ils ont beau être <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>gros<c type="kk">/</c> longs ou tordus à verrues<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>c’est toujours et ce sera toujours <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>des cornichons. Eugène, viens <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>voir! Eugène c’est Habert<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>Habert c’est celui qui a tué <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Dupuis vous savez...<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Et sa <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>jolie femme et sa vieille mère<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>tout le bordel quoi! Et <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Eugène peint, écrit dans les <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>journaux, voyage gratis en <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>Première<c type="kk">/</c> monsieur<c type="kp">_</c>– Il y a <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>de quoi rire ici à en pleurer<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>En dehors de son art<c type="kk">/</c> quelle sale <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>existence et est-ce vraiement <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>la peine que Jésus soit mort <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>pour tous ces sales pantins<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>En tant qu’artiste oui<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>en tant que réformateur je <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>ne crois pas.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> Le copain Bernard <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>travaille et tire des plan pour <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>venir aussi à Arles. Laval que <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>vous ne connaissez pas mais qui <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>vous connaît par vos lettres et <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>nos racontars se joint à nous <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>pour vous serrer la main<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab>A vous</ab>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab>Paul Gauguin</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_ol.html">Soleil ardent qui embrase</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_ol.html">arrête ta course echevelée</ab>
                <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_ol.html">je veux sans emphase</ab>
                <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_ol.html">peindre ta face orangée<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_ol.html">pour un <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>mirliton<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-50" n="50">savez &lt; Savez</note>
</div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Vincent</ab>
<ab>We’ve satisfied your desire; in a different way, it’s true, but what does it matter, since the result is the same? Our 2 portraits.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Having no silver white, I used lead white, and it could well happen that the colour becomes darker and heavier.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> And besides, it’s not done exclusively from the point of view of colour. I feel the need to explain what I was trying to do, not that you’re not capable of guessing by yourself, but because I don’t believe that I’ve achieved it in my work. The mask of a thief, badly dressed and powerful like Jean Valjean,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> who has his nobility and inner gentleness. The rutting blood floods the face, and the tones of a fiery smithy, which surround the eyes, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> suggest the red-hot lava that sets our painters’ souls ablaze. The drawing of the eyes and the nose, like the flowers in Persian carpets, epitomizes an abstract and symbolic art. That girlish little background, with its childish flowers, is there to testify to our artistic virginity. And that Jean Valjean, whom society oppresses, outlawed; with his love, his strength, isn’t he too the image of an Impressionist today? By doing him with my features, you have my individual image, as well as a portrait of us all, poor victims of society, taking our revenge on it by doing good — ah! my dear Vincent, you would have plenty to amuse you, 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> seeing all these painters here, pickled in their mediocrity like gherkins in vinegar. Makes no difference whether they’re fat, long or twisted and warty, they’re still, and will always be, nitwit gherkins. Eugène, just look at him! Eugène, that’s <rs type="pers" key="358">Habert</rs>, Habert’s the one who killed <rs type="pers" key="357">Dupuis</rs>, you know...<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> And his pretty wife and his old mother, and the whole bloody lot! And Eugène paints, writes for the newspapers, travels free in First class, sir. There’s enough there to make you laugh till you cry. Aside from his art, what a lousy existence, and was it worth the trouble that Jesus died for all these lousy buffoons? As an artist, yes; 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> as a reformer, I don’t believe so.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Our pal <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> is working and making plans to come to Arles too. <rs type="pers" key="1148">Laval</rs>, whom you don’t know, but who knows you through your letters and our little bits of gossip, joins us in shaking your hand.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours,</ab>
<ab>
                    <rs type="pers" key="1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                </ab>
    <vg:whiteline/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_tr.html">Burning sun who settest all ablaze</ab>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_tr.html">halt thy furious race</ab>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_tr.html">without ado I wish</ab>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_tr.html">to paint thine orange face.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
    <ab rend="html" html="692_01_tr.html">{For a penny whistle<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> }</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="831">Emile Bernard</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Self-portrait with portrait of Gauguin</hi>, 1888 (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs type="ill" key="2261">Ill. 2261</rs>; and <rs type="pers" key="1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>, <hi rend="ital">Self-portrait with portrait of Bernard, ‘Les misérables’</hi>, 1888 (W309/W239) (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs type="ill" key="2262">Ill. 2262</rs>. Van Gogh received the portraits soon afterwards; <ref target="let696.xml">see letter 696</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Lead white has a tendency to darken to black, particularly when it is left unvarnished in a film of oil. See Ashok Roy, <hi rend="ital">Artists’ pigments: a handbook of their history and characteristics</hi>. Washington 1993, vol. 2, p. 72, and for nineteenth-century sources, Carlyle 2001, p. 260.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> titled his painting ‘les misérables’ and dedicated it ‘to my friend Vincent’ (à l’ami Vincent). He also described it in a letter to <rs type="pers" key="1357">Schuffenecker</rs> of 8 October 1888. See <hi rend="ital">Correspondance Gauguin </hi>1984, pp. 248-249.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">At the beginning of <rs type="pers" key="666">Victor Hugo</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="310">Les misérables</rs>
                        </hi> the central character, Jean Valjean, has just been released after serving a term of hard labour. Because of his shabby appearance he is viewed with suspicion and regarded as dangerous. This rejection and exclusion reminds him of the injustice of his prison term and brings his hate to the surface. He turns against the church. Through contact with the bishop, who stands by him in his moral reform, his goodness gradually returns. The desire for vengeance gives way to compassion. Valjean has now become a father to everyone and assumes the care of Cosette, the little daughter of a prostitute. Cf. also <ref target="let333.xml#n-12">letter 333, n. 12.</ref>
                    </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Merlhès believes that Gauguin derived the inspiration for his self-portrait from Hugo’s descriptions of Jean Valjean’s appearance. The contrast of warm and cool colours in the painting reflects the ‘dualism of light and shade, of good and evil’ (dualisme de l’ombre et de la lumière, du bien et du mal) which defines Jean Valjean’s character and plays an important part in Hugo’s oeuvre. See Merlhès 1989, p. 103.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>On 29 April 1888 the painters <rs type="pers" key="357">Félix Dupuis</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="358">Eugène Habert</rs> fought a duel with pistols in the Bois de Boulogne in Paris, and Dupuis was killed. The incident, which sparked off a national debate about the legality of duelling, received wide coverage in the press. Habert was acquitted by the court in June. See <hi rend="ital">Gauguin lettres</hi> 1983, p. 247 (n. 3), and <hi rend="ital">Correspondance Gauguin</hi> 1984, pp. 501-502.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>It is quite conceivable that <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> is referring here to the discussions about Christ between Van Gogh and <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>. In <ref target="let632.xml">letter 632</ref>, which Bernard had shown to Gauguin (<ref target="#n-24">see n. 24</ref> to that letter), Van Gogh calls Christ ‘an artist greater than all artists’ (un artiste plus grand que tous les artistes).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Changes to the verse were made in a different hand; the final version reads:</ab>
<ab>‘Burning sun who passest by</ab>
<ab>halt thy scurvy steed</ab>
<ab>without sleight-of-hand I’d</ab>
<ab>paint thy face O chrome two!’</ab>
<ab>(Soleil ardent qui passe</ab>
<ab>arrête ton coursier scabreux</ab>
<ab>je veux sans passe passe</ab>
<ab>peindre ta face Ô chrome deux!)</ab>
<ab>According to Cooper, <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> wrote the little rhyme himself, and he probably made the changes too. See <hi rend="ital">Gauguin lettres</hi> 1983, p. 249 (n. 4). Merlhès does not comment on this question in <hi rend="ital">Correspondance Gauguin</hi> 1984 and Merlhès 1989.</ab>
</note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>