<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Thursday, 2 May 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let767"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">767</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">589</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">770</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Arles</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 2 May 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Arles, Thursday, 2 May 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Vincent’s first crisis and hospitalization <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Vincent’s plan to join the Foreign Legion <ref target="let763.xml">(763)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Decision regarding Vincent’s admission to the asylum at Saint-Rémy <ref target="let760.xml">(760)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b636 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>In <ref target="let765.xml">letter 765</ref> of 30 April, Van Gogh wrote that he was busy packing up his paintings; now he mentions having sent two crates (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). He also says: ‘It has been very hot today’ <ref target="#l-121">(l. 121)</ref>. On Thursday, 2 May it was relatively warm: on 1 May it had been only 16.5 degrees, whereas on 2 May the temperature rose to 19.4 (<hi rend="ital">Météo-France</hi>). Vincent has clearly not yet received Theo’s letter of 2 May (<ref target="let766.xml">letter 766</ref>), containing his reaction to Vincent’s plans to join the Foreign Legion. For these reasons we have dated the letter to Thursday, 2 May 1889. This date was also ascribed to the letter by Jo van Gogh-Bonger in <hi rend="ital">Brieven </hi>1914, and it is possible that she had a postmark to rely on. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0636" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000870_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000870_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000870_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000870_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000870_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0636" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000870_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000870_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000870_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000870_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000870_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000870_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>de ces jours-ci j’ai expédié <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>deux caisses de toiles. <hi rend="ital">D 58 &amp; 59</hi> – par <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>petite vitesse &amp; cela prendra bien une huitaine de jours <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>encore avant que tu les reçoives<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Il y a un tas de croutes <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>dedans qu’il faudra détruire mais je les ai envoyés tel <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>quels afin que tu pourras garder ce qui te paraitrait <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>être passable. J’y ai ajouté des masques d’escrime <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>et des études à Gauguin<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> et le livre de Lemonnier.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ayant pris la précaution de payer 30 francs <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>à l’euconome<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> en avance je suis naturellement <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>ici encore – mais on ne saurait m’y garder <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>indéfiniment et il est plus que temps de se <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>decider. Songes y bien qu’en m’internant <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>dans un asile cela coûtera cher à la longue <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>quoique moins probablement que de reprendre <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>une maison – recommencer à vivre <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>seul d’ailleurs me fait absolument horreur.– <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>J’aimerais à m’engager; ce que je crains ici <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>c’est – mon accident étant connu ici en ville – <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>qu’on me refuse – mais ce que je redoute <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>ainsi ou plutôt ce qui me rend timide c’est <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>la possibilité<c type="kk">/</c> la probabilité ici d’un refus. Si j’avais quelque <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>connaissance qui pourrait me coller pour <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>cinq ans dans la legion j’irais<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Seulement je ne veux pas que ce soit considéré <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>comme un nouvel acte de folie de ma <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>part et c’est pourquoi je t’en cause ainsi <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>qu’à m<c type="kp">_</c> Salles pour qu’en y allant cela <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>soit en toute serenité et reflexion <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>faite.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
      <ab rend="indent">Car songes y bien<c type="kk">/</c> continuer à depenser <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>de l’argent dans cette peinture alors <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>que les choses pourraient en venir là qu’on <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>manquerait d’argent de ménage<c type="kk">/</c> c’est atroce <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>et tu sais assez que la chance de réussir est <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>abominable. D’ailleurs cela m’a tant frappé <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>que c’est une telle force majeure qui m’aie <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>contrariée.– D’ailleurs dans l’avenir <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>il y aurait possiblement encore les soeurs <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>pour lesquelles il faudrait chercher à prévoir<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>Peut etre – dis-je – mais enfin quoi <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>qu’il en soit: Si je savais qu’on m’accepterait <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>j’y irais à la legion. C’est que je suis <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>devenu timide et hesitant depuis<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>je vis comme machinalement<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Cependant la santé va fort bien <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>et je travaille un peu. j’ai en train <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>une allée de maronniers à fleurs roses <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>avec un petit cérisier en fleur et une plante <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>de glycine et le sentier du parc tâcheté <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>de soleil et d’ombre.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>
<ab rend="indent">Cela fera pendant au jardin qui est <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>dans le cadre en noyer.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Si je te parle de m’engager pour cinq ans <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>ne vas pas songer que je fasse cela dans <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>une idée de me sacrifier ou de bien faire<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Je suis “mal pris” dans la vie et <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>mon etat mental <hi rend="ital">est</hi> non seulement <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>mais <hi rend="ital">a été</hi> aussi – abstrait<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>
<ab rend="indent">de façon que quoi qu’on ferait pour moi <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>je ne <hi rend="ital">peux</hi> pas réflechir à équilibrer ma <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>vie. Là où je <hi rend="ital">dois</hi> suivre une règle comme <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>ici à l’hospice je me sens plus tranquille<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>Et dans le service ce serait plus ou moins <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>la même chôse. Maintenant si certes <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>ici je risque fort d’être refusé parcequ’ils <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>savent que je suis aliéné ou épileptique <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>probablement pour de bon (quoique à ce que <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>j’ai entendu dire il y ait 50 mille epileptiques <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>en France dont 4000 seulement internés <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>et qu’ainsi c’est pas si extraordinaire) <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>peutêtre que à Paris en le disant par ex. <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>à Detaille ou Caran Dache je serais vite <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>casé.–<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> Ce serait pas plus un coup de tête <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>qu’autre chôse – enfin – réfléchissons – mais <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>pour agir<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab rend="indent">En attendant je fais ce que je peux et pour <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>travailler à <hi rend="ital">n’importe quoi</hi>
                    <c type="kk">/</c> peinture compris<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>j’ai passablement de la bonne volonté. <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Mais l’argent que coute la peinture cela <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>m’écrase sous un sentiment de dette et de <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>lâcheté et il serait bon que cela cesse <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>si possible.</ab>
                <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
<ab rend="indent">D’ailleurs j’ai dit une fois pour de bon<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>mieux vaut qu’à present s’il y a un parti <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>à prendre que toi et M. Salles décident <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>pour moi. Et sache le bien<c type="kk">/</c> je ne refuse <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>rien<c type="kk">/</c> pas même d’aller à S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Remy malgré <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>ces obstacles de pension plus elevée que <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>d’abord on esperait<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> et de ne pas avoir <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>complète liberté de sortir dehors pour <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>peindre. Il faudra bien se décider <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>car on ne peut pas indefiniment <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>me garder ici.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je disais à l’euconome que j’etais content <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>de payer ici par exemple 60 francs au lieu <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>de 45 si je pourrais indéfiniment y rester <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>mais leur règlement est à prix fixe parait-il<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>Quoique donc jusqu’à présent à moi on <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>n’aie rien dit<c type="kk">/</c> je crois qu’il serait juste de <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>s’en aller. Je pourrais peutêtre aller de <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>nouveau loger dans le café de nuit où j’ai <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>remisé mes meubles<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> mais... journellement <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>on est en contact alors juste avec mes <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>voisins d’il y a quelque temps car c’est à côté <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>de la maison où j’avais mon atelier.</ab>
                <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dans la ville cependant à présent on ne me <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>dit plus rien et je peins actuellement dans <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>le jardin public sans être beaucoup gêné <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>autrement que par de la curiosité des passants<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’ai relu l’article sur Monet du Figaro<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> et il me <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>parait maintenant beaucoup mieux que d’abord.</ab>
                <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pour les choses materielles ne nous <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>decourageons pas trop mais tâchons <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>au moins d’etre raisonnables là-dedans. <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>C’est toujours bon <hi rend="ital">qu’à la rigueur</hi> je pourrai <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>aller loger dans ce café de nuit ici et même <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>y être en pension car ces gens sont de mes <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>amis – naturellement aussi parcequ’on <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>a été et est leur client. Il a fait tres chaud <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>aujourd’hui ce qui me fait toujours <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>du bien. j’ai travaille avec plus d’entrain <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>qu’il m’etait encore arrivé.</ab>
                <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je te serre bien la main à toi ainsi <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>qu’à ta femme.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>
<ab>t<c type="kp">_</c> à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-18" n="18">m’engager; &lt; m’engager</note>
<note target="l-42" n="42">soit: &lt; soit</note>
<note target="l-43" n="43">irais &lt; iriais</note>
<note target="l-58" n="58">
                        <hi rend="ital">est &lt; </hi>est</note>
<note target="l-59" n="59">
                        <hi rend="ital">a été</hi> &lt; a été</note>
<note target="l-68" n="68">probablement &lt; probable</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I recently sent off two crates of canvases. <hi rend="ital">D58 and 59</hi> – by goods train, and it will take a good week more before you receive them.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> There’s a heap of daubs in there which will have to be destroyed, but I’ve sent them as they are so that you can keep what appears passable to you. I’ve added <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s fencing masks and studies,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and the <rs type="pers" key="688">Lemonnier</rs> book.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Having taken the precaution of paying 30 francs to the <rs type="pers" key="109">bursar</rs>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> in advance I am naturally still here – but they wouldn’t be able to keep me here indefinitely and it’s more than time to decide. Bear in mind that by confining me in an asylum it will cost a lot in the long run, although less probably than taking another house – besides, beginning to live alone again absolutely horrifies me. I would like to enlist; what I fear here is – my accident being known here in town – that I will be turned down – but what I dread, or rather what makes me timid, is the possibility, the probability here of a rejection. If I had some acquaintance who could stick me in the legion for five years I would go.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Only I don’t want that to be considered as a new act of madness on my part, and that’s why I’m talking to you about it as well as to <rs type="pers" key="663">Mr Salles</rs>, so that if I go it will be in all serenity and after due consideration. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
      <ab rend="indent">For bear it firmly in mind, continuing to spend money on this painting when things could come to the point where there was a lack of money for housekeeping, that’s atrocious, and you’re sufficiently aware that the chance of succeeding is abominable. Besides, it has struck me so much that it’s such a <hi rend="ital">force majeure</hi> that has frustrated me. Besides, in the future there would possibly be our <rs type="pers" key="401 407">sisters</rs> too for whom we should try to provide.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Perhaps – I say – but anyway, whatever the case: if I knew that I would be accepted I would go to the legion. It’s that I’ve become timid and hesitant since, I live like a machine.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">However, my health is very good and I’m working a little. I have on the go an avenue of chestnut trees with pink flowers with a little cherry tree in flower and a wisteria plant and the path in the park flecked with sunlight and shade.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It will make a pendant to the garden that’s in the walnut frame.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">If I speak to you of enlisting for five years don’t go and think that I’m doing it with an idea of sacrificing myself or doing good. I’m ‘in a hole’ in life, and my mental state not only <hi rend="ital">is</hi> but also <hi rend="ital">has been </hi>– distracted. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">So that whatever might be done for me I <hi rend="ital">can’t</hi> think of a way of balancing my life. Where I <hi rend="ital">must</hi> follow a rule, like here at the hospital, I feel more tranquil. And in the armed forces it would be more or less the same thing. Now if here I certainly run a strong risk of being rejected because they know that I’m a madman or an epileptic, probably for good (although from what I’ve heard tell there are 50 thousand epileptics in France, of whom only 4,000 are confined, and that it’s thus not so extraordinary), perhaps in Paris by telling it for example to <rs type="pers" key="985">Detaille</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="929">Caran d’Ache</rs> I would soon be found a place.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> It would be no more of an impulse than anything else – anyway – let’s think about it – but in order to act.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the meantime I’m doing what I can, and I have a fair bit of good will to work at <hi rend="ital">anything</hi>, painting included. But the money that painting costs, that crushes me under a feeling of debt and of cowardice, and it would be good for that to stop if possible.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Besides, I’ve said once and for all, better if there’s a decision to be made at present that you and <rs type="pers" key="663">Mr Salles</rs> decide for me. And be well aware, I won’t refuse anything, not even going to St-Rémy, despite these obstacles of the cost of board and lodging being higher than we hoped at first,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> and not having complete freedom to go outside to paint. We must decide anyway, for they can’t keep me here indefinitely. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I was saying to the bursar that I was happy to pay for example 60 francs here instead of 45 if I could stay here indefinitely, but their rule is fixed price, it appears. So, although no one has said anything to me up to now, I think it would be right to leave. I could perhaps go again to lodge at the night café where I’ve stored my furniture,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> but... then I’m in daily contact with my very neighbours from a while ago, for it’s beside the house where I had my studio.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the town, though, at present nobody says anything to me any more, and I’m currently painting in the public garden without being disturbed much other than by the curiosity of passers-by.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve re-read the article on <rs type="pers" key="1222">Monet</rs> from Le Figaro<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> and it now appears much better to me than at first.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards material things, let’s not become too discouraged but let’s try at least to be sensible about them. It’s still good that <hi rend="ital">if necessary</hi> I can go and lodge in that night café here, and even board there, for those people are friends of mine – naturally also because I have been and am their customer. It has been very hot today, which always does me good. I’ve worked with more gusto than I had yet had.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I give you a hearty handshake, you and your <rs type="pers" key="416">wife</rs>.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This consignment can be largely reconstructed. Van Gogh wrote in <ref target="let765.xml">letter 765</ref> that the following works from the consignment should be put on stretching frames: <hi rend="ital">The night café </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2711">F 463 / JH 1575</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The green vineyard</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2726">F 475 / JH 1595</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The bedroom</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Ploughed fields (‘The furrows’) </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2719">F 574 / JH 1586</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Ploughed field with a tree-trunk (‘The furrows’)</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2740">F 573 / JH 1618</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Eugène Boch (‘The poet’) </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2710">F 462 / JH 1574</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The Alyscamps (‘Leaf-fall’)</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2741">F 486 / JH 1620</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The Alyscamps (‘Leaf-fall’) </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2742">F 487 / JH 1621</rs>), ‘the poet’s garden’, <hi rend="ital">The public garden with a couple strolling (‘The poet’s garden’)</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2730">F 479 / JH 1601</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2772">F 455 / JH 1668</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Sunflowers in a vase </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2771">F 458 / JH 1667</rs>), ‘Scabious &amp;c’ and ‘asters and marigolds’ (possibly <hi rend="ital">Zinnias in a majolica jug</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2706">F 592 / JH 1568</rs>); <ref target="let765.xml#n-34">see letter 765, n. 34</ref>). In the present letter Van Gogh mentions a ‘garden that’s in the walnut frame’ <ref target="#l-52">(l. 52)</ref>, so that painting, <hi rend="ital">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>) (<ref target="#n-7">see n. 7</ref> below) was also in the consignment (cf. also <ref target="let777.xml">letter 777</ref>).</ab>
      <ab rend="indent">The consignment contained four versions of <hi rend="ital">Augustine Roulin (‘La berceuse’)</hi>, namely <rs type="ill" key="2762">F 504 / JH 1655</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="2774">F 506 / JH 1670</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="2776">F 507 / JH 1672</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="2775">F 508 / JH 1671</rs>, as well as <hi rend="ital">Joseph Roulin</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2777">F 436 / JH 1675</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Sower with setting sun</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2746">F 450 / JH 1627</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Marcelle Roulin</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2753">F 441 / JH 1641</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Starry night over the Rhône</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2723">F 474 / JH 1592</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Van Gogh’s chair</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2749">F 498 / JH 1635</rs>). <ref target="let774.xml">See letter 774</ref>. It is likely that <hi rend="ital">Gauguin’s chair</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2750">F 499 / JH 1636</rs>) was sent together with its pendant F 498 (cf. <ref target="let736.xml">letter 736</ref>). In addition to the two previously mentioned canvases with sunflowers, the consignment must also have contained <rs type="ill" key="2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="2701">F 453 / JH 1559</rs>, <rs type="ill" key="2702">F 459 / JH 1560</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="2770">F 457 / JH 1666</rs>. <ref target="let774.xml#n-7">See letter 774, n. 7.</ref> <hi rend="ital">Marie Ginoux (‘The Arlésienne’)</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2744">F 489 / JH 1625</rs>) was also in the batch; <ref target="let768.xml#n-26">see letter 768, n. 26.</ref> </ab>
<ab rend="indent">It may be deduced from <ref target="let796.xml">letter 796</ref>, written by <rs type="pers" key="647">Roulin</rs>, that Theo had received the portraits of all the members of the <rs type="pers" key="647 648 649 650 651">family</rs>, so <hi rend="ital">Armand Roulin</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2755">F 493 / JH 1643</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Camille Roulin</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2757">F 538 / JH 1645</rs>), both of which have Theo van Gogh as their provenance, were probably also in the consignment. A comparison of <hi rend="ital">Young man with a cap</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="859">F 536 / JH 1648</rs>) with the two portraits <rs type="ill" key="2754">F 492 / JH 1642</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="2755">F 493 / JH 1643</rs> suggests that this, too, is a portrait of <rs type="pers" key="649">Armand Roulin</rs>. Its provenance, anyway, is from Theo, so it would have been part of this consignment  (see <hi rend="ital">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 177).</ab>
      <ab rend="indent">It emerges from <ref target="let827.xml">letter 827</ref> that the watercolour <hi rend="ital">Breton women in the meadow (after Emile Bernard)</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2761">F 1422 / JH 1654</rs>) was also at Theo’s; it must have been in this last consignment from Arles.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Regarding these studies left behind by <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>, <ref target="let736.xml#n-12">see letter 736, n. 12.</ref> Gauguin had asked Van Gogh in <ref target="let734.xml">letter 734</ref> to send his fencing masks and gloves.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="688">Lemonnier</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="301">Ceux de la glèbe</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let752.xml#n-4">see letter 752, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Read: ‘l’économe’ (bursar). <rs type="pers" key="109">Marius Huard</rs> fulfilled this function at the hospital in Arles (<hi rend="ital">L’indicateur marseillais </hi>1889). </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Vincent is referring to <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="401">Elisabeth</rs>; <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs>, the eldest of the three sisters, was already married.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Avenue of chestnut trees in blossom</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2785">F 517 / JH 1689</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This painting of the park was probably <hi rend="ital">The public garden (‘The poet’s garden’) </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2713">F 468 / JH 1578</rs>). According to Dorn it was <hi rend="ital">Entrance to the public garden</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2718">F 566 / JH 1585</rs>). See Dorn 1990, pp. 189, 438. Unlike that work, however, we know that F 468 definitely had a walnut frame (<ref target="let699.xml">see letter 699</ref>; cf. also <ref target="let673.xml#n-16">letter 673, n. 16</ref>). It is also more likely that Van Gogh, who was very keen on contrasts when choosing pendants, selected a painting of the ‘poet’s garden’ to pair with <rs type="ill" key="2785">F 517</rs>, and not F 566, which shows the same area of the park as in F 517 in an almost identical composition.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘distrait’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Van Gogh links these two artists to the Foreign Legion, because both had painted military scenes. <rs type="pers" key="985">Edouard Detaille</rs> made military history paintings; the caricaturist <rs type="pers" key="929">Caran d’Ache</rs> (the pseudonym of Emmanuel Poiré) had become known in 1886 for his designs for the shadow play ‘L’épopée’ (Epic) about the Napoleonic campaigns for the Cabaret du Chat Noir in Montmartre.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Van Gogh thought at first that the cost of bed and board in the asylum was 80 francs a month (<ref target="let760.xml">letter 760</ref>); in the meantime he had learned from <rs type="pers" key="663">Salles</rs> that the minimum would be 100 francs (<ref target="let765.xml">letter 765</ref>). <rs type="pers" key="568">Peyron</rs> had also written to Theo about this on 29 April 1889. See Hulsker 1993-2, p. 177. When Vincent moved into the asylum, Theo began to make monthly notes in his account book of these expenses; see <hi rend="ital">Account book</hi> 2002, pp. 44-45. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Van Gogh had stored his furniture in the Café de la Gare owned by <rs type="pers" key="382">Joseph Ginoux</rs>; <ref target="let760.xml#n-4">see letter 760, n. 4.</ref> He had lodged there from 7 May to 17 September 1888.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>An allusion to the neighbours’ objections to Van Gogh’s abnormal behaviour, which had led to the petition complaining about him (<ref target="let750.xml">letter 750</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
      <ab>For <rs type="pers" key="706">Mirbeau</rs>’s article ‘<rs type="lit" key="586">Claude Monet</rs>’, <ref target="let754.xml#n-7">see letter 754, n. 7.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>