<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, between about Monday, 8 July and about Friday, 12 July 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let788"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">788</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">598</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">787</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about Monday, 8 July and about Friday, 12 July 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, between about Monday, 8 July and about Friday, 12 July 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Cor’s departure for South Africa <ref target="let784.xml">(784)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Theo’s engagement and marriage to Jo Bonger <ref target="let728.xml">(728)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b646 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>In a letter to Theo and Jo of 16 July 1889, Mrs van Gogh said of this letter that she had received it ‘last week’ (<ref target="#n-1">see n. 1</ref>). For this reason we have dated the letter to some time between Monday, 8 July and about Friday, 12 July 1889.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0646" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000882_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
    <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
        <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000882_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000882_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
    <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000882_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000882_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0646" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000882_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
    <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
        <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000882_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000882_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000882_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000882_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000882_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="nl">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste Moeder,</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>als U zegt dat U een moeder <lb n="2"/>van bijna 70 jaar zijt dan is dat wel waar <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>maar aan Uw schrift zou men dat zeker niet merken <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>want het viel me op dat dat al bijzonder ferm is.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Overigens schreven Theo en Wil me dat U op nieuw <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>jong schijnt te worden<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> – en dat vind ik erg best <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>en is in het leven wel eens meer noodig. Het <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>nieuws betreffende Cor, geen wonder U er mede <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>vervuld zijt en het zal voor weerskanten bar <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>zijn om te moeten scheiden. Hij heeft mijns <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>inziens echter groot gelijk niet te aarzelen die <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>plaats maar aan te nemen. daar het schijnt men <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>op een afstand van die groote mesthoop steden<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>Londen<c type="kk">/</c> Parijs<c type="kk">/</c> niet alleen maar Amsterdam<c type="kk">/</c> Rotterdam <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>en zooveel anderen in Europa<c type="kk">/</c> beter en gelukkiger <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>door de wereld kan komen dan in hun nabijheid<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Er is nog meer natuurlijks in de wereld en goeds <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>dan men hier in ons werelddeel veronderstellen <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>zou. En van Cor vind ik het consequent dat hij <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>naar ginder gaat. Wel niet precies over de <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Transvaal maar b.v. over Australië heb ik <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>dikwijls hooren spreken door wie er van daan <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>waren en er altijd weer naar terugverlangden<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Zoo b.v. ook over Haiti<c type="kk">/</c> over la Martinique <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>waar Gauguin die met me te Arles was<c type="kk">/</c> geweest <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>was.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> En dat de Transvaal met Australie nog <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>al een &amp; ander gemeen zal hebben durf ik <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>wel veronderstellen. Enfin men heeft er kans <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>zich beter te kunnen ontwikkelen en zijn werkkracht <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>te kunnen gebruiken dan in de Europeesche <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>circumlocutie.</ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat nu betreft, beste moeder, het verdriet dat wij hebben en <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>houden over scheiding en verlies, mij dunkt het is <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>instinktmatig dat wij zonder dat in scheidingen niet <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>zouden kunnen berusten en het zal ons waarschijnlijk <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>dienen om bij latere gelegenheden er elkaar <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>aan te herkennen en terug te vinden.– De dingen <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>kunnen nu eenmaal niet op hun plaats blijven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>En toch vallen de appels niet ver van den stam en <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>zullen uit hun pitten vooreerst nog geen brandnetels <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>oprijzen. Verder weet ik er echter niet van.</ab>
                <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>
<ab rend="indent">Van Theo en Jo heb ik goede berigten<c type="kk">/</c> intusschen <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>verwondert het mij minder dan iemand dat hij hoest enz. <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>Soms wenschte ik wel zij buiten Parijs woonden en niet <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>op een 4<hi rend="ss">e</hi> of 5<hi rend="ss">e</hi> verdieping enz<c type="kp">_</c>, en toch<c type="kk">/</c> er op aandringen te <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>veranderen zou ik niet op mij durven nemen omdat Theo <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>een zekere behoefte heeft aan beweging<c type="kk">/</c> zaken en vrienden <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>te Parijs zelf. Laat zijn vrouw zorgen hij zooveel mogelijk <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>zijn ouden hollandschen kost terug vinde<c type="kk">/</c> daar hij een jaar 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>of 10 aan één stuk verstoken is geweest daarvan en <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>met restauratie eten gevoed<c type="kk">/</c> zonder eenig familieleven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Ik heb alle hoop zij dit wel vatten zal en misschien <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>reeds gevat heeft.</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het voornaamste is mogelijk dit: herinnert U zich nog van <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>een historie in dat boek “de pruuvers” waarin verhaald <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>wordt van een zieke die iederen morgen naar de meid keek <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>die den vloer veegde en vond dat zij – “iets geruststellends” had.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>Dat is het voornaamste waar in de meest verschillende en <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>’t verst uiteenloopende ziektegevallen de beterschap voor een <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>vrij aanmerkelijk deel aan kan worden toegeschreven<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Ik zou dus<c type="kk">/</c> hoe wreed dit zij<c type="kk">/</c> de ongerustheid over het al <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>dan niet sterk zijn van het gestel van Theo maar aan haar <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>overlaten en haar een jaartje laten tobben en scharrelen <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>er aan, vóór wij er ons over bekommeren en het komt <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>mij voor dan ons er niet in ’t minst ongerust over <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>schijnen<c type="kk">/</c> zou kunnen blijken een bewijs <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>van ons eigen vertrouwen in “iets geruststellends” <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>in de natuur in het algemeen.</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het komt mij voor dat het hier in den zomer niet heel veel <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>warmer is dan bij ons wat betreft er hinder van hebben<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>daar de lucht hier helderder en zuiverder is<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>Verder hebben we zeer dikwijls veel wind<c type="kk">/</c> le mistral<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Ik heb op ’t heetst van den dag in de korenvelden <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>geschilderd zonder dat het me veel hinderde<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Doch aan het snel geel worden van het koren <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>ziet men soms wel de zon zoo tamelijk kracht <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>hebben kan. Maar de velden zijn bij ons oneindig <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>mooier bebouwd, regelmatiger dan hier waar <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>de grond door de rotsachtigheid van veel <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>plekken niet voor alles geschikt is.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>
<ab rend="indent">Er zijn hier zeer mooie velden olijfboomen die <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>grijs en zilverachtig van groen zijn als knotwilgen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>Dan verveelt de blaauwe lucht mij nooit. Boekweit <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>of koolzaad ziet men hier nooit en over ’t algemeen <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>is er misschien wat minder afwisseling dan bij ons. <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>En juist zou ik zoo graag eens een boekweitveld in bloei <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>schilderen of het oliezaad in bloei of vlas. Maar <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>daar vind ik ligt later in Normandie of Bretagne de <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>gelegenheid toe. Dan ziet men hier ook nooit die <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>bemoste boerendaken op de schuren of hutten van <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>bij ons<c type="kk">/</c> ook geen eikenhakhout en geen spurrie en <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>geen beukenheggen met hun roodbruine blâren <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>en witachtige gekruiste oude stammen.</ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ook geen eigentlijke hei en geen berken die <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>in Nunen zoo mooi waren.</ab>
                <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar wat in ’t zuiden mooi is zijn de wijngaarden <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>waar die zijn in ’t vlakke land of tegen de heuvels aan<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>Ik heb er gezien, en trouwens aan Theo een schilderij <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>van gestuurd<c type="kk">/</c> waar een wijngaard geheel paarsch<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>vuurrood en geel en groen en violet is als de wilde <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>wingerd in Holland.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> Ik zie net zoo graag een wijngaard <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>als een korenveld<c type="kp">_</c> Dan zijn de heuvels vol thijm en andere <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>geurige planten hier zeer mooi en door de helderheid <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>van de lucht ziet men zooveel verder dan bij ons<c type="kk">/</c> van <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>af de hoogten.</ab>
                <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu<c type="kk">/</c> ik eindig met U te zeggen dat ik geloof U in uw <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>schik zijt uw zoon Theo eindelijk tot trouwen <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>gekomen is. Ik zou nu als ik U was maar niet <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>gaan tobben over zijn gezondheid maar wel zou <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>ik zorgen in uw plaats dat ik het van hem gedaan <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>kreeg zijne vrouw en hij U tweemaal s’jaars kwamen <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>bezoeken in plaats van ééns. Vooral nu Cor <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>vertrekt ware dit voor U en hen wel goed. Voor <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>zijn zaken kan ’t hem volstrekt geen kwaad dat <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>zijn gedachten eens afleiding hebben en zijne vrouw<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>wees er verzekerd van<c type="kk">/</c> zal het U niet kwalijk nemen indien <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>U de lust om nu en dan met haar naar Holland te komen <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>bij hem opwekt. Vergeet het niet dat wij evenveel redenen tot <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">on</hi>dankbaarheid als tot dankbaarheid hebben jegens de Parijsche <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>zaken en in uw kwaliteit van Moeder van bijna 70 <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>jaren moogt U dat wel eens laten gelden.</ab>
                <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>
<ab rend="indent">In gedachten omhels ik U en met een handdruk voor <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>Cor wensch ik hem regt goeden moed toe in zijn onderneming<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>Geloof me steeds</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="124*" xml:id="l-124s"/>
<ab>Uw liefh.</ab>
                <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear <rs type="pers" key="524">Mother</rs>,</ab>
    <ab>If you say that you’re a mother approaching 70 then it must be true, but one would certainly not tell it from your writing, for it struck me that it’s exceptionally firm.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> What’s more, Theo and <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> wrote to me that you seem to be getting young again<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> – and I think that’s very good and is sometimes needed in life. The news about <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> – no wonder you’re taken up with it and it will be hard on both sides to have to part. To my mind, though, he’s absolutely right not to hesitate to accept this position, since it seems that one can get through the world better and more happily at a distance from those great dung-heap cities, not only London, Paris, but Amsterdam, Rotterdam and so many others in Europe, than in their vicinity. There is more that’s natural in the world and good than one would suppose here in our continent. And I think Cor’s being consistent going there. I’ve often heard talk, not about the Transvaal precisely, but about Australia, for instance, by those who came from there and always longed to go back.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> The same about Haiti, say, about Martinique where <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>, who was with me in Arles,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> had been. And I dare suppose that the Transvaal will have one thing and another in common with Australia. Anyway, one has a chance to be able to develop and to be able to use one’s energy better than in the European circumlocution.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now, my dear <rs type="pers" key="524">mother</rs>, as regards the sorrow that we have and retain about parting and loss, it seems to me that it’s instinctive, that without it we wouldn’t be able to accept partings, and it will probably serve us on later occasions to recognize and find one another again. Things simply can’t stay in one place. And yet the apples never fall far from the tree, and stinging nettles won’t spring from their pips just yet. For the rest, though, I don’t know.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve had good reports from Theo and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>; meanwhile it surprises me less than anyone that he’s coughing etc. Sometimes I wish they lived outside Paris and not on the 4th or 5th floor etc., and yet I wouldn’t dare presume to urge a change, because Theo has a certain need for movement, business and friends in Paris itself. His wife should see to it that he returns to his old Dutch diet as far as possible, since he’s been deprived of it for 10 years 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> or so at a stretch, and fed on restaurant food without any family life. I have every hope she’ll understand this, and perhaps already has understood.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The main thing is possibly this: do you remember a story in that book ‘De pruuvers’, where there’s an account of a sick person who watched the maid sweep the floor every morning and thought that she — had ‘something reassuring’?<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> That’s the main thing to which recovery can be attributed to a quite significant degree in the most dissimilar and utterly divergent illnesses. So, cruel as this may be, I should simply leave the disquiet about whether or not Theo’s constitution is strong to her, and let her worry and work at it for a year or so before we concern ourselves about it, and it occurs to me that our appearing not in the least anxious about it could turn out to be a sign of our own confidence in ‘something reassuring’ in nature in general.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It occurs to me that in the summer here it’s not much hotter than at home as regards being bothered by it, since the air here is clearer and purer. What’s more, we very often have a strong wind, the mistral. I’ve painted in the wheatfields during the hottest part of the day without it bothering me much. But one can sometimes see that the sun can be quite strong from the way the wheat turns yellow quickly. But the fields at home are infinitely better farmed, more regularly than here, where the rockiness of the soil in many places means it’s not suitable for everything. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">There are very beautiful fields of olive trees here, which are grey and silvery in leaf like pollard willows. Then I never tire of the blue sky. One never sees buckwheat or rape here, and generally speaking there’s rather less variety than at home. And I’d so much like to paint a field of buckwheat in flower or rape in flower, or flax. But I’ll probably find the opportunity to do it later in Normandy or Brittany. Then here one also never sees the mossy peasant roofs on the barns or cottages like at home, and no oak coppices and no spurry and no beech hedges with their red-brown leaves and whitish tangled old stems.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Also no proper heathland and no birches, which were so beautiful in Nuenen.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But what are beautiful in the south are the vineyards, where they’re on the flat land or the hillsides. I’ve seen it, and come to that sent Theo a painting of it, where a vineyard is all purple, crimson and yellow and green and violet like the Virginia creeper in Holland.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> I like to see a vineyard as much as a wheatfield. Then the hills here, full of thyme and other aromatic plants, are very beautiful, and because of the clarity of the air one can see from the heights so much further than at home.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Well, I’ll end by telling you that I think you’re delighted that your son Theo has at last got round to marrying. If I were you, I wouldn’t worry about his health, but in your place I would see to it that I got his <rs type="pers" key="416">wife</rs> and him to come and visit you twice a year instead of once. This would be good for you and them, particularly now that <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs>’s leaving. In his business it can’t do him any harm at all for his thoughts to have some distraction, and his wife, rest assured, won’t take it amiss of you if you awaken a desire in him to come to Holland with her now and then. Don’t forget that we have as many reasons for <hi rend="ital">in</hi>gratitude as for gratitude to the Paris business, and in your capacity of <rs type="pers" key="524">Mother</rs> approaching 70 you may assert that sometimes.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I kiss you in thought, and with a handshake for <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> I wish him the best of good luck in his enterprise. Believe me always</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>On Tuesday, 16 July 1889, <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> wrote the following to Theo and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> about the present letter: ‘And now I must tell you that I indeed received such a nice letter from Vincent last week. Oh, how glad I was to get it, I had written to him, among other things: do you know I’ll be turning 70 in September, and now he writes so nicely about that, and he’s so happy about you too, and about the country there and about Holland and so warm-hearted about <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs>, and when he thinks about some of the nature and the crops, that later perhaps, missing them here, he’ll find them again if he returns to Normandy or Brittany. I cannot tell you how grateful I am for that letter. May God grant that things will improve for him and that things will go well for Cor and you too, dear children’ (FR b2406).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                        <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien van Gogh</rs> also wrote about this letter to Jo on 29 July 1889: ‘I shall ask Vincent for a small painting. He recently wrote such a nice letter to Ma, as he hasn’t written to Ma in years. He had been to Arles for a day, so he is indeed going out more. Has Theo been hearing occasionally from the director or doctor or some such person at Saint-Rémy?’ (FR b2932).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Theo had written this in <ref target="let762.xml">letter 762</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Van Gogh was presumably thinking here of the Australian painter <rs type="pers" key="1334">John Peter Russell</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Regarding <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s stay in Martinique, <ref target="let623.xml#n-3">see letter 623, n. 3.</ref> Gauguin had lived from October to December 1888 with Van Gogh in the Yellow House in Arles.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>‘<rs type="lit" key="470">De Pruuvers</rs>’ (The tasters) is the first novella in the volume <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="412">Etsen naar het leven</rs>
                        </hi> (Etchings from life) by <rs type="pers" key="659">H. Hollidee</rs>; <ref target="let498.xml#n-1">see letter 498, n. 1.</ref> The passage Van Gogh describes is not, as he maintains, from ‘De Pruuvers’, but from the story ‘<rs type="lit" key="573">Gekleurde figuren</rs>’ (Coloured figures). The narrator of that story recalls how, as a sick boy, he heard reassuring noises and experienced a ‘blissful feeling when, after such a frightening night, the realization of security flooded my soul, while I, listening to the clatter of tea-trays on the floor, to the clanging of dustpan and brush, sank into the downy arms of a deep, restful sleep’ (pp. 119-120).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>). This was part of the third consignment of paintings from Arles (<ref target="let767.xml">see letter 767</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>