<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Thursday, 9 May 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let772"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">772</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">591</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">775</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 9 May 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Thursday, 9 May 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Third consignment of paintings from Arles <ref target="let767.xml">(767)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b638 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Vincent thanks Theo and Jo for their letters of 8 May 1889. Because Jo dated the present letter to ‘9 May 1889’ (in <hi rend="ital">Brieven </hi>1914) – perhaps she had a postmark to rely on – and because Vincent asks whether the consignment has arrived – on 2 May he had assumed that it would still take around eight days (<ref target="let767.xml">letter 767</ref>) – we have dated the letter to Thursday, 9 May. Besides, the letter had arrived in Paris by 11 May, since Jo mentioned it in a letter written that day to her sister Mien (<ref target="#n-1">see n. 1</ref>).</p>
<p rend="indent">Pickvance dated the letter to about Wednesday, 15 May, but we think it unlikely that Van Gogh would wait so long to inform them of his arrival in Saint-Rémy, especially since Theo had asked about it in his previous letter (see exhib. cat. New York 1986, p. 27).</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0638" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000873_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000873_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000873_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000873_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000873_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0638" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000873_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000873_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000873_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000873_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000873_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000873_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>merci de ta lettre–.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Tu as bien <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>raison de dire que M. Salles a été parfait dans <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>tout ceci, j’ai de grandes obligations envers lui<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je voulais te dire que je crois avoir bien fait d’aller <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>ici<c type="kk">/</c> d’abord en voyant la <hi rend="ital">réalité</hi> de la vie des fous <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>ou toqués divers dans cette ménagerie je perds la <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>crainte vague<c type="kk">/</c> la peur de la chôse. Et peu à peu <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>puis arriver à considérer la folie en tant qu’etant une maladie <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>comme une autre. Puis le changement d’entourage<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>à ce que j’imagine<c type="kk">/</c> me fait du bien.</ab>
                <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pour autant que je sache le médecin d’ici est <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>enclin à considérer ce que j’ai eu comme une <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>attaque de nature épileptique.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Mais j’ai pas demandé <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>après.–</ab>
                <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>
<ab rend="indent">Aurais tu déjà reçu la caisse de tableaux<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> je suis curieux <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>de savoir s’ils ont encore souffert oui ou non.</ab>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’en ai deux autres en train – des fleurs <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>d’iris violets<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> et un buisson de lilas.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> deux <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>motifs pris dans le jardin.</ab>
                <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>
<ab rend="indent">L’idée du devoir de travailler me revient beaucoup <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>et je crois que toutes mes facultés pour le travail <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>me reviendront assez vite. Seulement le travail <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>m’absorbe souvent tellement que je crois <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>que je resterai toujours abstrait<anchor n="a" xml:id="note-o-a"/> et gaucher<anchor n="b" xml:id="note-o-b"/> pour <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>me débrouiller pour le reste de la vie aussi<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je ne t’ecrirai pas une longue lettre – je <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>chercherai à répondre à la lettre de ma <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>nouvelle soeur<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> qui m’a bien touchée mais <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>je ne sais si j’arriverai à le faire<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>
<ab>Poignée de main et tout à toi</ab>
                <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab>Ma chère Soeur,</ab>
                <lb n="32*" xml:id="l-32s"/>
<ab>merci beaucoup de votre <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>lettre dans laquelle j’ai surtout cherché <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>les nouvelles de mon frère. Et je les <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>trouves très bonnes<c type="kp">_</c> Je vois que vous <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>avez déjà observé qu’il aime Paris <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>et que cela vous étonne plus ou moins<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>vous qui ne l’aimez point ou plutôt <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>qui y aimez surtout les fleurs tels <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>que je suppose par exemple les glycines <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>qui probablement commencent à fleurir. <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Ne pourrait-il pas être le cas qu’en <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>aimant une chôse on la voit mieux <lb n="43a" xml:id="l-43a"/>et plus juste <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>qu’en ne l’aimant pas.</ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pour lui et pour moi Paris est certes <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>déjà en quelque sorte un cimetière <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>où ont péri bien des artistes <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>que nous avons directement ou <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>indirectement connus.</ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">Certes <hi rend="ital">Millet</hi> que vous apprendrez <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>à aimer beaucoup et avec lui bien <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>d’autres ont cherché à sortir hors de <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Paris<c type="kp">_</c>– Mais Eugène Delacroix <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>par exemple<c type="kk">/</c> difficilement on se le represente <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>“comme homme” autrement que <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>Parisien.–</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tout ceci pour vous engager – <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>sous toute reserve il est vrai – <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>de croire à la <hi rend="ital">possibilité</hi> qu’il <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>y ait à Paris des <hi rend="ital">maisons</hi> et non <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>pas seulement des apartements<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin – heureusement <hi rend="ital">vous</hi> êtes <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>vous-même sa maison.</ab>
                <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>
<ab rend="indent">Il est assez drôle peut être que le résultat <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>de cette terrible attaque<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> est qu’il y ait <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>dans mon esprit plus guère de désir <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>ni d’esperance bien nets et je <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>me demande si c’est ainsi qu’on <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>pense alors que les passions un peu <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>éteints on descend la montagne <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>au lieu de la monter. Enfin ma soeur <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>si vous pouvez croire, ou à peu près, que tout va toujours <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>pour le mieux dans le meilleur des mondes<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> alors <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>vous pourrez croire peut etre également que Paris <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>est la meilleure des villes là-dedans.</ab>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
<ab rend="indent">Avez vous déjà remarqué que les vieux chevaux de <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>fiacre y ont des grands beaux yeux navrés comme <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>des chrétiens quelquefois. Quoi qu’il en soit <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>nous ne sommes pas des sauvages ni des paysans <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>et nous avons peutetre <hi rend="ital">même le devoir</hi> d’aimer <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>la civilisation (ainsi nommée)<c type="kp">_</c> Enfin ce serait <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>probablement hypocrite de dire ou croire <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>que Paris est mauvais alors qu’on y vit<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>La première fois que l’on voit Paris il se peut d’ailleurs <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>que tout y semble contre nature<c type="kk">/</c> sale et triste<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Enfin si vous n’aimez <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>pas Paris<c type="kk">/</c> surtout n’aimez pas la peinture <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>ni ceux qui directement ou indirectement <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>s’en occupent car ce n’est que trop dubieux<anchor n="c" xml:id="note-o-c"/> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>que cela soit beau ou utile<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab rend="indent">Mais que voulez vous<c type="kk">/</c> il y a des gens qui <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>aiment la nature tout en etant toqués <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>ou malades<c type="kk">/</c> voilà les peintres<c type="kk">/</c> puis il y <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>en a qui aiment ce que fait la main <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>d’homme et ceux là vont meme jusqu’à <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>aimer les tableaux.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
<ab rend="indent">Quoiqu’ici il y ait quelques malades fort graves<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>la peur<c type="kk">/</c> l’horreur que j’avais auparavent <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>de la folie s’est déjà beaucoup adoucie<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab rend="indent">Et quoique continuellement on entende ici des cris <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>et des hurlements terribles comme des bêtes dans <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>une ménagerie<c type="kk">/</c> malgré cela les gens d’ici se <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>connaissent très bien entre eux et s’aident les <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>uns les autres quand ils tombent dans des crises<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>En travaillant dans le jardin ils viennent tous <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>voir et je vous assure sont plus discrets et plus <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>polis pour me laisser tranquille que par exemple <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>les bons citoyens d’Arles.</ab>
                <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>
<ab rend="indent">Il se pourrait bien que je reste ici assez longtemps<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>jamais j’ai été si tranquille qu’ici et à l’hospice <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>à Arles pour pouvoir enfin peindre un peu<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>Tout près d’ici il y a des petites montagnes <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>grises ou bleues<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> ayant à leur pied des blés <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>très très verts et des pins<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je me compterai très heureux si j’arrive à <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>travailler assez pour gagner ma vie car <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>cela me donne bien du souci lorsque je me dis <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>que j’ai fait tant de tableaux et de dessins sans <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>jamais en vendre. Ne vous pressez pas trop <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>de trouver que ce soit là une injustice<c type="kk">/</c> moi <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>je n’en sais rien.</ab>
                <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>
<ab rend="indent">En vous remerciant encore de m’avoir écrit <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>et étant bien content de ce que je sache <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>qu’à présent mon frère ne rentre plus dans <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>un apartement vide quand il revient le <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>soir<c type="kk">/</c> je vous serre la main en pensée <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>et croyez moi</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>
<ab>votre frère</ab>
                <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-75" n="75">la meilleure &lt; une la meilleures</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Thanks for your letter.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> You’re quite right to say that <rs type="pers" key="663">Mr Salles</rs> has been perfect in all of this, I’m much obliged to him.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I wanted to tell you that I think I’ve done well to come here, first, in seeing the <hi rend="ital">reality</hi> of the life of the diverse mad or cracked people in this menagerie, I’m losing the vague dread, the fear of the thing. And little by little I can come to consider madness as being an illness like any other. Then the change of surroundings is doing me good, I imagine.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As far as I know the doctor here is inclined to consider what I’ve had as an attack of an epileptic nature.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> But I haven’t made any enquiries.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Have you by chance yet received the crate of paintings,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> I’m curious to know if they’ve suffered more, yes or no.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I have two others on the go — violet irises<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> and a lilac bush.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Two subjects taken from the garden.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The idea of my duty to work comes back to me a lot, and I believe that all my faculties for work will come back to me quite quickly. It’s just that work often absorbs me so much that I think I’ll always be absent-minded and awkward in getting by for the rest of life too.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I won’t write you a long letter — I’ll try to answer the letter from my new <rs type="pers" key="416">sister</rs>,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> which greatly touched me, but I don’t know if I’ll manage to do it.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Handshake, and ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab>My dear <rs type="pers" key="416">sister</rs>,</ab>
<ab>Thanks very much for your letter, in which I above all looked for news of my brother. And I find it very good. I can see that you have already observed that he loves Paris and that this surprises you a little, you who don’t like it, or rather who above all like the flowers there, such as, I suppose, for example, the wisterias which are probably beginning to flower. Could it not be the case that in liking a thing one sees it better and more accurately than in not liking it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">For him and for me Paris is certainly already a cemetery in a way, where many artists have perished, whom we knew directly or indirectly.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Certainly <hi rend="ital">
                        <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>
                    </hi>, whom you’ll learn to like a lot, and with him many others, have tried to get out of Paris. But <rs type="pers" key="982">Eugène Delacroix</rs>, for example, it’s difficult to portray him ‘as a man’ other than as a Parisian.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">All this to urge you — with all caution, admittedly — to believe in the <hi rend="ital">possibility</hi> that there are <hi rend="ital">homes</hi> in Paris, and not just apartments. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Anyway — fortunately <hi rend="ital">you</hi> are now his home yourself.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s quite odd perhaps that the result of this terrible attack<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> is that in my mind there’s hardly any really clear desire or hope left, and I’m wondering if it is thus that one thinks when, with the passions somewhat extinguished, one comes down the mountain instead of climbing it. Anyway my sister, if you can believe, or almost, that everything is always for the best in the best of worlds<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> then you’ll also be able to believe, perhaps, that Paris is the best of the towns in it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Have you noticed yet that the old cab-horses there have big, beautiful heartbroken eyes, like Christians sometimes. Whatever the case, we’re not savages nor peasants, and we perhaps <hi rend="ital">even have a duty</hi> to love civilization (so-called). Anyway, it would probably be hypocritical to say or believe that Paris is bad when one lives there. The first time one sees Paris it may be, besides, that everything there seems against nature, dirty and sad.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> Anyway, if you don’t like Paris, above all do not like painting nor those who directly or indirectly are engaged in it, for it’s only too doubtful whether that’s beautiful or useful.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">But what can you do, there are people who love nature while being cracked or ill, those are the painters, then there are some who love what is done by the hand of man, and those even go as far as liking paintings. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Although there are a few people here who are seriously ill, the fear, the horror that I had of madness before has already been greatly softened.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And although one continually hears shouts and terrible howls as though of the animals in a menagerie, despite this the people here know each other very well, and help each other when they suffer crises.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> They all come to see when I’m working in the garden, and I can assure you are more discreet and more polite to leave me in peace than, for example, the good citizens of Arles.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s possible that I’ll stay here for quite a long time, never have I been so tranquil as here and at the hospital in Arles to be able to paint a little at last. Very near here there are some little grey or blue mountains,<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> with very, very green wheatfields at their foot, and pines.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I shall count myself very happy if I manage to work enough to earn my living, for it makes me very worried when I tell myself that I’ve done so many paintings and drawings without ever selling any. Don’t be in too much of a hurry to consider this an injustice, I don’t know anything at all about it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Thanking you again for writing to me, and being very happy to know that now my brother doesn’t return to an empty apartment when he comes home in the evening, I shake your hand in thought, and believe me</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>your brother</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Theo’s letter was <ref target="let770.xml">letter 770</ref>. On 11 May, <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> wrote the following to her sister <rs type="pers" key="24">Mien</rs> about the present letter, the first from Saint-Rémy: ‘The news from Vincent is rather good – he is now no longer in Arles but in Saint-Rémy, where he will let himself be well taken care of for a couple of months – he always writes so cleverly – I’ve seldom read such letters – but his head is a bit worn out – I hope so much that rest will do him good. This week Theo showed us some splendid drawings by him – the things of his I saw in the beginning were mostly so strange – but there are also some that are much more understandable and ever so beautiful!’ (FR b4287).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
      <ab>The admissions register of the asylum of Saint-Paul-de-Mausole contains the medical report sent by <rs type="pers" key="222">Dr Urpar</rs> from Arles about Van Gogh. He stated that Van Gogh ‘suffered an attack of acute mania with generalised delirium. At that time he cut off his ear. At present his condition has greatly improved, but he nevertheless thinks it helpful to be cared for in a mental asylum’ (a été atteint il y a six mois de Manie aiguë avec délire généralisé. À cette époque il s’est coupé l’oreille. Actuellement son état s’est beaucoup amélioré, mais cependant il lui paraît utile d’être soigné dans un asile d’aliénés.) The asylum’s physician, <rs type="pers" key="568">Dr Peyron</rs>, examined Van Gogh and recorded his findings on 9 and 25 May 1889. On 9 May 1889 he wrote in the admissions register: ‘I consider that Mr Van Gogh is subject to attacks of epilepsy, separated by long intervals, and that it is advisable to place him under long-term observation in the institution.’ (J’estime ... que M. Van Gogh est sujet à des attaques d’Epilepsie fort éloignées les unes des autres et qu’il y a lieu de le soumettre à une observation prolongée dans l’établissement.) <ref target="documentation.xml#id8May1889">See <hi rend="ital">Documentation</hi>, 8 May 1889</ref>. </ab>
                </note>
      <note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>In <ref target="let774.xml">letter 774</ref> of 21 May, Theo confirmed that he had received this consignment several days earlier.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Irises </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2787">F 608 / JH 1691</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Lilacs</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2788">F 579 / JH 1692</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="a" xml:id="n-a" target="#note-o-a">
<ab>Read: ‘distrait’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="b" xml:id="n-b" target="#note-o-b">
<ab>Read: ‘gauche’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>’s letter was <ref target="let771.xml">letter 771</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>By ‘this terrible attack’ Van Gogh is probably referring to his first attack of mental illness, during which he cut off part of his left ear. For subsequent attacks, <ref target="let750.xml#n-4">see letter 750, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>For this quotation from <rs type="pers" key="844">Voltaire</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="445">Candide</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let568.xml#n-3">see letter 568, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>After this Van Gogh crossed out an unfinished remark: ‘N’est ce pas <rs type="pers" key="534">Currer Bell</rs>’ (Isn’t it Currer Bell?).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="c" xml:id="n-c" target="#note-o-c">
<ab>Read: ‘douteux’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>On 25 May 1889 <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> wrote to her sister <rs type="pers" key="24">Mien</rs>: ‘If only I could always make Theo happy then all is well. But Vincent keeps coming [back], Vincent who doesn’t share in happiness and contentment because it’s better to wear out than to rust out – work, struggle, and he’s so instilled that in Theo. His letters from Saint-Rémy are sad, yet he feels rather content, paints a lot – but what he says about all those lunatics around him – about accepting his fate – gives me pain. What will ever become of it?’ (FR b4288).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>Saint-Rémy lies at the foot of the Alpilles, a small massif.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>