<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Thursday, 2 May 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let766"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">766</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">T6</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">769</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Theo van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Thursday, 2 May 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Thursday, 2 May 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Decision regarding Vincent’s admission to the asylum at Saint-Rémy <ref target="let760.xml">(760)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b733 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘<hi rend="ital">[Paris, le]</hi> 2 Mai <hi rend="ital">[</hi>188<hi rend="ital">]</hi>9’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0733" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000992_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000992_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000992_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000992_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000992_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0733" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000992_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000992_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000992_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000992_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000992_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000992_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>
                    <vg:suppliedMilestone type="open"/>Boussod, Valadon &amp; C<hi rend="ss">ie</hi>
                </ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="sc"> Succ</hi>
                    <hi rend="ss">rs</hi> <hi rend="sc">de Goupil &amp; C<hi rend="ss">ie</hi>
                    </hi>
                </ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="sc">editeurs imprimeurs</hi>
                </ab>
                <vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>
    <ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">Estampes, Livres d’Art</hi>
                </ab>
                <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>
    <ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">Tableaux</hi>
                </ab>
                <vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="sc">19, Boulevard Montmartre, 19</hi>
                </ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">Paris, le</hi>
                    <vg:suppliedMilestone type="close"/> 2 Mai <supplied>188</supplied>9</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent,</ab>
                <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>
<ab>Je te remercie bien <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>de ta lettre<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> qui nous montre qu’au <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>moins tes forces physiques ne laissent <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>pas à désirer, puisque tu dis que <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>tu en as de trop; cependant il faut <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>te méfier, quand on <hi rend="ital">sent</hi> ses <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>forces ce n’est pas prouvé qu’on <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>en a beaucoup, mais si cela est <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>le cas, tant mieux. Maintenant <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>il y a dans ta lettre quelque chose <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>que je désapprouve entièrement &amp; que <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>je vais te dire, tu feras après ce que 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>
                    <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>tu voudras. C’est tes projets pour la <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>légion étrangère. C’est un pis aller n’est <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>ce pas? car je ne pense pas que tu aies <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>spontanément pris un gout pour ce <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>métier. C’est que ne pas pouvoir faire <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>de la peinture en ce moment, que tu <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>es en convalescence<c type="kk">/</c> te donne l’idé <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>de ne plus pouvoir en faire du tout, alors tu te <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>dis que trois mois de soins sans pouvoir <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>travailler coutent de l’argent et n’en <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>rapportent point, mais tu oublies que <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>mettons qu’étant soldat on te laisse <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>travailler<c type="kk">/</c> tu es là tenu comme un <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>gamin dans un pensionnat et que si tu <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>crains déjà la surveillance d’une maison <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>comme à S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Remy tu as bien plus à <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>craindre les usages de la vie militaire. <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>En somme cette idé provient d’une <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>crainte excessive de me causer des <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>frais &amp; des ennuis &amp; inutilement tu te crées <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>des casse têtes. L’année dernière n’a pas <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>été mauvaise pour moi au point de vue 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>de l’argent<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> &amp; tu peux donc sans scrupule <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>et sans me gêner compter sur ce que <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>je t’envoyais avant. Si cela ne te repugne <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>pas d’aller à S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Remy pour disons qu’un <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>mois, tu aurais été examiné par des <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>médecins spécialistes &amp; probablement <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>aurais tu pu profiter de leur conseils.</ab>
                <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>
<ab rend="indent">D’un autre côté dans une lettre que <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>m’a écrit le Directeur de l’établissement <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>de S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Remy<c type="kk">/</c> il ne veut s’engager à <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>rien au sujet de t’accorder de sortir <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>quand tu le désirera avant de t’avoir <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>examiné,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> mais je suppose qu’après t’avoir <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>vu il n’y a pas de doute qu’il ne te laisse <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>libre de sortir pour aller travailler. Pour <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>moi j’attribue une grande partie de ta <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>maladie à ce que ton existance <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>matérielle a été trop négligé. Dans <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>un établissement comme à S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Remy <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>il y a à peu près la même régularité <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>dans les heures de repas etc. &amp; je crois <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>que cette régularité ne te feras pas de mal<c type="kk">/</c>
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>
                    <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/> au contraire. Maintenant si tu préfères <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>nous pouvons bien prendre des renseignements <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>sur la maison d’Aix ou de Marseille <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>pour voir si là on fera d’autres conditions<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Sais tu bien qu’à un point de vue <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>tu n’est pas à plaindre, quoiqu’il paraisse <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>autrement. Combien n’y en a t’il pas qui <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>voudraient avoir fait le travail que tu <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>as livré, qu’est ce que tu demandes en plus<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>n’était ce pas là ton désir d’avoir créé <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>quelque chose, s’il t’a été donné de faire ce <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>que tu as fait<c type="kk">/</c> pourquoi est ce que tu <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>désespérerais qu’il ne te vienne un temps <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>ou tu feras encore de la bonne besogne. Si <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>mauvais que soit la société actuellement il y <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>a moyen d’y vivre, la preuve Puvis de Ch<c type="kp">_</c>,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Degas, <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>et autres. Je suis persuadé que si tu veux tu <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>peux d’içi peu reprendre ton travail. Ne crois pas <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>cependant que je ne sens pas toute la désilusion <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>quand tu es rentré dans ton atelier par exemple <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>après qu’il fût moisi par l’humidité. Tiens encore <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>courage, tes désastres surement prendront fin.</ab>
                <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bien des choses de ma femme qui se porte bien. Elle s’habitue <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>bien à la maison. Bonne poignée de mains<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note n="-">
                        <hi rend="ital">Printed letterhead.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-69" n="69">qu’à un &lt; qu’au</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>[Letterhead: Boussod Paris]</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Paris, 2 May 1889</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Vincent,</ab>
    <ab>Many thanks for your letter,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> which shows us that at least your physical powers leave nothing to be desired, since you say that you have too much of them; however you must be wary, when one <hi rend="ital">feels</hi> one’s powers it isn’t proven that one has a great deal of them, but if that’s the case, so much the better. Now there’s something in your letter of which I disapprove entirely and which I’m going to tell you, afterwards you can do what 
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/> you want. It is your plans for the Foreign Legion. That’s a last resort, isn’t it? for I don’t think that you have spontaneously acquired a taste for this profession. It’s that not being able to do any painting at the moment, being in convalescence, gives you the idea of no longer being able to do it at all, then you tell yourself that three months’ care without being able to work cost money and don’t bring any in, but you’re forgetting that, supposing they let you work when you’re a soldier, you’re held there like a kid in a boarding school, and if you already fear the supervision of a house like the one at St-Rémy you have much more to fear from the practices of military life. All in all, this idea comes from an excessive fear of causing me expenses and problems, and you get yourself worked up needlessly. The last year hasn’t been bad for me from the point of view 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> of money,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and you can therefore, without scruples and without harming me, count on what I was sending you before. If you’re not averse to going to St-Rémy for let’s say a month, you would have been examined by specialist doctors and probably you would have been able to benefit from their advice.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">On the other hand, in a letter written to me by the <rs type="pers" key="568">Director</rs> of the St-Rémy establishment, he doesn’t want to promise anything on the subject of allowing you to go out when you wish before having examined you,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> but I assume that after seeing you there’s no doubt that he’ll leave you free to go out to go and work. For myself, I attribute a large part of your illness to the fact that your material existence has been neglected too much. In an establishment as at St-Rémy there’s more or less the same regularity in mealtimes etc., and I think that this regularity will do you no harm, 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/> on the contrary. Now if you prefer, we could obtain information about the institution at Aix or Marseille to see if other conditions are laid down there.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You should know that from one point of view you aren’t to be pitied, although it may appear otherwise. How many are there who would want to have done the work that you’ve delivered, what more do you ask for, wasn’t that your desire, to have created something, if it has been given to you to do what you’ve done, why would you despair whether a time will come when you’ll do good work again? However bad society may be at present, there’s the means to live in it, the proof <rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis de C</rs>.,<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> <rs type="pers" key="981">Degas</rs> and others. I’m sure that if you want you can take up your work again in a short while from now. However, do not believe that I don’t feel all the disillusionment when you went back into your studio, for example, after the damp made it go mouldy. Continue to be of good heart, your disasters will surely come to an end.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Best wishes from my <rs type="pers" key="416">wife</rs>, who is well. She’s becoming really accustomed to the house. Good handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This is <ref target="let765.xml">letter 765</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>The year 1888 had indeed been a prosperous one for Theo: in addition to his basic annual income of 4,000 francs, his share of the profits for that year amounted to 9,619.10 francs. See <hi rend="ital">Account book </hi>2002, pp. 15-16.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="568">Théophile Peyron</rs> wrote to Theo on 29 April 1889: ‘What I can assure you of at once, is that when I have observed your patient for some time and have gained the certainty that he may without deleterious consequences enjoy a greater degree of freedom, I shall be the first to grant him it. As for painting, and not leaving him in isolation in the establishment, I promise you that I will provide him with all the means of indulging his natural inclinations, and in the house allow him the greatest freedom compatible with his mental state’ (Ce que je puis vous assurer d’avance, c’est que lorsque j’aurai observé votre malade pendant quelque temps et que j’aurai acquis la certitude qu’il peut sans inconvénients jouir d’une liberté plus grande, je serai le premier à la lui accorder. Quant à faire de la peinture et à ne pas le laisser séquestré dans l’établissement, je vous promets de lui faciliter tous les moyens de se livrer à ses goûts naturels et à lui laisser dans la maison, la plus grande liberté compatible avec son état mental) (see FR b1059; Hulsker 1993-2, pp. 176-177).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Read: ‘<rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>’.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>