<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Sunday, 8 December 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let825"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">825</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">T21</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">827</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Theo van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 8 December 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Sunday, 8 December 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Fourth consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let824.xml">(824)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="4">
<p>Mrs van Gogh and Willemien’s move to Leiden <ref target="let798.xml">(798)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. nos. b748 a-b V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Paris le 8 Dec_ 1889’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0748 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001013_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001013_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001013_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001013_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001013_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0748 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001013_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001013_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001013_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001013_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001013_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001013_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0748 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001014_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-5">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001014_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001014_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001014_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0748 b" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001014_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-6">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001014_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001014_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001014_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Paris le 8 Dec<c type="kp">_</c> 1889</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Nous avons bien reçu <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>aujourd’hui les trois rouleaux <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>de tableaux ainsi que ta lettre.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>Parmi tes toiles il y en a dont <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>l’harmoni est cherché dans des tons <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>moins éclatants que généralement; <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>il y a cependant beaucoup d’air.</ab>
                <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>
<ab rend="indent">Comme je suis d’accord avec <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>toi quand tu dis dans ta dernière 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>lettre que tu veux travailler comme <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>un savetier,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> certes cela n’empêchera <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>pas de faire des toiles qui se tiennent <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>à côté de celles des maîtres. Ce que <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>je trouve que le temps moderne a <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>fait pour l’art c’est que actuellement <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>chacun peut faire comme il l’entend <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>et n’est plus tenu de travailler selon <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>des règles établis par une école. Ceçi <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>étant le cas il est permi de faire <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>un morceau de la nature tout <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>bonnement comme on le voit, sans être <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>obligé de le couper comme ceçi ou comme <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>cela. La sympathie que l’artiste a pour <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>de certaines lignes &amp; de certaines couleurs <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>feront que malgré lui son âme s’y reflète<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>
<ab rend="indent">Il y avait à l’exposition Universelle <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>un petit tableau de Manet, que peut-<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>être tu as vu dans le temps chez <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>Portier. Il représente une jeune femme <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>en robe blanche assise contre un tertre vert à côté <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>d’une petite voiture avec un enfant <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>dedans<c type="kp">_</c> Le père est couché négligemment <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>sur l’herbe derrière la femme.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Ceci <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>est certainement un des tableaux <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>pas seulement les plus modernes, <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>mais aussi où il y a de l’art le <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>plus élevé. Je crois que les recherches <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>du symbolisme par exemple n’ont pas <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>besoin d’aller plus loin que ce tableau-<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>là, et le symbole n’est pas voulu.</ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dans le dernier temps Tangui expose <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>beaucoup de tes toiles, il m’a dit 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>qu’il espère vendre le banc avec <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>le lierre.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> C’est un beau choix que <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>tu as fait pour Bruxelles. J’ai commandé <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>des cadres. Pour les tournesol<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> je laisse <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>le petit bord de bois qui est autour <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>et un cadre blanc autour. Pour les autres<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>des cadres blancs ou en bois naturel<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Tu ne me dis pas si tu veux exposer <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>des dessins<c type="kp">_</c> Quand Maus était içi <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>il les aimait beaucoup &amp; demandait <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>surtout d’en envoyer. On pourrait peut-<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>être en envoyer plusieurs dans un cadre.</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dans le temps tu disais souvent qu’il <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>faudrait que l’on publie un livre sur <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>Monticelli. Eh bien, j’ai vu une vingtaine <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>de très belles lithographies d’après lui <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>faites par un nommé Lauzet. Il y aura aussi <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>un texte, l’artiste doit venir voir nos tableaux <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>pour voir s’il y en a qu’il veut reproduire.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>Il sera surtout bon pour les Anglais 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/>
                    <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>et les Ecossais. Les lithographies sont <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>imprimées en différents tons &amp; ressemblent <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>comme procédé un peu à des eaux fortes <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>sur pierre, comme Marvy en faisait <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>dans le temps;<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> celui qui les a faites est <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>vraiment artiste. Il est venu encore <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>chez moi cet ami de Bernard <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>nommé Aurier qui est venu une fois <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>Rue Lepic. Il s’intéresse beaucoup <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>à ce que tu fais &amp; m’a montré une <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>petit journal qu’il a dirigé où il <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>a parlé de la boutique de Tangui &amp; <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>où il cite aussi tes tableaux.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Nous <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>sommes içi en plein hiver &amp; il y a de <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>la neige sur les toits. Comment est <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>le climat chez toi. J’écris à M. Peyron 
<pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/>
                    <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>pour lui dire que probablement tu <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>seras obligé de travailler dans une <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>chambre &amp; qu’il veuille bien dans ce <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>cas te laisser faire du feu, dont il <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>peut me porter les frais en compte.</ab>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je suis très content que tu puisses <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>dire que tu te portes bien. Pour <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>l’avenir, qui est ce qui nous le dira, <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>ne te fais surtout pas de soucis plus <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>qu’il ne le faut. Un jour ou un autre <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>il y aura bien de meilleurs jours pour <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>toi &amp; nous nous verrons plus souvent.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> Les Corot<c type="kk">/</c> Millet<c type="kk">/</c> etc<c type="kp">_</c> n’ont pas vendu <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>cher leur peinture mais ils ont cependant <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>fini par vendre, mais il faut de la patience<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>
<ab rend="indent">Jo te dit bien le bonjour, nous avons reçu <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>d’Amsterdam tout un envoi de petites affaires <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>pour le bébé. Tu lui feras son portrait quand <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>il sera là. Wil vient probablement nous donner un <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>coup de main en Janvier. Elles se plaisent bien à Leide<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>
<ab rend="indent">bon courage<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="100*" xml:id="l-100s"/>
<ab>t<c type="kp">_</c> à toi</ab>
                <lb n="100**" xml:id="l-100ss"/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Paris 8 Dec. 1889</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Vincent,</ab>
<ab>Today we safely received the three rolls of paintings as well as your letter.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> Among the canvases there are some whose harmony is sought in less dazzling tones than generally; there is however a lot of atmosphere.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How I agree with you when you say in your last letter 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> that you want to work like a cobbler,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> certainly that won’t prevent you from doing canvases that hold their own alongside those of the masters. What I consider modern times have done for art is that nowadays each person can do as he intends and he isn’t forced to work according to rules established by a school. This being the case, it’s permissible to do a piece of nature simply as one sees it, without being obliged to cut it like this or like that. The fondness the artist has for certain lines and certain colours will cause his soul to be reflected in them in spite of himself. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">At the World Exhibition there was a little painting by <rs type="pers" key="1182">Manet</rs>, which perhaps you saw earlier at <rs type="pers" key="601">Portier</rs>’s. It shows a young woman in a white dress sitting against a green knoll beside a little carriage with a child inside. The father is lying nonchalantly on the grass behind the woman.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> This is certainly one of the paintings that aren’t only the most modern, but also in which there is the highest art. I think that the searches for symbolism, for example, need go no further than this painting, and the symbol isn’t deliberate.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Lately <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs> has been exhibiting a lot of your canvases, he told me 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> that he hopes to sell the Bench with the ivy.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> It’s a fine choice you’ve made for Brussels. I’ve ordered frames. For the Sunflowers<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> I’m leaving the little wooden edge that’s around it, and a white frame around that. For the others,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> white or natural wood frames. You don’t tell me if you want to exhibit drawings. When <rs type="pers" key="505">Maus</rs> was here he liked them very much and asked above all for some to be sent. We could perhaps send several of them in a frame.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You often used to say that a book should be published about <rs type="pers" key="1240">Monticelli</rs>. Well, I’ve seen about twenty very fine lithographs after him done by someone called <rs type="pers" key="1149">Lauzet</rs>. There will also be text, the artist is to come and see our paintings to see if there are any he wants to reproduce.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> It will be especially good for the English 
<pb f="2r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-5" facs="#zone-pb-2r-5"/> and the Scottish. The lithographs are printed in different tones, and in terms of the process they somewhat resemble etchings on stone, like <rs type="pers" key="1198">Marvy</rs> made back then;<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> the man who did them is a real artist. That friend of <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>’s called <rs type="pers" key="521">Aurier</rs> also came to my place, the one who came to rue Lepic once. He’s very interested in what you’re doing and showed me a little journal he ran in which he talked about <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs>’s shop, and in which he also mentions your paintings.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> Here we are in the full throes of winter and there’s snow on the roofs. How’s the climate where you are? I’m writing to <rs type="pers" key="568">Mr Peyron</rs> 
      <pb f="2v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-6" facs="#zone-pb-2v-6"/> to tell him that you’ll probably be obliged to work in a room, and that in that case will he please let you make a fire, the cost of which he can add to my account.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m very pleased that you can say that you’re well. For the future, who can say, above all don’t worry yourself more than necessary. One day or another there will indeed be better days for you, and we’ll see each other more often.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> The <rs type="pers" key="971">Corot</rs>s, <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>s etc. didn’t sell their painting for high prices but they nevertheless ended up selling, but one must have patience.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> sends her warm regards, we’ve received a whole consignment of little things for the baby from Amsterdam. You’ll do its portrait when it’s here. <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> is probably coming to lend us a hand in January. They’re enjoying themselves in Leiden.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Be of good heart.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Theo</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This was <ref target="let824.xml">letter 824</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Theo is referring here to <ref target="let823.xml">letter 823</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1182">Edouard Manet</rs>, <hi rend="ital">In the garden</hi>, 1870 (Shelburne, Vermont, The Shelburne Museum). <rs type="ill" key="228">Ill. 228</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Trees with ivy in the garden of the asylum </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2789">F 609 / JH 1693</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2704">F 454 / JH 1562</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Sunflowers in a vase</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2703">F 456 / JH 1561</rs>). Van Gogh had framed these works himself with strips of wood; <ref target="let776.xml#n-6">see letter 776, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>The other works that Van Gogh eventually exhibited were <hi rend="ital">Orchard in blossom with a view of Arles </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2781">F 516 / JH 1685</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">The red vineyard</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This resulted in the publication <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="517">Adolphe Monticelli</rs>
                        </hi>. Paris (Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie) 1890, which appeared in June of that year. The large-format album contains lithographs by <rs type="pers" key="1149">Auguste Lauzet</rs> after twenty paintings by <rs type="pers" key="1240">Monticelli</rs>, as well as two portraits of the artist, a ‘biographical and critical study’ by<hi rend="ital"> </hi>Paul Guigou and ‘an introductory poem’ by<hi rend="ital"> </hi>Fernand Mazade. Lauzet included two works from the collection of the Van Gogh brothers: no. 4 <hi rend="ital">The Italian girl</hi> and no. 15 <hi rend="ital">Woman at a well </hi>(both Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum). <rs type="ill" key="309">Ill. 309</rs> and <rs type="ill" key="2306">2306</rs>. For this publication, see Sheon 2000.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>A technique frequently employed by <rs type="pers" key="1198">Louis Marvy</rs> is that of ‘crayon-manner etching’ with a ‘soft varnish’ (vernis mou) whereby it seems as though the lithographed etchings have been worked up in pencil. This last term was recorded below a number of prints he made in the 1840s. For this technique, see André Béguin, <hi rend="ital">Dictionnaire technique de l’estampe</hi>. Paris 1998, pp. 102-104.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Luc le Flaneur (the pseudonym of <rs type="pers" key="521">Albert Aurier</rs>), ‘En quête de choses d’art’, <hi rend="ital">Le Moderniste</hi> <hi rend="ital">Illustré </hi>2 (13 April 1889), p. 14. Aurier was the editor-in-chief of this weekly magazine. He writes: ‘Do you know <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs>? Yes or no? 14 rue Clauzel; an ugly-looking shop, and so small! But with little caskets, fine ointments. Go in and you’ll see treasures out of the Arabian Nights... This <hi rend="ital">père</hi> Tanguy, what an astute spotter of masterpieces! How good he’s been at discovering today’s unknowns, tomorrow’s masters!... But let’s go in with no more ado... Look, here are some incomparable marvels by <rs type="pers" key="932">Cézanne</rs>! Look, here are some canvases by Vincent, extraordinarily fiery, intense, sunny’. (Connaissez-vous Tanguy? Oui, non. Rue Clauzel, 14; vilaine boutique et si petite! mais aux petites boëtes, les bons onguents. Entrez et vous verrez des trésors mille-et-une-nuitesques... Ce père Tanguy, quel fin dénicheur de chefs-d’oeuvre! Comme il a su les découvrir les méconnus d’aujourd’hui, les maîtres de demain!... Mais entrons sans plus tarder... Tenez, voici d’incomparables merveilles de Cézane! tenez, voici des toiles de Vincent, formidables de fougue, d’intensité, d’ensoleillement).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the summer of 1889, <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> had prepared a short article about Van Gogh for the same magazine and sent it to Aurier. See Van Gogh 2007, pp. 360-365 and exh. cat Mannheim 1990, pp. 381-382.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Theo later added ‘&amp; nous ... souvent’.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>