<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Wednesday, 19 March 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let858"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">858</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">T29</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">858</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Theo van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Wednesday, 19 March 1890</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Wednesday, 19 March 1890.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Fourth attack in Saint-Rémy <ref target="let857.xml">(857)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Entry for the 1890 Indépendants exhibition <ref target="let854.xml">(854)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b756 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Paris le 19 Mars 1890’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0756" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001024_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001024_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001024_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001024_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001024_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0756" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001024_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001024_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001024_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001024_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001024_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001024_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Paris le 19 Mars 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Nous étions bien content <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>de recevoir ta dernière lettre mais <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>nous regrettons du fond du coeur que <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>tu ne puis pas nous donner de meilleures <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>nouvelles.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Il te faudra énormément <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>de patience pour surmonter l’ennui <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>que doit te causer ton état.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Cependant <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>il y a une tendance à amélioration<c type="kk">/</c> ce <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>dont nous devons commencer par nous <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>réjouir. Le temps froid a toujours de <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>l’influence sur toi &amp; il est donc possible <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>que le temps plus doux te remette entièrement<c type="kk">/</c> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>espérons le &amp; ne te fatigue pas de trop.</ab>
                <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>
<ab rend="indent">Comme j’aurais été content si tu avais <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>été là à l’exposition des Indépendants<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>C’était le jour de vernissage où Carnot <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>est venu.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> J’y étais avec Jo. Tes tableaux <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>sont bien placés &amp; font très bien. Il y en <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>a beaucoup qui sont venus pour me prier <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>de te faire leurs compliments. Gauguin <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>disait que tes tableaux sont le clou <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>de l’exposition. Il propose un échange <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>d’une de ses toiles contre celui des Alpines.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>Je lui ai dit que je croyais que <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>tu n’y trouverais pas <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>d’inconvenient, au contraire qu’il te <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>ferait plaisir qu’il aime ton tableau. <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Moi aussi je l’aime beaucoup, ce tableau<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>et il fait admirablement bien à l’exposition<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Seurat y a exposé un bien curieux <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>tableau où il y a la recherche d’exprimer 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>des choses par la direction de la ligne.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>Certes il exprime du mouvement, mais <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>cela a un aspect bien curieux &amp; pas <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>très généreux comme idées. Guillaumin <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>expose plusieurs choses parmi lesquelles <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>il y en a de très bonnes,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> de Lautrec a un <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>excellent portrait de femme au piano &amp; <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>un grand tableau qui se tient très bien.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Malgré son sujet scabreux il y a une <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>grande distinction<c type="kp">_</c> En général il est <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>à remarquer que le public commence <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>à s’intéresser de plus en plus aux <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>jeunes impressionnistes, il y a au <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>moins un certain nombre d’amateurs <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>qui commencent à en acheter. L’exposition <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>de Pissarro est fini, il est venu beaucoup <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>de monde &amp; il y en a eu 5 de vendus.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Pour le moment c’est tout ce que nous <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>espérions. Dimanche prochain Bernard <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>&amp; Aurier doivent venir voir tes dernières 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>toiles<c type="kp">_</c> Bernard a été un peu malade <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>mais il va mieux. Sous ce pli tu trouveras <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>une lettre d’Aurier. Il doit venir prochainement <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>pour voir les Gauguin &amp; faire un article <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>sur lui. J’ai reçu de Bruxelles <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>l’argent de ton tableau<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> &amp; Maus <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>m’écrit “A l’occasion dites bien à votre <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>frère que j’ai été très heureux de sa participation <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>au Salon des XX où il a trouvé dans la <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>mêlée des discussions, de vives sympathies <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>artistiques”<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Veux tu que je t’envois l’argent? <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>je le tiens à ta disposition pour quand <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>tu le voudras. J’espère mon cher frère <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>que tu pourras nous donner bientôt <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>de plus satisfaisantes nouvelles de ta santé. <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Si tu voyais ton petit filleul tu te <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>sentirais plus heureux. Tâches de savoir du <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>D<hi rend="ss">r </hi>Peyron si quand tu seras remis de <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>cette crise il ne voit pas de danger que tu <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>viennes à Paris. Jo te dit bien bonjour <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>&amp; se joint à moi pour faire les meilleurs <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>voeux pour ta prompte guérison<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
<ab rend="indent">bonne poignée de mains<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-56" n="56">prochainement &lt; prochainemt</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Paris, 19 March 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Vincent,</ab>
<ab>We were really pleased to receive your last letter, but we’re sorry from the bottom of our hearts that you can’t give us better news.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> You’ll need an enormous amount of patience to overcome the trouble your condition must cause you.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> However, there’s a tendency to improvement, which we must begin by being extremely glad about. The cold weather always has an influence on you, and so it’s possible that milder weather will cure you entirely, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> let’s hope so, and don’t tire yourself out too much.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">How pleased I would have been if you’d been there at the Independents’ exhibition.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> It was the day of the private viewing when <rs type="pers" key="327">Carnot</rs> came.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> I was there with <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>. Your paintings are well placed and look very well. Many people came up to ask me to give you their compliments. <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> said that your paintings are the key to the exhibition. He suggests an exchange of one of his canvases for the one of the Alpilles.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> I told him that I didn’t think you’d have any objection, on the contrary that it would please you that he likes your painting. I also like it very much, that painting, and it looks admirably well in the exhibition.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="1353">Seurat</rs> exhibited a most curious painting there, searching to express 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> things through the direction of the line.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> Certainly he expresses movement, but it has a most curious appearance and not very generous as regards ideas. <rs type="pers" key="1065">Guillaumin</rs> is exhibiting several things, some very good ones among them,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> <rs type="pers" key="1392">De Lautrec</rs> has an excellent portrait of a woman at the piano, and a large painting which holds its own very well.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> There’s a great distinction in it, despite the risqué subject. In general it’s noticeable that the public is beginning to be more and more interested in the young Impressionists, there are at least a certain number of art lovers who are beginning to buy them. The <rs type="pers" key="1268">Pissarro</rs> exhibition is over, lots of people came, and 5 were sold.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> For the moment that’s all we were hoping for. Next Sunday <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="521">Aurier</rs> are to come and see your latest 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> canvases. Bernard has been a bit ill but is feeling better. Enclosed with this you’ll find a letter from Aurier. He’s to come shortly to see the <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>s and do an article on him. I’ve received the money for your painting from Brussels,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> and <rs type="pers" key="505">Maus</rs> writes to me: ‘When you have an opportunity please tell your brother that I was very happy that he participated in the Salon of Les Vingt where, in the melée of discussions, he found lively artistic sympathies’.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> Do you want me to send you the money? I’m holding it for you for whenever you want it. I hope, my dear brother, that you can soon give us more satisfactory news of your health. You’d feel happier if you saw your little godson. Try to find out from <rs type="pers" key="568">Dr Peyron</rs> if he sees no danger in your coming to Paris when you’ve recovered from this crisis. <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> sends you her warm regards, and joins with me in sending best wishes for your speedy recovery.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Good handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The letter from Vincent, for which Theo thanks him, is <ref target="let857.xml">letter 857</ref>. </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Theo had sent Vincent something to read to combat the boredom, as he reported at the beginning of March to their sister <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs>: ‘Wil, many thanks for the plays by Ibsen. I find them more genuine in German than in French. They certainly contain inducement for much that is good. I sent Nora to Vincent, but in his present condition I’d prefer to keep back “Ghosts” for a while’<hi rend="ital"> </hi>(FR b941). Theo is referring here to <rs type="pers" key="1828">Henrik Ibsen</rs>’s plays <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="527">Nora or A Doll’s House</rs>
                        </hi> and <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="528">Ghosts</rs>
                        </hi>. The latter is considered Ibsen’s darkest and most scandalous family drama. It is a harrowing tale that shows how lies and good intentions can destroy people.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The opening of the exhibition had taken place earlier that day (19 March). Theo had already written to <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> to say how sorry he was that Vincent could not be present: ‘19 of this month opens the exhibition of the Indépendants here, with ten paintings by him. I had hoped that he would be here for the opening, for he would certainly have had success among the public who follow the movement of the younger school. But that is not possible now’ (FR b927, 14 March 1890).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="327">Carnot</rs> was the French president.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Ravine</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2853">F 662 / JH 1804</rs>). It is possible that Theo did exchange the painting with <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>, or perhaps he (or <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>) gave it to him, because in 1905 the painting was in the possession of Amedée Schuffenecker and before that of Chaudet, with whom Gauguin stored his paintings when he went to Tahiti. Provenance information from the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1353">Seurat</rs>, <hi rend="ital">The Chahut</hi>, 1889-1890 (Otterlo, Kröller-Müller Museum). <rs type="ill" key="2313">Ill. 2313</rs>. See exhib. cat. Paris 1890-2, p. 36, cat. no. 726.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1065">Guillaumin</rs> exhibited eight paintings and two pastels.<hi rend="ital"> </hi>See exhib. cat. Paris 1890-2, p. 22, cat. nos. 416-425.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1392">Toulouse-Lautrec</rs> exhibited two works: <hi rend="ital">Mademoiselle Dihau at the piano</hi>, 1890 (Albi, Musée Toulouse-Lautrec). <rs type="ill" key="431">Ill. 431</rs>, and the painting, measuring 100 x 150 cm, <hi rend="ital">At the Moulin Rouge: The dance</hi>, 1889-1890 (Philadelphia Museum of Art, The Henry P. Mcllhenny Collection in Memory of Frances P. McIlhenny). <rs type="ill" key="436">Ill. 436</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>From 25 February to 15 March 1890 Theo organized an exhibition of recent work by <rs type="pers" key="1268">Pissarro</rs>. There were sixteen canvases, seven distempers and four gouaches on display. See <hi rend="ital">Exposition d’oeuvres récentes de Camille Pissarro</hi>. Exhib. cat. Paris (Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie), Février 1890. Paris 1890. The invitation has been preserved (FR b1498). See also Pissarro and Durand-Ruel Snollaerts 2005, vol. 1, pp. 218-219, 363. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The following five paintings were sold by Theo in the first months of 1890, for a total of 4,800 francs: <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="915">Paysage à Auvers</rs>
                        </hi> (Landscape at Auvers), on 3 January 1890 for 600 francs to Oppenheim; <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="916">Prairie à St. Charles</rs>
                        </hi> (Meadow at Saint Charles) 1889 (<hi rend="ital">Girl tending cattle</hi>, Saint-Charles, Eragny, private collection), on 4 March 1890 for 1,200 francs to L. Bouglé; <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="917">L’abreuvoir</rs>
                        </hi> (The watering place), 1889 (Peasant girl raking hay at Eragny, private collection), on 8 March 1890 for 1,200 francs to Thiébault; <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="918">Paysanne gardant chèvres</rs>
                        </hi> (Peasant woman tending goats), on 22 March 1890 for 800 francs to Gallimard; <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="919">Meules et moutons</rs>
                        </hi> (Wheat stacks and sheep), on 28 March 1890 for 1,000 francs to Marcigny. See GRI, Goupil Ledgers, nos. 20005, 20342, 20364, 20405 and 20419; and Pissarro and Durand-Ruel Snollaerts 2005, vol. 3, pp. 566-567, 572-573, cat. nos. 866, 872. Pissarro was highly pleased. See <hi rend="ital">Correspondance Pissarro</hi> 1980-1991, vol. 2, pp. 329-334 and Jampoller 1986, pp. 53, 57-58.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>Van Gogh’s painting <hi rend="ital">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>) had been sold in Brussels for 400 francs; <ref target="let855.xml#n-5">see letter 855, n. 5.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>The letter from <rs type="pers" key="505">Octave Maus</rs> to Theo is not known. The writer of the article ‘L’exposition des XX’ in <hi rend="ital">L’Art Moderne</hi> of 26 January 1890 also heaped praise on Van Gogh’s paintings: ‘He’s a strange artist, who tried to express this same symbolic vision of things through the medium of colour. That’s Vincent van Gogh. Visitor, overcome your initial shock at the sight of these loud, sonorous, disorderly paintings, the Sunflowers, the Ivy, and especially the Red vineyard at Montmajour ... And when you open your eyes again, look hard at these three extraordinary paintings and ask yourself if their wild disorder, their wealth of vivid, raw, bleeding, resonant tones does not render with miraculous intensity the scars that the sight of the things themselves has left deeply imprinted in you’. (Il est un artiste bizarre qui a essayé de réaliser cette même vue symbolique des choses, au moyen de la couleur. C’est Vincent Van Gogh. Surmonte, ô visiteur, la première commotion devant ces bruyantes, sonores et désordonnées peintures que sont les <hi rend="ital">Tournesols</hi>, le <hi rend="ital">Lierre</hi>, et surtout la <hi rend="ital">Vigne rouge au Mont-Major</hi> ... Et, rouvrant les yeux, fixe ces trois tableaux extraordinaires et demande-toi si leur fougueux désordre, leur opulence de tons vifs, crus, saignants, sonnants, ne rend pas avec une intensité miraculeuse ce que la vue des réalités a laissé en toi de plus profondément empreint, en cicatrices).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>