<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Saturday, 10 May 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let869"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">869</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">T34</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">870</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Theo van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 10 May 1890</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Saturday, 10 May 1890.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Decision to go to Auvers <ref target="let868.xml">(868)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b761 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Paris le 10 Mai 1890’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0761" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001029_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001029_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001029_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001029_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001029_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0761" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001029_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001029_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001029_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001029_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001029_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001029_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Paris le 10 Mai 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Merçi bien de tes <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>deux lettres;<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> je suis bien content <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>que le mieux persiste &amp; si tu <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>pouvais faire le voyage, sans <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>danger, cela me ferait bien <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>plaisir. Est ce qu’il te semble aussi <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>qu’il y a si longtemps que nous <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ne nous sommes pas vus. Puisque <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>tu trouves si gênant de voyager <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>avec quelcun de la maison, mon 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>dieu il faut le risquer, quoique je <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>ne suis pas comme toi &amp; que je <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>ne le ferais<c type="kk">/</c> pour éviter en cas <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>où la crise te reprenait toutes les <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>misères qui sortiraient en cas où <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>à une gare inconnue tu aies à faire <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>à des gens que tu ne connais pas <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>&amp; qui te traiteraient on ne sait <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>pas comment. Maintenant si tu <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>pars envois moi sans faute une <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>dépêche pour que je sâche à quelle <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>heurre tu arriveras à la gare de <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>Lyon pour que j’aille t’y prendre. <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>Bien entendu que tu viens chez nous <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>si tu veux bien te contenter de la petite <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>chambre où nous avons logé Wil &amp; plusieurs <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>autres. J’ai écrit hier au D<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Gachet 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>pour lui demander quand il vient <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>à Paris, car il donne consultation alors. <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>&amp; je lui ai demandé en même temps <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>de s’informer pour un logement pour toi.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Si<c type="kk">/</c> le changement de pays pourrait <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>te faire du bien, mais vers l’hiver il <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>vaut peut être mieux que tu sois dans <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>un climat plus chaud. Mais nous aurons <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>le temps de causer de tout cela. J’ai encore <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>écrit au D<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Peyron pour lui dire <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>que s’il n’y a pas un <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>absolut danger, il fasse selon <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>ton désir &amp; te laisse aller. Comme il a <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>été bon pour toi<c type="kk">/</c> tâches de ne pas <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>le froisser. J’avais commandé à <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>Tangui &amp; à Tasset les couleurs que <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>tu demandais<c type="kk">/</c> me disant que cela ne <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>serait jamais perdu. Si les couleurs n’étaient 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>pas encore arrivées laisse des ordres <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>pour la réexpédition. Est ce qu’enfin <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>tu pourras trouver un endroit où <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>être un peu au calme sans qu’il <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>y ait autour de toi des gens &amp; des <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>choses qui te tracassent. Je l’espère de <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>tout mon coeur et il est possible <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>qu’en tous les cas ceçi soit une amélioration <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>mais les gens son partout à peu près les <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>mêmes &amp; quand les choses d’art vous <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>préoccupent on trouve bien peu de gens <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>qui vous comprennent. C’est du latin <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>pour eux &amp; il n’y voient qu’un passe temps <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>qu’il ne faut pas prendre au sérieux.</ab>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je n’ai pas encore été au Salon,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> qui doit <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>être bien médiocre dit on, mais il y a une <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>exposition de dessins &amp; crépons japonais <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>que tu verras quand tu viendra, qui est <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>superbe.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Je voudrais que tu étais déjà içi<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>n’oublie pas de me télégraphier. Bien bonjour <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>de Jo &amp; du petit, ils vont bien tout les deux.</ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">bonne poignée de mains &amp; au revoir<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>
<ab>Je t’envois çi inclus fr<c type="kp">_</c> 150.– pour le voyage<c type="kk">/</c> si par hasard il <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>n’y avait pas assez télégraphiez moi<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-39" n="39">au &lt; àu</note>
<note target="l-69" n="69">au revoir &lt; à revoir</note>
<note target="l-71" n="71">150.– &lt; 150.</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Paris 10 May 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Vincent,</ab>
<ab>Thanks very much for your two letters;<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I’m very happy that the improvement continues, and it would give me great pleasure if you could make the journey, without danger. Does it also seem to you that it’s such a long time since we saw each other? Since you find it such an annoyance to travel with someone from the asylum, for heaven’s sake, 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> you must risk it, although I’m not like you and wouldn’t do it, to avoid, should the crisis seize hold of you again, all the miseries that would emerge should you, at an unknown station, have to deal with people you don’t know and who would treat you who knows how. Now if you leave, send me a telegram without fail so that I know what time you’ll be arriving at the Gare de Lyon so that I can come and fetch you. Of course you must come to our place, if you don’t mind making do with the little bedroom where we’ve put up <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> and several others. I wrote to <rs type="pers" key="389">Dr Gachet</rs> yesterday 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> to ask him when he’s coming to Paris, for he gives consultations then. And at the same time I asked him to find out about lodgings for you.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Yes, the change of region might do you good, but towards winter it’s perhaps better that you should be in a warmer climate. But we’ll have time to talk about all that. I’ve written to <rs type="pers" key="568">Dr Peyron</rs> to tell him that if there isn’t a definite danger, he should do as you wish and let you go. As he’s been kind to you, try not to hurt him. I had ordered the colours you asked for from <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="785">Tasset</rs>, telling myself that anyway it wouldn’t be lost. If the colours hadn’t 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> yet arrived, leave orders for them to be sent on. Will you at last be able to find a place where you can have a little tranquillity without having people and things around you that annoy you? I hope so with all my heart, and it’s possible that in any event this might be an improvement, but people are more or less the same everywhere, and when artistic things preoccupy you, you find very few people who understand you. It’s Latin to them, and they regard it only as a pastime that isn’t to be taken seriously.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I haven’t yet been to the Salon,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> which is apparently very mediocre, so they say, but there’s an exhibition of Japanese drawings and prints which you’ll see when you come, which is superb.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> I’d like you to be here already, don’t forget to telegraph me. Warm regards from <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> and the <rs type="pers" key="418">little one</rs>, they’re both well.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Good handshake, and au revoir.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>I’m enclosing 150 francs for the journey, telegraph me if by chance it isn’t enough.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>These were <ref target="let866.xml">letters 866</ref> and <ref target="let868.xml">868</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>In his letter to <rs type="pers" key="389">Dr Gachet</rs> of 9 May, Theo referred to their meeting and informed him about Vincent. He said he hoped that Gachet would take his brother under his wing, and asked his opinion about having someone accompany Vincent during his railway journey. ‘He’s very well at the moment and writes me very sensible letters. He has a great wish to come to Paris for a few days and then to go and work in the country ... Do you think it would be prudent to have someone accompany him during the journey? He himself feels revulsion at having to be supervised and begs me to let him make the journey alone. I should very much like to have your opinion on the matter’ (Il est très bien en ce moment &amp; m’écrit des lettres très raisonnables. Il a un grand désir de venir à Paris pour quelques jours &amp; ensuite pour aller travailler à la campagne ... Croyez vous qu’il serait prudant de le faire accompagner par quelcun pendant le voyage. Lui même sent une répulsion à devoir être gardé &amp; me supplie de lui laisser faire le voyage seul. J’aimerais beaucoup avoir vôtre avis la dessus) (FR b2014).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>The Salon had opened on 1 May (see exhib. cat. Paris 1890-1).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This exhibition, held at the Ecole des Beaux-Arts and organized by <rs type="pers" key="290">Siegfried Bing</rs>, had 725 works on display. See <hi rend="ital">Exposition de la gravure Japonaise à L’Ecole des Beaux-Arts à Paris du 25 avril au 22 mai. Catalogue</hi>. Paris 1890 and <hi rend="ital">Correspondance Pissarro</hi> 1980-1991, vol. 2, p. 352 (n. 2). Theo saw the exhibition on 27 April (<hi rend="ital">Account book </hi>2002, p. 73).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>