<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Sunday, 9 February 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let852"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">852</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">T28</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">853</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Theo van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Sunday, 9 February 1890</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Sunday, 9 February 1890.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Willemien is staying with Theo and Jo <ref target="let835.xml">(835)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b755 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Paris le 9 Fev: 1890’. </p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0755" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001023_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001023_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001023_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001023_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001023_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0755" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001023_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001023_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001023_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001023_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001023_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001023_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Paris le 9 Fev: 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Tu nous a fait bien <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>plaisir avec ta dernière lettre<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> &amp; <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>nous voyons heureusement que cela <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>va assez bien avec la santé.</ab>
                <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>
<ab rend="indent">Chez nous cela marche bien<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Jo nourit le bébé &amp; ne manque <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>pas de lait &amp; le petit quelquefois <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>est couché les yeux larges ouverts <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>&amp; les poings au visage. Alors il a l’air <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>de se porter tout à fait bien. Il a <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>des yeux bleux comme le bébé que 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>tu as peint<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> &amp; de grosses joues. Il donne <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>pas mal de tracas à sa mère, mais <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>cela parait inévitable &amp; elle le <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>supporte très bien. d’Ici quelques jours <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>elle va pouvoir se lever. Ce matin <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>Wil est parti, elle nous a donné un <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>bon coup de main, dans le ménage. <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>C’est une brave fille. J’étais une fois <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>avec elle chez Degas qui disait qu’elle <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>le rappelait plusieurs figures de dans les <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>vieux tableaux Hollandais &amp; lui donnait <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>bien envie d’aller voir les musées <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>chez nous.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Il a sorti plusieurs choses <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>pour lui faire voir<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui lui plaisait <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>beaucoup. Les femmes nues, elle les comprenait <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>très bien. Nous étions aussi un matin dans le <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Louvre où il y a plusieurs tableaux de 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>déplacés. Le v<c type="kp">_</c>d<c type="kp">_</c> Meer de Delft<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> à la cimaise<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>les petits philosophes de Rembrandt<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> sont <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>un peu nettoyés<c type="kk">/</c> ce qui permet de les <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>voir comme jamais. L’infante Marguerite<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>est au salon carré.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Enfin on a fait <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>quelque remaniements qui étaient bien <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>nécessaires. Le medecin qui est venu chez Jo <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>disait de Wil<c type="kk">/</c> elle est bien trop bonne <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>pour se marier. Néamoins je serais <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>bien aise si elle l’était.– Hier <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>Gauguin est venu à Paris &amp; il <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>demandait beaucoup après toi. Il <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>vient içi pour voir s’il peut trouver <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>à se placer pour faire n’importe quoi <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>pour gagner sa vie,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> car il parait que <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>de Haan est très gêné aussi. Sa <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>famille ne comprend pas du tout pourquoi <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>il ne reste pas parmi elle et comme 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ce sont des juifs terribles ils pensent <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>probablement le forcer à revenir <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>en coupant les vivres. de Haan m’a <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>envoyé un tableau pour expédier à son <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>frère. On voit qu’il fait beaucoup <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>d’efforts, ce sont des oignons roses &amp; orangés<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>des pommes vertes &amp; un pot en terre<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>C’est très étudié comme valeurs &amp; influence <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>de tons les uns sur les autres. J’aimerais <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>y voir un peu plus de laisser aller mais <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>c’est très étudié et tenu dans une <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>gamme assez claire. Il y a içi trois <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>expositions<c type="kk">/</c> des Mirlitons<c type="kk">/</c> du cercle <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>Volney &amp; des Aquarellistes<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> mais il n’y <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>a pour ainsi dire rien de bon<c type="kk">/</c> c’est comme <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>si les hommes au pouvoir deviennent <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>de plus en plus gâteux. J’espère que ta <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>santé continuera à être bonne &amp; que les choses <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>qui te donnent des soucis puissent disparaître<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">bien bonjour de Jo, Bon courage &amp; merçi encore <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>de ta bonne lettre. Poignée de mains<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-31" n="31">cimaise<c type="kk">/</c> &lt; cimèse</note>
<note target="l-60" n="60">gamme &lt; game</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Paris 9 Feb. 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Vincent</ab>
<ab>You gave us great pleasure with your last letter,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and fortunately we can see that things are going fairly well as regards your health.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Things are going well at home with us, <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> is nursing the <rs type="pers" key="418">baby</rs> and has no lack of milk, and the little one sometimes lies down with his eyes wide open and his fists against his face. Then he has the look of being completely well. He has blue eyes like the <rs type="pers" key="651">baby</rs> 
      <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> you painted,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> and fat cheeks. He gives his mother all sorts of trouble, but that seems inevitable and she bears it very well. In a few days from now she’ll be able to get up. This morning <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> left, she gave us a lot of help in the household. She’s a good girl. I was once with her at <rs type="pers" key="981">Degas</rs>’s place; he said that she reminded him of several figures from the old Dutch paintings, and made him very much want to go and see the museums in our country.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> He brought out several things to show her, which pleased her greatly. She understood the female nudes very well. One morning, too, we were in the Louvre, where several paintings 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> have been moved. The <rs type="pers" key="1421">Vermeer</rs> of Delft<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> at eye height, <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s little Philosophers<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> are cleaned a little, which enables one to see them as never before. The Infanta Marguerita<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> is in the Salon Carré.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> Anyway, they’ve made a few reorganizations that were really necessary. The <rs type="pers" key="640">doctor</rs> who came to Jo said of Wil, she’s really much too good to get married. Nevertheless I’d be really happy if she were. Yesterday <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> came to Paris and he asked a lot of questions about you. He has come here to see if he can find a position to do anything at all to earn his living,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> for it seems that <rs type="pers" key="1075">De Haan</rs> is very hard up too. His family don’t understand at all why he doesn’t remain with them, and as 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> they’re terrible Jews they’re probably thinking that they can force him to come back by cutting off his allowance. De Haan sent me a painting to dispatch to his brother. One can see that he’s trying very hard, it’s pink and orange onions, green apples and an earthenware pot.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> It’s very carefully studied as regards values and influence of tones, one on another. I’d like to see a little more casualness in it, but it’s very carefully studied and kept in quite a bright range of colours. There are three exhibitions here, of the Mirlitons, the Volney circle and the Aquarellistes,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> but there is, so to speak, nothing good in them, it’s as if the men with the power are becoming more and more senile. I hope that your health will continue to be good and that the things that make you worry will disappear.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Warm regards from <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>, be of good heart, and thank you again for your kind letter. Handshake.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This was <ref target="let850.xml">letter 850</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Marcelle Roulin </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2753">F 441 / JH 1641</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>Theo and <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> probably visited <rs type="pers" key="981">Degas</rs> in his studio at 19 rue Fontaine on 17 January 1890. This, at any rate, is the date recorded in the ledgers of the firm of <rs type="pers" key="797">Boussod, Valadon &amp; Cie</rs> for the purchase by Theo of a work by Degas (<hi rend="ital">GRI, Goupil Ledgers</hi>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1421">Jan Vermeer of Delft</rs>, <hi rend="ital">The lacemaker</hi>, c. 1669-1671 (Paris, Musée du Louvre). <rs type="ill" key="443">Ill. 443</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
      <ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1295">Rembrandt</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="1711">Philosopher in meditation</rs>
                        </hi> and <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="1712">Philosopher with an open book</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let034.xml#n-6">see letter 34, n. 6.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1402">Diego Rodríguez de Silva y Velázquez</rs>,<hi rend="ital"> The Infanta  Margarita, daughter of Philip <hi rend="sc">iv</hi>, king of Spain (1651-1673)</hi> (Paris, Musée du Louvre). <rs type="ill" key="439">Ill. 439</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>For the Salon Carré, <ref target="let567.xml#n-2">see letter 567, n. 2.</ref> <rs type="pers" key="1402">Velázquez</rs>’s painting formerly hung in the room containing the <rs type="pers" key="480">La Caze</rs> Collection. See Baedeker 1889-1, pp. 128-129.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s plan to go to Tonkin, <ref target="let840.xml#n-3">see letter 840, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Still life: pot, onions, bread and green apples</hi>, 1889-1890 (Pont-Aven, Musée de Pont-Aven). <rs type="ill" key="915">Ill. 915</rs>. The work is signed ‘A mon cher frère MH’. <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> painted the same still life from a different angle in <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="912">Still life with onions</rs>
                        </hi>, 1889 (W380) (Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptotek) and <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="otherart" key="949">Still life with onions</rs>
                        </hi>, 1889 (no W-no.) (private collection).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                        <rs type="pers" key="1075">Meijer de Haan</rs> had two brothers: <rs type="pers" key="95">Samuel</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="96">Aron</rs>. It is not clear for which brother the still life was intended. In the last years of his life, Meijer must have been on good terms with Aron at least, since his studio was in Aron’s house in Amsterdam. In mid-October 1890 Gauguin wrote to <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> that De Haan’s problems with his family had not yet been resolved: ‘De Haan is in Paris at the moment to try to sort things out regarding his family, who have been cutting off his allowance for some time!’ (De Haan est à Paris en ce moment pour tâcher de se débrouiller vis-à-vis de sa famille qui lui coupe les vivres depuis quelque temps!). See <hi rend="ital">Gauguin lettres</hi> 1946, p. 204.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>The exhibitions of the Cercle de l’Union artistique (Cercle des Mirlitons), the Cercle artistique et littéraire de la rue Volney, and well as of the Société d’Aquarellistes français, belonged to the so-called ‘petits Salons’, which were organized in the first months of the year by the artists’ associations. In contrast to the Salon, these were small exhibitions for an aristocratic public, where established artists were given the opportunity to exhibit their ‘informal’, more personal or unfinished works. See Martha Ward, ‘Impressionist installations and private exhibitions’, <hi rend="ital">The Art Bulletin</hi> 73 (December 1991), pp. 605-609.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">All that is known about the exhibition of the Cercle de l’Union artistique is that it took place in rue Boissy d’Anglais and ran from 3 February to 12 March 1890 (<hi rend="ital">Moniteur des Arts</hi>, 7 February 1890, p. 46, column on ‘Expositions ouvertes’).</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The exhibition of the Cercle Volney, which was held from 27 January to 24 February 1890, was reviewed in detail in the Moniteur des Arts of 31 January. Of the several dozen artists who took part, <rs type="pers" key="1392">Toulouse-Lautrec</rs> was one of the most modern.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">On display at the twelfth exhibition of Société d’Aquarellistes français (founded in 1879), held at Georges Petit’s at 8 rue de Sèze, were 194 watercolours and drawings by 38 artists, including Albert Besnard and Jean-Georges Vibert. A facsimile of the catalogue appears in G. Dugnat, <hi rend="ital">La Société d’Aquarellistes français 1879-1896</hi>: catalogue illustrés des expositions. Dijon 2002, vol. 2 (unpaginated).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>