<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Tuesday, 26 November 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let823"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">823</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">615</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">825</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Tuesday, 26 November 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Tuesday, 26 November 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mrs van Gogh and Willemien’s move to Leiden <ref target="let798.xml">(798)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Vincent has paintings intended for his mother and Willemien <ref target="let803.xml">(803)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="4">
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. nos. b664 V/1962 and b2970 V/1982 (envelope)</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>An extant envelope probably belonged to the present letter, because it bears writing in another hand, which says: ‘Superb letter to be reproduced almost in its entirety. The olive trees’. In the present letter Van Gogh treats this subject in detail. The envelope is postmarked 26 November, so we have dated the letter to Tuesday, 26 November 1889.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>The front of the envelope bears the postmark ‘ST REMY DE PROV /4e 26 NOV 89’, and the back is marked ‘PARIS DISTRIBON /3e 27 NOV 89’. Stamp: 15 centimes. The address reads: ‘Monsieur Th. van Gogh/ 8 Cité Pigalle/ <hi rend="ital">Paris</hi>’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <surface n="b 0664" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000907_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000907_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000907_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
        <surface n="b 0664" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000907_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000907_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000907_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000907_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000907_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000907_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
        <surface n="b 2970 V/1982" xml:id="surf-pb-2r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001004167_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2r-4">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001004167_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001004167_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001004167_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
        <surface n="b 2970 V/1982" xml:id="surf-pb-2v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001004167_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-2v-5">
                <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001004167_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001004167_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001004167_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>j’ai à te remercier beaucoup d’un envoi de <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>couleurs qui était encore accompagné d’un veston de laine excellent<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Que tu es bon pour moi et comme je voudrais pouvoir faire quelque <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>chôse de bon afin de te prouver que je voudrais être moins ingrat<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Tes couleurs m’arrivaient au bon moment car ce que j’avais <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>rapporté d’Arles<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> est presqu’épuisé. C’est que j’ai travaillé ce mois <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>ci dans les vergers d’oliviers car ils m’avaient fait enrager <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>avec leurs Christs au jardin où rien n’est observé.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> Bien entendu chez <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>moi il n’est pas question de faire quelque chôse de la bible – et <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>j’ai écrit à Bernard et aussi à Gauguin que je croyais que la <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>pensée et non le rêve était notre devoir<c type="kk">/</c> que donc j’étais étonné <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>devant leur travail de ce qu’ils se laissent aller à cela. Car Bernard <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>m’a envoyé photos d’après ses toiles<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> Ce que cela a c’est que ce sont <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>des espèces de rêves &amp; cauchemars<c type="kk">/</c> qu’il y a de l’érudition – on voit <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>que c’est quelqu’un qui raffole des primitifs – mais franchement <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>les préraphaelites anglais<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> faisaient cela bien mieux et <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>puis Puvis et Delacroix c’est bien plus sain que ces préraphaelites<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Donc cela me laisse pas froid mais cela me cause un sentiment <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>pénible de dégringolade au lieu de progrès. Eh bien pour secouer <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>cela<c type="kk">/</c> matin et soir de ces jours clairs et froids mais par <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>un bien beau et franc soleil<c type="kk">/</c> je suis allé tripoter dans les <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>vergers et il en est resulté 5 toiles de 30<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> qui avec les 3 études <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>d’oliviers que tu as<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> constituent au moins une attaque de la <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>difficulté. L’olivier est changeant comme notre saule ou tétard <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>du Nord. Tu sais que les saules sont fort pittoresques<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>malgré que cela paraisse monotone c’est l’arbre dans le <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>caractère du pays. Or ce que le saule est chez nous<c type="kk">/</c> exactement <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>la même importance ont l’olivier et le cypres ici. Ce que j’ai fait <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>est un peu dur et grossier réalisme à côté de leurs abstractions <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>mais cela donnera pourtant la note agreste et sentira le terroir<c type="kp">_</c>– Que je voudrais <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>voir les études sur nature de Gauguin et de Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> le dernier me parle de <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>portraits qui sans doute me plairaient davantage.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’espère m’habituer à travailler dans le froid – le matin il y a des effets <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>de gelée blanche et de brouillard fort interessants puis j’ai toujours <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>le grand désir de faire pour les montagnes et pour les cyprès ce que je viens <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>de faire pour les oliviers<c type="kk">/</c> donner un coup de collier<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>
<ab rend="indent">C’est que cela a rarement été peint l’olivier et le cyprès et au point de vue <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>de placer les tableaux cela <hi rend="ital">doit</hi> aller en Angleterre<c type="kk">/</c> je sais assez ce qu’ils cherchent <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>par là<c type="kp">_</c>– Quoiqu’il en soit<c type="kk">/</c> de cela je suis presque sûr de faire ainsi de temps à autre <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>une chôse passable. C’est reellement de plus en plus mon opinion ainsi que je l’ai <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>dit à Isaacson<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> en travaillant assidument sur nature sans se dire d’avance<c type="kk">/</c> je veux faire <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>ceci ou cela<c type="kk">/</c> travaillant comme si l’on faisait des souliers<c type="kk">/</c> sans préoccupations artistiques<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>on ne fera pas toujours bien mais les jours où l’on y pense le moins on trouve <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>un motif qui se tient avec le travail de ceux qui nous ont dévancés<c type="kp">_</c> On apprend <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>à connaitre un pays qui est au fond tout autre qu’il ne parait à première vue<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>Au contraire on se dira<c type="kk">/</c> je veux achever mes tableaux davantage<c type="kk">/</c> je veux les faire avec <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>soin; un tas d’idées comme cela devant les difficultés du temps<c type="kk">/</c> de l’effet changeant<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>se trouve reduit à ne pas être praticable et je finis par me résigner en <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>disant<c type="kk">/</c> c’est l’experience et le petit travail <hi rend="ital">de chaque jour </hi>qui à la longue <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>seul murit et permet de faire plus complet ou plus juste<c type="kp">_</c> Alors <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>le travail lent et long est la seule route et toute ambition d’y tenir à <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>bien faire<c type="kk">/</c> fausse<c type="kp">_</c> Car il faut tout aussi bien rater des toiles en montant <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>à la brèche chaque matin que d’en réussir<c type="kp">_</c>– Pour peindre<c type="kk">/</c> l’existence <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>tranquille réglée serait donc absolument necessaire et au temps qui court <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>qu’y peut on<c type="kk">/</c> lorsqu’on voit que par ex. Bernard est pressé pressé toujours pressé <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>par ses parents. Il ne peut pas comme il veut et bien d’autres avec lui<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>Se dit-on<c type="kk">/</c> je ne peindrai plus<c type="kk">/</c> mais que fera-t-on alors? Eh – il faudrait <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>inventer un procédé de peinture plus expeditif<c type="kk">/</c> moins couteux que l’huile <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>et pourtant durable. Un tableau... ca finira par devenir banal comme un <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>sermon<c type="kk">/</c> un peintre comme un être en retard d’un siècle. C’est pourtant <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>dommage qu’il en soit ainsi. Or si les peintres eussent mieux compris Millet <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>comme homme – or de certains tel Lhermitte et Roll l’ont saisi – les chôses <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>n’en seraient pas ainsi. Il <hi rend="ital">faut</hi> travailler autant et avec aussi peu de prétentions <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>qu’un paysan si on veut durer.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>
<ab rend="indent">Et mieux aurait valu que de faire des expositions grandioses<c type="kk">/</c> s’adresser au <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>peuple et travailler pour que chacun puisse avoir chez soi des tableaux <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>ou des reproductions qui soient des lecons comme l’oeuvre de Millet.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je suis tout à fait au bout de ma toile et lorsque tu pourras <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>je te prie de m’en envoyer 10 mètres<c type="kp">_</c>– Alors je vais attaquer <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>les cyprès et les montagnes. Je crois que cela doit être le centre <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>du travail que j’ai fait çà et là en Provence et alors nous pouvons <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>conclure le sejour ici lorsque cela conviendra<c type="kp">_</c>– Ce qui n’est pas <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>pressé car Paris ne fait en somme que distraire<c type="kp">_</c> Je ne sais pourtant <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>pas n’etant pas toujours pessimiste – je me dis toujours que j’ai encore <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>au coeur de peindre un jour une librairie de romans avec l’etalage <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>jaune rose<c type="kk">/</c> le soir<c type="kk">/</c> et les passants noirs – c’est un motif si <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>essentiellement moderne. Parceque ca parait aussi au figuré un tel <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>foyer de lumière<c type="kp">_</c>– Tenez cela serait un motif qui ferait bien <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>entre un verger d’oliviers et un champ de blé<c type="kk">/</c> les semailles <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>des livres<c type="kk">/</c> des estampes<c type="kp">_</c>– Cela je l’ai bien au coeur pour le faire <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>tel qu’une lumière dans les ténèbres. Oui il y a moyen de voir Paris <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>en beau<c type="kp">_</c>– Mais enfin les librairies ne sont pas des lièvres et <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>ca ne presse pas et j’ai bonne volonté pour travailler encore ici <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>un an ce qui sera probablement plus sage.</ab>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab rend="indent">La mère doit depuis une bonne quinzaine être à Leyde.</ab>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab rend="indent">j’ai tardé à t’envoyer les toiles pour elles<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> parceque je les joindrai à <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>la toile du champ de blé pour les Vingtistes.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Bien des choses à Jo<c type="kk">/</c> elle est bien brave de continuer à <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>se bien porter.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> merci encore une fois des couleurs et <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>du veston de laine et bonne poignée de main en pensee<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab>t. à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
    <ab>Vincent</ab>
                <pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/>
                <pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-47" n="47">soin; &lt; soin</note>
<note target="l-62" n="62">– or <supplied>
                            <hi rend="ital">...</hi>
                        </supplied> saisi – &lt; <hi rend="ital">Dashes added by us.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>I have to thank you very much for a consignment of colours, which was also accompanied by an excellent woollen waistcoat.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> How kind you are to me, and how I’d like to be able to do something good in order to prove to you that I’d like to be less ungrateful. Your colours reached me at the right moment, for what I brought back from Arles<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> is almost exhausted. The thing is, I’ve been working this month in the olive groves, for they’d driven me mad with their Christs in the garden, in which nothing is observed.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> Of course there’s no question of me doing anything from the Bible – and I’ve written to <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, and also to <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>, that I believed that thinking and not dreaming was our duty, that I was therefore astonished when looking at their work by the fact that they give way to that. For Bernard has sent me photos of his canvases.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> The thing about them is that they’re sorts of dreams and nightmares, that there’s some erudition there – one can see that it’s someone who’s mad about the primitives – but frankly the English Pre-Raphaelites<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> did this much better, and then <rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="982">Delacroix</rs> are much healthier than those Pre-Raphaelites. So this doesn’t leave me cold, but it gives me an uncomfortable feeling of a tumble rather than progress. Well, to shake this off, I’ve been messing about in the groves morning and evening on these bright and cold days, but in very beautiful, clear sunshine, and the result is 5 no. 30 canvases<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> which, with the 3 studies of olive trees that you have,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> at least constitute an attack on the problem. The olive tree is variable like our willow or pollard in the north. You know that willows are very picturesque, despite the fact that it appears monotonous, it’s the tree typical of the country. Now what the willow is in our native country, the olive tree and the cypress have exactly the same importance here. What I’ve done is a rather harsh and coarse realism beside their abstractions, but it will nevertheless impart the rustic note, and will smell of the soil. How I’d like to see the studies from nature by <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, the latter tells me of portraits which doubtless would please me more. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I hope I’ll get used to working in the cold – in the morning there are very interesting effects of white frost and fog, and I still have the great desire to do for the mountains and for the cypresses what I’ve just done for the olive trees, have a really good go at them.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The thing is, the olive tree and the cypress have rarely been painted, and from the point of view of placing the paintings this <hi rend="ital">ought</hi> to go to England, I know well enough what they’re looking for over there. Whatever the case, I’m almost sure that in this way I’ll do something passable from time to time. As I said to <rs type="pers" key="1103">Isaäcson</rs>,<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> it’s really more and more my opinion that by working assiduously from nature, without saying to oneself in advance, I want to do this or that, by working as if one were making shoes, without artistic preoccupations, one won’t always do well, but on the days when one thinks about it the least one finds a subject that holds its own with the work of those who came before us. One learns to know a country that’s basically quite different from what it appears at first sight. On the contrary, one will say to oneself, I want to finish my paintings better, I want to do them with care; in the face of the difficulties of the weather, of changing effects, a heap of ideas like this finds itself reduced to being impracticable, and I end up resigning myself by saying, it’s experience and <hi rend="ital">each day’s</hi> little bit of work alone that in the long run matures and enables one to do things that are more complete or more right. So slow, long work is the only road, and all ambition to be set on doing well, false. For one must spoil as many canvases as one succeeds with when one mounts the breach each morning. To paint, the tranquil, regulated life would therefore be absolutely necessary, and at present what can one do when one sees that <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, for example, is always put under pressure, pressure, pressure by his <rs type="pers" key="15 16">parents</rs>. He can’t do as he wants, and many others with him. One says to oneself, I shan’t paint any more, but what will one do then? Ah – a more expeditious painting process should be invented, less expensive than oil and yet durable. A painting... it will end up becoming as commonplace as a sermon, a painter like someone who’s a century behind the times. It’s a shame, though, that it should be so. Now if the painters had better understood <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs> as a man – now some like <rs type="pers" key="1179">Lhermitte</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="1329">Roll</rs> have grasped him – things wouldn’t be so. One <hi rend="ital">must</hi> work as hard and with as few pretensions as a peasant if one wants to last. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And instead of putting on grandiose exhibitions, it would have been better to address oneself to the common people, and work so that everyone may have paintings or reproductions at home, which are lessons like the work of <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m completely at the end of my canvas, and when you can please send me 10 metres. Then I’m going to attack the cypresses and the mountains. I think that this must be the centre of the work I’ve done here and there in Provence, and then we can conclude the stay here when it’s convenient. Which isn’t urgent, for Paris only distracts, after all. I don’t know, though, not always being a pessimist – I keep telling myself that I still have it in my heart to paint a bookshop one day with the shop window yellow-pink, in the evening, and the passers-by black – it’s such an essentially modern subject. Because it also appears such a figurative source of light. I say, that would be a subject that would look good between an olive grove and a wheatfield, the sowing of books, of prints. I have that very much in my heart to do, like a light in the darkness. Yes, there’s a way of seeing Paris as beautiful. But anyway, bookshops aren’t hares, and there’s no hurry, and I have a good will to work here for another year, which will probably be wiser.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">
                    <rs type="pers" key="524">Mother</rs> must have been in Leiden for a good fortnight by now.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve delayed sending you the canvases for them<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> because I’ll include them with the canvas of the wheatfield for the Vingtistes.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Warm regards to <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>, she’s very good, continuing to be well.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> Thank you once again for the colours and for the woollen waistcoat, and good handshake in thought.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
    <ab>Vincent</ab>
                <pb f="2r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-4" facs="#zone-pb-2r-4"/>
                <pb f="2v" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-2v-5" facs="#zone-pb-2v-5"/>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
    
    <note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
                    <ab>For the paint order, see <ref target="let816.xml">letter 816</ref>. On 17 November 1889 Theo recorded in his account book the purchase of a ‘gilet de chasse’ (hunting waistcoat) for Vincent for 9 francs. See <hi rend="ital">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 64.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
                    <ab>Van Gogh had bought paint on his last visit to Arles; see letter <ref target="let820.xml">820</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
                    <ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> had sent Van Gogh a sketch of his painting <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="101">Christ in the Garden of Olives</rs>
                        </hi>; see <ref target="let817.xml">letter 817</ref>. <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, too, had recently painted a <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="2">Christ in the Garden of Olives</rs>
                        </hi> and had sent a photograph of it to Vincent (<ref target="let819.xml#n-4">see letters 819, n. 4</ref> and <ref target="let822.xml#n-10">822, n. 10</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
                    <ab>The letter to <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> is not known; the letter to <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs> is <ref target="let822.xml">letter 822</ref>. Bernard had sent photographs not only of the work just mentioned, but also of his paintings <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="2308">The adoration of the shepherds</rs>
                        </hi>, <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="2309">The annunciation</rs>
                        </hi> and <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="2301">Christ meeting his mother</rs>
                        </hi>. See <ref target="let822.xml">letter 822</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
                    <ab>For the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, see <ref target="let625.xml#n-10">letter 625, n. 10</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
                    <ab>These five no. 30 canvases of olive groves are <hi rend="ital">Olive grove</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2871">F 707 / JH 1857</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive grove</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2869">F 708 / JH 1855</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive grove</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2870">F 710 / JH 1856</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive pickers</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2867">F 587 / JH 1853</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Olive grove</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2868">F 586 / JH 1854</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
                    <ab>
                        <hi rend="ital">Olive trees with the Alpilles in the background</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2803">F 712 / JH 1740</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive grove</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2819">F 715 / JH 1759</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Olive grove</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2818">F 585 / JH 1758</rs>) were at Theo’s. See letters 805 and 806.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
                    <ab>Van Gogh is referring to the letter to <rs type="pers" key="1103">Isaäcson</rs> that he had enclosed with letter <ref target="let820.xml">820</ref> to Theo, asking him to forward it.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
                    <ab>Vincent had seven canvases which he intended his <rs type="pers" key="524">mother</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> to have; see <ref target="let811.xml">letter 811</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
                    <ab>
                        <hi rend="ital">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
    <note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
                    <ab>Theo’s health was not at all good. This was confirmed yet again in October 1889, when his application for life insurance was denied. This rejection was a disillusionment and Theo felt that he had let his family down. <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> wrote to her sister <rs type="pers" key="24">Mien</rs>: ‘Make sure nobody writes a single word about it or alludes to it in any way – for heaven’s sake make sure they do not do that’ (FR b4294, 28 October 1889; <hi rend="ital">Brief happiness</hi> 1999, p. 35).</ab>
                </note>
</div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>