<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Monday, 21 October 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let811"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">811</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">612</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">813</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Monday, 21 October 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Monday, 21 October 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mrs van Gogh and Willemien’s move to Leiden <ref target="let798.xml">(798)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Cor’s departure for South Africa <ref target="let784.xml">(784)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Vincent has paintings intended for his mother and Willemien <ref target="let803.xml">(803)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="4">
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b660 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Van Gogh writes: ‘I wanted to write to you one more time while you’re still in the old house’ (<ref target="#l-1*">ll. 1*-2</ref>). Mrs van Gogh and Willemien were to move on Saturday, 2 November 1889 from Breda to Leiden. He wrote the same thing to his sister Willemien (<ref target="let812.xml">letter 812</ref>), so there is a good chance that the two letters were sent at the same time. Moreover, Vincent thanks his mother for sending him news of Cor (who has gone to South Africa), news which she had also passed on to Theo (<ref target="let813.xml">see letter 813</ref> of 22 October). Assuming that Mrs van Gogh sent her sons news of their brother at more or less the same time, and that Vincent responded immediately, we have dated both letters sent to Breda to about Monday, 21 October 1889.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0660" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000903_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000903_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000903_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000903_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000903_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0660" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000903_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000903_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000903_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000903_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000903_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000903_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste Moeder,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Nog een keer wilde ik U <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>schrijven terwijl U nog in het oude huis zijt. <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>om U voor Uw laatsten brief en de tijding <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>van Cor’s goede reis te bedanken.</ab>
                <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik geloof dat hij er met animo zal werken <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>en nu en dan wat pleizier in zijn leven <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>hebben<c type="kp">_</c> Wat hij U schrijft doet mij denken <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>aan wat mijn vriend Gauguin me vertelde <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>van Panama en Brazilië.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> Dat Isaäcson <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ook naar de Transvaal gaat wist ik nog niet<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>U weet dat ik hem nooit persoonlijk heb ont<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>moet – maar laatst heb ik hem eens geschreven<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>omdat hij min of meer van plan was in een <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>Hollandsche courant over mijn werk te schrijven<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>wat ik hem verzocht niet te doen<c type="kk">/</c> doch tevens <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>om hem voor zijn trouwe sympathie te <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>bedanken want van begin af aan dachten <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>wij dikwijls aan elkaars werk en hebben <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>dezelfde idees betreffende onze oude Hollandsche <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>en de tegenwoordige fransche schilders<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">En het werk van de Haan houd ik ook veel <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>van.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>
<ab rend="indent">Nu kan ik U mededeelen dat wat ik U <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>beloofde geheel klaar is – namelijk <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>vijf van mijn landschapstudies<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> en een klein <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>portret van me zelf.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> en een studie van een <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>interieur.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Het zal U echter vrees ik tegen<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>vallen en een en ander U onbelangrijk <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>en leelijk lijken. Wil en U kunt er <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>mede doen wat U wilt en indien U lust heeft <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>er aan de andere zusters een paar van geven<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>daarom stuur ik er een paar <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>meer.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Maar dit is iets wat mij niet aangaat<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>alleen wilde ik zorgen dat er wat van mij <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>in de familie zij en tracht er alleen naar <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>het een en ander een soort geheel vorme <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>dat ik liever bij een zag blijven zoo dat <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>het met der tijd wat belangrijker wordt<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>Alleen<c type="kk">/</c> ik kan me al vooruit begrijpen <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>U geen plaats zult hebben voor alle 6 en dus <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>doe er mede wat U wilt. Maar ik raad <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>U aan ze althans eenigen tijd bij een <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>te houden<c type="kk">/</c> daar U dan beter oordeelen kunt <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>welke op den duur U het best bevallen.</ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het spijt mij dat Tante Mina zooals U <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>schrijft zoo lijdende is<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> het is al heel wat jaren <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>geleden ik haar zag<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Zeker ben ik het met U eens dat het voor Theo <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>zóó heel wat beter is dan vroeger en hoop <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>maar alles goed afloope met Jo’s bevalling<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>dan zijn ze voor een heelen tijd er boven op<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Het is altijd goed men het eens ondervinde <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>hoe een mensch in de wereld komt en <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>dat brengt menig karakter tot meer <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>rust en waarheid<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">De natuur is hier zeer mooi in den herfst<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>en de geele blaren. Het spijt mij alleen <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>er hier niet meer wijngaarden zijn<c type="kk">/</c> ik <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>ben er een gaan schilderen op een paar <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>uur afstand echter.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Het gebeurt een <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>groot veld geheel purper en rood wordt <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>zoo als bij ons de wilde wingerd en daar<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>naast een vierkant geel en wat verder <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>een plek die nog groen is.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dat alles onder een lucht van prachtig <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>blaauw en lilas rotsen in het verschiet<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>Verleden jaar had ik beter gelegenheid <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>om dat te schilderen dan nu<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik had gaarne zoo iets gevoegd bij <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>wat ik U stuur maar dat blijf ik U <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>schuldig voor een volgend jaar.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Aan het portretje van mezelf dat ik er bij <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>voeg zult U zien dat ofschoon ik Parijs<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>Londen en zooveel andere groote steden zag <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>en dat jaren lang<c type="kk">/</c> ik toch er zoo min <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>of meer als een boer van Zundert<c type="kk">/</c> b.v. <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>Toon of Piet Prins<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> uit ben blijven <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>zien en ik verbeeld me soms ik ook <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>zoo gevoel en denk<c type="kk">/</c> alleen zijn de boeren <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>van meer nut in de wereld. Eerst als men <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>al de rest heeft krijgen de menschen gevoel <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>voor<c type="kk">/</c> behoefte aan schilderijen<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>boeken<c type="kk">/</c> enz. In mijn eigen schatting reken <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>ik me dan ook bepaald beneden de boeren. <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Enfin ik ploeg op mijn doeken als zij op hun <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>akkers<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>
<ab rend="indent">Het gaat anders in ons vak triest genoeg – <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>dat is wel altijd zoo geweest eigentlijk – maar <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>het is tegenwoordig al heel bar.</ab>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab rend="indent">En toch zijn er nooit zulke prijzen besteed <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>voor schilderijen als heden ten dage<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat maakt dat wij nog werken is vriendschap <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>onder elkander en liefde voor de natuur <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>en enfin<c type="kk">/</c> als men zich al de moeite heeft <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>getroost om meester van zijn penseel te <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>worden <hi rend="ital">kan men het schilderen niet laten</hi>
                    <c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik behoor bij anderen vergeleken <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>nog tot de gelukkigen maar <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>reken eens hoe het zijn moet als iemand <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>het vak begint en het moet laten steken voor <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>hij iets gedaan heeft<c type="kk">/</c> en zóó zijn er velen<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>
<ab rend="indent">Reken er 10 jaar noodig zijn om het vak <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>te leeren<c type="kk">/</c> wie er nu 6 b.v. doormaakt en <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>bekostigt en dan ’t moet opgeven<c type="kk">/</c> als U <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>wist hoe miserabel dat is en hoevelen er zoo <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>zijn<c type="kp">_</c>– En die hooge prijzen waarvan men hoort, <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>betaald voor werk van schilders die dood zijn en <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>bij hun leven zoo niet betaald werden, t’is een <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>soort tulpenhandel<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> waarvan de levende schilders <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>meer nadeel dan voordeel hebben. En als een <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>tulpenhandel zal dat ook vergaan.–</ab>
                <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>
<ab rend="indent">Men kan echter redeneeren dat ofschoon <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>de tulpenhandel al lang vergaan en vergeten <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>is<c type="kk">/</c> de bloem kweekers toch gebleven zijn en blijven <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>zullen. En zóó beschouw ik het schilderen dan <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>ook<c type="kk">/</c> dat het blijvende er van een soort van <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>bloemen kweeken is<c type="kp">_</c> En wat dat aangaat reken <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>ik mij gelukkig er in te zijn. Maar de rest!</ab>
                <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dit een en ander om U te bewijzen men zich <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>geen illusies moet maken. Mijn brief moet <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>weg – ik ben op t’oogenblik bezig aan een portret <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>van een van de zieken hier.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> Het is zonderling <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>dat als men een tijd lang met hen is en er <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>aan gewend is men er niet meer aan <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>denkt dat zij gek zijn. In gedachten <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>omhelsd door</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="127*" xml:id="l-127s"/>
<ab>Uw liefh.</ab>
                <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-38" n="38">bijeen &lt; bij een</note>
<note target="l-43" n="43">bijeen &lt; bij een</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear <rs type="pers" key="524">Mother</rs>,</ab>
<ab>I wanted to write to you one more time while you’re still in the old house, to thank you for your last letter and the news of <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs>’s safe passage.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I believe that he’ll work there with enthusiasm and have some enjoyment in his life now and then. What he writes to you reminds me of what my friend <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> told me about Panama and Brazil.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I didn’t know that <rs type="pers" key="1103">Isaäcson</rs> is also going to the Transvaal.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> You know that I never met him personally — but I did write to him recently<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> because he more or less intended to write about my work in a Dutch newspaper, which I asked him not to do, but at the same time to thank him for his loyal sympathy, because from the beginning we often thought about each other’s work and have the same ideas about our old Dutch and the present-day French painters.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And I also like <rs type="pers" key="1075">De Haan</rs>’s work a lot.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now I can inform you that what I promised you is entirely ready — that’s to say five of my landscape studies<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and a small portrait of myself<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> and a study of an interior.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> I’m afraid it will disappoint you, though, and a few things seem unimportant and ugly to you. <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> and you can do with them as you wish, and give the other <rs type="pers" key="401 412">sisters</rs> a couple of them if you like, that’s why I’m sending a couple more. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">But this is something that doesn’t concern me, only I wanted to make sure that there were things of mine in the family, and am only trying to form a few things into a sort of ensemble that I would prefer to see stay together so that in time it becomes rather more important. Only, I can understand in advance that you won’t have room for all 6, and so do with them as you wish. But I advise you to keep them together, at least for a while, since then you’ll be better able to judge which you like best in the long run.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m sorry that <rs type="pers" key="317">Aunt Mina</rs> is suffering so, as you write;<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> it’s a good many years since I saw her.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I certainly agree with you that it’s a good deal better for Theo like this than before, and just hope everything goes well with <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>’s confinement, then they’ll be set up for quite a while. It’s always good to experience how a human being comes into the world, and that leads many characters to more peace and truth.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The countryside here is very beautiful in the autumn, and the yellow leaves. I’m just sorry there aren’t more vineyards here, though I did go and paint one a few hours away.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> What happens is a large field turns entirely purple and red, like the Virginia creeper at home, and next to it a square of yellow and a little further on a patch that’s still green.
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">All that beneath a sky of magnificent blue, and lilac rocks in the distance. Last year I had a better opportunity to paint that than now.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I would have liked to include something like that with what I’m sending you, but I’ll have to owe it to you till another year.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll see from the little portrait of myself that I include that although I saw Paris, London and so many other large cities, and that for years at a time, I still look more or less like a peasant from Zundert, <rs type="pers" key="603">Toon</rs> or <rs type="pers" key="604">Piet Prins</rs>,<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> say, and I sometimes imagine that I feel and think like that too, only the peasants are of more use in the world. It’s only when they have all the rest that people get a feeling for, need for paintings, books etc. So in my own estimation I definitely reckon myself below the peasants. Anyway, I plough on my canvases as they do in their fields.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Otherwise things are wretched enough in our profession — that’s always been so, in fact — but it’s really very bad at present.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And yet there have never been such prices paid for paintings as nowadays.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">What keeps us working is friendship for one another and love of nature, and anyway, when one’s taken the trouble to become master of the brush, <hi rend="ital">one can’t stop painting</hi>.
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Compared with others I’m still among the fortunate ones, but just imagine what it must be like when someone starts in the profession and has to give it up before he’s done anything, and there are many like that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Reckon on 10 years needed to learn the profession, anyone who gets through 6, say, and pays for them and then has to give up, if you knew how miserable that is and how many there are like that. And the high prices one hears about, paid for work by painters who are dead and weren’t paid like that in life, it’s a sort of tulip mania<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> from which the living painters get more disadvantage than advantage. And it will also pass like tulip mania.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">One can reason, however, that although tulip mania is long gone and forgotten, the flower growers have remained and will remain. And so I regard painting in the same way, that what remains is a sort of flower growing. And as to that I reckon myself fortunate to be in it. But the rest!</ab>
<ab rend="indent">These things to prove to you than one mustn’t be under any illusions. My letter must go off — at the moment I’m working on a portrait of one of the patients here.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> It’s strange that when one is with them for some time and is used to them, one no longer thinks about their being mad. Embraced in thought by</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s travels to Brazil, <ref target="let616.xml#n-2;">see letter 616, n. 2;</ref> for his stay in Panama, <ref target="let623.xml#n-3">see letter 623, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>For a while there was talk of <rs type="pers" key="1103">Isaäcson</rs>’s going to the Transvaal. On 27 November 1889, he wrote from Amsterdam to Theo and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> that he was planning to leave in three or four weeks (FR b1901). However, it emerges from <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> van Gogh’s letter of 3 April 1890 to <rs type="pers" key="282">Dries</rs> and<rs type="pers" key="283"> Annie Bonger</rs> that he had meanwhile abandoned his Transvaal plans (FR b2864).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>This letter for <rs type="pers" key="1103">Isaäcson</rs> (which is no longer extant) had been sent by Vincent along with <ref target="let810.xml">letter 810</ref> to Theo.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Vincent’s opinion of <rs type="pers" key="1075">De Haan</rs>’s work was based only on photographs, which Theo had sent to him, of two of De Haan’s drawings (<ref target="let708.xml#n-3">see letter 708, n. 3</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>These five landscape studies were a painting of olive trees, <hi rend="ital">Wheatfield and cypresses </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2842">F 743 / JH 1790</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Reaper </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2844">F 619 / JH 1792</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Field with a ploughman </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2825">F 625 / JH 1768</rs>) and a painting of an orchard in blossom.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Self-portrait with clean-shaven face</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2769">F 525 / JH 1665</rs>). It measures 40 x 13 cm.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">The bedroom </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2845">F 483 / JH 1793</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="317">Aunt Mina (Willemina)</rs>, a sister of <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and the widow of the <rs type="pers" key="318">Rev. J.P. Stricker</rs>, lived in Amsterdam. A letter written by Mrs van Gogh to Theo and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> at the beginning of September 1889 reveals that Aunt Mina had a bad knee (FR b2906).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>
                        <hi rend="ital">Landscape in the neighbourhood of Saint-Rémy</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="3107">F 726 / JH 1874</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>In November 1888 Van Gogh had made the painting <hi rend="ital">The red vineyard </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2745">F 495 / JH 1626</rs>) in the vicinity of Arles.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
      <ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="603">Antonie (‘Toon’) Prins</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="604">Petrus (‘Piet’) Prins</rs>, who had been Vincent’s classmates at elementary school in Zundert . They were brothers of <rs type="pers" key="599">Wouterina</rs>, the Van Gogh’s maidservant, and sons of Anthonie Prins and Pieternella Konings, tenants on the Welstandshoeve no. 40 in De Wildert (south of Zundert), later no. 71. Cf. Kools 1990, pp. 52, 54, 56, 98 and 153, n. 89, and <ref target="let145.xml#n-19">letter 145, n. 19</ref>, <hi rend="ital">Map of Etten and environs</hi>, no. 39.</ab>
                </note>
      <note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
                    <ab>‘Tulip mania’ refers to buying and selling a product purely for profit. <ref target="let409.xml#n-5">See letter 409, n. 5.</ref>
                    </ab>
      </note>
      <note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
            <ab>
                  <hi rend="ital">Portrait of a man </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2855">F 703 / JH 1832</rs>) or <hi rend="ital">Portrait of a one-eyed man </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2760">F 532 / JH 1650</rs>). The latter portrait was not painted in Arles – as was long assumed – but in Saint-Rémy. See exhib. cat. Essen 1990, p. 119.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>