<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
    <title>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 December 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let826"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">826</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">616</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">828</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Anna van Gogh-Carbentus</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 December 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Anna van Gogh-Carbentus. Arles, Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 December 1889.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Mrs van Gogh and Willemien’s move to Leiden <ref target="let798.xml">(798)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="2">
<p>Entry for the Les Vingt exhibition in Brussels <ref target="let792.xml">(792)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="3">
<p>Jo’s pregnancy <ref target="let786.xml">(786)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b665 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Because this letter was most likely enclosed with a letter to Willemien (<ref target="let827.xml">letter 827</ref> of Monday, 9 or Tuesday, 10 December 1889), we have assigned it the same date.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>Most likely enclosed with <ref target="let827.xml">letter 827</ref> to Willemien.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0665" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000908_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000908_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000908_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000908_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000908_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0665" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000908_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000908_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000908_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000908_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000908_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000908_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Beste Moeder,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Regt goed kan ik het me <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>begrijpen dat U zegt in uw schrijven dat het <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>U goed deed “weer eens met zijn velen” te zijn <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>toen de kinderen van Anna<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> en Lies bij U waren<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>Wil heeft mij de woning uitvoerig beschreven en <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>erg blij ben ik dat het U in de bevinding blijkt <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>dat de verandering gemotiveerd was.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> En zoo hoop <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>ik dat U nog vele regt goede dagen zult <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>beleven te Leiden – en wees er van verzekerd <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ik zeer dikwijls aan U denk hier<c type="kk">/</c> waar ik <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>meer in me zelven gekeerd mijn dagen doorbreng <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>dan bij wijle me wenschelijk toeschijnt. Toch <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>heb ik bepaald geen reden hoegenaamd om <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>te klagen<c type="kk">/</c> me sterker &amp; gezonder en bedaarder <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>gevoelende dan vroeger en bij verleden jaar <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>om dezen tijd vergeleken<c type="kk">/</c> toen dacht ik <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>bepaald er niet meer aan te herstellen. <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>Den schok van toen zal ik echter altijd <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>blijven voelen en als ik me maar bepaal <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>bij mijn werk zal ’t beste zijn<c type="kk">/</c> de rest <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>gansch overgevende als moeielijk vereenigbaar <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>en als kunnende zorg over een en ander <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>weinig toe of afdoen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>
<ab rend="indent">Wat de tentoonstelling in Brussel betreft<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>daarom laat dat me niet onverschillig omdat <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>ik er een paar schilderijen<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> zal hebben van <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>hier die niettegenstaande ze in een heel <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>andere streek zijn gemaakt<c type="kk">/</c> geheel en al <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>gebleven zijn als waren ze b.v. in Zundert of <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>Calmpthout geschilderd en geloof ik ook <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>door menschen die geen wat men noemt <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
                    <hi rend="ital">verstand</hi> van schilderijen hebben zouden kunnen <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>worden begrepen. En zoo zal men kunnen zeggen <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>’t misschien eenvoudiger ware geweest ik maar <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>stillekens in Noordbrabant ware gebleven – <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>maar dat is al zoo als ’t is en wat zal <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>een mensch er aan doen<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>
<ab rend="indent">U zult in gedachten veel bij Theo en Jo zijn<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>erg best vind ik ’t plan dat Wil er een handje <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>zou gaan helpen in Januarij en hoop dat <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>daar maar van komen zal en als U <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>in dien tusschentijd bij Tante Mina <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>gaat logeeren zal daar ook pleizier <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>doen nu tante ziek is.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> U zult als <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>U haar ziet niet vergeten haar voor <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>me te groeten<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is moedig van haar <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>dat zij zooals U schrijft lijdt zonder klagen.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ik stel me voor een groot gedeelte van <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>’t volgend jaar hier ook door te brengen <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>daar zulks<c type="kk">/</c> al ware ’t voor mijn gezondheid <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>niet absoluut meer noodig<c type="kk">/</c> voor mijn werk – <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>daar ik hier nu wat georienteerd ben – het <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>best zou uitkomen. Het is wel niet goedkoop <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>voor wat men er voor heeft – doch met veranderen <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>komt het schilderen steeds schadelijk uit <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>en daarom denk ik er sterk over te <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>blijven aangezien ik hier in mijn werk <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>zeer geregeld kan zijn. En overigens <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>de streek niet of weinig door anderen <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>geschilderd is nog<c type="kp">_</c> Want ’t is hier een streek <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>van ’t zuiden<c type="kk">/</c> niet warmer dan bij ons en <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>de andere schilders gaan meest wat verder<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>b.v. naar Nice<c type="kp">_</c>– Het is groot nieuws dat <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>Tante niet meer te Prinsenhage is<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>maar in alle geval erg groot gelijk heeft <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>ze Jakob en consorte maar te <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>hebben afgeschaft<c type="kk">/</c> daar inderdaad die <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>steeds de eigentlijke eigenaars hebben <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>geschenen van t’heele gedoente – en <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>dit de spuigaten nog al erg uitliep<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Dat zijn van die rare dingen in t’leven <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>waar men moeielijk een touw aan <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>vast kan maken om er de reden van zijn <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>van te begrijpen. Enfin ik vind ze <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>groot gelijk heeft – en toch zal ze aan <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>Prinsenhage gehecht zijn geweest of nog zijn<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>En de gehechtheid aan de dingen is ons eigen <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>en kunnen anderen ons moeielijker afnemen.</ab>
                <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>
<ab rend="indent">En nu zeg ik U en Wil voor <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>heden goeden dag. dank nog <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>voor de berigten betreffende Cor – <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>en in gedachten omhelsd door</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>
<ab>Uw liefh<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Dear <rs type="pers" key="524">Mother</rs>,</ab>
<ab>I can very well understand that you say in your letter that it did you good ‘to have lots of people around again’ when Anna’s <rs type="pers" key="414 415">children</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="401">Lies</rs> were with you.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> described the house to me in detail, and I’m very glad that your experience proves that the reasons for the change were justified.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> And so I hope that you’ll have many more very good days in Leiden — and rest assured I think of you very often here, where I spend my days more turned in on myself than sometimes seems to me desirable. All the same, I certainly have no reason whatsoever to complain, feeling stronger and healthier and calmer than before and compared with this time last year; then I certainly thought I wouldn’t recover again. I’ll always go on feeling the shock of that time, though, and if I just stick to my work it will be all right, wholly giving up the rest as difficult to reconcile, and as worrying about things can do little either way.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards the exhibition in Brussels, why it doesn’t leave me indifferent is because I’ll have a few paintings<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> from here which, notwithstanding that they were made in a very different region, have remained completely and utterly as if they were painted in Zundert, say, or Kalmthout, and I believe could also be understood by people who don’t, as they say, <hi rend="ital">know</hi> anything about paintings. And so people could say that it would perhaps have been simpler had I just stayed quietly in North Brabant — but that’s as it is, and what is a body to do about it?<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Your thoughts will be much with Theo and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>; I think it’s a very good plan for <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> to go and lend a hand in January and hope that that will work out, and if you go to stay with <rs type="pers" key="317">Aunt Mina</rs> in the meantime will also be doing a favour there, now Aunt is ill.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> Please don’t forget to remember me to her when you see her. It’s brave of her that, as you write, she suffers without complaining. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I imagine I’ll spend a large part of next year here, too, since even if this were no longer absolutely necessary for my health, it would turn out best for my work — since I’m now fairly oriented here. It’s certainly not cheap for what one gets for it — but change is always damaging to the painting, and so I’m seriously thinking about staying, seeing as I can be very regular in my work here. And apart from that the region has hardly been painted, if at all, by anyone else yet. Because this is a region of the south here that’s no warmer than at home, and the other painters usually go a little further, to Nice, for instance. It’s great news that <rs type="pers" key="853">Aunt</rs> is no longer in Princenhage,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> but in any case she was very right to have dispensed with <rs type="pers" key="804 805">Jacob and Co.</rs>, since they indeed seemed to have always been the actual owners of the whole show — and that was really too much to bear.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> It’s one of those strange things in life that one finds hard to make head or tail of  in order to understand the reason for them. Anyway, I think she’s absolutely right — and yet she must have been or still is attached to Princenhage. And attachment to things is a part of us and it’s hard for others to take away from us.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And now I say goodbye to you and <rs type="pers" key="407">Wil</rs> for today. Thanks again for the messages about <rs type="pers" key="420">Cor</rs> — and embraced in thought by</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Your loving</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This remark must refer only to Anna’s children, and not to Lies’s illegitimate daughter, Hubertine Normance, who was born on 3 August 1886 and lived until 1969. Cf. Benno Stokvis, <hi rend="ital">Lijden zonder klagen: het tragische levenslot van Hubertina van Gogh</hi>. Baarn 1969. Vincent’s sister <rs type="pers" key="412">Anna</rs> and her husband, <rs type="pers" key="413">Joan van Houten</rs>, had two daughters, <rs type="pers" key="415">Sara</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="414">Annie</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> described her new apartment to Theo and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> as follows: ‘Wil actually has a nice little room of her own, very conveniently separated from my bedroom by a glass door that remains open a crack at night. We live in an agreeable suite, and we laid out a completely empty garden with our own shrubbery, so that we are happy to have accomplished so much’ (FR b2858).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> knew of the exhibition because Theo had written to <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> about it. <ref target="let827.xml#n-4">See letter 827, n. 4.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>For this saying of ‘Jong Jochem’, <ref target="let027.xml#n-10">see letter 27, n. 10.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Regarding <rs type="pers" key="317">Aunt Mina</rs>’s illness, <ref target="let811.xml#n-8">see letter 811, n. 8.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>After the death of her husband, <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent van Gogh</rs>, on 28 July 1888, <rs type="pers" key="853">Cornelia van Gogh-Carbentus</rs> moved to The Hague on 28 November 1889.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>This must refer to the domestic servants <rs type="pers" key="804">Jacob Vreeswijk</rs> and his wife, <rs type="pers" key="805">Sara van Toorn</rs>. By the terms of <rs type="pers" key="423">Uncle Vincent</rs>’s will, drawn up in 1877, they received 1,000 guilders. See <hi rend="ital">Testament</hi> 1977 and <hi rend="ital">GAB</hi>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>