<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Thursday, 19 December 1889.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let829"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">829</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">617</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">830</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Saint-Rémy-de-Provence</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Thursday, 19 December 1889</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh. Saint-Rémy-de-Provence, on or about Thursday, 19 December 1889.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b666 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>In <ref target="let830.xml">letter 830</ref> of 22 December, Theo confirms the receipt of the paintings mentioned in the present letter as having been sent ‘yesterday’ <ref target="#l-26">(l. 26)</ref>. Because there is nothing to indicate how long it took for this consignment to reach Paris, we assume that it was about four days. We have therefore dated the present letter to about Thursday, 19 December 1889.</p>
                    </note>
<note type="additionalDetail" xml:id="additionalDetail">
<p>The order <ref target="#l-76">(l. 76)</ref> Van Gogh enclosed for canvas and paint has not been preserved.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0666" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000909_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000909_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000909_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000909_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000909_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0666" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000909_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000909_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000909_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000909_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000909_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000909_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Theo,</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>Merci bien de ta dernière lettre,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> je suis bien aise que <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>ta santé et celle de Jo vont bien et pense bien souvent à vous autres<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab rend="indent">C’est très intéressant ce que tu racontes d’une publication de lithographies <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>coloriées avec un texte sur Monticelli<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> cela me fait franchement un <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>plaisir très vif et je serais très curieux de les voir un jour. J’espère <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>qu’il reproduira en couleur le bouquet que tu as<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> car cela est <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>une chose de première ordre comme couleur. J’aimerais bien <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>un jour faire une planche ou deux dans ce genre moi-même <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>d’après mes toiles. Ainsi je travaille à un tableau dans <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>ce moment<c type="kk">/</c> des femmes cueillant des olives<c type="kk">/</c> qui s’y prêterait je crois<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Voici les couleurs<c type="kk">/</c> le terrain est violet et plus loin ocre jaune<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>les oliviers aux troncs bronze ont un feuillage vert gris<c type="kk">/</c> le <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>ciel est entierement rose et 3 figurines rose aussi<c type="kp">_</c> Le tout <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>dans une gamme fort discrète.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> C’est une toile que je travaille <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>de tête d’après l’etude de même grandeur faite sur place<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>parceque je veux une chôse lointaine comme un vague <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>souvenir adouci par le temps. Il n’y a que deux notes<c type="kk">/</c> rose <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>et vert<c type="kk">/</c> qui s’harmonisent<c type="kk">/</c> se neutralisent<c type="kk">/</c> se font <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>opposition. J’en ferai probablement 2 ou trois répétitions car <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>enfin c’est le résultat d’une demi douzaine d’études d’oliviers<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je trouve probable que je ne ferai plus guère des chôses empâtées<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>c’est le resultat de la vie calme de reclusion que je mène et je m’en <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>trouve mieux. Au fond je ne suis pas si violent que cela<c type="kk">/</c> enfin je me <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>sens davantage <hi rend="ital">moi</hi> dans le calme.</ab>
                <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tu le verras peutêtre aussi dans la toile pour les Vingtistes que <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>j’ai expediée hier<c type="kk">/</c> le champ de blé au soleil levant.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> En même <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>temps tu recevras la chambre à coucher.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> J’y ai encore joint <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>deux dessins.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> Je suis curieux de savoir ce que tu diras du <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>champ de blé<c type="kk">/</c> il faudra le regarder pendant quelque temps <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>peutêtre. Cependant j’espère que tu m’écriras bientôt si c’est <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>arrivé en bon ordre si tu trouves une demi heure de loisir semaine <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>prochaine.–</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je serais tout à fait résigné à rester ici encore l’année prochaine parceque <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>je crois que le travail marchera un peu. Et je sens le pays ici<c type="kk">/</c> par le séjour <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>prolongé<c type="kk">/</c> autrement que le premier endroit venu – les bonnes idées germent <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>maintenant un peu et faudra les laisser se développer. Et ainsi je <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>me serais si peu écarté de l’idée d’aller chercher quelque chôse dans le pays <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>de Tartarin.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> J’ai grand désir de faire encore et les cyprès et les Alpines <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>et faisant souvent de longues courses dans toutes les directions j’ai noté <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>bien des motifs et connais de bons endroits pour lorsque les beaux jours <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>viendront. Puis en changeant au point de vue des dépenses il n’y <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>aurait guère d’avantage je crois et la réussite du travail est encore <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>plus douteuse en changeant. J’ai reçu une lettre de Gauguin encore fort bien<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>une lettre bien impregnée du voisinage de la mer<c type="kk">/</c> je crois qu’il doit <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>faire de belles choses un peu sauvages.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tu me dis de ne pas me faire <hi rend="ital">trop</hi> de soucis et que de meilleurs jours viendront <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>encore pour moi. Je dirais que ces meilleurs jours ont déjà commencés pour moi <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>même<c type="kk">/</c> lorsque j’entrevois la possibilité de compléter un peu le travail de <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>façon que tu aies une serie d’études provençales un peu senties qui se tiendront, <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>voilà ce que j’espère, avec nos lointains souvenirs de jeunesse en Hollande <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>et ainsi je me fais une fête de refaire encore les oliveuses pour la mère et <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>la soeur.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/> Et si je pouvais un jour prouver que je n’apauvrirais pas <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>la famille cela me soulagerait. Car à présent j’ai toujours beaucoup <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de remords de dépenser de l’argent qui ne rentre pas. Mais comme <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>tu dis<c type="kk">/</c> patience et travailler est la seule chance de sortir de là<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je me le dis cependant souvent que si j’avais fait comme toi<c type="kk">/</c> si <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>j’étais resté chez les Goupil<c type="kk">/</c> si je m’étais borné à vendre des <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>tableaux<c type="kk">/</c> j’aurais mieux fait.– Car dans le commerce <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>si on ne produit pas soi-même on fait produire les autres à present <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>que tant d’artistes ont besoin de soutien dans les marchands et n’en <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>trouvent que rarement.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>
<ab rend="indent">L’argent qui était chez M. Peyron est épuisé et même il <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>m’a il y a quelques jours donné 10 francs en avance. <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>et dans le courant du mois il m’en faudra bien encore <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>dix et je trouverais juste de donner à Nouvel an quelque <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>chôse aux garçons de service d’ici et au concierge<c type="kk">/</c> ce <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>qui fera encore une dizaine de francs.</ab>
                <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>
<ab rend="indent">Pour ce qui est des vêtements d’hiver<c type="kk">/</c> ce que j’ai n’est pas <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>grand chôse comme tu comprendras mais c’est chaud assez <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>et donc nous pouvons attendre jusqu’au printemps <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>avec cela<c type="kp">_</c>– Si je sors c’est pour travailler donc alors <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>je mets ce que j’ai de plus usé et j’ai un veston et pantalon <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>en velours pour ici. Je compte au printemps<c type="kk">/</c> si je suis ici<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>aller faire quelques tableaux à Arles aussi et si vers cette <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>époque-là je prends quelque chose de neuf cela suffira.</ab>
                <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je t’envoie ci-inclus une commande de toile et <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>de couleurs mais j’en ai encore et cela peut <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>attendre le mois prochain si celui ci serait trop chargé <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>déjà.</ab>
                <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>
<ab rend="indent">Du tableau de Manet dont tu parles<c type="kk">/</c> je me souviens<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="13" xml:id="note-o-13"/> <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>un ideal de figure est pour moi toujours resté le <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>portrait d’homme de Puvis de Chavannes<c type="kk">/</c> un vieillard lisant <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>un roman jaune<c type="kk">/</c> ayant à côté de lui une rose et des pinceaux <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>d’aquarelle dans un verre d’eau – et le portrait de <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>dame qu’il avait à la même exposition<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="14" xml:id="note-o-14"/> une femme <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>déjà vieille mais tout à fait telle que Michelet le sentait<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>qu’il n’y a pas de vieille femme.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-o-15"/> Ce sont là des chôses consolantes<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>voir la vie moderne claire malgré ses inévitables tristesses.</ab>
                <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>
<ab rend="indent">l’année dernière vers cette époque je ne pensais certes pas que j’en reviendrais <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>encore tant que cela.</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>
<ab rend="indent">Dis bien des chôses à Isaacson si tu le vois et à Bernard<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je regrette de ne pas pouvoir de ces jours ci envoyer les <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>oliviers mais cela sèche si mal qu’il faudra attendre<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je crois que ce serait une bonne mesure de faire venir <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>la soeur en Janvier. Ah si celle là se mariait ce serait <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>une bonne chôse.</ab>
                <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je te serre bien la main en pensée<c type="kk">/</c> je vais encore travailler <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>un peu dehors<c type="kk">/</c> il fait du mistral<c type="kp">_</c>– Vers le moment <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>du coucher du soleil cela se calme un peu d’habitude<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>alors il y a des effets superbes de ciels citron pâle <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>et les pins désolés détachent leurs silhouettes là contre <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>avec des effets de dentelle noire exquise<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>
<ab rend="indent">d’autres fois le ciel est rouge<c type="kk">/</c> d’autres fois <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>d’un ton extremement fin<c type="kk">/</c> neutre<c type="kk">/</c> de citron pâle encore <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>mais neutralisé par du lilas fin.</ab>
                <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>
<ab rend="indent">J’ai un effet de soir d’un pin encore contre du rose et du jaune vert.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-o-16"/> <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>Enfin sous peu tu verras ces toiles dont la première<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>le champ de blé<c type="kk">/</c> vient de partir. à bientôt j’espère<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>bien des choses à Jo<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>
<ab>t. à t<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-12" n="12">aux &lt; àux</note>
<note target="l-103" targetEnd="l-104" n="103-104">d’autres fois d’un &lt; d’autrefois d’un</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo,</ab>
<ab>Thanks very much for your last letter,<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I’m very glad that you and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> are in good health, and very often think of you both.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s very interesting what you tell me about a publication of coloured lithographs with a text on <rs type="pers" key="1240">Monticelli</rs>,<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> honestly, that gives me very great pleasure, and I’d be very curious to see them one day. I hope that he’ll reproduce in colour the bouquet you have,<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> for that’s a thing of the first order as regards colour. One day I’d very much like to do a print or two myself in this vein after my canvases. Thus I’m working on a painting at the moment, women picking olives, which would lend itself to it, I think. These are the colours: the field is violet and further away yellow ochre, the olive trees with bronze trunks have grey-green foliage, the sky is entirely pink, and 3 small figures pink also. The whole in a very discreet range.<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> It’s a canvas I’m working on from memory after the study of the same size done on the spot,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> because I want a far-off thing like a vague memory softened by time. There are only two notes, pink and green, which harmonize, neutralize each other, oppose each other. I’ll probably do 2 or three repetitions of it, for in fact it’s the result of a half-dozen studies of olive trees.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think it likely that I’ll do hardly any more things in impasto, it’s the result of the calm life of seclusion I’m leading, and I feel I’m better for it. Fundamentally I’m not as violent as that, anyway I feel more <hi rend="ital">myself</hi> in calmness.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll perhaps also see it in the canvas for the Vingtistes that I sent yesterday, the Wheatfield with rising sun.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> You’ll receive the Bedroom at the same time.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> I’ve also added two drawings to them.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> I’m curious to know what you’ll say about the Wheatfield, you may have to look at it for a while perhaps. However, I hope that you’ll write to me soon whether it’s arrived in good order if you find a free half hour next week. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’d be completely resigned to staying here next year too, because I think the work will get along a little. And through the prolonged stay, I feel the country here differently from the first place encountered – good ideas are now germinating a little and should be allowed to develop. And thus I wouldn’t be so very far removed from the idea of going to look for something in the land of Tartarin.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> I have a great desire to do more of both the cypresses and the Alpilles, and often going on long walks in all directions I’ve noted many subjects and know good places for when the fine days come. Then, from the point of view of expenditure there would hardly be any advantage in moving I think, and moving makes the success of the work all the more doubtful. I’ve received another very nice letter from <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>, a letter thoroughly impregnated with the proximity of the sea, I think he must be doing fine, rather savage things.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You tell me not to give myself <hi rend="ital">too many</hi> worries and that better days will come again for me. I’d say that these better days have already begun for myself, when I glimpse the possibility of completing, to some extent, the work in such a way that you’ll have a series of Provençal studies done with feeling which will hold up, this is what I hope, with our far-off memories of youth in Holland, and thus I’m treating myself by redoing the olive trees again for our <rs type="pers" key="524">mother</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="407">sister</rs>.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> And if I could one day prove that I wouldn’t impoverish the family, that would relieve me. For at present I always have a great deal of remorse in spending money that doesn’t come back. But as you say, patience and working is the only chance of getting out of that.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">However, I often tell myself that if I’d done like you, if I’d stayed at the Goupils’, if I’d restricted myself to selling paintings, I would have done better. For in the trade, if one doesn’t produce oneself one makes others produce, now that so many artists need support among the dealers and only rarely find it. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The money that was with <rs type="pers" key="568">Mr Peyron</rs> has run out, and a few days ago he even gave me 10 francs in advance. And in the course of the month I’ll certainly need another ten, and at New Year I’d consider it right to give something to the servant lads who work here, and to the porter, which will make another ten francs or so.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">As regards winter clothing, what I have isn’t very much, as you’ll understand, but it’s warm enough and so we can wait until spring with that. If I go out it’s to work, so then I put on the most worn-out things I have, and I have a velvet waistcoat and trousers for here. In the spring, if I’m here, I’m planning to go and make a few paintings in Arles as well, and if I get something new around then, that will suffice.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’m sending you enclosed an order for canvas and colours, but I still have some and it can wait until next month if this one is too heavily burdened already.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I remember the painting by <rs type="pers" key="1182">Manet</rs> you speak of.<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> As to figure, the portrait of a man by <rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs> has always remained an ideal for me, an old man reading a yellow novel, with beside him a rose and watercolour brushes in a glass of water – and the portrait of a lady that he had in the same exhibition,<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> a woman already old but completely as <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs> felt, that there’s no such thing as an old woman.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/> These are consolatory things, to see modern life as bright despite its inevitable sadnesses.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Last year around this time I was certainly not thinking that I would recover as much as this. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Give my kind regards to <rs type="pers" key="1103">Isaäcson</rs> if you see him, and to <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I regret not being able to send the olive trees one of these days, but it’s drying so badly that I’ll have to wait.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think it’ll be a good course of action to have our <rs type="pers" key="407">sister</rs> come in January. Ah, if that one could get married, that would be a good thing.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I shake your hand warmly in thought, I’m going to work some more outside, the mistral’s blowing. It usually dies down by the time the sun’s about to set, then there are superb effects of pale citron skies, and desolate pines cast their silhouettes into relief against it with effects of exquisite black lace.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">At other times the sky is red, at other times a tone that’s extremely delicate, neutral, still pale lemon but neutralized by delicate lilac.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I have an evening effect of a pine again against pink and green-yellow.<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> Anyway, shortly you’ll see these canvases, of which the first, the Wheatfield, has just left. More soon, I hope, warm regards to <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>Vincent</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This was <ref target="let825.xml">letter 825</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1149">Lauzet</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="517">Adolphe Monticelli</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let825.xml#n-7">see letter 825, n. 7.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1240">Monticelli</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="306">Vase of flowers</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let578.xml#n-4">see letter 578, n. 4.</ref> <rs type="pers" key="1149">Lauzet</rs>’s publication did not include a lithograph after this painting.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>This second version was <hi rend="ital">Women picking olives </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2880">F 656 / JH 1870</rs>). Cf. <ref target="let827.xml#n-13">letter 827, n. 13.</ref> Van Gogh says later on <ref target="#l-19">(l. 19)</ref> that he intends to make two or three repetitions. In fact he made one more repetition – <hi rend="ital">Women picking olives </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2879">F 655 / JH 1869</rs>) – for his <rs type="pers" key="524">mother</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> (<ref target="#n-12">see n. 12</ref> below).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>The first study, painted on the spot, is <hi rend="ital">Women picking olives </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2878">F 654 / JH 1868</rs>). <ref target="let827.xml#n-13">See letter 827, n. 13.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>These ‘half-dozen’ studies consisted of <hi rend="ital">Olive grove </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2871">F 707 / JH 1857</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive grove </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2869">F 708 / JH 1855</rs>),<hi rend="ital"> Olive grove </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2870">F 710 / JH 1856</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive pickers </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2867">F 587 / JH 1853</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Olive grove </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2868">F 586 / JH 1854</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Women picking olives </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2878">F 654 / JH 1868</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Wheatfield at sunrise </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2874">F 737 / JH 1862</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Vincent sent both the first version, <hi rend="ital">The bedroom </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2735">F 482 / JH 1608</rs>), and the repetition, <hi rend="ital">The bedroom </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="3007">F 484 / JH 1771</rs>); <ref target="let830.xml">see letter 830</ref>, in which Theo confirms receipt of the consignment.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Vincent probably sent drawings because Theo had asked him if he also wanted to show his drawings at the exhibition of Les Vingt (<ref target="let825.xml">see letter 825</ref>). It is not known which two drawings he sent, but possibilities include the <hi rend="ital">Wheatfield at sunrise</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="909">F 1552 / JH 1863</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">The garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs type="otherart" key="910">F 1545 / JH 1851</rs>), according to Pickvance in exhib. cat. New York 1986, p. 56, and Herzogenrath and Hansen in exhib. cat. Bremen 2002, p. 96, cat. no. 25. There is, however, no indication whatsoever that these are the drawings in question.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>For <rs type="pers" key="583">Daudet</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="459">Tartarin de Tarascon</rs>
                        </hi> and <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="460">Tartarin sur les Alpes</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let583.xml#n-9">see letter 583, n. 9.</ref> These novels are set in Provence.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>This was <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s <ref target="let828.xml">letter 828</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>The version intended for <rs type="pers" key="524">Mrs van Gogh</rs> and <rs type="pers" key="407">Willemien</rs> was <hi rend="ital">Women picking olives </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2879">F 655 / JH 1869</rs>). <ref target="let827.xml#n-13">See letter 827, n. 13.</ref> They probably never received the work, because it is assumed that <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo van Gogh-Bonger</rs> sold it in 1895. See <hi rend="ital">Account book </hi>2002, p. 183.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="13" xml:id="n-13" target="#note-t-13">
<ab>Theo had written about <rs type="pers" key="1182">Manet</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="228">In the garden</rs>
                        </hi>, which the brothers had seen at <rs type="pers" key="601">Portier</rs>’s. <ref target="let825.xml#n-2">See letter 825, n. 2.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="14" xml:id="n-14" target="#note-t-14">
      <ab>For <rs type="pers" key="1286">Puvis de Chavannes</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="320">Portrait of a man (Eugène Benon)</rs>
                        </hi> and <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="ill" key="2214">Portrait of a woman (Maria Cantacuzène)</rs>
                        </hi>, <ref target="let655.xml#n-10">see letter 655, n. 10.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="15" xml:id="n-15" target="#note-t-15">
<ab>For this passage from <rs type="pers" key="707">Michelet</rs>’s <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="11">L’amour</rs>
                        </hi>, see <ref target="let655.xml">letter 655</ref> and <ref target="let027.xml#n-2">letter 27, n. 2.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="16" xml:id="n-16" target="#note-t-16">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Pine trees with setting sun </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2863">F 652 / JH 1843</rs>). See Hendriks and Van Tilborgh 2001, p. 155 (n. 87).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>