<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Saturday, 3 May 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let867"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">867</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">T33</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">868</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Theo van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Paris</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 3 May 1890</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Theo van Gogh to Vincent van Gogh. Paris, Saturday, 3 May 1890.</p>
<note type="ongoingTopic" n="1">
<p>Seventh consignment of paintings from Saint-Rémy <ref target="let863.xml">(863)</ref>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b760 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Letter headed: ‘Paris le 3 Mai 1890’.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0760" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001028_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001028_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001028_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001028_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001028_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0760" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001028_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001028_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001028_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001028_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001028_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001028_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Paris le 3 Mai 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent,</ab>
                <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>
<ab>Je ne puis pas te <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>dire combien j’étais content de <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>ta lettre ou plustôt de tes deux <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>lettres;<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> je disais la veille de ma <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>fête<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> à Jo<c type="kk">/</c> s’il venait une lettre de <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>Vincent je ne saurais plus ce que <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>je pourais désirer qui manque à mon <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>bonheur. Et voilà que ta lettre <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>arrive. Bien entendu je voudrais <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>que tu te sentais encore mieux <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>&amp; surtout que tes tristesses puissent 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>se dissiper. Ton envoi de toiles est <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>arrivé aussi &amp; il y en a qui sont <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>bien bien belles. Le surveillant<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> &amp; l’autre <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>bonhomme avec sa face boursouflée<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>sont extraordinaires, la branches des <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>amandiers en fleurs<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> montre que <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>dans ces sujets tu n’es pas épuisé<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>Si cette année tu as manquée la <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>saison des arbres en fleurs<c type="kk">/</c> une <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>prochaine fois espérons que cela ne sera <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>pas. Les copies de Millet<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> sont peut être <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>ce que tu as fait de plus beau et <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>me fait croire que le jour où tu <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>te mettras à faire des compositions de <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>figures il nous attend encore de grandes <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>surprises. L’envoi de couleurs Tasset 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>&amp; Tangui est parti<c type="kk">/</c> je n’avais pas <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>encore reçu ta seconde lettre &amp; je me <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>disais que tu pourrais bien utiliser <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>la moitié de plus.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> La toile d’Aurier<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/> est <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>une des plus belles que tu aies encore <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>faite, elle a la richesse d’une queu de <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>paon. Toute à l’heure je vais la lui porter<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>j’avais fait faire le cadre que tu avais <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>décrit<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> car je lui dois bien cela et il n’est <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>pas riche. Et maintenant ce qu’il y a <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>de plus important dans ta seconde lettre<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>c’est tes projets de venir par içi. Je suis <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>très heureux que tu te sens la force pour <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>entreprendre un changement &amp; j’approuve <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>absolument qu’<hi rend="ital">aussitôt possible</hi> tu <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>viennes, mais tu dis que moi je dois fixer <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>l’époque quand tu dois venir. Je n’ose <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>pas prendre une décision &amp; il n’y a que <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>toi avec les conseils du D<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Peyron qui 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>puisses prendre sur toi cette responsabilité<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>Ton voyage à Arles t’était absolument <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>funeste<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="10" xml:id="note-o-10"/> est ce que cette fois çi le déplacement <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>ne te fera pas de mal? Si j’étais toi <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>j’agirais entièrement avec la manière <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>de voir de M<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Peyron &amp; en tous les <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>cas le jour que tu es décidé à venir <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>içi il faut absolument te faire accompagner <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>durant <hi rend="ital">tout le trajet</hi> par quelcun en <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>qui tu as confiance. La fatigue du voyage <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>et la sensation de retrouver des endroits <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>connus peuvent influencer sur ta maladie<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>Si possible j’aimerais tant t’avoir avec <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>nous au moins pendant quelque temps &amp; <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>si tu fais tout pour te ménager il est <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>très probable que tout marchera bien. Tu dis <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>que les gens là-bas ne comprennent rien à la <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>peinture, mais içi c’est absolument la même <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>chose &amp; il ne faut pas croire que n’importe où <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>tu trouvera cela autrement que par exception. <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>Nous avons fréquenté <hi rend="ital">une</hi> cathégorie de gens, qui <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>en ont fait leur principale occupation, mais à part <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>ceux-là c’est de l’hébreux pour le monde &amp; les choses simples <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>sont encore moins compris que là où on peut se creuser la <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>tête sur le sujet etc. J’espère que tu pourras m’écrire <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>que tu vas de mieux en mieux et que tes projets <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>pourront se réaliser prochainement. Ne te fais <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>cependant pas trop d’illusions sur la vie dans <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>le nord, en somme chaque pays a son pour &amp; <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>contre. Je t’écrirai prochainement &amp; je chercherai <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>des lith: des maitres. Je les enverrai en même <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>temps que les dessins de Brabant.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-o-11"/> Bon courage <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>&amp; bonne poignée de mains. Merci encore de tes <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>lettres &amp; de ton envoi. Si tu as besoin de quelque <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>chose dis-le. Les affaires marchent bien &amp; j’ai tout <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>ce qu’il faut. Bien bonjour de Jo &amp; du petit<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>Çi inclus leur portrait.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-o-12"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="85*" xml:id="l-85s"/>
<ab>À toi</ab>
                <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>
<ab>Theo</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-17" n="17">boursouflée &lt; bousouflée</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>Paris, 3 May 1890</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>My dear Vincent,</ab>
<ab>I can’t tell you how pleased I was by your letter, or rather your two letters;<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> I was saying to <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> the day before my birthday<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> that if a letter came from Vincent I would no longer know what I could wish for to complete my happiness. And there you are, your letter arrived. Of course I’d like you to feel better still, and above all that your sadnesses might 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> be dispelled. Your consignment of canvases has arrived too, and there are some that are very, very beautiful. The orderly<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> and the other fellow with his swollen face<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> are extraordinary, the branch of the almond trees in blossom<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> shows that you haven’t exhausted these subjects. You may have missed the season of the blossoming trees this year, but let’s hope that that won’t be the case next time. The <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs> copies<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> are perhaps the finest things you’ve done, and make me believe that big surprises still await us the day you set yourself to doing figure compositions. The consignment of <rs type="pers" key="785">Tasset</rs> 
      <pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> and <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs> colours has left, I hadn’t yet received your second letter, and I told myself that you could well use the extra half.<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> The <rs type="pers" key="521">Aurier</rs> canvas<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> is one of the finest you’ve yet done, it has the richness of a peacock’s tail. I’ll take it to him directly, I’d had the frame made that you described,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> for I certainly owe him that, and he isn’t rich. And now the most important thing in your second letter, that is your plans to come here. I’m very happy that you feel the strength to undertake a change, and I absolutely agree that you should come <hi rend="ital">as soon as possible</hi>, but you say that I myself must fix the time when you’re to come. I daren’t take a decision, and only you, with <rs type="pers" key="568">Dr Peyron</rs>’s advice, 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> can take this responsibility upon yourself. Your journey to Arles was absolutely disastrous for you,<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> will the travelling not do you harm this time? If I were you I’d act entirely in accordance with Mr Peyron’s view, and in any event on the day you’ve decided to come here you absolutely must be accompanied during <hi rend="ital">the entire journey</hi> by someone you trust. The fatigue of the journey and the sensation of rediscovering places you have known may have an influence on your illness. If possible I’d so much like to have you with us at least for a while, and if you do everything to take care of yourself it’s very likely that all will go well. You say that the people down there understand nothing of painting, but here it’s absolutely the same, and you mustn’t think that you’ll find it otherwise anywhere, except as an exception. We have frequented <hi rend="ital">one</hi> category of people, who have made it their principal occupation, but apart from them it’s Hebrew to the people, and simple things are even less understood than there where one can puzzle over the subject etc. I hope that you’ll be able to write to me that you’re getting better and better, and that your plans can soon be realized. However, don’t have too many illusions about life in the north, after all every part of the world has its pros and cons. I’ll write to you soon and shall look for lithographs of the masters. I’ll send them at the same time as the Brabant drawings.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> Be of good heart, and good handshake. Thanks again for your letters and for your consignment. If you need anything, say so. Business is going well and I have everything I need. Warm regards from <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> and the <rs type="pers" key="418">little one</rs>. Enclosed is their portrait.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Yours,</ab>
<ab>Theo</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The first letter is <ref target="let863.xml">letter 863</ref>, in which Vincent wishes Theo a happy birthday. The second is <ref target="let865.xml">letter 865</ref>, as may be deduced from a passage later in the present letter, where Theo responds to what Vincent wrote (<ref target="#l-45">ll. 45-46</ref> and <ref target="#l-64">ll. 64-66</ref>). Cf. also <ref target="#n-7">n. 7</ref> below.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Theo also wrote on 3 May to his <rs type="pers" key="524">mother</rs>, saying how happy he was to receive Vincent’s letters: ‘It is nevertheless progress, that he could write again. At the time he didn’t have the courage to read your and my letters, for his indisposition is characterized above all by melancholy spells, and everything that reminds him of the past makes him sad and melancholy. Through it all he longs to be allowed to leave the asylum and then, for example, to come here, accompanied by someone from the asylum. May that happen without harming him. <rs type="pers" key="568">Dr Peyron</rs> would prefer that he stay a while longer, but Vincent already wrote earlier on that he thought he could recover better in a house without nuns. I’ve written to both of them, to Vincent to say that he must talk to Dr Peyron before making a decision and to the Doctor that I very much wanted to comply with Vincent’s wishes, but did not want to do anything imprudent, so I’m longing to hear something from them ... I forgot to tell you that Vincent sent a number of new paintings, including some very beautiful ones. It’s amazing that, in spite of it all, he can still deliver so much work’ (FR b929).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Theo had turned 33 on 1 May.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Charles-Elzéard Trabuc </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2829">F 629 / JH 1774</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>Probably <hi rend="ital">Portrait of a one-eyed man </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2760">F 532 / JH 1650</rs>). This was not made in Arles – as was long assumed – but in Saint-Rémy. See exhib. cat. Essen 1990, p. 119 (Dutch version only).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Almond blossom </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2890">F 671 / JH 1891</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>The consignment probably contained 16 copies after prints by <rs type="pers" key="1226">Millet</rs>; <ref target="let863.xml#n-3">see letter 863, n. 3.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>For this order of paint, brushes and canvas, <ref target="let863.xml">see letter 863</ref>. The ‘second letter’ is <ref target="let865.xml">letter 865</ref>, in which Vincent announces his plan to come to the North. Theo assumed that he would remain for a while in Saint-Rémy and had therefore ordered extra paint.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>
      <hi rend="ital">Cypresses </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2809">F 620 / JH 1748</rs>); <ref target="let863.xml#n-9">see letter 863, n. 9.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>Theo had read in Vincent’s letter to <rs type="pers" key="521">Aurier</rs> suggestions about the frame (cf. the postscript to <ref target="let854.xml">letter 854</ref>, with which letter 853 to Aurier was enclosed).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="10" xml:id="n-10" target="#note-t-10">
<ab>The severe attack from which Vincent was still recovering began during his last trip to Arles on 22 February (<ref target="let857.xml#n-1">see letter 857, n. 1</ref>).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="11" xml:id="n-11" target="#note-t-11">
<ab>Vincent had asked Theo to send lithographs by old and modern artists, as well as some figure drawings he had made in Nuenen. <ref target="let863.xml">See letter 863</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="12" xml:id="n-12" target="#note-t-12">
<ab>Theo must have sent the photograph of <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> and little <rs type="pers" key="418">Vincent</rs> by <rs type="pers" key="1730">Raoul Saisset</rs> (Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b4822). <rs type="ill" key="2314">Ill. 2314</rs>.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>