<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Le Pouldu, on or about Saturday, 28 June 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/let892"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">892</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">GAC 42</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">897</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Paul Gauguin</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Vincent van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Le Pouldu</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>on or about Saturday, 28 June 1890</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>Paul Gauguin to Vincent van Gogh. Le Pouldu, on or about Saturday, 28 June 1890.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b884 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Gauguin responds to the new version (which has not survived) of <ref target="RM23.xml">RM23</ref> of about 17 June. It is not clear how soon after RM23 Van Gogh wrote the new version. Gauguin says that he found the letter waiting for him upon his return from a five-day stay in Pont-Aven. At any rate, the present letter had not arrived in Auvers by 28 June, since <ref target="let893.xml">letter 893</ref>, written on that day, makes no mention of it. (It is mentioned, however, in <ref target="let896.xml">letter 896</ref> of 2 July). We have therefore dated Gauguin’s letter to about Saturday, 28 June 1890.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0884" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001178_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001178_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001178_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001178_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001178_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0884" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001178_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001178_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001178_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001178_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001178_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001178_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Vincent</ab>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>En rentrant d’un petit voyage j’ai <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>trouvé, et votre lettre<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> et votre <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>épreuve eau forte<c type="kp">_</c>–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Nous avions été<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>de Haan et moi<c type="kk">/</c> passer 5 jours <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>à Pont-Aven, mon ancienne résidence <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>qui est à 6 lieues du Pouldu<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>
<ab rend="indent">Votre lettre ne me dit pas grand chose – <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>Si vous avez vu mes études à Paris <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>chez Goupil, ce que vous en pensez! <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>Si mon voyage projeté pour Madagascar <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>vous parait déraisonnable. J’en rêve <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>tous les jours au point que je ne travaille <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>presque pas en ce moment, voulant me <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>reposer un peu, prendre des forces <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>nouvelles po<supplied>u</supplied>r là-bas<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>
                <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>
<ab rend="indent">Et vous, vous êtes insatiable; je vois <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>que vous n’avez pas perdu de temps <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>à Auvers<c type="kp">_</c>– Il est bon cependant de se <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>reposer quelquefois l’esprit et le corps.</ab>
                <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>
<ab rend="indent">Votre idée de venir en Bretagne <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>au Pouldu me paraît excellente si elle <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>était réalisable<c type="kp">_</c>– Car nous sommes<c type="kk">/</c> de <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>Haan et moi<c type="kk">/</c> dans un petit trou <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>éloigné de la ville<c type="kp">_</c> Sans d’autre <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>communication qu’une voiture de louage. <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>Et pour un malade qui a besoin <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>de médecin quelquefois c’est scabreux. <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>À Pont Aven c’est autre chose<c type="kk">/</c> il y <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>a médecin et du monde<c type="kp">_</c>– En outre <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>si je parviens à faire mon affaire pour <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>aller à Madagascar je ne serai plus ici 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>au commencement de Septembre, ainsi <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>que de Haan qui va repartir <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>en Hollande. Voilà en toute <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>franchise la situation. Et cependant <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>Dieu sait avec quel plaisir je <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>verrais l’ami Vincent près de nous.</ab>
                <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je ne connais pas le docteur <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>Gachet mais j’ai entendu parler de <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>lui souvent par le père Pissarro. <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Et ce doit être pour vous <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>agréable d’avoir près de vous quelqu’un <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>qui sympatise avec votre travail, <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>vos idées<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>
<ab rend="indent">Hélas, moi je me vois condamné <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>à être de moins en moins compris, <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>et je dois m’en tenir à suivre 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/>
                    <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>ma voie <hi rend="ital">seul</hi>, traîner une existence <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>sans famille comme un paria<c type="kp">_</c>– <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>Aussi la solitude dans les bois me paraît <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>dans l’avenir être un paradis nouveau <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>et presque rêvé<c type="kp">_</c>– Le sauvage retournera <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>au sauvage.</ab>
                <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin! destinée écrite ne <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>peut se renverser<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>
<ab rend="indent">Amitiés de l’ami de Haan<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>
<ab rend="indent">Cordialement</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="58*" xml:id="l-58s"/>
<ab>T<c type="kp">_</c> A V.</ab>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab>Paul Gauguin</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-16" n="16">po<supplied>u</supplied>r &lt; <hi rend="ital">Text lost due to a hole in the paper.</hi>
                    </note>
<note target="l-32" n="32">plus ici &lt; plus</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Vincent</ab>
<ab>On my return from a little trip I found both your letter<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> and your proof etching.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> <rs type="pers" key="1075">De Haan</rs> and I had been to spend 5 days in Pont-Aven, my former residence which is 6 leagues from Le Pouldu.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Your letter doesn’t tell me very much: if you’ve seen my canvases in Paris at Goupil’s, what do you think of them! If my planned journey to Madagascar appears unreasonable to you. I dream of it every day, to the point where I’m scarcely working at all at the moment, wanting to rest a little, gain new strength for down there.
<pb f="1r" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-2" facs="#zone-pb-1r-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And you, you’re insatiable; I see that you haven’t been losing any time in Auvers. It’s good, though, to rest the mind and the body sometimes.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Your idea of coming to Brittany at Le Pouldu seems excellent to me if it could be put into effect. For we are, <rs type="pers" key="1075">De Haan</rs> and I, in a little hole far from the town. Without any communication other than a hired cart. And for a sick man who needs a doctor, it’s sometimes risky. At Pont-Aven it’s different, there’s a doctor and people. In addition, if I manage to sort things out to go to Madagascar I’ll no longer be here 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> at the beginning of September, like De Haan, who’s going to go back to Holland. That, in all honesty, is the situation. And however God knows how much it would please me to see our friend Vincent close to us.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t know <rs type="pers" key="389">Doctor Gachet</rs> but I’ve often heard <hi rend="ital">père</hi> <rs type="pers" key="1268">Pissarro</rs> speak of him. And it must be pleasant for you to have someone close to you who sympathizes with your work, your ideas.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Alas, I see myself condemned to be less and less understood, and I must hold fast to following 
<pb f="1v" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-4" facs="#zone-pb-1v-4"/> my way <hi rend="ital">alone</hi>, to drag out an existence without a family like a pariah. So the solitude in the woods seems to me in the future to be a new and almost dreamed-of paradise. The savage will return to savagery.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">At last! Destiny once written cannot be overturned.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Friendly greetings from our friend <rs type="pers" key="1075">De Haan</rs>.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Cordially</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Ever yours,</ab>
<ab>
                    <rs type="pers" key="1039">Paul Gauguin</rs>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>This letter is <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs>’s reaction to a new version (which has not survived) of <ref target="RM23.xml">RM23</ref>. Cf. Hulsker 1998, pp. 44-45. Around 7 July 1890, Gauguin informed Theo ‘I have had 2 quite calm letters from Vincent, which I enjoyed’ (j’ai eu 2 lettres de Vincent assez calmes qui m’ont fait plaisir) (FR b873). See <hi rend="ital">Gauguin lettres</hi> 1983, p. 189.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Later Gauguin wrote in <hi rend="ital">Avant et après</hi>: ‘The last letter I had was dated from Auvers, near Pontoise. He told me that he had hoped to recover sufficiently to come and meet me in Brittany, but that now he was forced to acknowledge the impossibility of a cure.</ab>
<ab>“Dear master (the only time he uttered this word), it is more worthy, after having known you and having caused you trouble, to die in a good state of mind than in a degraded state.”’ (La dernière lettre que j’ai eue était datée d’Auvers près Pontoise. Il me disait qu’il avait espéré guérir assez pour venir me retrouver en Bretagne, mais qu’aujourd’hui il était obligé de reconnaître l’impossibilité d’une guérison.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">“Cher maître (la seule fois qu’il ait prononcé ce mot), il est plus digne après vous avoir connu et vous avoir fait de la peine, de mourir en bon état d’esprit qu’en état qui dégrade.”) See Gauguin 1923, pp. 23-24. The letter Gauguin claims to quote is not known.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>This is the etching <hi rend="ital">Doctor Gachet with a pipe</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2921">F 1664 / JH 2028</rs>). The provenances of the various impressions do not reveal which one <rs type="pers" key="1039">Gauguin</rs> received (see Van Heugten and Pabst 1995, p. 85).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>