<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Prose passage copied from Henri Conscience’s <hi rend="ital">Le conscrit</hi> (The conscript). Ramsgate or Isleworth, between about July and November 1876.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/RM08"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">RM08</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters"/>
<idno type="brieven1990">-</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Isleworth</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>between about July and November 1876</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
</vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b88 a V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
    <p>Because Van Gogh copied this very passage in Annie Slade-Jones’s guestbook, the contributions to which are dated between July and November 1876, this loose leaf must also date from about the same time. See Pabst 1988, pp. 65-66. In <ref target="let093.xml">letter 93</ref> of October 1876, Van Gogh quotes Conscience’s <hi rend="ital">Le conscrit</hi>. We therefore date this sheet to a period beginning around July and running through November 1876. It was placed in <hi rend="ital">De brieven</hi> 1990 with letter 89 of 26 August 1876, but we see no reason to connect it with that letter.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0088 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000091_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000091_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000091_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000091_01_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0088 a" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000091_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000091_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000091_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000091_02_nf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>L’heure du départ a sonné! Devant les chaumières se tient un beau <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>jeune homme, le bâton de voyage sur l’épaule, un sac sur le dos. <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Ses yeux, ordinairement si vifs, errent lentement autour de lui; <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>sa physionomie est calme, et tout en lui semble annoncer une <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>grande tranquilité d’âme; et cependant son coeur bat violem<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>ment, et sa poitrine oppressée s’élève et s’abaisse péniblément. <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Sa mère serre une de ses mains et lui prodigue les marques <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>de la plus ardente affection; la pauvre femme ne pleure pas; <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>ses joues frémissent sous l’effort qu’elle fait pour dissimuler <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>sa douleur. Elle sourit à son enfant pour le consoler; mais <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>ce sourire, contraint et pénible, est plus triste que la plainte <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>la plus déchirante. L’autre veuve est occupée à calmer le <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>petit garçon, et essaie de lui faire accroire que Jean reviendra <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>bientôt; mais l’enfant a compris à la tristesse qui accable ses <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>parents depuis un an que la séparation est un terrible malheur, <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>et maintenant il jette des cris perçants.– Le grand-père et <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>Cathérine font à l’intérieur les derniers préparatifs du voyage: <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>ils creusent un pain de seigle et le remplissent de beurre. Ils <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>sortent avec les provisions de route et s’arrêtent auprès du jeune <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>homme. L’étable est ouverte; le boeuf regarde tristement son <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>maître et pousse par intervalles un mugissement doux et <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>mélancolique; on dirait que l’animal comprend ce qui <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>va arriver. Tout est prêt: il va partir. Déjà il a serré la <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>main de sa mère d’une étreinte plus vive et fait un pas en <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>avant; mais il jette les yeux autour de lui, embrasse d’un <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>regard affectueux l’humble chaumière qui abrita son berceau, la <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>bruyère et les bois témoins de son enfance et les champs <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>arides si souvent fécondés par les sueurs de sa jeunesse! <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>Puis son oeil s’arrête tour à tour sur les yeux de tous ceux <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>qu’il aime, sur les yeux de ce boeuf aussi, le compagnon <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>de ses rudes travaux; il couvre son visage de sa main, cache <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>les larmes qui coulent sur ses joues, et dit d’une voix presque <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>inintelligible: – A Dieu.–</ab>
                <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>
<ab rend="indent">Il relève la tête, secoue l’abondante chevelure qui tombe sur <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>son cou comme une crinière, et marche résolument en avant. <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>Mais tous le suivent: le moment de la séparation n’est pas encore venu. <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>A une certaine distance dans la direction du village à l’endroit où <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>les chemins se croisent, s’élève un tilleul auquel est suspendue <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>une Sainte Vierge. Trine l’y a placée un beau soir de Mai, <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>et Jean a fait au pied de l’arbre un prie-Dieu en gazon. <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>C’est en ce lieu sacré, où chaque jour quelqu’un d’entre <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>eux venait remercier et prier Dieu, que les paroles déchi<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>rantes de l’à Dieu échapperont à leurs lèvres tremblantes...</ab>
                <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>
<ab rend="indent">Déjà apparait au loin le tilleul, limite où doit commencer la <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>fatale séparation. Le jeune homme ralentit sa marche, tan<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>dis que sa mère, tout en lui prodiguant des caresses lui dit: <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>Jean, mon fils, n’oublie jamais ce que je t’ai dit. Aie toujours <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>Dieu devant les yeux, et ne manque jamais à dire tes prières <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>avant d’aller te coucher. Aussi longtemps que tu le feras, tu <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>resteras bon; mais s’il devait arriver qu’un soir tu oubliasses <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>de prier, songe à moi le lendemain, songe à ta mère, et tu <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>redeviendras bon et brave; car celui qui pense à Dieu et à <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>sa mère, est à l’abri de tout mal, mon cher enfant.–</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je penserai toujours, toujours à vous, mà mère, dit le jeune <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>homme avec un soupir, mais d’une voix calme, si je suis <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>triste et que je perde courage, votre souvenir sera mon appui <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>et ma consolation; et je le sens, je serai malheureux, je vous <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>aime trop tous.</ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ensuite il ne faut pas jurer, sais tu, ni mener mauvaise vie<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>Tu iras à l’église, n’est ce pas? Tu nous donneras aussi souvent <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>que possible des nouvelles de ta Santé, et tu n’oublieras <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>jamais que le moindre mot de son enfant rend heureuse <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>une mère n’est ce pas? Oh je dirai tous les jours une prière <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>à ton saint Ange gardien pour qu’il ne t’abandonne jamais! <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>Jean est profondement ému par la voix douce et pénétrante <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>de sa mère; il n’ose porter les yeux sur elle, tant le frappe à <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>cette heure solennelle, le regard brillant de la digne femme: <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>c’est la tête baissée qu’il écoute. Sa seule réponse est par<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>fois un serrement de main plus fort et un long soupir auquel <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>se mêlent de temps en temps les mots: Mère, chère Mère! <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>Ils approchaient en silence du carrefour; le grand-père se <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>plaça de l’autre côté du jeune homme, et lui dit d’un <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>ton grave: Jean, mon fils, tu rempliras tes devoirs sans répug<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>nance et avec amour, n’est ce pas? Tu seras obéissant envers tes <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>supérieurs, et tu souffriras, sans te plaindre l’injustice, <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>s’il arrive, par hasard, qu’il t’en soit fait une? Tu seras prévenant <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>et serviable pour chacun; tu feras preuve de bon vouloir, et <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>t’acquitteras courageusement de tout ce qui te sera ordonné? <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>Alors Dieu t’aidera, tes officiers et tes camarades t’aimeront. <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>Trine, sa mère et le petit garçon étaient déjà sous le tilleul, priant <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>agenouillés sur le banc de gazon. Jean n’eut pas le temps de <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>répondre aux recommandations du grand-père; sa Mère l’attirait <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>vers le banc. Tous se mirent à genoux et prièrent les mains levées <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>au ciel.–</ab>
                <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>
<ab rend="indent">Le vent murmure doucement dans les branches des sapins, le <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>soleil printanier dore de ses rayons joyeux le chemin de sable, <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>les oiseaux chantent leur gaie chanson; pourtant il règne <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>un silence solennel, car on entend distinctement la prière s’élever <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>autour du tilleul... C’est fini; tous se lèvent, mais de tous les <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>yeux s’échappe un torrent de larmes. La mère embrasse son fils <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>en poussant des plaintes déchirantes, et bien que les autres <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>aient déjà les bras ouverts pour la triste étreinte de l’àDieu, <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>elle ne laisse pas aller son enfant, elle étanche sous ses <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>baisers les larmes qui baignent ses joues, et laisse échapper <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>d’inintelligibles paroles d’anxiété et d’amour, et elle <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>pleure sur son épaule.</ab>
                <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>
<ab rend="indent">Enfin la pauvre femme abattue, épuisée et toujours <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>pleurante va s’affaisser sur le banc. Jean embrasse <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>précipitamment son grand-père et la mère de Trine; il <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>se dégage avec une douce violence de l’étreinte de son <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>petit frère au désespoir, court encore à sa mère, la <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>serre dans ses bras, dépose un baiser sur son front <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>et s’écrie d’une voix déchirante: à Dieu<c type="kp">_</c>–</ab>
                <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>
<ab rend="indent">Et, sans oser se retourner, il marche rapidement <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>dans la direction du village, jusqu’à ce qu’au <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>coin du bois, il ait disparu aux yeux de ses parents. </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>
<ab>(Conscience<c type="kk">/</c> Le Conscrit)<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-16" n="16">grand-père &lt; grand père</note>
<note target="l-49" n="49">longtemps &lt; long temps</note>
<note target="l-67" n="67">femme: &lt; femme</note>
<note target="l-71" n="71">grand-père &lt; grand père</note>
<note target="l-82" n="82">grand-père &lt; grand père</note>
<note target="l-99" n="99">grand-père &lt; grand père</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>The clock has struck the hour to leave! In front of the cottages stands a handsome young man, his traveller’s stick across his shoulder, a bag on his back. His glance, usually so bright, wanders slowly about him; his expression is calm, and everything about him seems to suggest great peace of mind; and yet his heart is beating fast, and his weighed-down bosom painfully rises and falls. His mother grips one of his hands and pours out upon him the signs of the most ardent affection; the poor woman does not weep; her cheeks tremble under the effort she makes to hide her sorrow. She smiles at her child to comfort him, but her smile, forced and pained, is sadder than the most heart-rending cries. The other widow is busy calming the little boy, and tries to convince him that Jean will come back soon; but the child has understood from the sadness that has overcome his family for the past year that separation is a terrible misfortune, and now he is crying loudly. Inside, the grandfather and Catherine are making the last preparations for the journey: they hollow out a rye loaf and fill it with butter. They go outside with the provisions for the journey and stand near the young man. The cowshed is open; the bull looks sadly at his master, and from time to time makes a soft, melancholy lowing; it is as if the animal understands what is about to happen. Everything is ready: he is about to leave. He has already squeezed his mother’s hand with a harder grip and taken a step forward; but he casts his gaze around him, casts an affectionate glance over the humble cottage that held his cradle, the heath and woods that witnessed his childhood and the arid fields so often watered with the sweat of his youth! Then his eye meets in turn the eyes of all those whom he loves, and those of that bull, too, companion of his hard labours; he covers his face with his hand, hides the tears that run down his cheeks, and says in a voice than can scarcely be understood: Farewell.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">He raises his head, shakes the thick hair that falls over his neck like a mane, and steps firmly forward. But they all follow him; the moment of separation has not yet come. At a certain point on the way to the village, at the place where the roads cross, stands a lime tree, on which is hung an image of the Holy Virgin. Trine put it there on a beautiful May evening, and Jean made a prie-dieu of turf at the foot of the tree. It is in this holy place, where every day, one of them would come to thank and to praise God, that the heart-rending words of farewell will escape their trembling lips…</ab>
<ab rend="indent">In the distance can already be seen the lime tree, the point at which the inevitable separation must begin. The young man slows his pace, while his mother, still lavishing caresses upon him, says: Jean, my son, never forget what I have told you. Always have God before your eyes, and never fail to say your prayers before you go to bed. As long as you do that, you will always be good; but if it should happen that one evening you forget to pray, think of me the next day, think of your mother, and you will be good and brave again; for the man who thinks of God and of his mother, is protected from all evil, my dear child.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I shall always, always, think of you, my mother, said the young man with a sigh, but in a calm voice; if I am sad, and I lose courage, your memory will be my support and my consolation; and I feel it, I shall be unhappy, I love you all too dearly. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">And then you mustn’t swear, you know, or lead a bad life. You’ll go to church, won’t you? You’ll give us news about your Health as often as possible, and you won’t forget that the smallest word from her child makes a mother happy, isn’t that so? Oh, I’ll say a prayer every day to your blessed guardian Angel, praying that he will never abandon you! Jean is deeply moved by his mother’s soft, penetrating voice; he dare not look at her, so much is he struck at this solemn moment by the worthy woman’s clear look: it is with bowed head that he listens. His only answer is from time to time a tighter handclasp, and a long sigh, with which now and then are mingled the words, Mother, dear Mother! They approached the crossroads in silence; the grandfather stood on the other side of the young man, and said to him in a grave voice: Jean, my boy, you’ll do your duty without reluctance and with love, won’t you? You’ll be obedient to your superiors, and you’ll put up with an injustice without complaining about it, if one should be done to you? You’ll be considerate and obliging to everyone, you’ll show you’re willing, and you’ll carry out courageously all the orders you’re given? Then God will help you, your officers and comrades will love you. Trine, his mother, and the little boy were already under the lime tree, praying on their knees on the turf bench. Jean had no time to reply to his grandfather’s recommendations; his Mother drew him towards the bench. They all knelt and prayed with hands raised to heaven.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">The wind murmurs softly in the branches of the pines, the spring sunshine gilds the sandy road with its joyful rays, the birds sing their gay song; and yet a solemn silence reigns, for one can clearly hear the prayers rising from around the lime tree... It is done; they all rise, but from every eye falls a torrent of tears. The mother embraces her son while giving heart-rending cries, and though the others’ arms were already opened wide for the sad farewell embrace, she does not let her child go, she staunches with her kisses the tears that bathe his cheeks, and utters unintelligible words of anxiety and love, and she weeps on his shoulder.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">At last, the poor woman, worn out, exhausted and still weeping, goes and sinks down on the bench. Jean hastily kisses his grandfather and Trine’s mother; he releases himself with gentle force from the embrace of his despairing little brother, runs back to his mother, presses her tightly in his arms, places a kiss on her forehead and shouts in an agonizing voice: Farewell!</ab>
<ab rend="indent">And without daring to look back, he walks rapidly in the direction of the village, until at the corner of the wood, he has disappeared from his family’s sight.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>(Conscience, Le conscrit)<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The differences in text in the various editions consulted reveal that Van Gogh knew <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="95">Scènes de la vie flamande</rs>
                        </hi>, by <rs type="pers" key="572">Henri Conscience</rs>, translated by <rs type="pers" key="1663">Léon Wocquier</rs>. First series, new edition. Paris 1864. Van Gogh himself must have added the phrase ‘et elle pleure sur son épaule’ (and she weeps on his shoulder) <ref target="#l-95">(ll. 95-96)</ref>; it does not occur in either Conscience’s manuscript or the editions consulted. Remarkably, the early Dutch edition includes, precisely in the place where this sentence occurs, a print by <rs type="pers" key="587">Eduard Dujardin</rs> depicting a girl crying on the conscript’s shoulder. It is therefore possible that Van Gogh had read this version of the book earlier, and had remembered the illustration while copying out the passage. An indication of this is that his version does not correspond thematically: in the print, it is the girl Trien who cries, whereas in the text it is the conscript’s mother. There might indeed be an edition in which this phrase occurs as a caption below an illustration.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>