<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Prose passage copied from ‘Scheveningen’ by Henri Alphonse Esquiros. Probably May 1877.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/RM11"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">RM11</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters"/>
<idno type="brieven1990">-</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Amsterdam</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>probably May 1877</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
</vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b1461 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
    <note type="date" xml:id="date">
                        <p>This excerpt occurs twice on separate sheets in the estate. In addition to this sheet, it appears on FR b1460, which is appended to <ref target="let118.xml">letter 118</ref>. See also that letter and cf. Pabst 1988, pp. 79-82.</p>
<p rend="indent">In <ref target="let118.xml">letter 118</ref>, dated 31 May 1877, Vincent wrote to Theo: ‘Herewith something by Esquiros’. We assume that the present text, likewise by Esquiros, was also written in this period, why is why we think it likely that this sheet originated in May 1877.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 1461" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001346_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001346_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001346_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001346_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001346_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 1461" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001346_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001346_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001346_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001001346_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001001346_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001001346_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">Scheveningen</hi>
                    <anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/>
                </ab>
                <vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>
<ab>Les côtes de la Hollande sont masquées par des chaînes de dunes <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>qui dérobent au voyageur la vue des eaux.– Après une longue et <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>pénible ascension dans ces collines de sable, levez les yeux – la <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>mer est là! Cette mer du Nord était mal connue des anciens qui <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>l’envisageaient à travèrs des fables et de superstitieuses terreurs.– <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>Tacite lui-même se la représentait comme bouleversée par des <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>vents éternels et comme peuplée de monstres. La verité est que ses côtes <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>sont tempêteuses, sa couleur est changeante; sur le premier plan, <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>elle est d’un jaune écumeux qui ressemble à l’eau de lessive; plus loin <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>d’un vert mourant; là-bas, d’un bleu évaporé qui se confond <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>avec la ligne ondoyante du ciel.– De grands nuages projettent <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>obliquement de distance en distance leur ombre grave sur ce miroir <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>indécis.– Aucuns rochers, aucunes falaises ne brisent l’effort <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>des vagues: cette mer se roule sur le lit de sable qu’elle s’est fait <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>elle-même et qu’elle étend toujours.– La physionomie des <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>côtes de la Hollande varie peu: du sable et puis du sable, de <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>l’eau et puis de l’eau, le ciel et puis le ciel.– Sur ces côtes, qui <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>donnent le sentiment de l’infini, s’élèvent, depuis l’embou<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>chure de la Meuse jusqu’au Helder, plusieurs villages de <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>pecheurs. Le plus intérèssant de ces villages est Scheveningen<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>La plage de Scheveningen est frequentée pendant la belle saison <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>par les baigneurs. Un joli village, relié à La Haye par une route <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>plantée d’arbres et par une promenade en forme de bois qui se <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>perd dans les dunes, reçoit durant l’été des etrangers de toute <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>les nations.– Ici tout se ressent du voisinage de l’Océan. <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>L’église qui ne manque point d’élégance, conserve l’enorme <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>crâne et quelques vertèbres d’un cachalot qui fut jeté sur le <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>rivage en 1617 par une tempête. Ce silencieux debris est com<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>me un commentaire de ces paroles de Job “Les monstres Te <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>racontent, ô Seigneur”! Dans la principale rue, qui conduit à <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>la mer, on rencontre plusieurs marchands de coquillages.– <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>Cette mer, dont on entend la voix, ne se montre elle-même que <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>quand le voyageur a les pieds tout près de l’eau. Le brusque <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>plaisir de la surprise et la grandeur de la scène qui se deploie <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>alors, compensent bien cette gradation d’effets qu’on rencontre <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>sur d’autres rivages. Une flottille de pêche, dont les flibots sont <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>ou échoués sur le sable, ou maintenus par l’ancre, ou épar<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>pillés au large comme les pensées du cerveau de la mer, <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>associe l’image du travail aux souvenirs historiques. Ici l’Ocean <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>a lieu d’être fier de la Hollande et des Hollandais, en 1673, de <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>Ruyter défit en vue de Scheveningen les flottes Anglaises et Francaises. 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                    <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>Ce petit village est le Cherbourg de la Hollande. Il a vu des exils <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>et des infortunes royales. C’était par une froide journée de Janvier <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>1795; les pêcheurs chargeaient dans deux barques des ballots <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>et des malles de voyage; d’une voiture qui débouchait à l’extrémité <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>du village, sortirent un homme enveloppé d’une large pelisse et une <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>femme qui portait un enfant dans ses bras. Cet homme était le <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>Prince d’Orange; l’enfant était le petit fils du dernier Stadhouder, <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>le futur roi Guillaume II<c type="kp">_</c>– En 1813, cette plage revit et reçut <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>au milieu des acclamations (l’Empire venait de tomber) le repré<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>sentant de la meme famille, assise maintenant sur le trone des <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>Pays Bas.–</ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Si vous continuez sur la droite votre promenade dans les sables, vous <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>rencontrez l’hôtel des bains où les habitants de La Haye se rendent <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>le Dimanche soir pour entendre de la musique. C’est à la tombee <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>de la nuit, quand la mer vole au ciel toutes ses étoiles, un point <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>de vue solennel et magnifique. J’ai assisté, devant cet hôtel, <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>à un feu d’artifice sur l’eau, dont le motif était naturellement <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>l’incendie d’un navire. Je n’ai pas grand gout pour les fusées <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>et les chandelles romaines; mais ici la vulgarité de ces fêtes <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>se relevait par la grandeur du théatre. La sombre mer faisait <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>presque à elle seule tous les frais du spectacle, et grace à <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>son fracas sublime, à ces nuages déchirés, aux catastrophes trop <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>réelles dont l’imagination pouvait se retracer le tableau <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>dans cette incendie artificielle<c type="kk">/</c> la scène ne manquait point de ma<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>jesté.– Cette grande rue, ces bains, ces cafés, ces hôtels, tout cela <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>n’est pourtant point Scheveningen. On peut avoir habité cet endroit <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>pendant plusieurs étés et ne point connaitre le village des pêcheurs<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>Derrière d’élégantes habitations, qui servent veritablement de <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>trompe l’oeil, se cachent des rues étroites, de pauvres niches de <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>brique, dans lesquelles se dissimule une population silencieuse <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>et misérable. A la porte de ces reduits, devant lesquelles, sèchent du <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>linge, des filets, des chemises rouges et des chapelets de poissons <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>enfilés dans une corde, apparait de temps à autre une figure <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>de femme triste, vieille et amaigrie par la fièvre. Les enfants <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>eux, jouent à travers toute cette detresse, comme si c’était un <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>des priviléges de leur âge d’ignorer le mal et la pauvreté.– <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>La population de Scheveningen est de 6.800 habitants parmi <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>lesquels 450 catholiques seulement. Il est à noter que la plu<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>part des aubergistes et des marchands de poisson professent le <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>catholicisme, tandis que les armateurs et les pêcheurs sont <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>reformés. Il y a pour le village deux ecoles de l’état que nous <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>avons visitées, et qui sont parfaitement tenues. La première est, <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>à vrai dire, une salle d’asile qui reçoit 250 enfants des deux <lb n="85a" xml:id="l-85a"/>sexes. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                    <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>Les enfants quittent cette première école vers l’age de six ans et <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>entrent alors dans l’école primaire, qui contient 500 élèves. <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>L’instruction est distribuée par un chef, cinq sous-maîtres et <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>cinq surveillants. On enseigne la lecture, l’écriture, le calcul<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>la geographie et un peu d’histoire. Les enfants sortent de cette <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>seconde ecole entre dix et douze ans: le vaisseau les reclame. <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>La langue des pecheurs est une sorte de patois qui diffère <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>essentiellement du hollandais ordinaire, et dans lequel certains <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>linguistes ont cru reconnaître des traces de l’anglo saxon qui pa<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>rait avoir été la souche de l’idiome national. Leur costume <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>est particulier, surtout celui des femmes: elles portent durant <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>l’hiver, un corsage de serge ou d’indienne, une jupe de serge brune, <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>un long camail de la même étoffe et de la même couleur, doublé <lb n="99" xml:id="l-99"/>de rouge, avec un collet droit et raide. Cet habillement a quelque <lb n="100" xml:id="l-100"/>chose d’austère et de cénobitique: on est d’ailleurs forcé de convenir <lb n="101" xml:id="l-101"/>qu’il s’adapte bien au climat et à la profession. Un grand chapeau <lb n="102" xml:id="l-102"/>de grosse paille, bordé d’un ruban noir, doublé d’une indienne à <lb n="103" xml:id="l-103"/>fleurs, abaissé légèrement de chaque côté, relevé par derrière et par <lb n="104" xml:id="l-104"/>devant en forme de nacelle, leur sert à maintenir sur la tête <lb n="105" xml:id="l-105"/>jusqu’à trois ou quatre corbeilles. Ces femmes ont une stature ro<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="106" xml:id="l-106"/>buste, une grande taille, une figure mediocrement jolie, mais <lb n="107" xml:id="l-107"/>qui respire un air de santé, des yeux bleus dont les paupières sont <lb n="108" xml:id="l-108"/>peu ouvertes, et des membres vigoureux. A trente ans elles ont déjà <lb n="109" xml:id="l-109"/>beaucoup perdu de leur fraîcheur; leur peau est hâlée, circon<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="110" xml:id="l-110"/>stance qui tient sans doute au voisinage de la mer et à l’habita<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="111" xml:id="l-111"/>tion dans les dunes. Les dunes constituent un pays dans <lb n="112" xml:id="l-112"/>le pays même, le sable y réfléchit plus fortement qu’ailleurs <lb n="113" xml:id="l-113"/>les rayons du soleil: c’est l’Arabie de la Hollande.</ab>
                <lb n="114" xml:id="l-114"/>
<ab rend="indent">Les hommes sont relativement de petite taille, leur costume, veste <lb n="115" xml:id="l-115"/>et pantalon noirs, favorise peu leur tournure qui est grave, mais <lb n="116" xml:id="l-116"/>lourde. Ils ont le visage rond, le col court, les cheveux le plus souvent <lb n="117" xml:id="l-117"/>bruns et frisés. Leur grand luxe consiste dans des boutons de <lb n="118" xml:id="l-118"/>chemise et dans des boucles d’argent, qu’ils attachent aux <lb n="119" xml:id="l-119"/>pieds et à la ceinture.– Cette persistance dans le costume, sur<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="120" xml:id="l-120"/>tout dans celui des femmes, cette fixité des traits physiques, ces <lb n="121" xml:id="l-121"/>caractères de race qui se conservent par le soin qu’ont les garçons <lb n="122" xml:id="l-122"/>et les filles de Scheveningen de ne se marier qu’entre eux, tout cela <lb n="123" xml:id="l-123"/>est peutêtre une consequence de leur commerce avec la mer. L’Ocean<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="124" xml:id="l-124"/>dans lequel certains poètes ont cru voir une image de l’incon<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="125" xml:id="l-125"/>stance, est au contraire une image de l’éternité, c’est de tous les <lb n="126" xml:id="l-126"/>éléments, celui qui a subi le moins de vicissitudes depuis l’origine <lb n="126a" xml:id="l-126a"/>du monde.–</ab>
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                <lb n="127" xml:id="l-127"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tel l’aurore de la creation l’a vu naître tel il roule encore <lb n="128" xml:id="l-128"/>maintenant. Il se déplace; il ne change pas. Aux forces du temps <lb n="129" xml:id="l-129"/>qui minent les rochers, qui altèrent le niveau des continents, qui <lb n="130" xml:id="l-130"/>transforment la nature vivante et les destinées humaines, il <lb n="131" xml:id="l-131"/>oppose, lui, sa mobile stabilité.– Les moeurs des pecheurs qui <lb n="132" xml:id="l-132"/>habitent la côte participent du caractère de l’Ocean. Ils n’ont <lb n="133" xml:id="l-133"/>aucune des habitudes de la ville. Le fond de leur caractère est <lb n="134" xml:id="l-134"/>l’indépendance<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/> Il semble que le commerce avec la mer developpe <lb n="135" xml:id="l-135"/>chez eux le sentiment de la dignité humaine. Ces hommes n’aiment <lb n="136" xml:id="l-136"/>point la terre: il leur faut l’espace, la libre immensité des mers<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="137" xml:id="l-137"/>le flot indompté, le ciel, bleu le jour, étoilé la nuit, l’acre brise du <lb n="138" xml:id="l-138"/>Nord, la conscience de l’homme debout sur ses actes comme le <lb n="139" xml:id="l-139"/>mat du vaisseau sur les mouvements de l’Ocean. Soldats du <lb n="140" xml:id="l-140"/>travail ils aiment à braver volontairement le feu de l’éclair, le hen<c type="shy">-</c>
                    <lb n="141" xml:id="l-141"/>nissement des flots qui courent sans mors et la bouche écumante <lb n="142" xml:id="l-142"/>autour de la quille du vaisseau. A terre ils ont le mal du pays. <lb n="143" xml:id="l-143"/>Etrangers aux conventions sociales, ils ne veulent être ni règlés <lb n="144" xml:id="l-144"/>ni protégés. Ce sentiment d’independance est visible sur leur <lb n="145" xml:id="l-145"/>physionomie<c type="kp">_</c> Les matelots et les pecheurs se distinguent des autres <lb n="146" xml:id="l-146"/>hommes par la manière dont ils portent la tête haute en marchant. <lb n="147" xml:id="l-147"/>C’est pour eux, on le dirait du moins, qu’a été fait le vers d’Ovide:<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/> <lb n="148" xml:id="l-148"/>Il a donné à l’homme une face qui regarde le ciel.</ab>
                <lb n="149" xml:id="l-149"/>
<ab rend="indent">Cet amour de la liberté déteint jusque sur leurs croyances religieuses. <lb n="150" xml:id="l-150"/>Les pecheurs de la côte, ainsi que nous l’avons vu, sont tous ou <lb n="151" xml:id="l-151"/>presque tous réformés: ils ne reconnaissent que deux livres qui ont le <lb n="152" xml:id="l-152"/>droit de leur parler de Dieu, la Bible et la mer. Il semble que <lb n="153" xml:id="l-153"/>l’Ocean excerce sur eux un action morale et sanctifiante. <lb n="154" xml:id="l-154"/>L’ivrognerie est rare parmi les pecheurs de Scheveningen; mais <lb n="155" xml:id="l-155"/>ceux-là meme qui boivent du genièvre à terre avec excès, <lb n="156" xml:id="l-156"/>s’abstiennent de toute intempérance quand ils naviguent. A <lb n="157" xml:id="l-157"/>bord du vaisseau, les jurons sont inconnus<c type="kp">_</c> La vie de la mer exalte <lb n="158" xml:id="l-158"/>chez ces hommes simples et ignorants le sentiment religieux<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="159" xml:id="l-159"/>Quand un bateau part chaque pecheur emporte sa Bible. <lb n="160" xml:id="l-160"/>On ne prend jamais un repas sans prière, et le repas finit <lb n="161" xml:id="l-161"/>egalement par une action de grâces. Le dimanche, si les <lb n="162" xml:id="l-162"/>hommes sont en mer, ils s’abstiennent de pêcher, s’ils sont <lb n="163" xml:id="l-163"/>à terre, on entend dès le matin dans leurs petites maisons <lb n="164" xml:id="l-164"/>le chant des Psaumes.–</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="165" xml:id="l-165"/>
<ab>Alphonse Esquiros</ab>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-51" n="51">(l’Empire venait de tomber) le &lt; , l’Empire venait de tomber. Le  <hi rend="ital">Corresponding to the original text.</hi>
                    </note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>
                    <hi rend="ital">Scheveningen</hi>.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/>
                </ab>
                <vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Holland’s coasts are hidden by ranges of dunes that deprive the traveller of the sight of the waters. After a long and arduous climb up these sandy hills, raise your eyes, and there’s the sea! This North Sea was poorly known to the ancients, who imagined it in terms of fables and superstitious terrors. Even Tacitus pictured it as being churned up by constant winds and inhabited by monsters. The fact is that its coasts are stormy, and its colour is variable; in the foreground it is a scummy yellow that looks like dirty washing water, further off, a weak green, and in the distance, a faded blue that blends into the wavy line of the sky. Here and there, great clouds cast their sombre shadows obliquely over this indistinct mirror. No rocks, no cliffs break the force of the waves: this sea rolls on its sandy bed, which it had made for itself and which it is constantly expanding. The physiognomy of Holland’s coasts varies very little: sand, and more sand, water and more water, sky and more sky. On these coasts, which give the impression of being limitless, there stand, between the mouth of the Maas and Den Helder, a number of fishing villages. The most interesting of these villages is Scheveningen. The beach at Scheveningen is frequented by bathers during the summer. At that time of year, a pretty village, linked with The Hague by a tree-lined road, and a promenade built of timber that disappears among the dunes, welcomes foreigners from every country. Here everything shows the effects of proximity to the Ocean. The church, which by no means lacks elegance, contains the enormous skull and a few vertebrae of a sperm whale that was cast up on the shore in a storm, in 1617. These silent fragments are like a commentary on these words of Job: “The monsters proclaim Thee, O Lord”. In the main street, which leads to the sea, are to be found several vendors of shellfish. This sea, whose voice can be heard, shows itself only when the traveller’s feet are almost at the water. The sudden delight of surprise, and the grandeur of the scene that then opens up, fully compensate for the gradation of effects found on other shores. A fishing fleet, whose smacks are beached on the sand, or riding at anchor, or scattered out at sea like the thoughts of the sea’s brain, associates the image of labour with historical memories. Here the Ocean must be proud of Holland and the Dutch; in 1673, De Ruyter defeated the English and French fleets within sight of Scheveningen.
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/> This little village is Holland’s Cherbourg. It has seen exiles and royal misfortunes. It was a cold January day in 1795; the fishermen were loading two boats with packages and travelling trunks; from a conveyance that appeared at the far end of the village came a man enveloped in a wide cloak and a woman carrying a child in her arms. That man was the Prince of Orange; the child was the grandson of the last Stadholder, the future King William II. In 1813, this shore once again saw and welcomed amid acclamations (the Empire had just fallen) the representative of that same family that now occupies the throne of the Netherlands.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">If you continue your walk along the sands to the right you will find the spa hotel, where people from The Hague come on Sunday evenings to listen to music. At nightfall, when the sea steals from the sky all its stars, it is a solemn and magnificent prospect. I have seen, in front of this hotel, a display of fireworks on the water, whose subject was, of course, the burning of a ship. I am not especially fond of rockets or Roman candles, but in this case the vulgarity of such entertainments was redeemed by its theatrical grandeur. The darkling sea was almost in itself worth the whole cost of the performance, and with its sublime din, with those tattered clouds, with the only too real catastrophes which the imagination could picture to itself in this pretended conflagration, the scene by no means lacked majesty. And yet this main street, these baths, these cafés, these hotels – all of that is not Scheveningen. A person may have spent many summers in this place and yet not know the fishing village at all. Behind some elegant dwellings, which are a true example of <hi rend="ital">trompe l’oeil</hi>, are hidden narrow streets, and poor brick hovels, in which a silent and wretched population conceals itself. At the doors of these poky cubby-holes, in front of which are drying washing, nets, red shirts and strings of fish threaded on a line, there appears from time to time the figure of a woman, sad, aged and wasted by fever. Children play in the midst of all this wretchedness, as if it were one of the privileges of their age to be unaware of misfortune and poverty. The population of Scheveningen is 6,800, of whom only 450 are Catholics. It should be noted that the majority of the innkeepers and fish merchants profess the Catholic faith, whereas the shipowners and the fishermen are Protestants. For the village there are two government schools, which we visited and which are kept in perfect order. The first, if truth be told, is a ward in an asylum, which holds 250 children of both sexes. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/> The children leave this first school at the age of about six, and then enter the primary school, which has 500 pupils. Teaching is shared among a head, five assistant masters and five monitors. The children are taught reading, writing, arithmetic, geography and a little history. They leave this second school at between ten and twelve years of age: the boats claim them. The fishermen’s language is a kind of patois that is fundamentally different from ordinary Dutch, and in which some linguists have believed they recognize traces of the Anglo-Saxon that seems to have been the source of the national language. Their dress, especially the women’s, is distinctive. In the winter, they wear a bodice of serge or calico, a brown serge skirt, a long cape of the same stuff and the same colour, lined in red, with a tall, stiff collar. There is something austere and monkish about this form of clothing; one must in any case admit that it is well suited to the climate and to their occupation. A large hat of coarse straw with a border of black ribbon, lined in flower-printed calico, bent slightly downward on either side and rising at the back and the front like a boat, enables them to hold up to three or four baskets on their heads. These women are tall, and robustly built, with rather plain but healthy-looking faces, blue eyes with somewhat drooping lids, and sturdy limbs. By the age of thirty they have already lost much of their freshness; their skin is weather-beaten, a condition due, no doubt, to the proximity of the sea and to their living in the dunes. The dunes form a country within the country itself; the sand reflects the sun’s rays more strongly than elsewhere; this is Holland’s Arabia. </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The men are comparatively short in stature; their dress – black jacket and trousers – does not suit their bearing, which is serious, but awkward. They have round faces, short necks, usually brown and curly hair. Their great treasures are their shirt-buttons and the silver buckles which they attach to their feet and their belts. This conservatism in their dress, especially the women’s, this consistency in their physical traits, these racial characteristics that are preserved due to the concern shown by the boys and girls of Scheveningen to marry only amongst themselves, are all, perhaps, a consequence of their dealings with the sea. The Ocean, in which some poets have believed they have seen an image of inconstancy, is, on the contrary, an image of eternity; of all the elements, it is the one that has suffered the fewest vicissitudes since the beginning of the world. 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">The dawn of creation saw it born thus, and thus it still rolls today. It moves, it does not change. The Ocean sets its ever-moving stability against the forces of time that undermine the rocks, that alter the level of the continents, that transform living nature and human destinies. The ways of the fishermen who live on the coast share the nature of the Ocean. They have none of the habits of the city. The essence of their character is independence.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> It seems that dealings with the sea foster in them the sense of human dignity. These men have no love of the land; they need space, the free vastness of the seas, the untamed flood, the sky, blue by day, full of stars by night, the sharp north wind, the mind of a man standing upright in his actions like the ship’s mast upon the movements of the Ocean. Soldiers of toil, they love deliberately to brave the lightning’s bolt, the whinnying of the waves that run, without a bit and foaming at the mouth, about the boat’s keel. On land, they are homesick. Strangers to social conventions, they wish to be neither governed nor protected. This feeling of independence can be seen on their faces. Sailors and fishermen differ from other men in the way they carry their heads high as they walk. One would at the very least say that for them was written Ovid’s line:<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> He gave man a face that looks at the sky.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">This love of liberty even rubs off on their religious beliefs. As we have seen, all, or almost all, of the fishermen of the coast are Protestant; they acknowledge only two books that have the right to speak to them of God: the Bible and the sea. It appears that the Ocean exerts a moral and sanctifying effect on them. Drunkenness is rare among the fishermen of Scheveningen, but even those who drink Hollands gin to excess on land abstain from any form of intemperance when they are at sea. Swearing is unknown on board a boat. The seafaring life strengthens and increases religious feelings in these simple and ignorant men. When a fishing boat sails, each fisherman takes his Bible with him. A meal is never eaten without grace being said, and is also followed by a prayer of thanks. On Sunday, if the men are at sea, they abstain from fishing, and if they are on land, the singing of the Psalms can be heard in their little houses from morning onwards.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>
                    <rs type="pers" key="600">Alphonse Esquiros</rs>
                </ab>
            </div>
    <div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>The copied quotation was included in <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="136">La Néerlande et la vie hollandaise</rs>
                        </hi>. See Esquiros 1859, pp. 231-238. Van Gogh occasionally skips bits of text as well as whole sentences. There are, moreover, a few slight differences to the printed version.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Van Gogh omitted the following sentence: ‘Scheveningen furnishes almost no domestic staff: girls and boys, no one wants to be a servant.’ </ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>
                        <rs type="pers" key="600">Esquiros</rs> quoted: ‘<hi rend="ital">Os homini sublime dedit</hi>’ (Ovid, <hi rend="ital">
                            <rs type="lit" key="54">Metamorphoses</rs>
                        </hi>, <hi rend="sc">i</hi>, 85).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>