<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Last Changed Date: 2018-07-18 12:32:41 +0200 (Wed, 18 Jul 2018) | SVN Revision: 2206 --><!--Licensed under Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)--><?xml-model href="https://xmlschema.huygens.knaw.nl/vgodd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:vg="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/">
<teiHeader xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Auvers-sur-Oise, Saturday, 24 May 1890.</title>
<editor>Leo Jansen</editor>
<editor>Hans Luijten</editor>
<editor>Nienke Bakker</editor>
            </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>
                    <name>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis (KNAW)</name>
                    <email>info@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </publisher>
<publisher>Van Gogh Museum</publisher>
<pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
<date type="first" when="2009">2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/ https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/legalcode">
<p>Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0) </p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
<ptr target="http://vangoghletters.org/orig/RM20"/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <vg:letDesc>
                    <vg:letIdentifier>
<idno type="jlb">RM20</idno>
<idno type="collectedletters">648</idno>
<idno type="brieven1990">877</idno>
                    </vg:letIdentifier>
                    <vg:letHeading>
                        <author>Vincent van Gogh</author>
                        <vg:addressee>Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger</vg:addressee>
                        <vg:placeLet>Auvers-sur-Oise</vg:placeLet>
                        <vg:dateLet>Saturday, 24 May 1890</vg:dateLet>
                    </vg:letHeading>
                    <vg:letContents>
<p>To Theo van Gogh and Jo van Gogh-Bonger. Auvers-sur-Oise, Saturday, 24 May 1890.</p>
                    </vg:letContents>
<note type="sourceStatus" xml:id="sourceStatus">
<p>Original manuscript</p>
                    </note>
<note type="location" xml:id="location">
<p>Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b696 V/1962</p>
                    </note>
<note type="date" xml:id="date">
<p>Vincent is disappointed because he has still heard nothing from Theo and Jo ‘in these early days’ (<ref target="#l-1*">l. 1*</ref>). According to Hulsker, who dates this piece of writing to Saturday, 24 May 1890, it was never sent. To be sure, this letter and <ref target="let875.xml">letter 875</ref> have a striking number of subjects in common, but <ref target="let875.xml">letter 875</ref> is obviously the new version. Vincent’s disappointment at the failure of his allowance to arrive must meanwhile have been dispelled, since he received 50 francs on Sunday. There is, in fact, a good chance that Van Gogh did not send the present letter for this very reason. The fact that this letter nevertheless survived means that Theo found it after Vincent’s death and saved it. See Hulsker 1998, p. 51.</p>
                    </note>
                </vg:letDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
<surface n="b 0696" xml:id="surf-pb-1r">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_01.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_01_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000945_01_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-1">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_01_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000945_01_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000945_01_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1r-4">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_01_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000945_01_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000945_01_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
<surface n="b 0696" xml:id="surf-pb-1v">
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_02.TIF" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_02_n.tif" rend="norend"/>
            <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000945_02_nt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
            <zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-2">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_02_nL.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000945_02_nLt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000945_02_nLf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
<zone xml:id="zone-pb-1v-3">
<graphic mimeType="image/tiff" url="VGM001000945_02_nR.tif" rend="norend"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/jpeg" url="VGM001000945_02_nRt.jpg" height="50px" rend="thumbnail"/>
                <graphic mimeType="image/png" url="VGM001000945_02_nRf.png" width="380px" rend="facstab"/>
            </zone>
</surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
        <body>
<div type="original" xml:lang="fr">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
                <lb n="1" xml:id="l-1"/>
<ab>Mon cher Theo &amp; chère Jo.</ab>
                <lb n="1*" xml:id="l-1s"/>
<ab>de ces premiers jours ci certes j’aurais <lb n="2" xml:id="l-2"/>dans des conditions ordinaires espéré un petit mot de vous déjà<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="3" xml:id="l-3"/>Mais considérant les chôses comme des faits accomplis – ma foi – <lb n="4" xml:id="l-4"/>je trouve que Theo<c type="kk">/</c> Jo et le petit sont un peu sur les dents et <lb n="5" xml:id="l-5"/>éreintés – d’ailleurs moi aussi suis loin d’etre arrivé à quelque <lb n="6" xml:id="l-6"/>tranquilité. Souvent, très souvent je pense à mon <lb n="7" xml:id="l-7"/>petit neveu – est ce qu’il va bien. Jo voulez vous me <lb n="8" xml:id="l-8"/>croire – si cela vous arrive de nouveau, ce que j’espère, <lb n="9" xml:id="l-9"/>d’avoir encore d’autres enfants – ne les faites pas en ville<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="10" xml:id="l-10"/>accouchez à la campagne et restez y jusqu’à que l’enfant <lb n="11" xml:id="l-11"/>aye 3 ou 4 mois. A présent – il me semble que <lb n="12" xml:id="l-12"/>l’enfant n’ayant encore que 3 mois<c type="kk">/</c> déjà le lait devient <lb n="13" xml:id="l-13"/>rare<c type="kk">/</c> déjà vous etes comme Theo fatiguée trop<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="14" xml:id="l-14"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je ne veux pas dire du tout éreintée mais enfin les ennuis <lb n="15" xml:id="l-15"/>prennent trop de place<c type="kk">/</c> sont trop nombreux et vous semez <lb n="16" xml:id="l-16"/>dans les épines.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-o-1"/> C’est pourquoi que je vous donnerais <lb n="17" xml:id="l-17"/>à penser de ne pas aller en Hollande cette année ci<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="18" xml:id="l-18"/>c’est très très couteux toujours le voyage et jamais cela <lb n="19" xml:id="l-19"/>a fait du bien. Si<c type="kk">/</c> cela fait du bien si vous voulez à <lb n="20" xml:id="l-20"/>la mère qui aimera à voir le petit – mais elle comprendra <lb n="21" xml:id="l-21"/>et préférera le bien être du petit au plaisir de le voir<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="22" xml:id="l-22"/>D’ailleurs elle n’y perdra rien<c type="kk">/</c> elle le verra plus tard. <lb n="23" xml:id="l-23"/>Mais – sans oser dire que ce soit assez – quoi qu’il <lb n="24" xml:id="l-24"/>en soit il est certes préférable que père<c type="kk">/</c> mère et enfant <lb n="25" xml:id="l-25"/>prennent un repos absolu d’un mois à la campagne.</ab>
                <lb n="26" xml:id="l-26"/>
<ab rend="indent">D’un autre côté moi aussi je crains beaucoup d’être <lb n="27" xml:id="l-27"/>ahuri – et trouve étrange que je ne sache aucunement <lb n="28" xml:id="l-28"/>sous quelles conditions je suis parti – si c’est comme <lb n="29" xml:id="l-29"/>dans le temps à 150 par mois en trois fois – Theo n’a rien <lb n="30" xml:id="l-30"/>fixé et donc pour commencer je suis parti dans <lb n="31" xml:id="l-31"/>l’ahurissement.–<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-o-2"/>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                <lb n="32" xml:id="l-32"/>
<ab rend="indent">Y aurait-il moyen de se revoir encore plus calme – je l’espère. <lb n="33" xml:id="l-33"/>mais le voyage en Hollande<c type="kk">/</c> je redoute que ce sera un comble <lb n="34" xml:id="l-34"/>pour nous tous.</ab>
                <lb n="35" xml:id="l-35"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je prévois toujours que cela fait souffrir l’enfant plus tard d’être <lb n="36" xml:id="l-36"/>élevé en ville. Est ce que Jo trouve cela exagéré<c type="kp">_</c> Je l’espère <lb n="37" xml:id="l-37"/>mais enfin je crois que pourtant il faut être prudent<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="38" xml:id="l-38"/>Et je dis ce que je pense parceque vous comprenez <lb n="39" xml:id="l-39"/>bien que je prends de l’intérêt à mon petit neveu <lb n="40" xml:id="l-40"/>et tiens à son bien être; puisque vous avez bien voulu <lb n="41" xml:id="l-41"/>le nommer après moi<c type="kk">/</c> je desirerais qu’il eût l’âme <lb n="42" xml:id="l-42"/>moins inquiete que la mienne. qui sombre<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="43" xml:id="l-43"/>
<ab rend="indent">Parlons maintenant du D<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Gachet. J’ai été <lb n="44" xml:id="l-44"/>le voir avant hier<c type="kk">/</c> je l’ai pas trouvé<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="45" xml:id="l-45"/>
<ab rend="indent">De ces jours ci je vais très bien<c type="kk">/</c> je travaille dur et <lb n="46" xml:id="l-46"/>ai quatre études peintes et deux dessins.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-o-3"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="47" xml:id="l-47"/>
<ab rend="indent">Tu verras un dessin d’une vieille vigne avec une figure de <lb n="48" xml:id="l-48"/>paysanne. Je compte en faire une grande toile<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="49" xml:id="l-49"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je crois qu’il ne faut <hi rend="sc">aucunement</hi> compter sur <lb n="50" xml:id="l-50"/>le D<hi rend="ss">r</hi> Gachet. D’abord il est plus malade que moi à <lb n="51" xml:id="l-51"/>ce qu’il m’a paru<c type="kk">/</c> ou mettons juste autant<c type="kk">/</c> voilà<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="52" xml:id="l-52"/>Or lorsqu’un aveugle mènera un autre aveugle<c type="kk">/</c> ne <lb n="53" xml:id="l-53"/>tomberont ils pas tous deux dans le fossé<c type="kp">_</c>
                    <anchor n="4" xml:id="note-o-4"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="54" xml:id="l-54"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je ne sais que dire<c type="kp">_</c> Certes ma dernière crise<c type="kk">/</c> qui fut <lb n="55" xml:id="l-55"/>terrible<c type="kk">/</c> était due en considérable partie à l’influence des <lb n="56" xml:id="l-56"/>autres malades<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="5" xml:id="note-o-5"/> enfin<c type="kk">/</c> la prison m’écrasait et le pere Peyron <lb n="57" xml:id="l-57"/>n’y faisait pas la moindre attention<c type="kk">/</c> me laissant vegeter <lb n="58" xml:id="l-58"/>avec le reste corrompu profondément<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-orig-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                <lb n="59" xml:id="l-59"/>
<ab rend="indent">Je peux avoir un logement<c type="kk">/</c> 3 petites pieces à 150 par an<c type="kp">_</c> <lb n="60" xml:id="l-60"/>Cela si je ne trouve pas mieux<c type="kk">/</c> et j’espère trouver mieux<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="61" xml:id="l-61"/>en tout cas est preferable au trou à punaises chez Tanguy<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-o-6"/> <lb n="62" xml:id="l-62"/>et d’ailleurs j’y trouverais un abri moi-meme et pourrais <lb n="63" xml:id="l-63"/>retoucher les toiles qui en ont besoin<c type="kp">_</c> De telle facon <lb n="64" xml:id="l-64"/>les tableaux s’abimeraient moins et en les tenant <lb n="65" xml:id="l-65"/>en ordre la chance d’en tirer quelque profit <lb n="66" xml:id="l-66"/>augmenterait. Car – je ne parle pas des miennes – <lb n="67" xml:id="l-67"/>mais les toiles Bernard<c type="kk">/</c> Prevot<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="7" xml:id="note-o-7"/> Russell<c type="kk">/</c> Guillaumin<c type="kk">/</c> <lb n="68" xml:id="l-68"/>Jeannin qui s’etaient egarés là – c’est pas leur place.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-o-8"/>
                </ab>
                <lb n="69" xml:id="l-69"/>
<ab rend="indent">Or des toiles comme celles là – encore une fois des miennes <lb n="70" xml:id="l-70"/>je ne parle pas – c’est de la marchandise qui a <lb n="71" xml:id="l-71"/>et gardera une certaine valeur et la negliger c’est <lb n="72" xml:id="l-72"/>une des causes de notre gène mutuelle.</ab>
                <lb n="73" xml:id="l-73"/>
<ab rend="indent">Cela m’attriste bien un peu de devoir insister <lb n="74" xml:id="l-74"/>sur ce que tu m’envoies une partie au moins de <lb n="75" xml:id="l-75"/>mon mois dès le commencement. Mais je ferai <lb n="76" xml:id="l-76"/>encore mon possible de trouver que tout va bien<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
                <lb n="77" xml:id="l-77"/>
<ab rend="indent">Il est certain je crois que nous songeons tous <lb n="78" xml:id="l-78"/>au petit et que Jo dise ce qu’elle veut<c type="kk">/</c> Theo comme <lb n="79" xml:id="l-79"/>moi j’ose croire se rangeront à son avis. Moi je ne <lb n="80" xml:id="l-80"/>peux dans ce moment que dire que je pense <lb n="81" xml:id="l-81"/>qu’il nous faut du repos à tous. Je me sens – raté – <lb n="82" xml:id="l-82"/>voilà pour mon compte – je sens que c’est là le sort <lb n="83" xml:id="l-83"/>que j’accepte. et qui ne changera plus. Mais raison de <lb n="84" xml:id="l-84"/>plus<c type="kk">/</c> <hi rend="ital">mettant de côté toute ambition</hi> nous pouvons <lb n="85" xml:id="l-85"/>des années durant vivre ensemble sans nous ruiner <lb n="86" xml:id="l-86"/>de part ou d’autre. Tu vois qu’avec les toiles qui sont encore <lb n="87" xml:id="l-87"/>à S<hi rend="ss">t</hi> Remy<c type="kk">/</c> il y en a au moins 8<c type="kk">/</c>
                    <anchor n="9" xml:id="note-o-9"/> avec les 4 d’ici je cherche à <lb n="88" xml:id="l-88"/>ne pas perdre la main. Cela c’est absolument pourtant 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/>
                    <lb n="89" xml:id="l-89"/>la vérité<c type="kk">/</c> c’est difficile d’acquerir une certaine facilité <lb n="90" xml:id="l-90"/>de produire et en cessant de travailler je la perdrais <lb n="91" xml:id="l-91"/>bien plus vite<c type="kk">/</c> plus facilement que cela m’aie coûté de peines <lb n="92" xml:id="l-92"/>pour y arriver. Et la perspective s’assombrit<c type="kk">/</c> je ne <lb n="93" xml:id="l-93"/>vois pas l’avenir heureux du tout.</ab>
                <lb n="94" xml:id="l-94"/>
<ab rend="indent">Ecris moi par retour si tu n’as pas encore écrit <lb n="95" xml:id="l-95"/>et bonnes poignées de main en pensee<c type="kk">/</c> j’espererais <lb n="96" xml:id="l-96"/>qu’il y eût une possibilité de se revoir bientot à têtes <lb n="97" xml:id="l-97"/>plus reposées<c type="kp">_</c>
                </ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
                <lb n="98" xml:id="l-98"/>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<div type="textualNotes">
<note target="l-40" n="40">être; &lt; être</note>
<note target="l-46" n="46">ai quatre &lt; quatre</note>
<note target="l-67" n="67">Prevot &lt; <hi rend="ital">It is possible that Van Gogh wrote </hi>‘Presvot’.</note>
                </div>
            </div>
<div type="translation">
<pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
<ab>My dear Theo and dear <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs>.</ab>
<ab>In normal circumstances I would certainly have already hoped for a brief line from you in these early days. But considering things as <hi rend="ital">faits accomplis</hi> – my word – I think that Theo, <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> and the <rs type="pers" key="418">little one</rs> are a little on edge and worn out – besides, I too am far from having arrived at some kind of tranquillity. Often, very often, I think of my little nephew – is he well? Jo will you believe me – if you again happen to have more children, which I hope, don’t have them in town, give birth in the country and stay there until the child is 3 or 4 months old. At present – it seems to me that although the child is no more than 3 months old yet, the milk is already becoming sparse, already you’re like Theo, too tired.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t at all want to say exhausted, but anyway troubles are taking up too much room, are too numerous, and you’re sowing among thorns.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> That’s why I’d have you consider not going to Holland this year, the journey is always very, very costly and it has never done any good. Well yes, it does <rs type="pers" key="524">Mother</rs> good, if you like, as she’ll love to see the <rs type="pers" key="418">little one</rs> – but she’ll understand and will prefer the little one’s well-being to the pleasure of seeing him. Besides, she won’t lose anything by it, she’ll see him later. But – without daring to say that it might be enough – whatever the case it’s certainly preferable that father, mother and child take an absolute rest in the country for a month.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">On the other hand, I too greatly fear being confused – and find it strange that I shouldn’t know at all under what conditions I left – if it’s as before at 150 a month in three instalments – Theo didn’t arrange anything, and so to begin with I left in confusion.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> 
<pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Would there be a way of seeing each other again more calmly – I hope so. But the journey to Holland, I fear that it would be the last straw for all of us.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I still foresee that it makes the <rs type="pers" key="418">child</rs> suffer later to be brought up in town. Does <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> consider that an exaggeration? I hope so, but anyway I believe that one must be prudent, though. And I say what I think because you well understand that I take an interest in my little nephew and care about his well-being; since you really wanted to name him after me, I’d wish him to have a less anxious soul than mine. Which is foundering.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Let’s talk now about <rs type="pers" key="389">Dr Gachet</rs>. I went to see him the day before yesterday, I didn’t find him.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I’ve been very well the past few days, I’m working hard and have four painted studies and two drawings.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">You’ll see a drawing of an old vineyard with a figure of a peasant woman. I’m planning to do a large canvas of it.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">I think that we must <hi rend="sc">in no way</hi> count on <rs type="pers" key="389">Dr Gachet</rs>. In the first place he’s iller than I am, it seemed to me, or let’s say just as much, there you have it. Now when one blind man leads another blind man, do they not both fall into the ditch?<anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I don’t know what to say. Certainly my last crisis, which was terrible, was due in considerable part to the influence of the other patients,<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> anyway, the prison was crushing me, and <rs type="pers" key="568">
                        <hi rend="ital">père</hi> Peyron</rs> didn’t pay the slightest attention to it, leaving me to vegetate with the rest, who were profoundly corrupted. 
<pb f="1v" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-3" facs="#zone-pb-1v-3"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">I can have lodgings, 3 small rooms at 150 a year. This if I don’t find better, and I hope to find better, is in any case preferable to the bedbug-infested hole at <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs>’s,<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> and besides I’d find a shelter myself there and could retouch the canvases that need it. In such a way the paintings will be less spoiled, and by keeping them in order the chance of deriving some profit from them would increase. For – I’m not talking about my own – but the <rs type="pers" key="831">Bernard</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="1275">Prévost</rs>,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> <rs type="pers" key="1334">Russell</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="1065">Guillaumin</rs>, <rs type="pers" key="1112">Jeannin</rs> canvases that ended up there – that’s not the place for them.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/>
                </ab>
<ab rend="indent">Now canvases like those – once again I’m not talking about my own – are merchandise which has and will retain a certain value, and neglecting it is one of the causes of our mutual financial embarrassment.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It rather saddens me to have to insist that you send me at least part of my month right at the beginning. But I’ll still do all I can to ensure that all goes well.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">It’s certain, I think, that we’re all thinking of the <rs type="pers" key="418">little one</rs>, and <rs type="pers" key="416">Jo</rs> must just say what she wants, I dare believe that Theo, like me, will go along with her opinion. Myself, all I can do at the moment is say that I think that we all need some rest. I feel – a failure – that’s it as regards me – I feel that that’s the fate I’m accepting. And which won’t change any more. But one more reason, <hi rend="ital">setting aside all ambition</hi>, we can live together for years without ruining ourselves on either side. You see that with the canvases that are still in St-Rémy – there are at least 8 of them<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> – and with the 4 from here, I’m trying not to lose my touch. That, though, is the absolute 
<pb f="1r" n="4" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-4" facs="#zone-pb-1r-4"/> truth, it’s difficult to acquire a certain facility of production, and by ceasing to work I would lose it much more quickly, more easily than it cost me in troubles to acquire it. And the prospect darkens, I don’t see a happy future at all.</ab>
<ab rend="indent">Write to me by return of post if you haven’t already written, and good handshakes in thought, I would hope that it might be possible to see each other soon with more rested minds.</ab>
<vg:whiteline/>
<ab>Vincent.</ab>
            </div>
<div type="notes">
<note n="1" xml:id="n-1" target="#note-t-1">
<ab>Cf. <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Jer" chap="4" v="3">Jer. 4:3</bibleref>: ‘ne semez plus parmi les épines’ (and sow not among thorns).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="2" xml:id="n-2" target="#note-t-2">
<ab>Vincent appeared to be unnecessarily worried about his financial circumstances: between his arrival in Paris on 17 May and his death on 29 July, he received a total of 490 francs from Theo, who also paid <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs> 136 francs for painting materials in June 1890 and settled a bill from <rs type="pers" key="785">Tasset</rs> for 231.80 francs in July 1890 (see <hi rend="ital">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 45 and <ref target="let890.xml">letter 890</ref>). Tanguy and Tasset also received another, unknown amount on 21 September (see <hi rend="ital">Account book</hi> 2002, p. 78).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="3" xml:id="n-3" target="#note-t-3">
<ab>These four paintings included <hi rend="ital">Thatched cottages and houses</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2908">F 750 / JH 1984</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Chestnut tree</hi> <hi rend="ital">in blossom</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2912">F 751 / JH 1992</rs>) and<hi rend="ital"> Chestnut tree</hi> <hi rend="ital">in blossom</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2911">F 752 / JH 1991</rs>); <ref target="let874.xml">see letters 874</ref> and <ref target="let875.xml">875</ref>. The fourth painting was possibly <hi rend="ital">Vineyard and houses </hi>(<rs type="otherart" key="914">F 794 / JH 2002</rs>), which displays the same house and vineyard seen in the drawing mentioned below, which is titled <hi rend="ital">Vineyard with a woman</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2909">F 1624 / JH 1985</rs>). The second drawing was probably <hi rend="ital">Landscape with houses </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2910">F 1640r / JH 1986</rs>). See exhib. cat. New York 1986, p. 200, and cat. Amsterdam 2007, p. 423.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="4" xml:id="n-4" target="#note-t-4">
<ab>
  <bibleref xmlns="http://www.vangoghletters.org/ns/" book="Matt" chap="15" v="14">Matt. 15:14</bibleref>, ‘Indien nu de blinde den blinde leidt, zo zullen zij beiden in de gracht vallen’ (And if the blind lead the blind, both shall fall into the ditch).</ab>
                </note>
<note n="5" xml:id="n-5" target="#note-t-5">
<ab>Regarding Van Gogh’s last crisis in Saint-Rémy, <ref target="let857.xml#n-1">see letter 857, n. 1.</ref>
                    </ab>
                </note>
<note n="6" xml:id="n-6" target="#note-t-6">
<ab>Theo had Vincent’s paintings stored in a little room at <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs>’s; <ref target="let792.xml">see letter 792</ref>.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="7" xml:id="n-7" target="#note-t-7">
<ab>It is possible that Van Gogh wrote ‘Presvot’ instead of ‘Prevot’.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="8" xml:id="n-8" target="#note-t-8">
<ab>Evidently these paintings from the brothers’ collection were also stored at <rs type="pers" key="772">Tanguy</rs>’s. With regard to the paintings in the family collection by the artists mentioned, see cat. Amsterdam 1987.</ab>
                </note>
<note n="9" xml:id="n-9" target="#note-t-9">
<ab>These were the eight paintings that Van Gogh had made in Saint-Rémy in May 1890 after his last period of illness: <hi rend="ital">Irises in a vase </hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2904">F 678 / JH 1977</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Irises in a vase</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2905">F 680 / JH 1978</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Roses</hi> <hi rend="ital">in a vase</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2903">F 681 / JH 1976</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Roses</hi> <hi rend="ital">in a vase</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2906">F 682 / JH 1979</rs>), <hi rend="ital">The garden of the asylum with dandelions and tree-trunks </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2899">F 676 / JH 1970</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Meadow in the garden of the asylum</hi> (<rs type="ill" key="2902">F 672 / JH 1975</rs>), <hi rend="ital">Couple walking among olive trees in a mountainous landscape with crescent moon </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="3066">F 704 / JH 1981</rs>) and <hi rend="ital">Road with a cypress and star </hi>(<rs type="ill" key="2907">F 683 / JH 1982</rs>).</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>